Git, a distributed source
control repository.
I tried to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system.
Were the commit messages
like history books?
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day: Git Real.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Git Real and
this is Level Five where we're
going to be talking about remote
branches and tags.
So in level three,
Olivier taught
you about local branches.
But what about remote
branches?
There's going to be times where
you have a branch, let's
say an admin branch, and you
want other people to be able
to work on it.
You're going to need to be
able to push that branch
remotely so other people can
pull it down and work on it,
and continue working on
until it's ready to
merge back into master.
Also, it's good practice, if
you're working on a branch
that's going to last longer than
the day you might want to
back it up.
And you can back it up of course
by making it a remote
branch and pushing
it to GitHub.
In our case, we want to start
working on a shopping cart.
So we create a
shopping_cart branch.
And then to push it to GitHub,
we run git push origin
shopping_cart.
So that is going to link the
local branch to the remote
branch and start tracking it.
Then maybe we'll get some
work done on the branch.
We'll add the cart, we'll do
commit, and then when we do
push because it is a tracking
branch, it knows to push the
local shopping_cart branch
to the remote
shopping_cart branch.
If we jump back over to GitHub
now and click that button
right there we're going to see
a list of all the branches,
all the remote branches,
right here.
We can click on shopping_cart
and we can see the last commit
of the shopping_cart branch
and all the files.
So we created a branch, we
push it up to GitHub.
And then maybe I tell my
co-worker, hey Jane, I started
the remote branch for
shopping cart stuff.
If you want to work on it,
go ahead and grab it.
So do things look like from
Jane's perspective?
Well the next time she does a
pull, it's going to show her
on the output that we have a
new remote branch called
shopping_cart.
If she does git branch, she's
not going to see it as a local
branch yet, but if she does git
branch -r, she's going to
be able to see all the
remote branches.
She's going to run git checkout
shopping_cart, to
start working on the branch.
And it's automatically set up
as a tracking remote branch.
So from here she can her changes
and when she's done,
she can git push to that
remote branch.
One of the most useful commands
for working with
remote branches is the git
remote show command.
And so then origin, of course,
is our remote name.
So this is going to show us all
of our remote branches and
whether they're tracked
or not.
It'll show us all the local
branches and which remote
branches they merge with.
And lastly, it will show us
all the local branches
configured for when
we do a git push.
The cool part about this is it
even goes out to the server
and checks to see if
any of our local
branches are out of date.
In which case here, we can
see that our shopping
cart is out of date.
Remote branches, like local
branches, don't last forever.
You might get done
with a feature.
To delete the remote branch
you're going to run git push
origin colon, and then
the branch name.
This is only going to delete
the remote branch though.
You're still going to
have a local branch
for shopping_cart.
So we're also going to want to
delete that so we run git
branch -d shopping_cart.
Uh, oh, it's not letting
us delete that branch.
It says that there's some
commits that we
haven't merged anywhere.
It's a cool feature of Git.
If you try to delete a branch
and there's commits that
haven't been merged anywhere,
it's going to say hey, you're
deleting changes that
you might want.
So it gives you a warning.
But if you really do want to
delete the branch you can do
capital D, and it
will delete it.
So Jane is the one who deleted
the remote commit, but Gregg
is the one that created
it in the first place.
So what happens when he tries
to push to that remote that
doesn't exist anymore.
Let's take a look.
So Gregg is working
on that branch.
He commits something, then
he tries to do a push.
Nothing happens because the
remote doesn't exist.
Locally, it's just
a remote branch.
To figure out what's going on
Gregg might run git remote
show origin.
Here he's going to see that
look, that shopping_cart
branch is stale.
Somebody deleted it, OK.
To remove that reference, he's
going to want to run git
remote prune origin just as it
says and it'll clean up all
the old, stale branches.
This command is something you
probably want to run every
once in awhile if you're on a
large project that a lot of
remote branches that get
deleted at some point.
It's going to remove all of
those stale references.
Let's say one of our remote
branches is a
Heroku staging server.
We called it Heroku staging.
The thing about Heroku is that
it only deploys the branch,
which is named master.
So if we have, let's say a
staging branch, and we do a
git push Heroku staging staging,
it's going to try to
push a remote branch called
staging and nothing's going to
get deployed because as I
mentioned a minute ago, Heroku
only looks for the
master branch.
It only deploys from
the master branch.
In this case we would
run git push Heroku
staging staging master.
What that's going to do is
link up our local staging
branch to the remote Heroku
master branch.
So when we push to it, it's
going to push from staging to
master and deploy.
So now that we've talked about
remote branches we're going to
talk a little bit about tags
before we go on to the
challenges.
Tags are basically a reference
to a specific commit.
It's a good way to jump back to
that state of what the code
was in any given time.
A lot of people use it for
release versioning.
So when we have our code in a
good state, we might tag it
version 0.1.
So to list out all the tags,
we can do git tags.
To check out that tag and go
back to what the code looked
like when we tagged it we
do git checkout, and
then the tag name.
To add a new tag, we can simply
do git tag -a, add the
tag name and then give
a tag description.
And lastly, to push our tags
we actually have to specify
push --tags, and that will
push it to a remote.
Otherwise, the tags
will remain local.
Now if we go back over to GitHub
and click the branch
button you're going to see
that there is a tags tab.
If we click that we're going to
see a list of the tags for
our current repository.
We can click one and then we're
brought to a page where
we can see the state that
our code was and
when we tagged it.
All right, we've reach the
end of Level Five.
It's time for you to push
some remote branches
and make some tags.
[MUSIC PLAYING]