Git, a distributed source
control repository.
I tried to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system. Were
the commit messages like
history books?
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day: Git Real.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
This is Git Real.
You made it to the
final level.
We're going to talk about
history and configuration.
In the previous levels we've
used git log repeatedly to see
a list of our recent commits.
Those commits usually include
the SHA hash, and then the
author, the date, and
the commit message.
The output from log is not
usually the most easy thing to
read, so we're going to go
over a couple of ways to
improve the output.
The first thing you should do if
you haven't already done it
is to turn UI colors to true.
It will emphasize your commit
hash every single time.
You can also format the output
for the log differently.
So if you pass in git log
--pretty=oneline, it will
display one commit per line with
the SHA at the beginning
and the commit message
right after.
Even better, you can format the
output of the log exactly
how you want it by
using format.
You can use a bunch of place
holders to organize the output
at each commit in your log.
If you want look at what each
commit changed in the log
output, you can use the git log
--oneline -p for patch output.
And that will show you what
lines were removed and what
lines were added for
the files that were
modified during each commit.
git log --oneline --stat will
show you how many insertions
and deletions were made
for each file
included in each commit.
If we use the graph option,
we'll get a visual
representation of the branches
and the commits on so that
maybe you can see your
merge bubbles.
It's not always useful to
have the entire log
history right there.
So what you can do is specify a
range between a certain date
and another date where you
want to see the log.
You can also limit the log
output based on time using
flags like until 1 minute ago,
since 1 day ago, since 2 weeks
ago, or between a month ago
and until 2 weeks ago.
As you saw previously, git diff
can be really useful to
see what has changed since
our last commit.
You can see the remove lines
and the added lines in the
files that were included.
git diff HEAD does exactly the
same thing as git diff.
If you want to see the
difference between the files
now and 2 or 3 or 5 commits
ago, diff gives you the
following commands to do that.
You can also compare two
different commits such as the
second most recent against
the most recent.
If you remember those commit
SHAs that we saw in the log
you can use those as well to
compare between 2 commits
specifically by naming
the SHAs.
Sometimes you'll see these SHA
hashes abbreviated on places
like GitHub.
You can also use these
abbreviated SHAs to run diffs,
and you can also use branches
to run diffs.
So for instance, you could say
git diff master bird if you
had a bird branch you wanted
to compare against.
Finally, like git log, you
can use time-based
ranges for git diffs.
When projects go on for a
while sometimes you come
across a change that has been
made in the file that you
really can't understand.
And a good tool for
that is git blame.
You can run git blame and file
name to see all of the changes
on each line and who made them
when, and which commit created
that change.
So let's move on to some more
advanced configurations.
There may come a time in a
project when you need to work
on a specific folder, but you
don't want to include this
folder inside your repository
and share it
with your other coworkers.
In this case we have an
experiments folder that we
want to exclude from our
local repo, but not
exclude from elsewhere.
What we can do is put that
experiments folder inside of
the git info exclude file.
Put the name of that folder in
there and when you run git
status, you won't see
that folder anymore.
You can also use exclusion
patterns in that file.
You can specifically exclude the
tutorial.mp4 file or all
files that have the
mp4 extension.
You can exclude a whole
folder like we saw.
You can also exclude
every log file
inside of the log directory.
Speaking of logs, nobody should
ever include log files
inside of a repository.
Why?
Because they always change
differently depending on who's
using the application.
So what you want to do is use
instead of an exclude, a git
ignore file which will ignore
all log files not in your
local repository, but also
for everybody else.
So here we have a server log
file that we want to not have
in our repository.
We're going to put log slash
star.log so that any log file
in that logs folder will
never get included.
And then we'll run git status.
As you can see, there's no log
files showing anymore.
And then commit that.
One thing we haven't covered up
until now is how to remove
a file from your repository.
So you can use the git rm
command and then pass it a
file or folder.
If you do git rm readme, it will
remove your readme and
then add that change
to the stage.
And you simply can commit,
remove readme and that file
will now disappear.
But in the case of log files,
if you were already tracking
the file, you don't
want to delete it
from your file system.
All you want to do is tell Git
stop caring about the file,
stop tracking it.
To do that you can use a git
rm --cached which will stop
watching for changes, stop
tracking a file.
After that, if you do git
status, you'll see that it's
deleted the same way, but it
won't be deleted from your
file system.
And after you've un-tracked that
log file, you can do the
same git ignore and commit
and no more log
files will be tracked.
In Level One we saw some basic
configuration for the
user and the email.
Let's look at more configuration
details
that you can have.
You can configure a specific
merge tool if you want to see
merge conflicts in
a better way.
There's also a very useful
feature if you're working with
Windows or Unix systems that
will convert files to the
Windows or Unix formats once
they're committed.
Then when you run config --list,
you'll see your global
email first and then the email
specifier for this repository
second, which overrides
the previous one.
You can verify this by running
git config user.email inside
of your repository and it will
show you which email is set
for this repository.
Then it will show you which
email it's currently using.
If you remember the log formats
we went over in the
beginning of this level, there's
a bunch of really
tricky options you
can pass to them.
And it's really hard to remember
that all the time.
What you can do though is create
an alias to these log
output formats.
So for instance, you would use
a special my log format that
triggers log pretty format
and has a custom format.
Another popular output format
for git log is the lol format
which will show you a graphical
output, like we saw before.
Here we have a my log format
that gives us a nice output
without having to pass
any options.
You'll notice as you use Git
every day that the same
commands keep coming up
over and over again.
You use git status, you use
git checkout, you use git
branch and commit.
But you can alias those commands
to shorter ones by
doing the following.
So now if we simply type
git st, we can see
the git status output.
So that's it for level seven,
you have the last stretch of
challenges ahead of you
and we'll see you guys
in the wrap up video.
[MUSIC PLAYING]