Git, a distributed source
control repository.
I tried to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system. Were
they commit messages like
history books?
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day: Git Real.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Git Real.
I'm Olivier Lacan.
This is Level 3.
We're going to talk about
Cloning and Branching.
So in Level 2, we saw that
Gregg pushed the
repository to GitHub.
And now a new coworker called
Jane needs to get those files.
She will ask something like,
where do I get those files?
And Gregg is going to simply
say to her, just clone the
repository.
How do you do that?
If you're using something like
GitHub, you would go to the
repository, get the URL that
you saw for the repo.
So you go back to your command
line, type in git clone, that
URL, and it will create a local
directory with that
repository.
It will be called the
name that the
repository was called.
If you want to change that name
to something else, you
can say the same thing, git
clone, URL, and pass in a name
like git demo.
The first thing that git clone
does is download the
repository.
The second thing it does is
create a remote called origin
and point it to the URL
we passed it to.
We can check that by simply
running git remote -v. And it
would list all the remotes, so
you will see origin and any
URL that we passed it to.
And finally, it will check out
the initial branch, likely
master, and set the branch right
there and set the HEAD.
So Jane is all set up, but
she wants to start
working on a feature.
To do that it's best
to create a branch.
So we're going to create
a branch called cat.
git branch cat, will
create that branch.
But if we check with git branch,
we can see we're still
on the master branch.
To move to the cat branch, we're
going to need to git
checkout cat.
When we're doing that, what
we're actually doing is
switching timelines.
We're not in the master
timeline anymore.
We're in a different timeline.
We can do whatever we want and
then move back onto master
whatever we need to.
We're going to run this command
right here and what it
does is create a cat.txt file,
and inside of it, put the word
Schrodinger.
Then we're going to add it to
the stage, commit it, and put
a commit message like "Create
quantum cat." And this commit
will be added to our cat
timeline, not to our master
branch, but to our cat branch.
If we run ls command to list all
the files in the current
directory, you will see that
we have the readme.txt file
that Gregg created, and
this cat.txt file
that we just created.
Now if we move back to master
using git checkout master and
do the same command, we can't
see any cat.txt file.
It's not there, it does not
exist in this timeline.
Now if we run git log, same
thing, no commit.
That "Create quantum cat"
commit is not there.
Just to make sure we're not
crazy, if we move back to the
cat branch and do the ls command
again, the cat.txt
file is still there,
we're not crazy.
So let's assume we're done with
that feature branch
now, the cat branch.
We're going to go back to
master, git checkout master.
And now it's time to merge
those two timelines.
It sounds really fancy, but
it's actually quite easy.
git merge cat.
Now that we're on master, git
will merge the cat branch into
it and it will tell us that
it fast forwarded.
It will say fast forward.
What does that mean?
So when we create a branch and
make one commit, or several,
and we do nothing on the other
branch, it's very easy for Git
to merge the cat branch back
into master because nothing
was modified on master
in the meantime.
And now that we're done, we
can safely delete the cat
branch by running git
branch, -d cat.
And Git will show it that
it actually did that.
Our next assignment is to work
on the admin features for our
application.
So we need to create another
branch to work on those.
To do that we're going to use a
shortcut by simply doing git
checkout -b admin.
The -b over there creates a
branch and then checks it out.
Now we'll do a bunch of
changes, like create a
dashboard.html file, add it to
the stage and commit it.
Add a users.html file
and commit it also.
And as you can see on this
graphic over here, every time
we do a commit, our HEAD
moves with it.
So there we are working on the
admin branch and we get a late
night text message from our boss
saying oh, there are bugs
on master, you need
to fix them.
So we have to stop what we're
doing, git checkout master.
We can run git branch
to make sure that we
are actually on master.
And then we're going to pull
from the remote repository to
make sure that we have
the latest changes.
Then we're going to do our fixes
by fixing the store.rb
and product.rb files.
And finally, we're going to push
those changes back up to
the master remote.
Now that the emergency has been
taken care of, it's time
to move back to our
feature branch.
So we go git checkout admin.
So we finish off our changes.
git checkout master when we're
ready to merge things back
into master, and get
merge admin.
And suddenly, you're
in a weird editor.
Don't panic, this is Vi.
You may have seen this before,
but just in case here are
commands at the bottom of the
screen to navigate around Vi.
It's simply Git asking you OK, I
made this commit message for
you because I've seen what
you're trying to do, you're
trying to merge those
two branches.
But if you need to be more
explicit, please add to this
message at the top.
As you can see it wrote
merge branch admin.
You can modify this message
if you want to.
And then when you're done, type
colon w for write, and q
for quit to go back to
your command line.
Since we merged two branches
with two sets of changes, Git
had to do a recursive merge.
When that happens Git creates a
commit right there when the
branches are melded
back together.
If you look at your log, you
will see that that merge
commit was actually created
in the log.
It doesn't contain any files,
but it simply says at this
point, master and admin
became one branch.
Thanks for watching
Level Three.
Now it's time for you to go play
with branches and merging
in the challenges.