Git, a distributed source
control repository.
I tried to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system.
Were the commit messages
like history books?
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day: Git Real.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Level
One of Git Real.
I'm Gregg Pollack, and in this
level, we're going to go over
some of the real basics
of using Git.
So if you're already familiar
with these basics, maybe you
did tryGit, feel free to skip
over the video and go straight
to the challenges.
The first time I got a gig
working with the web it was
pretty typical.
So there I was, first
day on the job and I
needed to edit a website.
I was told to FTP the file down,
make changes locally,
and FTP them back up which works
fine until you find out
there is somebody else who is
also working on a project.
And at times they may pull
down the same file, make
changes, and you both may try
to upload and override each
other's changes.
And it's a big mess.
This is where you might need
a version control system.
So what is a source control
repository and what
does it do for you?
Well the first thing it does is
it deals with these sort of
situations where you have two
different people working on
the same file, and you both
check in that same file, it
will try to merge that
file for you.
The second and more important
thing is that it works as a
time capsule.
So over time as you make changes
to files and you check
them into your source control,
it keeps a time log so that
you've got a complete history
of all the files that have
changed and even why
they changed.
You can see these are
all the different
versions in version control.
Up until recently, most version
control systems used a
centralized repository.
What this means is that you have
multiple people and when
they make changes and they make
commits and store that
history, it's all
going to central
repository, one server.
Some version control systems
like Git are distributed.
This means that everybody has
a complete copy of the repo.
The nice thing about this is
that you can make commits
really quickly.
You can work on it offline,
and everybody
has a complete copy.
That way if one gets destroyed,
everybody has a
copy of the repo.
Unlike working with a
centralized repository, if you
lose all your backups and
your server goes down,
you are out of luck.
So now what it means when we
called Git a distributed
version control system,
or DVCS.
Git was created by Linus
Torvalds, when he was working
on the Linux operating system
and he lost access to the
proprietary version control
system he was using.
He wanted to create something
new, something that was fast,
that's distributed, and was good
with working with large
code bases, like Linux.
Most people work with Git
on the command line.
So in this course we're going
to be teaching all of the
command line tools.
That being said, there's still
a lot of graphical user
interfaces that you
can check out.
And if you want to install Git
or download some of those
GUIs, you can go over
to git-scm.com.
Like most command line tools,
Git comes with a help system.
So if you ever get stuck,
you can run git help.
It'll give you a list
of the commands.
And then if you want to get more
specific, you can type
git help and then the command
you need more information
about and it'll have pretty
good documentation.
Your first step when you install
Git is to set some
basic configuration.
You're going to want to set your
username, your user email
because what good is filling a
commit with awesome code if
you can't take some credit
for it, right?
And we're going to run one
last command to get some
pretty colors on the output
of our command line.
So you've installed Git and
you're ready to work on your
first repository.
We're going to need a directory,
so let's create a
directory if we haven't.
We're going to go into
that directory.
We can work on some files at
this point, and we're ready to
start the repository, we
simply type git init.
This is going to create a
local Git repo for us.
It's not up on any server,
it's local.
It's actually stored in that
.git hidden directory.
You're never going to need to go
in to that directory, just
know that's where
it's all stored.
Let's start working with Git.
And we're going to talk about
our workflow before we get
into commands.
So Jane, our user here, is going
to create a readme file.
That readme starts
out as untracked.
When we're ready to start
tracking that file we're first
going to add it to
a staging area.
We're getting ready to
take a snapshot.
Then, we're going to create
our first commit.
And a commit is like taking a
snapshot of those files that
we put on the stage.
We then might work in our
project more, maybe we modify
the readme and add a license.
We're going to add those files
to the staging area and make
another commit.
So this is the workflow
for Git.
You do a little bit
of work, you stage
it, you make a commit.
Let's jump into the commands.
One of the most important
commands with Git is the git
status command.
This is going to tell
you what has changed
since your last commit.
So we've run git status, we
don't have any commits yet.
It's going to tell us that we
have one newly created file
that's not being tracked.
To start tracking it we
first need to add it
to the staging area.
We do that using the git add
command doing git add README.
And if we do another git status
at this point, we're
going to see that this file is
now ready to be committed,
it's currently staged.
Now we're ready to make
our first commit.
We do this by running git
commit -m, and then we
describe what these
changes do.
So in this case, create
a readme.
When we run that command this
creates our first commit which
takes a snapshot of the stage.
And that gets added
to our timeline.
If we run git status at this
point we can see that there's
nothing else to commit, there's
no other changes or
files that we've modified that
we haven't committed yet.
Git status also tells us that
we are on branch master.
All you have to understand here
is that we've got one
main timeline at this
point and we're
going to call it master.
We'll get more into branches
on Level Three.
Now we're going to do some
work on some files.
We're going to modify the readme
and add a license.
Now if we run git status, we're
going to see that our
tracked file, readme,
has been modified.
It's keeping an eye
on that file so it
knows it has been modified.
And we have a new file we need
to add that's not tracked
called license.
We want to commit both these
file so we need to add them
both to the staging area.
We can do this by simply
doing git add, and
listing both of the files.
Or we can do git add --all,
which will add up all new,
modified, or deleted
files to our stage.
Now if we run git status again,
we're going to see we
have two files that are
ready to be committed.
So from here, we need to go back
and do another commit.
So here you can see we
do git commit -m.
Now we can commit our changes
off of the stage and specify
what the commit does,
in this case, add
license and finish readme.
This is going to create a
snapshot and add a commit to
the top of our timeline.
Now we have two commits, but
how do we list from the
command line what those are?
How do we look at the history?
That's where the git log
command comes in.
So if we run it here we can see
we have our two commits
listing the author, the date,
and our commit message.
As you can imagine when you're
working on a larger project,
commit messages are very,
very important.
And so you want to try to be as
descriptive as possible as
to what they do.
Plus it's good to keep
in the present tense,
not the past tense.
I could've said created
a readme file.
It might be tempting to do that,
but what you want to do
is think about what
the commit does.
In this case, create a readme.
Now we're going to go over some
different ways to use the
add command.
As you saw you can simply
list out files.
You can use git add --all.
git add *.txt will add
all the text files
in the current directory.
If we want, we can specify
a directory
like docs/*.txt.
We can also add all the files
in a specific directory and
all of its sub-directories
by doing git add docs.
And lastly, if you put quotes
around *.txt, it's going to
go add all the txt files
in the entire project.
You've reached the
end of Level One.
It's time to start
running your own
commands and Git Real.