Git, a distributed source
control repository.
I tred to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system. Were
the commit messages like
history books?
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day: Git Real.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Git Real.
And this is Level Four, where
we're going to be going over
some collaboration scenarios.
What happens when things don't
go as smoothly as Olivier
showed you in the
previous level.
So here we have Gregg,
he pushes up his
source code to github.
And Jane of course
wants a copy.
As we saw, Jane is going to
clone his copy off of github
and then she's going to want
to add some changes.
So let's continue down
that timeline.
So she adds some changes.
You can see there's
two new files.
We do a git add --all,
to add those files.
And then add store and
product models.
Then she pushes up to
github when she's
done making her changes.
And her commit is going to be
represented by that little
pink commit down there.
Now let's jump back
over to Gregg.
See Gregg is also working at
the same time as Jane, and
Greg makes a commit, basically
adds a change to the readme.
So now we have Jane's commit
which is sitting up on github
and Greg's local commit which
is sitting on his local
repository, and they
are different.
So what do we do
at this point?
If Gregg tries to push to github
at this point, well
he's going to be rejected
because as you can see here,
the tip of his current branch
is behind the remote branch.
So what we'd have to do here is
we could simply do a pull
first, and then a push,
and it would work.
It's important that we know
what's going on under the hood
when we run this pull command.
So the first thing that pull
does, is it fetches or syncs
our local repository from
the remote one.
It's the same thing as doing
a git fetch command.
So in this case, it's going to
copy down Jane's commit into
our local repo.
However it's not actually going
to update any of our
local code.
If we looked under the covers
here we will see that in our
local repo, we actually have a
branch called origin master.
That's our remote branch.
And now the second step with
pull is that it merges the
origin master with master.
It's the same thing as running
git merge origin master.
So like you saw with the
previous level, when we try to
do a merge for two different
branches that have different
commits, it's going to pop us
straight into an editor where
we have to create
a merge commit.
In this case, our message says
that it's merging branch
master from the remote
repository.
Once we save from the editor
it's going to give us some
output from the pull command
and tell us that it did a
recursive merge.
If we look back at the time line
we're going to see that
we had two branches, and they
merged on the merge commit.
You might notice here though
that we have our local master
still has that merge commit, but
the origin master doesn't
yet know about Gregg's change
and about the merge commit.
And it's not going to know about
it until we do git push.
At that point, origin master
points to the same master
branch and everything's
been updated.
And now if we check the
log we can see,
there's our merge commit.
Now some people aren't big
fans of merge commits.
Some people think they pollute
our repository, pollute our
history because if you have a
lot of collaborators, you
might have 10 things that
changed and maybe three or
four of them are the
merge commits.
It can start to get
pretty sloppy.
And in a later level, we're
going to be talking about
rebase, which is one
way to get around
doing these merge commits.
But for now, let's move on
to another scenario.
So Gregg and Jane, once again,
are working on the same code
at the same time except this
time they happen to be working
on the same file,
the same readme.
Gregg thinks that cake is a lie
and Jane thinks that cake
is telling the truth.
And they both edited
that same file.
Jane committed her changes and
pushed to github and Gregg
committed locally.
So now you can see that we
still have two different
commits, but they're
on the same file.
What's going to happen now?
So when Gregg does a pull
it does two things.
Remember it syncs the
repository, pulls down the
changes, pulls down
Jane's commit and
then it tries to merge.
But the merge was
not successful.
We have a conflict.
It tells us there is a
conflict in readme.
So we're going to have to edit
that readme since it spit us
back out on the command line.
If we do a status, we can see
that well, we have to edit
this file and then make
a merge commit.
So if we jump into the readme
at this point we're going to
see what looks like a diff.
Inside this diff, it has our
local version, that's the
head, and we have
Jane's version.
We're going to need to edit this
file manually to fix it.
So we're going to delete all the
extra text and make it so
that the cake is a lie because
that's what we think--
well it is a lie.
And then we call git
commit -a.
We're going to leave off the
message because it's going to
boot us back into an editor.
It'll give us a good commit
message, and even list the
conflicted files
that we fixed.
Once we've saved that, our tree
again look something like
this with our merge commit.
And once we push, once again
the origin master syncs up
with our local master.
So we've reached the end of
Level Four and now you know a
little bit more about merge
commits and conflicts.
And it's time for you to resolve
some of your own
conflicts in the challenges.