Git, a distributed source
control repository.
I tried to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system where
the commit message like
history books.
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day: Git Real.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Git Real and
this is Level Two where we're
going to be talking about
staging and remotes.
So let's say you're in your
local repo and you made a
change to a file, but you
don't remember what that
change was, like for example
the license file here.
To figure out what that
change was you can run
the git diff command.
You're going to see here that
it's going to show you
unstaged differences since
the last commit.
In the red you can see the line
that was removed and in
the green, the line
that was added.
The diffs here in the command
line aren't that
understandable.
Luckily there are tools to make
it easier to read, which
we'll go over in the outro
in the very end.
But let's go ahead and add that
license file to our stage.
Once we've added it to our
stage, if we run git diff
again, well nothing's going to
print out because there's no
differences since all the
changes have been staged.
If we do want to get a diff on
all of our stage changes, we
can run git diff --staged,
and we'll get the same
output that we did before.
So if we do get status right now
we're going to see that we
have that one license file
that's staged and
ready to get committed.
But what if we staged
stuff that we
didn't mean to get staged?
Because keep in mind, you might
have a lot of modified
files and you might want to take
two of them and do then
on one commit and take two more
files and do it on the
next commit.
So how do we get things
off the stage?
Well you'll notice in this git
status output, it says use
git, reset, HEAD, and then
the file name to unstage.
Then when we run the command
you can see it says that we
unstaged license.
You might be wondering what that
HEAD command is there.
Well HEAD refers to our last
commit on the current branch,
or timeline that we're on.
Now if we run git status we're
going to see that the license
file is not on the stage,
but it still has its
modifications.
But what if we change our mind
and we don't want those
modifications?
What if we want to reset it to
the state that that file was
in at the last commit, or the
last time it was changed?
Well we can do that by doing git
checkout, -- ,
then the file name.
So if we do that and we run git
status again, we're going
to see that the file has
been restored to
its previous state.
Now let's go ahead and make a
change to the readme talking
about how the cake is a lie.
If we wanted to commit this
change, we'd have to add it
and then commit it.
Well there's a shortcut.
We can run git commit,
-a, -m,
on the commit message.
What this is going to do is it's
going to add any of our
tracked files to the stage
and then commit them.
Now the caveat here is that
it's not going to add any
files that we're not tracking.
So if I've created a new file
and ran this command, well
it's not going to be included
in the commit.
There's going to be a time when
you're running Git where
you're going to make you commit
and then you're going
to instantly regret it because
you probably forgot to add a
file or make some sort of
modification that you wanted
to be included.
How do you deal with that?
Luckily we have this git reset
command you see here which
will undo the last commit and
move everything from that
commit back into staging.
So that HEAD command you see
there with the little carrot,
what that's saying is move to
the commit one before the
current HEAD.
So now if you run git status you
can see that our changes
from that commit
are now staged.
I can make changes, add files
if I want to and recommit.
Another way to modify commit
is to use the amend option.
So if we wanted to add that
todo.txt file to our last
commit, we could simply add it
to the stage and then do git
commit --amend, which
is going to add it to
last commit.
And then if we want, we can
even specify a new commit
message which is going
to override our
previous commit message.
Here are the two commands
we just went over.
You've got git reset
which will roll
back the last commit.
And then you have git commit
amend which will add things to
the last commit.
There's two more that you
should know about.
If you want to do git reset,
hard HEAD, that's going to
blow away the last commit.
So if you went horribly wrong
and you want to blow it away,
you run hard HEAD.
And then if you want to
undo the last commits?
Well, you add another carrot
on to the end.
So that's saying blow away the
last two commits before the
current HEAD.
So up until now, we've been
working with our own local
repository on our computer,
but how do we push that
repository up to other people so
they can contribute to it?
Well that's where the push and
pull command comes in.
So here I am in my local master,
I can push that to a
remote repository and then other
people can pull that
repository down and start
making changes.
And then when they're
done, they can push
back up their changes.
When we're dealing with remote
repositories it's all about
the git remote command
which we'll be
going into in a minute.
The other thing worth mentioning
is that Git doesn't
take care of access
control for you.
It doesn't allow you to say,
just these people have access
to this repository, and just
this group of people have
access to this one.
That's where you are going to
need some additional software.
You are either might want to
use a hosted solution like
GitHub or BitBucket so
they take care of
access control for you.
Or if you want to roll your
own, you can use something
like Gitosis or Gitorious and
they take care of access
control and all that
configuration.
If we wanted to store our
repository on GitHub, we would
create a GitHub account and
then we'd create a new
repository on GitHub.
It would give us a form
that looks like this.
We would specify a name of that
repository and specify a
couple options.
Then once we create it, GitHub
is going to give us a URL.
To push to GitHub we're first
going to have to run Git,
remote, add, origin.
Origin is the name
of the remote.
We could give it any name, but
usually we refer to our
canonical repository, our
official repository that most
of our people are using for
our project, as origin.
So origin is what we're
going to call it.
And then we specify the URL
that GitHub gave us.
To get a list of all the remotes
that our local the
repository knows about, we can
simply run git remote -v.
Now we haven't actually
pushed our repository.
These remotes are
like bookmarks.
We are bookmarking that this
origin refers to this URL, we
might have multiple repos.
Now if we want to push our
repository we simply run git
push, specify the remote
repository name which of
course the origin, and the local
branch we want to push
there, which is master.
Since we're are using GitHub,
it's going to ask for our
GitHub username and password to
authorize us to push to the
GitHub remote.
Now if you don't want to enter
in your username and password
every time you push, you're
going to want to follow this
link down here at the bottom
which talks about password
caching so you only
have to do once.
So we've pushed our local
repository up to GitHub and
now if we go back into our
browser and refresh, we're
going to see that GitHub now
knows about our repository and
all the data in it.
On this page you'll notice
there's a commit button, also
a history button.
If we put those, we actually get
the same information that
we got previously
from git log.
We can view all the different
commits inside our repo.
So we've pushed our repo
up to GitHub, but how
do we pull it down?
How do we pull down
from a remote?
Well that's where they git
pull command comes in.
That's what you're going to want
to run when you know that
other people have made changes,
you're not the only
person working on the project,
and you want
to get their changes.
You run git pull.
It will go up to GitHub, it'll
pull down your changes and
sync up your local repository.
So we GitHub as our canonical
remote called origin, but it's
not uncommon to have multiple
remotes with a project.
We might have a test server that
runs our test for us that
we occasionally want to push
our repo over there.
We might have a hosting
provider that has our
production code it and we might
want to push our repo
onto our production server
so it can host the code.
As we saw before, to add a new
remote you use this syntax,
git remote, add, specify a name,
it can be any name, and
then the address.
To remove remotes we simply
do git, remote, rm,
and then the name.
And lastly, to push our
repository to remotes, we run
git, push, -u,
and specify the
name and the branch.
You might be wondering what
this -u option does?
Basically it makes it so the
next time run git push, you
don't have to specify the
name and the branch.
You can run git push.
Lastly, I want to talk about
Heroku, a hosting platform and
the way they use remotes.
So if you have a Heroku account
and you install the
Heroku gem, and you're working
on your code and you type
heroku create, you can see it
does a couple things for you.
One of which it gives you
a git repo ssh address.
Now before, we were using a
URL, GitHub gave us a URL.
Well a lot of times when you're
working with git repos,
you might instead have
a ssh address.
As you can see here, Heroku
already added a remote for us.
It called the remote heroku.
And now if we want to push our
code for Heroku, we simply
write git, push,
heroku master.
That's going to push our local
repository to Heroku.
And when Heroku gets the code,
it's going to deploy it.
One last thing before we finish
Level Two, remember
these commands where
you can roll back
commits, blow away commits?
Well you only want to run them
before you've pushed those
commits, right?
Because if you have some commits
and you push, and then
you change them locally, it's
like you're changing history
and as we all know, that's
a very dangerous
thing, so don't do it.
It's time for you to get into
the challenges and Git Real
once again.
[MUSIC PLAYING]