Git.
A distributed source
control repository.
I tried to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system.
Were the commit messages
like history books?
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day: Git Real.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Git Real, and
this is level six, where we're
going to be talking
about rebase.
So you remember in previous
levels, we talked about merge
commits not being so great.
You've got merge commits from
local branches, merge commits
from remote branches.
And it might seem like it's
polluting your history.
That's not so good.
But there's an alternative to
doing these sort of merges
with merge commits, and
that's called rebase.
So let's jump back into the
scenario we were at before,
where we have Jane's commit up
on GitHub, which is different
than Gregg's commit
that's on local.
So instead of doing pull and
push, we're going to do fetch,
and then rebase.
So if you remember when we do
fetch, that goes to GitHub and
pulls down any changes, but
doesn't merge them.
So if we took a look at our
current branch, it looks
something like this.
We have master and
origin master.
Git rebase does three things.
First, it's going to move all
changes to master, which are
not in origin master.
So it's going to take Gregg's
commit and move that to a
temporary area.
Then it's going to run all
of the origin master commits
one at a time.
So there it goes.
We've run that commit
on master.
And then third step, it's going
to run all the commits
in the temporary area on top of
our master one at a time.
So just like that.
Now as you notice, there's
no merge commits here.
It's just one after the
next, after the next.
Back in level three when we
first learned about local
branches, remember we had this
admin branch, and then we had
to go back and fix
some bugs on master.
And then we had to merge
the admin into master.
Well, how might we rebase
instead of doing merge?
Well, what we might do is first
check out the admin
branch, then run git
rebase master.
This is going to first run the
master commits, and that's
going to run our additional
admin commits.
Then the next step is to check
out the master branch, and
then merge from the admin
back into master.
All this is going to do is one
of those fast forwards that we
talked about.
So it's just going to run the
same commits one after the
next, after the next, and
we're good to go.
Even if we're running
rebase, we still
might run into conflict.
So let's take a look at a
scenario with a conflict.
As you can see here, up on
GitHub we have an extra
commit, as we do locally.
And those two extra commits
both modify
that same readme file.
OK.
So step one, we fetch
from GitHub.
Step two, we run git rebase.
That's going to take all of our
new commits from master,
and move them into
a temporary area.
Then it's going to run all of
the origin master commits.
And then finally, it's going to
run all of the commits in
the temporary area one at a
time, which of course is going
to lead to a conflict.
So here is what you see when
rebase runs into a conflict.
You can see it's asking us to
fix the merge conflict in
readme.txt, and when we resolve
the problem, run git
rebase --continue.
However, if we want to skip the
patch, we could run git
rebase skip.
Or if we want to roll back and
pretend we never rebased, we
can just do it git
rebase abort.
If we ran a git status, we would
see that we're not on
any particular branch.
We're in the middle
of the rebase.
So after we edit the readme,
we do git add readme.
Then we type git rebase
--continue, and it continues
applying the commits.
If we took a look at the commit
messages at this point,
it would look something
like this.
So once again, you can see there
is no merge conflict.
It's all just one after the
next, and feels a bit cleaner.
I'm not saying that rebase is
the answer all the time.
Sometimes you might want to
rebase, sometimes you might
want to merge.
If you're dealing with a branch
that's been around for
a long time and it has a lot of
changes, you probably want
to do a merge instead
of a rebase.
That way you know exactly when
it got merged back in, and you
have a log of everything that
got changed in that one merge
when it came over.
Yeah.
So it's time for you
to get your hands
dirty, and do some rebasing.