[MUSIC PLAYING, VIDEO
GAME EFFECTS]
Hi, I am Caike Souza,
and you're watching
Ruby Bits, part two.
In level one, we're going to be
looking at blocks, procs,
and lambdas.
You might remember back in part
one, where we showed you
that you can actually pass
around blocks of code between
curly braces or do/end end
blocks that gets executed
elsewhere, using the
yield function.
So we can see in this function
that, because we have the
yield function being called
twice, when we pass in a
block, that block will get
executed two times.
But what if we wanted to store
that block of code in a
variable and pass it along
for execution later.
While we can do that using
a proc object.
Now let's look at two
ways that we can
create a proc object.
First is by using Proc.new.
That will create an object
from the proc class.
And whatever we pass in, as a
block to the proc object, will
get executed once we invoke
the call function.
You can see here that the
Proc.new accepts both blocks
and curly braces or
do end blocks.
Another way that we can create
a proc object is by using the
keyword lambda.
Although they are technically
not the same thing, we'll
assume that they are for the
time being, since they respond
to the same interface, which
is the method call.
There's an alternate syntax
for creating lambdas,
available since Ruby
1.9, which is
called stabby lambdas.
And they look something
like this.
Yep, they're really called
stabby lambdas.
Now let's look at some example
code and see how we can
refactor it in order to
use proc objects.
Here, we can see a tweet class
with a post method.
First, the post method tries
to authenticate the user,
using the username
and password.
And if that succeeds, then it
yields to the block that was
passed to the method.
Otherwise, it will
raise an error.
So in order to invoke this
post method, we call the
method, passing in a block.
Another way to write this would
be to manually create a
proc object and pass it as an
argument to the post method.
That way, we can explicitly call
the proc object with call
instead of yield.
But if we wanted to pass in
multiple proc objects, for
example, to replace raising an
error with a proper error
handler proc.
First, let's create that
error proc and pass it
along to our method.
Then, all we have to do is
adjust our method signature to
accept that extra argument and
explicitly call it if the
authentication fails.
Sometimes you might need to
convert between proc objects
and blocks.
So let's look at a couple
of examples of
how you can do that.
Here, we have the tweets array
that we pass in a block to the
each method that prints
each of the tweets.
Now let's see how we
can extract that
bloc into a proc object.
Using the lambda keyword,
we assign it
to the printer variable.
And you might think that all
we have to do is pass along
the printer to the each.
However, that will raise an
error, because the each method
expects a block not
a proc object.
In order to fix that, we need
to prefix the parameter with
the ampersand, which will turn
the proc into a block.
And the code will work
as intended.
So there's two ways you can
use ampersand in Ruby to
convert between proc
objects and blocks.
The first one, which we just
saw, is turning a proc into a
block, by using the ampersand
before the argument on the
method call.
The second way is when you're
defining a method, then you're
going to want to use the
ampersand, if you want to turn
a block into a proc, so that
it can be assigned to a
parameter or executed later.
Often you're going to see these
two used together, so
let's take a look
at an example.
In this example, we have the
timeline class with a bunch of
tweets and an each method.
The each method, pretty much,
iterates through the tweets
and yields each of them
to the block.
In order to use this class, we
instantiate it, passing in a
bunch of tweets, then call the
each method, which will print
each of the tweets.
Another way we can write this
code is by passing the block
through the each method.
And the first thing that we
have to do is to use the
ampersand on the signature
of each method on
the timeline class.
That will turn the block
into a proc.
Then we'll use the block local
variable and pass it along to
the tweets.each method,
prefixing with the ampersand,
so that we can turn the proc
back into a block, which is
what the tweets.each method
is expecting.
Now let's look at another trick
that we can do with the
ampersand, which is turning a
symbol into a proc object.
Here we can see the tweets.map
takes in a block that iterates
over the tweets and calls
the user method
on each one of them.
There's a shorter way to do
that using symbol to proc,
which is basically using the
ampersand followed by the
symbol that corresponds to the
method being called on each of
the elements.
Now, you might be tempted to go
ahead and call methods on
the symbol.
However, this is not allowed.
Now let's take a look
at optional blocks.
Here, we have the same timeline
class where we're
sending in tweets.
So we want to be able to call
the print method without a
lock, like so, but also
with a block.
So how might we write
that in Ruby?
Let's look at the
print method.
Here, in the timeline class,
the print method uses the
block given method, which is
built into Ruby, and detects
if a block was passed
into the method.
If so, it's going to
yield each of the
tweets to the block.
Otherwise, it's going to join
the tweets with a comma
followed by a white space.
Often in Ruby, you're going to
see objects being instantiated
with a block.
One way we can do that is by
using the block given method
and optionally yielding the
object to the block in the
constructure.
One last thing I want to show
you is how proc objects create
closures, which means that they
keep the current state of
the local variables at the
moment that they were created.
In this example, we have the
tweet.as method that takes in
an argument and returns
a new proc object.
Now when we call the proc
object, all we have to pass in
is the tweet, because it
remembers the user.
We have just reached the
closure of level one.
So get your hands dirty on
some procs and lambdas.
And I'll see you on level two.