Welcome back.
We've learned a lot of advanced
Ruby techniques in
the first four levels of
Ruby that's Part 2.
And now we'd like to take the
next two levels to put all of
that together and build
a simple DSL.
First let's talk about
what a DSL is.
DSL stands for Domain Specific
Language, and it's a language
that has terminology and
constructs designed for a
specific domain.
If you're familiar with Rails,
ActiveRecord is a good
example of a DSL.
It's designed specifically to
allow you to describe how
objects are stored
in a database.
We can further categorize DSLs
into external DSLs and
internal DSLs.
An external DSL is
a standalone DSL.
If you're familiar with Cucumber
in the Ruby world,
that's a good example.
To implement an external DSL
requires a lot of work.
You have to build a parser and
a compiler or run time, so
we're not going to talk
about those here.
What we'll build in this course
is an internal DSL.
That's a DSL that's implemented
within another
programming language.
Turns out that Ruby
is really good at
building internal DSLs.
Let's see how we
might do that.
Our sample DSL will be for
posting tweets to Twitter and
we'll start out by designing
our DSL.
What we'll do is simply write
out some code to figure out
what our DSL might look like.
Our code has to be valid
Ruby syntax.
So we can use things like "do"
and "end" as we've done here.
And when we run our code, we'd
like it to output the tweet
that you see here.
Our first step to implement
our DSL is to define a
tweet_as method.
We see here that we need to be
able to call tweet_as with a
user and pass a block to it.
So we'll define our tweet_as
method, we'll save off the
user, we'll create an empty
array to hold the contents of
our tweet, and then we'll
yield to the block.
Once the block's done executing,
we'll call a method
that we haven't written yet
called submit_to_twitter.
Inside the block we have
several methods--
text, mention, hashtag
and link.
And they all do very
similar things.
They just take a string and they
add that content onto the
tweet that we're building up.
Now all that's left to
do is to define our
submit_to_twitter method.
All that's going to do is join
together the tweet content
separated by spaces and then,
for the purposes of this
example, print that content
out to the console.
So with that, we can execute
our DSL code.
And it'll work, but
it's not so great.
All these methods that we've
just written are in the global
name space and that's not really
a very good practice.
How can we clean that up?
First we'll create a tweet
class, and we'll move as many
of those methods into the
tweet class as we can.
In this case, submit_to_twitter,
text,
mention, hashtag, link have
all moved into the class.
They haven't changed their
implementations at all.
But we've added a new initialize
method in the tweet
to set the two instance
variables that we were adding
to the global name
space earlier.
Now in our tweet_as method, we
have to make a few changes.
First of all, we're creating
a new tweet object-- we're
passing that user into it.
We're yielding the tweet object,
and then we're calling
submit_to_twitter on the tweet
object once the block is done.
Notice that we've done
one thing here.
We've introduced a new
block parameter.
And so this is going to change
the syntax of our DSL just a
little bit.
Now the tweet has to be passed
into our block as a parameter,
and we have to specify tweet
dot in front of all the
methods inside the block.
So we've cleaned up our global
name space, but we've made our
DSL syntax ugly.
What can we do about that?
You might recall earlier when we
talked about instance_eval,
that we had an example
very similar to this.
So instead of using yield with
our block, let's capture the
block being passed in
to tweet_as, and use
instance_eval to execute the
block in the context of our
tweet object.
This allows us to remove that
blocked parameter and remove
the tweet dot in front of all
of our methods inside the
block, getting back to our
original clean syntax.
One last improvement we'd like
to make to the DSL is to allow
those methods that
we call inside of
our block to be chained.
You might have noticed that
all of those methods are
changing the state of the tweet,
but their return value
isn't really important.
All we have to do to implement
chaining is to take each of
those methods and return
self at the end.
This makes it so that when we
call the text method, the
tweet object gets returned.
And then we can call hashtag
or any of the other methods
directly on that return value.
So now it's time for you to go
through some challenges and
write a DSL of your own.
And then we'll come back in
Level 6 and extend our DSL
even further.