[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome back.
This is Ruby Bits part
two, level four.
And we're going to be talking
about missing methods.
Back in Ruby Bits part one,
we talked about hooks.
These are methods that Ruby
calls when certain events
happen in your program.
And the most important one of
these is method missing.
Ruby calls method missing any
time that you try to call a
method and it can't find it.
That gives us the opportunity
to respond to methods that
don't really exist.
Let's see how we
might do that.
Here we have a tweet class.
And we've just defined a simple
method missing method.
It takes the method name
and the arguments.
And all we're doing here is
we're printing out some text
to the console to let us know
that we tried to call a method
that didn't exist.
So if we create a new tweet and
then we try to call the
Submit method on it,
that doesn't exist.
And we'll see this output.
One way we might want to use
method missing is to print a
log message every time that
someone tries to call a method
in our class that
doesn't exist.
Here we're using a logger
to print out a
warning to a log file.
And then we're calling super,
which invokes Ruby's default
method missing handling.
And that'll raise a
no method error.
Another useful method missing
technique is to use it to
delegate methods to
another class.
Here we have a tweet
object with a user.
And we have defined methods
called username and avatar
that simply delegate to the
corresponding method names in
the user class.
Once we have more than a few of
these methods, it would be
nice to clean that up somehow.
We can do that with
method missing.
So what we've done here is to
define method missing in our
tweet class and then inside of
method missing, just use Send
to pass that same method
with the same
arguments on to our user.
Notice that this code will
delegate all missing methods
over to the user class.
So if the user class gets one
of those methods and doesn't
respond to it, its default
method missing handling will
raise a no method error.
Now you may be using this
technique, but you really
prefer to delegate just a few
methods to the user and not
just blindly delegate
them all.
We can do that by adding a
constant up at the top of our
class that lists our
delegated methods.
And then in our method missing,
we'll check to see if
the method name is
in that list.
If so, we'll do the delegation
that we were doing before.
And if not, we'll call super.
And that'll invoke the default
method missing handling, which
in most cases will raise
a no method error.
Just a side note-- this type of
delegation is pretty useful.
And so Ruby provides a Simple
Delegator class
that you can use.
Simply inherit from it, and it
will delegate all method calls
to some other object, unless
they're defined locally.
Let's take a look back at our
tweet class and see how we
might implement this code
using method missing.
What we have here
is a new tweet .
We'd like to be able to do as
with any method that starts
with hash underscore.
Let's see how we might
implement that.
Here's our tweet class.
And this time in our method
missing method, we're going to
match the method name against
a regular expression.
This one checks to make sure
that the method name starts
with hash and then underscore.
If it does, then we respond to
that method by adding the
appropriate hashtag
to our tweet.
If not, again, we call super
to get the default method
missing handling.
Another method that you'll
see used quite often in
conjunction with method
missing is respond_to.
This is a method that you can
call that returns true or
false and that tells you whether
or not a specific
object responds to
a given method.
In the case of our tweet
class, we can ask if it
responds to a method
called to_s.
And we defined that earlier,
so Ruby returns true.
We could also call our new hash
Ruby method on the tweet.
We know that works, because
we implemented
it with method missing.
But if we ask the tweet if it
responds_to hash_ruby, Ruby
says false.
And this is a lie.
So let's see if we can figure
out how to fix it.
The way to do that is
to provide a custom
implementation of respond_to
that matches what we've done
in method missing.
So in this case, we're taking
the method name.
We're checking against that same
regular expression to see
if the method name starts with
hash and then underscore.
If so, it will return true.
Otherwise, we call super, which
will return false in
cases where the method
doesn't exist.
So now we can ask our tweet if
it responds to hash Ruby.
And we get back true,
which is correct.
But there's still a problem,
because if we use the method
method that we learned about
earlier to try to get back a
method object for hash Ruby,
we get an exception.
Ruby 1.9.3 introduced a way
for us to get around this
problem as well.
If we implement respond_to_missing
instead of respond_to,
you'll see that the
implementation here is the same.
Then Ruby will return the proper
method object when we
try to look up the
dynamic method.
Let's take a look at one more
way that we can optimize the
code that we just wrote.
Here we're calling the method
hash_codeschool twice on the
same tweet object.
Every time we call
hash_codeschool it's going through the
method missing logic,
doing the match,
and some other things.
If it was really important for
us to optimize this and we
knew that hash_codeschool was
going to be called a lot of
times, we might want to actually
define that method
the first time that
we need it.
So let's do that.
In our method missing instead
of simply adding the hashtag
to the tweet, let's use define_method
to create a method name
hash_codeschool the first
time we need it.
You'll see that after we do that
we're also calling Send
to invoke the method
the first time.
Once we've done that one time,
the hash_codeschool method
exists on our tweet class.
And any additional times we call
it, Ruby will simply find
that method and invoke
it directly
instead of method missing.
It's time for you to go find
some missing methods with
these challenges, and we'll see
you back for level five.