Hi I'm Mark Kendall.
And you're watching
Ruby Bits, Part
Two.
This is level three,
"Understanding and Using
Self." So first let's take a
look at how Ruby sets the
value of Self as our
program executes.
We can do this just by printing
out Self at a few
different points
in our program.
We'll start by printing it out
before our class definition
and then after we open
our class definition.
And we can see that outside of
the class, Self is a special
object that Ruby creates
called Main.
So even when you're not in a
class, Ruby still has an
object that it's created
for you.
Inside of our class definition,
Self refers to the
Tweet class object.
So if we go one step further and
we create a Class method
on our Tweet class--
in this case self.find--
and we print out the value of
Self inside of there, we'll
see that, again, Self refers
to the Tweet class object.
So this gives us some insight
into how we define class
methods in Ruby and
how that works.
Inside of our Tweet class, when
we say def self.find,
Self is referring to that
Tweet class object.
So that's really equivalent
to saying def tweet.find.
And our new method gets defined
on the Tweet class.
Now using the class name to
define a class method, while
it works, isn't used
very often in Ruby.
So you'll see the self dot
syntax used a lot more
frequently.
So moving on, here we're
printing out the value of Self
inside of an Instance method,
the Initialize method for our
Tweet object.
Now when create a new Tweet,
we'll see printed out the
value of Self, which is
the Tweet instance
that we just created.
So why is it important to keep
track of the value of Self as
our code executes?
Well Ruby uses the value of Self
to figure out where to
call methods.
So if you try to call a method
without an explicit receiver,
without an object and a dot in
front of the method name, Ruby
tries to find that
method in Self.
So let's look at the code that
explains what this means.
Inside of our Tweet class,
the first line is an
attr_accessor.
That's actually just a method.
And Ruby's calling that method
on Self, which is the Tweet
class object.
Then, in Initialize method,
we're setting an Instance
variable, status.
And that Instance variable gets
set on Self, which is the
new instance of our
Tweet class.
And likewise, when we call a
method set_up_some_things,
that's being called on the
instance of our Tweet
So now that we understand a
little bit more about how Self
works in Ruby, let's look at
ways that we can change that
while our program executes.
The first of these is
class_eval, which is a method
that you can call
on any class.
And it takes a block and it sets
the value of Self for the
duration of that block, to the
class you called it on.
Let's see how that works.
Here we have a Tweet class
that has two attributes--
status and created at.
And we'd like to add a
third, for the user.
Instead of reopening the class
to add that new attr_accessor,
what we've done here is to call
class_eval on the Tweet
class, which sets the value of
Self to the Tweet class and
runs that block,
thus adding the
attr_accessor to the Tweet.
Now we can create a Tweet, and
we'll see that we have a user
attribute on that tweet
that we can set.
So let's look at a more
complicated example.
Here we'd like to create
a Method Logger class.
And here's how we'd
like to use it:
We'd like to be able to create
a Method Logger.
And then tell it to log a
method, given a class name and
a method name.
We'd like it to attach to that
method, and then print out some
logging information.
How might we implement that?
Before we write any code, let's
think about what this
Method Logger's going
to need to do.
We know that we need to write a
log_method method that takes
the class and the method name
that we're logging.
Inside of that, we're going to
use class_eval to execute some
code in the context
of the class.
We'll then use alias_method to
save off the old version of
the method that we're logging,
because we're about to
override it.
And then we'll use define_method
method to
override that method, and
log our method call.
And then use send to call the
original version of the method
that we had saved off.
So how might that
look in code?
So here in our Method Logger
class, we'll implement
log_method.
You'll notice it takes a class
and a method name.
You'll notice here that we've
spelled class with a "k."
That's because class
with a "c" is a
reserved keyword in Ruby.
And so the convention is
to use a "k" instead.
So first we use class_eval.
So now, inside of this block,
Self will be that class that
we're passing in.
And then we can modify that
class by using alias_method to
first save off the
original method.
And then use define_method
to redefine our
method that we're logging.
Inside of that, we're just
printing out the current time
and the method name.
And then we're using send to
call the original method that
we'd saved off earlier.
Now if we run the code that we
looked at earlier, we define
our Method Logger, we tell it
to log the say_hi method on
our Tweet class.
And then we create a new Tweet
instance and call say_hi.
We see our logging.
And then we see "hi" printed
out, because the original
version of the method is
also being called.
You may have noticed that our
Method Logger has one problem.
It only works for methods that
don't take any parameters and
don't take blocks.
Let's see if we can solve
that problem.
What we need to do is
capture the methods
arguments and its block.
Here we're using the Splat
operator to capture the
arguments in an array and the
ampersand to turn the block
into a proc.
That way we have a handle
to both of them.
And we can pass them on to send
when we call the original
version of the method.
So that's class_eval.
Ruby gives us another method
called instance_eval.
And it works much the same way,
except that it sets Self
to an instance of an object,
and then execute to block.
Here we have a simple Tweet
class that just has
attr_accessors for
user and status.
Let's create a new instance of
our Tweet, and then we'll call
instance_eval, which sets the
value of Self to that Tweet
object for the duration
of our block.
Then we can call status_equals
directly.
And it will call the
status_equals
method on our Tweet.
Remember back in level one we
used this code to initialize a
Tweet object?
Well there's some duplication
going on here.
We have to pass the Tweet
into our block.
And then we have to do
tweet.status and tweet.user
inside the block to
set its values.
Let's see if we can clean that
up with instance_eval.
To do that, we'll capture the
block that's being passed into
Initialize using
the ampersand.
And then instead of calling
yield, we'll call
instance_eval.
And we'll pass that
block through.
So this executes our block with
Self being set to our new
Tweet object.
And this allows us to not have
to pass the Tweet object into
the block and explicitly put
it in front of each of our
method calls.
We've reached the end
of level three.
So now it's time for you to
discover yourself with these
challenges.
I'll see you back
at Level four.