You're watching Ruby
Bits, Part Two.
This is level six.
We're going to be taking the
DSL that we built in level
five and extending
it even further.
Sometimes you learn about ways
that you'd like to modify your
DSL after you start using it.
Let's say, for example, that we
want to create a tweet that
just has text, no hash tags
or links or anything else.
Currently in our DSL syntax,
we'd have to do it like this.
Now that works, but it's
a little bit wordy.
It takes three lines of code,
and we'd like to simplify it
to just be a single
line like this.
Let's see how we might modify
our tweet_as method to support
this optional syntax.
First, we can see here that we
need to add an optional second
parameter for the tweet text.
We're defaulting it to
nil in case the user
doesn't specify one.
Then if that tweet text isn't
nil, we just go ahead and set
that directly after we've
created our tweet.
And finally, we need to make the
block optional by adding
if block_given at the end of
our instance_eval line.
So now we have both optional
text and an optional block.
And that allows us to use either
of our tweet syntaxes.
Here's another example of how we
might want to clean up our
DSL just a little bit.
Right now, if we want to mention
more than one person
in our tweet, we have to
call mention twice.
We'd like to be able to just
call it once and separate the
user names with a comma.
So how might we implement
that?
So if we look at our mention
method right now, it just
takes a single user.
But we can use the splat
operator to turn that into an
array of users.
And then we just have to make
a simple modification to the
method to iterate the users in
that array, and add each one
to our tweet.
Last time I was looking at
Twitter's API, I noticed that
they had recently added the
ability to attach a hash of
annotations to your tweet.
So we'd like to extend our DSL
to be able to support that.
What we'd like to do is to
build up this annotations
hash, with any arbitrary keys
and values, using this syntax
in our DSL.
This is a perfect candidate
for using method missing.
What we need to do is extend
our tweet class.
In its initialized method, we'll
initialize an empty hash
for the annotation.
Then when we submit the tweet
to Twitter, we'll just go
ahead and print those
annotations out to the console
right now so we can see them.
And then to actually fill that
annotations hash, we'll define
method missing.
And what we'll do here is we'll
turn the method name
into the key, and we'll turn the
method arguments into the
value, joining them
with a comma.
So with that, if we submit our
example tweet here, we see
that not only do we get the
tweet content, but we also get
this new annotations hash
with the three values.
One final thing we'd like to
do, just to make our DSL a
little bit easier to
use, is to add some
simple error handling.
So what we want to do here is
make sure that the tweet isn't
too long before we submit
it to Twitter.
We know that Twitter has 140
character limit on tweets.
So let's put that check into our
submit_to_twitter method.
Here we're just checking to see
if the tweet text length
is less than or equal
to 140 characters.
If it is, then we go ahead and
do the handling that we were
doing before.
If it's not, we'll just raise
an exception with a
descriptive message.
So what does this do for a user
that's using our DSL?
Well, if they try to submit
a tweet that's too long--
like this one here--
they'll get an exception with
our message, and they will see
some internal details
of our DSL.
In this case, the Submit
to Twitter method.
But that's a pretty fair
trade-off for adding some
pretty simple error handling.
That's the end of our
discussion of DSLs.
So you have some challenges to
do, and I'll see you on the
other side of those challenges
for the outro video.
We'll give you some more
resources if you'd like to go
discover more Bits of Ruby.