Hi, my name is Caike Souza, and
you're watching Ruby Bits
part two, dynamic classes
and methods.
Let's start by looking at the
Struct class, which is another
way in Ruby that we can
create custom classes.
Here, we have a Tweet
class that takes
a user and a status.
In order to use that class, we
instantiate it and then we can
call the user method or
the status method.
If we ask that object class
it belongs to, it knows it
belongs to the tweet class.
Another way we can write that
using a Struct is by using
Struct.new, passing in the
attribute accessor that we
want the class to have.
These two are doing the exact
same thing, so they produce
the same end result.
So the code that you're seeing
down here is going to run
exactly the same way.
Here, we can see that the tweet
class now has an extra
to_s method.
If we wanted to add that via the
Struct class, all we have
to do is pass in a block to
the Struct constructor.
I personally like to use Struct
for data structures
that deal more with data
than with behavior.
So if you find yourself adding
too many methods to a Struct,
you're better off
using a class.
If we take a look at the
following code, we will see
that we have two methods that
are basically doing the same
thing, although they have
different names.
We can refactor this code in
order to avoid duplication by
using the alias_method,
which creates a copy
of the tweets method.
Also, you might have noticed
that in this contrived
example, we could just replace
the tweets method with an
attribute reader and the
code would still work.
Now let's say that in our
Timeline class, we have our
print method that we want to
add authentication to.
For some reason, we don't want
to change the existing code.
So we're going to go ahead and
reopen the Timeline class, and
use alias_method to create a
reference to the old method
and create a new print method
that's going to override the
existing one.
Notice here that alias_method
creates a reference to the old
method via old_print that we can
call it from the new print
method, after we authenticate.
Now remember, back in part one,
we said that reopening
classes can be dangerous.
So another way we can do this
would be using inheritance.
So here, we create a new
authenticated Timeline class
that inherits from Timeline.
Then, we override the print
method and refer to the old
method via super.
This is definitely a cleaner
way to do it.
Next, in our Tweet class we have
three different methods
that update the status
of the tweet.
There's a little bit of
repetition going on here, so
let's see how define_method
can help us reduce that.
First, we create the states
constant that will hold all
the different states that our
tweet object can have.
Then, we iterate through those
different states and
dynamically create methods that
assign those states to
the status instance variable.
So once the tree class on the
right is loaded, it's going to
automatically define all the
methods that are listed on the
Tweet class on the left.
Now, the next time we have to
add a new state to our Tweet
class, all we have to do is add
it to the states array.
You can see now that our
Timeline class has a contents
method and a private method
called direct_messages.
If we instantiate the Timeline
class passing in a couple of
tweets, we can then call
the contents method
like we would normally.
We can also call it by using
the send method.
The send method takes an
argument, which can either be
a symbol or a string, which will
automatically call the
method with that name.
Send will also be able to call
protected or private methods.
If you want to avoid that, then
you can use public_send
instead, which is available
starting in Ruby 1.9.2.
Using public_send, if you try
calling it a protected or a
private method, it will
raise an error.
Now, going back to our Timeline
class, we've added a
show_tweet public method which
takes an index and prints the
corresponding tweet.
We can still instantiate the
Timeline object normally, but
instead of invoking the contents
method explicitly,
we'll capture it using
the method method.
Remember how we talked
about everything in
Ruby being an object?
Well, a method is also an
object, and this is how you
capture it.
Now to invoke it, you simply
have to call the call method,
just like you would in a Proc.
Now let's use the method
method once again, with
show_tweet this time.
Show_tweet has a parameter, so
when we call this method we
need to pass in an argument,
like so.
One last thing, and this
might blow your mind.
Remember how we talked about the
ampersand and being able
to convert between
Procs and blocks?
Well, it's also able to convert
between method objects
and blocks, as we can
see in this example.
Here we're passing the
show_method as an argument to
each, but we have to use the
ampersand to make sure that
it's converted to a block.
Then, inside the each method,
it's going to be called with
each index as an argument.
It's basically doing the same
thing as calling the
show_method explicitly
with an argument.
So we've reached the end of
level two, so get ready to do
some mind-bending exercises
and I'll see next time.