[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Testing
with RSpec.
This is Level 4.
We're gonna talk about hooks,
shared examples, and tags.
So in the previous level,
Greg showed you how to
organize your code.
In this level, we're gonna look
at how to dry things up a
little more using something
called hooks.
In this spec, we have two
examples that both call the
hungry method before they
run their expectation.
We can re-factor this code by
putting this hungry call
inside of a before block that
will run once before every
example we have in our spec.
By default, before
runs each time an
example is about to run.
You can also set it to run
before all examples or after
each or after all.
Let's take a look at another
example where we're using this
hungry call not only
in the same context
but a different context.
We can use a before block
here to call the
zombie.hungry method.
And it will execute before each
example, even the ones
deeply nested within
the context.
Within our context block,
there's still some duplication
we can get rid of by
using a before
block inside the context.
So we could say something like,
before zombie.vegetarian
equals true.
And it will be set for each
of those nested examples.
It's time for a new topic.
We're gonna look at
shared examples.
And we have two specs for two
different classes here that
both use the same kind
of behavior.
They're both checking to see
if the pulse of their
creature, zombie or
vampire, is false.
What we can do here is extract
these examples into a shared
example we can use
in both specs.
Let's assume our shared example
will work like this.
We want to check the behavior
of something, and we want to
make sure that the zombie
behaves like something that is
undead and doesn't
have a pulse--
the vampire as well.
We can create our shared example
within the specs
support directory we talked
about in Level 2.
And right here, we create a
shared_examples_for block,
pass it the undead as the name
of the shared example.
And within that
shared_examples_for block, we
can pass the example we were
using in those two specs and
make sure that we set the
expectation on the subject,
which will be either the
zombie or the vampire
depending on which one
is running this.
We saw in Level 3 that it could
be confusing to use an
implicit subject.
So instead of doing that, we
can send an explicit let
called undead to which we're
gonna pass a zombie.new or a
vampire.new.
And in the shared example,
we're gonna
replace subject by undead.
Another way we can write this
is by sending an instance of
zombie as the second parameter
to our shared example.
The shared example received the
instance of zombie as a
block argument we can use
just like we did before.
Another great feature of RSpec
is that we can tag or describe
context in it blocks so we can
run only specific part of our
specs from the command line.
Here you can see two tags,
focus: true on the
context and vegan: true
on the second example.
When we run our specs, we can
decide to only run the context
that has the tags focus.
If you don't want to put these
options in the command line
every time you run a test, what
you can do is put them in
the spec_helpers configure
block like this.
So if you run the RSpec command
once again, you'll see
that it still only runs
the focus examples.
Another great use case for this
is if you have a bunch of
examples that are really
slow, you can tag them
with the slow tag.
Then when you run the RSpec
command, you'll be able to
filter out those specific
examples from the test suite
using the tilde.
If by default you want to skip
those slow examples, you can
also set that in the
configuration
for your spec help.
Later, you can go back
and run just the slow
examples if you want.
That was a lot of new concept,
so have fun trying them out in
the challenges and I'll see
you a little later.