[MUSIC]
You're watching Testing with
RSpec, and this Level Two
where we're gonna go over
configuration and more
advanced matchers.
As we saw quickly in level one,
we can install RSpec with
gem install rspec
and rspec init.
Within a Rails project,
you have
three steps to go through.
First you have to put the RSpec
rails gem within your
Gemfile, then bundle.
And finally you have to run
rails generate rspec install,
which would create the specific
configuration
required for Rails.
The spec helper it creates is
a little different from the
one that we had in a standalone
Ruby application.
As you can see in the spec
helper, there's a line that
requires all files within
spec/support.
That's going to get really
useful when we do custom
matchers and helpers later
on in the course.
You can change the default RSpec
configuration with the
configure block.
For instance, you could replace
the mocking and
stubbing that RSpec comes with
with Mocha that we used in
Rails Testing for Zombies.
When running your specs in a
command line, you can pass a
bunch of different options like
--color, which
will give you more
colorful output,
--format documentation,
which will give you a more
verbose output and nested
examples so you see clearly
what's going on.
Now if you don't want to run
these long commands every
single time, you can put these
options within your .rspec
file that was generated
originally.
But let's take a look at a
few command line options to
run your tests.
If you want to run every
single test in the spec
directory, you can run
the rspec command.
If you want to run a specific
directory, you can just rspec
in that directory.
If you want to run a specific
file as we saw before, you can
simply name that full path.
Finally, by specifying a line
number, RSpec will try to find
the closest example
and run it.
So let's jump in and try
to test a rails model.
First we're going to require
the spec helper.
Then we're going to create a
describe block with the class
for zombie.
Then we're going to create an
example to make sure that the
zombie is invalid
without a name.
Once we instantiate a zombie,
we can write zombie
should not be valid.
Now be valid is a predicate
matcher, as we
saw in level one.
It's going to call the Active
Record valid?
method to make sure that
the zombie is valid.
If we ran the code, this would
fail because we haven't
written a validation
for this yet.
So we'll write one, validates,
name, presence, true.
Then if we run the code,
it passes as expected.
Let's take a look at some more
events matchers you could use.
If we wanted to check that our
zombie's name match a specific
pattern, we could use the match
method and pass it a
regular expression like so.
Now let's say we had tweets,
as we did in Rails for
Zombies, on the zombie.
We're going to create
two tweets.
Make sure that they're included
on that zombie.
And then test that they are
with the include method.
For instance, zombie.tweets
should include tweet one.
And zombie tweets should
include tweet two.
Include can be used anywhere
where you need to make sure
that an item is part
of an array.
So now let's say we want to
check that our zombie is born
with two weapons... that
makes sense.
We could run
zombie.weapons.count.should
== 2.
But we could also use that
have matcher to say
zombie.should have().weapons.
You can also use this with have
at least number or have
at most number.
If you want to get more specific
as to what you expect
from your application's
behavior, you could use the
expect block and the
change method.
First, you would, for instance,
create a zombie,
save it, and expect that zombie
to increase the zombie
count by one.
This would be written
like this.
You can also check that
something changed from
something to something
and chain those
methods as you wish.
Another great use of expect
would be to check whether a
method raises a specific
exception.
For instance, if we try to
save a new zombie without
doing anything to it and knowing
it should have a name,
it should raise an
ActiveRecord::RecordInvalid exception.
So we would write expect
zombie.save bang.
We use the save bang method
because we want an exception
to be raised.
to raise_error.
And then to find the specific
error we should be returning.
You can modify this by using
to, not to, or to not,
depending on how you want to
write your syntax for the
expectation.
Now there are many more matchers
to be used depending
on what you specifically
need to test.
The respond_to, be_ within.of,
exist, satisfy, be_kind_of,
be_an_instance_of.
Let's look at these
in context.
If we had a zombie, we could
check that it responds to
hungry with the respond_to
matcher.
We could check that a width is
within 0.1 units of 33.3.
We can check that
a zombie exists.
The satisfy method allows
you to pass a block.
And if this block returns true,
your expectation passes.
If we have hungry zombie class
that inherited from zombie, we
can check that it is a kind of
zombie or we could check that
a tweet's status as an
instance of string.
Thanks for watching level two.
Now it's time for you to play
with matchers in the
challenges.
[MUSIC]