[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching testing
for RSpec Level Three.
And in this level we're
going to look at
organizing your examples.
And lots of shortcuts you can
take to write even more
readable RSpec code.
Let's take a look at a new spec
where we want our zombie
to respond to name.
We get an instance
of a zombie.
And we check in our expectation
that it should
respond to name.
As you may remember, the
response to matcher checks to
see if there's a name method
on that zombie instance.
Let's try to simplify
this code.
Another way we could write
this is simply by writing
subject should respond
to name.
Well, where did that subject
variable come from?
Well, if you have a class
name in your describe--
if we say describe zombie--
when you refer to subject,
by default it's going to
instantiate that zombie.
And then it's going to
check to see if it
should respond to name.
So every time you run subject
inside an example, it's going
to instantiate a zombie.
It should be worth mentioning
here that this only is going
to work if your describe block
has a class in it.
Let's move this up to the top.
And I'm going to show you one
more way we can refactor this.
We can actually remove that
subject altogether because
it's going to use
that by default.
So if we just do should respond
to name, it's going to
check and see if an
instance of zombie
should respond to name.
We don't even have to
mention the subject.
Up until now, all of our
examples have been using the
do and the end block syntax.
But we can also use
curly braces.
So here you see up at the top,
responds to name should
respond to name.
There's a little duplication
going on here.
It seems like we're saying the
same thing twice, doesn't it?
Well, we can simplify this.
We can simply write it should
respond to name.
And RSpec is smart enough so
that when we run this test,
it's going to generate output
that is readable.
Here's another valid test
using a shorter syntax.
It subject name should
equal hash.
Now if we're using the subject
like this and we're calling a
method on the subject, we
can actually use its.
So i-t-s.
We can say its name, name being
a method we can call on
that instance, should
equal Ash.
And if we run this
test, it passes.
And you can see it even
has a good output.
Here's a few more examples
of using its.
We can say its weapons should
include weapon.
Weapon in this case
is an array.
And we're checking
to see if weapon
exists inside that array.
We can also write its
brain should be nil.
And its tweets.size
should equal 2.
As you can see, we have
that in a string.
And so as you can imagine, this
string is going to get
evaluated and then the
result tested.
Let's take a look at
another way we can
organize our examples.
So here's some code.
You can notice there's some
duplication going on here.
We have two examples that both
have a veggie preference.
One way we could refactor this
duplication is by separating
those examples with a veggie
preference into its own
describe block like so.
Now let's move this code up to
the top and see if there's
another way we can remove
some duplication.
You can see that each
of our examples
ends with when hungry.
So if we wanted to, we could
add another describe block.
So we say describe zombie when
hungry it craves brains, and
so on and so forth.
Now let's move this
up to the top.
And I'm going to give you
another way to write this.
Instead of using describe and
nesting describe blocks, RSpec
gives you another syntax for
describing different contexts
for your examples using
the context keyword.
So the same thing.
We can write context, when
hungry do wants brains context
with a vegetarian preference.
And I think it's a little
more readable.
Earlier in this level, you saw
how we could use subject and
it would create an instance
of the class.
Well, sometimes you're gonna
want to specify what that
subject is.
And we can do that in a
subject block like so.
Since the context here is with
a veggie preference, we want
our subject, in this case, to
be a vegetarian zombie.
And our example tests that are
vegetarians zombie craves
vegan brains.
There's another way we can
write this test here.
Remember we saw that
it syntax.
So we can say its craving should
equal vegan brains.
Sometimes when you're writing
your specs, you're gonna have
examples that need different
objects.
And you can only have one
subject per example.
So how do you deal with
different objects?
One way would be to use
the let keyword.
So in our example I'm about to
show you, we have a vegetarian
zombie and we also
have a weapon.
And we want to test with
both of those.
So here we're going to say let
axe be an instance of weapon
with the following attributes.
We can test that its weapons--
its meaning these zombie's
weapons--
should include axe.
We can also test that it can
use its axe when we call
subject.swing(axe) should
equal true.
Only when we call that axe
variable does it go then and
instantiate that weapon so we
can use it in our example.
One thing you might notice from
this code is that we are
using subject, subject,
subject.
And we're specifying that we're
talking about a zombie.
We know that we're talking
about a zombie.
But that might not always be
obvious to maybe other
developers looking
at our code.
Or if we have a long test and
we're like 10 pages down and
we see subject and we go, what
does subject refer to?
Instead of declaring our zombie
instance inside the
subject, we can declare
it inside let zombie.
And then we can just set
the subject equal
to that zombie instance.
This is basically aliasing
subject to zombie.
And then later on in our code we
don't use subject anymore.
We can just use zombie.
As we were recording this video,
we noticed that a newer
version of RSpec is going to
have a slightly improved
syntax for these three
lines of code.
We can simplify this if we want
to simply by specifying
subject zombie zombie,
just like that.
And it's going to
set the subject.
And it's also going to give
us a alias for zombie.
Let's take a closer look at
what's going on under the hood
of this let and subject
and its.
So what happens is when it runs
its name should be nil.
The example begins to run.
It says, oh, I need to
know the subject.
So it goes looking
for the subject.
The subject says, oh, go
look for the zombie.
Then we call let zombie, and
that instantiates the zombie,
which then gets evaluated
in our example.
This is an example of
lazy evaluation.
It's not until we call zombie
that it actually gets
instantiated through the subject
through the let.
So if we had this bit of code
here, it creates a zombie,
zombie count one.
If we wanted to check to see
if the zombie was actually
created in the database,
well, this wouldn't work.
It wouldn't work because we're
not calling zombie.
We're not creating an instance
of the zombie.
If you did want to work around
for this, if for some reason
you wanted to make sure the
zombie gets created every time
that let gets called, you
could call let with an
exclamation point.
And that's going to instantiate
the zombie before
every example, no matter what.
Now before I let you go on the
challenges, we're going to
refactor some RSpec
code together.
So here's some bad RSpec code.
Take a moment.
See if you can figure out how
we might improve this.
You'll notice first that we are
calling zombie create in
every single example.
So let's go ahead and refactor
that up to let zombie, zombie
create, and subject zombie.
The next test, it has no name.
We can use the its syntax we saw
earlier to say its name it
should be nil.
For the second example,
we can say it
should be craving brains.
And for that last example,
instead of checking to see
before that it's true and after
that it's false, we can
use an expectation so that
when the zombie eats the
brains that its hunger changes
from true to false.
Whoa, that was a long level
and a lot of content.
I know your brain must
be expanding.
So it's time for you to get
into the challenges, and
[? Olivier ?] will see
you in level four.
[MUSIC PLAYING]