[MUSIC]
You're watching Testing With
RSpec, and this is level five
where we're going to be going
over mocking and stubbing.
And if you played it through
Rails Testing for Zombies,
some of this code is gonna
look really familiar.
We're going to go over the same
examples so it's really
easy to understand how RSpec
does mocking and stubbing.
So here we have a
zombie class.
Zombie has 1 weapon.
And we've got 1 method in there
called decapitate, which
uses the weapon to slice off
the head and then sets the
zombie status to dead again.
We need to test this method.
But we need to keep in mind as
we test it that we don't want
that call to weapon that
calls the slice
method to be executed.
We don't want that
to be executed.
So we need a stub or mock.
Well, which one is which
and what do they mean?
Well, first of all a stub is
for replacing a method with
code that returns a
specified result.
And a mock is just a stub with
an expectation attached to it.
So back in this example
we need to stub
out the slice method.
To stub it out, all we
need to do is call
zombie weapon stub slice.
What this does is it goes into
the weapon instance and it
stubs out--
basically blanks out--
that slice method.
So it's just going to return
nil, as you see here.
So that's how we
stub in RSpec.
But let's bring that into the
context of our specification.
So here you can see we
have describe zombie.
We're going to let zombie equal
to a zombie create.
We're going to set
the context of to
method that we're testing.
This is a pattern that you
might see when you start
reading other people's RSpec
code, is they have a context
for each function inside
of their class.
So inside of our context, we're
going to make sure that
it's set status to dead again.
We stub out the slice method,
call decapitate, then we write
an expectation that a status
should equal dead again.
So we're testing that the status
gets set properly.
But we also need to test the
slice function gets called.
So that blank space in there
is where we're going
to write our test.
So we need a mock.
And to create a mock in RSpec,
we simply write zombie weapon
should receive slice.
This is going to stub out
the slice method.
Plus it's going to set an
expectation that that method
is going to get called inside
of our example.
Now we're going to move
our mock back into our
expectation.
And then we need to make sure we
call the decapitate method.
Once we call the decapitate
method, it's going to try to
call the slice.
That expectation is gonna
get fulfilled.
And our test is going to pass.
If we didn't call
the decapitate
method, it would fail.
Because, well, slice isn't
getting called.
Let's look at a couple more
complex examples.
You can see here inside of our
zombie class we have a
geolocate function which calls
out to our Zoogle web service
to maybe get the lat and
long of our graveyard.
We need to write a test to make
sure that when we call
this method, that it calls out
to be graveyard locator.
So here we're going to say
Zoogle should receive-- we're
creating our mock for
graveyard locator.
And we're also going to say
with zombie graveyard.
This allows us to test not
only that the method gets
called, but it gets called with
this specific parameter.
Then we'll call the geolocate
function to fulfill the
expectation.
Now that geolocate function
that you see up there, I'm
tweaking it a little bit.
This time I'm assuming that it's
returning a hash from our
web service.
And we're going to use that
hash to create a string.
To make sure our test doesn't
error out, we need to make
sure that our mock has
a return value.
So to do that we do and return
and we specify the hash we
want it to return.
Then we call the geolocate
function.
So we're already testing that
our geolocate function calls
our graveyard locator, but now
that our method is two
different lines, we also need to
test that the right string
is constructed and returned.
So here you can see instead of
doing a mock, we're going to
stub out our graveyard
locator, specify the
parameters we're sending in,
what is getting returned.
And then we can test to make
sure that what gets returned
from the geolocate function
is a string of 2 comma 3.
One more time I'm going to
make that that geolocate
function more complex.
This time graveyard locator
is returning an object.
The object has a latitude and
longitude, as you see here.
So how would we test this?
We've made it a little
bit more complex.
In this case, we want
to create a stub.
Some people call
these a double.
To create the stub, we're
going to send in a hash.
Those hash's keys are going to
become methods that we can
call on that stub.
So we can cal loc.latitude
and it will return 2.
And loc.longitude and
it will return 3.
We're then going to stub out the
graveyard locator and make
it return that stub object
that we just created.
And then we can check to make
sure that when we call
geolocate with object, it
returns the string 2 comma 3.
Now we're going to jump into
some new material, testing
some Rails with Action Mailer.
So here we have a
zombie mailer.
You can see this is our
welcome email when our
zombie signs up.
We're going to set our from
address, our to address, and
our subject.
To test this, we're going to
create a zombie mailer spec
inside of our mailers folder.
We're going to describe
the zombie mailer.
The context is going to be
that welcome function.
We're going to create a zombie
for each of our examples.
In this case, our subject,
though, is going to be a
little different.
What we're going to be testing
in each of our examples is
what gets returned when we
call the welcome method.
So that is what we're going
to call in our subject.
Now we can check different
methods on the mailer that
gets returned from the welcome
method to make sure that it's
from method should include
admin@codeschool.
It's to method should include
zombie.email.
And its subject should
equal "Welcome Zombie."
There's one thing that's
not very good about the
specification.
And that is, well, we're
creating an active record
object every time.
And there's really
no need for it.
Instead of instantiating a
zombie, we want to create a
fake object instead.
So here we can create a stub.
On that stub all we need
to do is be able to
call the email method.
So we send in like this and
get back an email address.
Now we put that stub into our
code and it's going to run a
little faster because we're
not creating active record
object every time.
Here are a few more examples
of options that you can use
when you're mocking to determine
different behavior.
For example, that a function
only gets called once or twice
or exactly a certain number of
times or at least or at most a
certain number of times or
any number of times.
We can also specify multiple
parameters for a method or say
that it can take anything
or any arguments or no
arguments at all.
Time to get mocking and stubbing
in the level five
challenges.
Good luck.
[MUSIC]