[MUSIC PLAYING]
This is Testing with RSpec.
Looks like you made
it to level six.
We're going to talk about
custom matchers.
Here we have a Zombie model with
a validation on name to
make sure that it's present.
The example that tests this
validation might look
something like this.
First it would instantiate
a zombie with no name.
Then it would test that the
zombie is valid and check that
it does have errors on
the name column.
This is the kind of
functionality we might need a
lot in our specs.
So what we should do is create
a custom matcher for that.
It should look something like
validate_presence_of_name.
Now let's implement this
custom matcher.
We're going to create this
custom matcher in the spec
support folder we talked about
first in level two.
We're going to call it
ValidatePresenceOfName and
it's going to be a module.
On that module, there's going to
be a class called Matcher.
In that class, we'll have a
method called matches that
does what our validation
example used to do.
This method should return
true or false.
And if it's false, the
expectation will fail.
We'll need another
method called
validate_presence_of_name in
which we'll simply instantiate
the matcher we just
created above.
And finally, we need to
configure RSpec to include
this custom matcher.
A good practice here is to set
the type of the custom matcher
to model, if we're using
this for models.
This way, it will only be
included if we're running
model specs.
If we run our test now,
it should succeed.
The problem with this custom
matcher is that it's not going
to be really useful beyond
name attributes.
We want it to be usable with
pretty much any attribute.
So we're going to give our
custom matcher a parameter so
we can send any attribute
to it.
If we run our spec now,
it will fail.
So let's fix our custom matcher
to behave the way we
expect it to.
We're going to refactor our
custom matcher by first
accepting an attribute, and then
sending that attribute to
the Matcher class when
we instantiate it.
Once we initialize this class,
we'll have to store this
attribute in an instance
variable, and we'll simply
have to use the attribute
instance variable in our
matches? method to check that
the error message contains
that attribute name.
If we run our spec, it succeeds,
as expected.
What if someone removes
the validation and
suddenly this fails.
When we run the spec, the
error output is not very
specific, and we get a
NoMethodError undefined method
failure_message.
That means our custom
matcher does not
have a failure message.
So let's fix that.
So inside our matches? method,
we're going to save that model
in an instance variable so we
can use its name in the
failure message.
Now we can define our failure
message method, give it the
model class name, explain that
it failed to validate, and
explain which attribute failed
to validate, because we still
have this instance variable
available to us.
And when the custom matcher
doesn't fail, we might want to
also say why it validated
successfully.
So we'll simply do the same
thing and explain what
attribute was supposed to be
there and was correctly there.
Now if we run our spec again
while still missing the
validation on name, we'll see
a proper error message that
tells us that it expected
Zombie to
have an error on name.
So we're back to our
Zombie model.
We've added the validation on
name again, but we've added a
custom message when
it errors out.
How would we test that with
our custom matcher.
One way would be to chain a
method called with_message on
it that passes a string
it expects to
receive as an error.
This won't work right now, so
we need to implement this in
our custom matcher.
All presence validation errors
in Rails return the "can't be
blank" string as an
error message.
So we'll set that within our
initialize method as an
instance variable message.
Then we'll define a with_message
method that
accepts a message argument.
It can override the
default message.
And finally, it returns itself
to be able to be chained with
any other matcher.
In the matches? method, we set
the model, run validations,
then we get all the errors for
that specific attribute and
check to see that the message
we sent to with_message is
stored in that array.
Final step, we run our spec,
and we see that everything
goes according to plan.
We validated the presence of
name and the message was the
one we set.
So this custom matcher we just
made is actually something
you'll find in the Shoulda gem
that gives you a bunch of
custom matchers you can use for
instance, to validate the
presence of, ensure inclusion
of, and check that a model has
a specific relationship with
another with specific options.
And you can even chain those
together the same way we did.
For instance, if we had a Zombie
model, we could check
that it has many tweets by
running should_have_many
tweets, that it is dependent
destroy, and has a
class name of Tweet.
So that's it for level six.
Good luck with the last
stretch of challenges.
We'll see you in the wrap-up
video to tell you more about
where to continue learning
testing with RSpec.