[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching testing
with RSpec.
I'm Gregg Pollack and this is
level one where we're going to
go over an introduction to RSpec
and start writing our
first specifications.
RSpec is one of the most
popular Ruby testing
frameworks.
And because it is so popular,
there's a huge community of
developers behind it which
means there's lots of
extensions and add-ons to it.
It also has a less
Ruby-like syntax.
You might call it a
domain-specific
language for testing.
In case you're not familiar
with that term,
domain-specific language, or
DSL, it means that we've taken
Ruby and RSpec has added
additional language features
on top of that to create the
most efficient language for
testing your code.
RSpec also has very good outputs
when you run your
tests so you can very easily
see what has gone wrong in
your code so you can
quickly debug it.
RSpec evolved out of this idea
called behavior-driven
development, or BDD.
There are several types
of testing.
You've got verification
testing, test-driven
development, and you could say
one level above that is
behavior-driven development
where we really focus on
describing the behavior
of our application.
And you'll see that RSpec and
the RSpec syntax makes it
really easy to do this.
All right.
Let's jump into building
our first
RSpec application together.
First step, obviously, we
need to install the gem.
So we just type gem
install rspec.
That's going to install RSpec
and all of its dependencies.
Then inside of our project
directory, we're going to call
rspec --init.
That's going to initialize two
files for us-- the spec helper
and the .rspec file, which
will go into more
detail in level two.
In our application, we're going
to be building a zombie.
Big surprise there.
That zombie.rb file is going to
live in our /lib directory.
So let's go ahead and create the
first test, before we even
write the zombie, that
describes the
behavior of our zombie.
In RSpec, instead of using the
word test we often substitute
the word specification.
But it basically means
the same thing.
This is why we're going to put
all of our specifications in
the spec directory.
Our zombies lives in that lib
directory, so we're going to
put our first zombie test inside
that lib directory.
Oops, I said test.
I meant specification.
And so our zombie specification
is going to be
called zombie_spec.rb .
With test unit, remember that
would have been zombie_test.
But we use specifications.
So we use zombie_spec.rb.
Inside this file we're going
to require the spec helper,
which will load the
configuration for the
specification.
Now we need to describe how we
want a zombie to behave.
So we start with writing
a describe block.
And we say describe
"A Zombie" do.
And we would then
put our test--
but we don't call them
tests in here.
We call them examples.
Here's another terminology
switch.
So we need to provide a lot of
examples to test our zombie
inside of our specification.
Hope you followed.
We want our zombie
to be named Ash.
So let's start describing
that behavior.
We're going to do that and
declare our first example by
using the it method.
So we're going to say
it is named Ash.
We haven't fleshed out the
example yet, but we're going
to run this spec anyways.
To do this on the command line,
we simply write rspec
and then the full path
to the file.
As you can see here, we have
one pending example.
Before we flesh out that example
though, I'm going to
show you a more typical syntax
that you would use in your
specifications.
Instead of saying a zombie as
a string at the top, instead
we're going to put the name of
the class that we're writing
examples for.
So we write describe zombie.
If we run this test again,
you're going to see-- uh oh.
It failed because--
well, we don't have that
zombie class yet.
So let's go ahead
and define it.
So as you can see above, inside
of our lib directory
we're creating our zombie.rb.
All we're going to do inside
there is declare our class.
Now back inside of our
specification, all we need to
do is require that class.
Then we can rerun the
specification on the command
line and here we are again.
We have one pending example.
Now let's write out the rest
of that example by first
creating a new zombie.
Then we're going to write zombie
name should equal Ash.
And we call that
an expectation.
If you went through Rails
Testing for Zombies, you might
have written an assertion which
looks like this, with
assert equals Ash zombie name.
Whereas with RSpec, we would
write it like this.
Zombie name should equal Ash.
And we call that--
not an assertion.
We call that an expectation.
And as you can see, it reads
a lot better than those
assertions.
Now if we run the test again,
it properly fails.
Woohoo.
We have our first failing
valid test.
So now we can start implementing
our zombie.
So inside of a zombie, we're
going to declare
an attribute accessor.
And inside of our initialize
method set its name to Ash.
So if we run our specification,
it passes.
From here, let's go ahead and
write another example inside
of our specification.
We're going to make sure zombie
has no brains when it
gets instantiated.
So we create our new zombie.
We test that zombie brain
should be less than one.
There's two components here
you should be aware of.
Ah, more terminology.
The modifier is should.
Should is the modifier
on our test.
And the matcher in this case
is that less than sign.
Later on in this course we're
going to be creating our own
custom matchers, which we
combine with modifiers.
If we run this test, it doesn't
pass, as we would expect.
After writing the failing test,
we can go back into
zombie class.
We can create a new attribute
accessor with brains.
And on the initialize set
brains equal to 0.
Then when we run the
spec, it passes.
Let's take a look at a couple
other examples of matchers that
you might use inside your
specifications.
We can check that zombie.alive
should equal false.
Another way we could write this
is zombie.alive should be
false using the be matcher.
We can check that zombie.rotting
should equal true, or
use the be true matcher.
We can check that height should
be greater than 5 or
greater than or equal
or less than.
We could also use the be matcher
in there if we like
the way that reads.
We could say brains should
be less than 1.
Completely optional.
Should, again, is
the modifier.
And we can switch out that
should modifier for should not
if you want to test that
the opposite is true.
In Ruby occasionally you run
into methods or you create
methods that end in the question
mark, which means
it's a predicate method and that
it returns true or false.
How would we test this
predicate method?
We could write an example that
looks like this to test that
zombie hungry should
equals true.
However, there's a better
way to write this.
We could use the be true matcher
that we just saw.
We can also use a predicate
matcher, which, as you can
see, reads really well.
Zombie should be hungry.
So that's going to call be
hungry question mark method on
zombie and test it.
Now if we run the spec again
from the command line, it
still passes.
As you saw at the beginning of
this level, one way to make an
example pending is to simply
leave off the example body.
Just have the it without
the do and the end.
And it will be pending.
There are two other ways,
though, you can have pending
examples which could be useful
if you're going back into a
big application and you have a
lot of failing tests and you
want to make one pass at a time,
you might want to make a
bunch of them pending and
implement them one at a time.
You can do this in two
different ways.
The first it is by putting
an x before the it.
So you just put x it.
And that will cause the
example to be pending.
You can also simply use the
pending keyword inside of your
example, and that will cause
the test to be pending.
That's all we have
for level one.
It's time to get your hands
dirty with the challenges.
And Olivier will
see you in level two.
[MUSIC PLAYING]