So you finished the
first corpse and
you're hungry for more.
I don't blame you.
You started to pick up
momentum, and there's
something to be said for that.
You're probably a little more
equipped to jump into Rails
development, but, well, you're
not flying quite yet.
Don't worry.
You'll get there eventually, and
we're not going to leave
you starving for more brains,
which is why we created Rails
for Zombies Two, Resurrected,
where we'll teach you more
Rails along with some of the new
shiny bits from Rails 3.1.
As with our other courses, we
have five levels, which means
five brand new screamcasts
produced by Gregg Pollack and
Oliver Tosh.
It also means we have 52 brand
new code challenges.
Let's take a quick look at
the challenge system.
At the top here, you'll see
the number of points this
question is worth, current
objective, and below that, you
can get a hint if you
need it, although it
costs you a few points.
Some of the challenges, like
this one, are going to be in
the command line, so we
built a command line.
When you get a question correct,
your total points
will increase, and you'll
advance to the next challenge.
Down below, you can
switch between
challenges if you get stuck.
And you'll definitely want to
download the slides and our
cheat sheet to help you get
through all the challenges.
Here are the topics for each
of the levels in Rails for
Zombies Two.
Let's go through
each of these.
Level one will start from the
ground up, starting with the
basic command line tools.
We'll talk about the new Ruby
1.9 hash syntax, and then how
to work with our database
using migrations.
In level two, we'll dive back
into our model layer,
exploring named scopes,
callbacks, has one, has many
through, and includes.
In level three, we'll make sure
everyone understands rest
before building some forms and
talking about nested resources
and view helpers.
In level four, we'll talk about
how to send emails in
our Rails app with Action
Mailer, followed by a dive
into the new Rails 3.1 asset
pipeline, and how to use Sassy
CSS, CoffeeScript, and Sprockets
with Rails right out
of the box.
In level five, we'll look at
rendering options, stuff you
need to know if you ever want
to build an API from Rails.
And lastly, we'll tie everything
together to do some
killer AJAX.
Every time you finish a level
in Rails for Zombies Two,
you'll get a new badge, finally
earning a course
completion badge.
But besides a badge, when you
finish the course, you'll get
access to the final course
video, a blooper reel about
takes from the videos, $5 in
Code School cash to apply
toward your next course or
towards your monthly
subscription, and a few prizes,
including a free month
of RailsCasts Pro from Ryan
Bates and $10 off Michael
Hartl's Rails Tutorial PDF
and screencast bundle.
If you haven't heard yet about
Code School's enrollment, for
a low monthly fee, you get
unlimited access to all paid
courses, priority access to
new courses as we develop
them, access to Code TV
screencasts with additional
content between course releases,
and a few other
privileges.
Whether you buy it outright or
get a subscription, we hope
you're ready for Rails
for Zombies Two.
So cleanse your palate because
here comes the second corpse.
Bon appetit.