(SINGING) Put down your brains
and your entrails.
It's time to stop and learn
some Rails, 'cause we got
something new to grab-- "Rails
for Zombies" by Envy Labs.
Congratulations, you made
it to Level 3--
REST in Pieces.
In this level, we're going to
be looking through REST.
You get a brief introduction
to REST, revisit some URL
helpers, take a closer
look at forms.
We haven't really done forms
yet, so I'm going to get you
familiar with the
form helpers.
We'll then jump into nested
resources, look at some
partials, and some additional
view helpers, which you may
need to use in your
rails views.
So let's jump into it.
So REST stands for
Representational State Transfer.
And it was coined by this guy,
Roy Fielding, in his
dissertation.
I highly recommend that you
skip his dissertation.
It's a lot of technical
reading.
It'll put to sleep.
But a good example of REST--
it has a lot of REST
principles--
is simply the HTTP protocol.
The protocol contains resources
addressable through
URIs, or Uniform Resource
Identifiers.
The HTTP protocol also
has standard methods.
A bunch of them-- four of them
that we care about in this
case-- are GET, POST,
PUT, and DELETE.
If you want to learn more
about REST and building
RESTful web services, check out
the book by the same name
by Leonard Richardson
and Sam Ruby.
In the early days
of Rails, things
weren't always so RESTful.
Let me show you an example.
Here's a controller--
a UserController--
and here are some actions
in there.
You see the actions are
all over the place.
This is bad because, well,
it lends itself to huge
controllers with lots
of methods and
lots of codes in it--
not so good--
also bad because there's going
to be multiple models per
controller, which is
also not good.
It's sort of become a best
practice to only have one
concern per controller, one
resource per controller.
With Rails 1, things started
getting more RESTful.
You can see here we have our
standard show, create, update,
and destroy actions, and in
comments next to them, you can
see how we call them, using
GET, POST, POST, and POST.
Not so good yet, because we're
repeating the verb.
If you look at the verb here,
which is GET and POST, and the
actual URIs, we're repeating
the verb.
If that doesn't make
sense, we'll come
back to it in a second.
As you saw a minute ago with
Rails 1, we have our standard
actions of show, create,
update, and destroy.
These actions map pretty well
to SQL statements, namely
select, create, update,
and delete.
Then how we're doing them in
REST with the controller,
we're using GET, POST,
POST, and POST--
something kind of fishy here.
With Rails 2 and above, though,
we have the same
actions, same SQL, except we're
using get, post, put,
and delete.
So that should feel a little bit
better because we're using
the proper verb.
So update is to put, and
destroy is to delete.
Let's take a look at the verbs
and the URI side by side.
So the verb we're using--
GET, POST, POST, and POST.
And then in Rails 1, we were
using /users/show/3,
/users/create, /users/update/3,
and
/users/destroy/3.
Can you see this?
We're repeating the verb.
We're repeating update
and destroy twice.
In Rails 2 and above, we're
using GET, POST, PUT, and
DELETE, which means we can
simplify this, get rid of
those verbs inside of our URIs
and simply have /users/3,
/users, /users/3,
and /users/3--
much cleaner.
Now, we're going to go through
some REST flash cards to get
things solidified
in your brain.
So I'm going to give you an
action, could be a method
name, and then, together, we're
going to figure out the
proper verb and the noun,
starting with Show user.
So when I say Show user,
what is that?
Well, that means GET User.
And this little URL down there,
that's giving you sort
of an example of a URL
you might use to
identify this user.
Create user-- what's
that going to be?
Well, that's going to be POST
User-- create is to post.
What about Update user?
Well, as we learned a minute
ago, update is PUT,
so we do PUT User.
What about Destroy?
Well, Destroy is DELETE User.
Now, we're going to make it a
little bit more complicated.
What about Play Global
Thermonuclear War?
How might we represent that
as a REST verb and noun?
Well, what are we doing when
we're playing a game?
We are creating a game, so
we might make this POST
GlobalThermonuclearWar--
makes sense.
What about Process credit
card transaction?
Hm.
Well, let's think about what
are we doing in that credit
card transaction.
We're creating a credit card
transaction, so we're doing
POST Transaction.
Take a look at that
URL down there.
I'm actually using a
nested URL here.
I'm signifying that it's for
order number 5, and that
credit card transaction
with order number 5.
What about Subscribe
to mailing list?
Well, what are we doing?
We're creating a subscription,
so POST Subscription--
makes sense.
What about Logout?
OK, this one's tricky.
What are we creating or
destroying in this case, when
we log out?
Well, really what we're
talking about
is a session, right?
When we log in, we're creating a
session, so when we log out,
we are deleting a Session.
Hopefully, with these examples,
REST is starting to
make a little more
sense to you.
Let's jump back into how
Rails is doing it.
So in Rails 1, here's our
actions and our URLs.
And in Rails 2, here's the same
actions, and here are the
proper URLs, or nouns.
It should feel a little
bit cleaner.
One thing you might be wondering
if you're taking a
close look at these URLs is
how do we link to them,
because some of these URLs,
the nouns are the same--
/users/3.
Well, let's take a look at how
we might do that in Rails.
For our show or our GET request,
we simply do link_to
'show' and then specify
the zombie.
For the create request,
we do 'create',
zombie, method: :post.
For calling the update,
we could call
zombie, method: :put.
And for destroy, we could do
zombie, method: :delete.
Now, on post input,
we typically
wouldn't have a link.
They'd typically be
a form, but this
is still valid syntax.
Right now, some of
you are thinking
wait a minute here,
wait a minute here.
Browsers don't support
PUT and DELETE.
Yeah, they don't.
That's actually a pretty
good point.
So how is it that our Rails
application understands both
PUT and DELETE?
Well, let's take a look at
what these links are
generating under the covers.
What they're generating is
something that looks like this
on our page.
Here you might notice two
HTML5 data attributes.
Hm.
That's interesting.
What are those doing there?
Well, it turns out that Rails
by default has some
unobtrusive JavaScript that
looks for these attributes and
it finds these attributes, it
grabs them, and changes the
code to create forms.
So in this case, it's going to
create a post form, and it's
going to hide that method inside
this hidden input field
called method, and it's
going to specify
the method in there.
Then when our Rails app sees
that method parameter, it's
going to grab it and set
that as our method.
It does this all
under the hood.
You never have to worry about
doing it yourself manually or
even worrying about that
browsers don't
support PUT or DELETE.
It's all invisible to you.
Remember, back in Zombies 1, we
talked a little bit about
routes and this line,
resources :zombies.
That's the line that
creates all of our
RESTful Rails routes.
Well, to list out all the
routes that it creates,
there's a rake task for that
called rake routes.
You can see here it prints out
our path names, our verbs, our
URLs, followed by
the action and
controller that gets called.
These paths on the left side, we
can use as a key to figure
out what to put in our
link_to calls.
So, here, we have link_to
zombies_path, link_to
new_zombie_path, link_to
edit_zombie_path.
Here we have zombie_path.
And to do that last one, Show
Zombie, we can also write that
by sending in the
actual zombie.
These zombie helpers, like
zombies_path and
new_zombie_path, generate the
relative path to the resource.
But what if we want
the full URL?
Let's say we want to provide
that URL so people can copy
and paste it, let's say, into
their blog, or social media,
or you're creating a tweet, or
you're liking it on Facebook,
or even in your email.
You're sending out an email,
and you need to provide the
full path-- the whole URL?
Well, in that case, we can use
these same paths, but we just
do zombies_url instead
of _path.
That's going to print out the
absolute path with the URL.
We're about halfway done.
Now, we're going to jump back
into Forms and Input Helpers.
So if you took a look in the
scaffold that we generated, it
has a form_for line that looks
something like this--
form_for zombie.
If zombie isn't saved to the
database yet, it's going to
generate a form which looks
like this-- doing a post.
And if our zombie's already
saved to the database, it's
going to create this HTML.
You can see here it's specifying
that the method on
this form is 'put'.
At the bottom of our
form, you'll see it
has a submit helper.
It calls f.submit.
If the zombie isn't saved to
the database, it's going to
create a commit button with the
value of Create Zombie.
And if zombie's already saved to
the database, it's going to
create a button with the
value Update Zombie.
Now, let's jump into some input
fields, starting with
text field.
When we submit this form, it's
going to send these request
parameters.
We could see these if we
looked in our log.
If zombie isn't saved to the
database yet, it's going to
print out something that
looks like this.
If zombie's already saved to the
database, it's going to
print out the same thing, except
it's going to put the
zombie name, which in
this case is Eric.
And if a zombie name has a
validation error-- if it
doesn't get saved properly--
it's going to wrap that
and in a div called
"field_with_errors", which will
allow us to put a big red
box around that field to
signify that it has a
validation error.
The other helper you're going
to see in your scaffold that
was created for you by default
are these labels.
So here we have f.label :name.
This is going to render
out label for-
"zombie_name">Name--
just a label for you to
use with your CSS.
And if the zombie has a
validation error, it's going
to wrap that, again, in a div
called "field_with_errors".
So if we have a validation on
our zombie name, which I think
we do, to make sure that it
has a name, it's going to
print out something that
looks like this in
our scaffold by default.
Here are a couple common input
helpers that you might use in
your Rails app.
We have text_area,
which in this case,
we're using for bio.
It's going to print out
a big text area box.
We have check_box, which is
really useful for booleans--
true or false.
For radio buttons, we can list
out a bunch of them here,
where we're selecting
the decomposition
status of the zombie.
For a select box, we use a
syntax that looks like this,
so we can select the
decomposition status--
"fresh", "rotting",
or "stale".
Sometimes we have select boxes
where an attribute is
associated with a number.
So, in this case, if "fresh"
was 1, and "rotting" was 2,
and "stale" was 3, we would
write this out.
Next, I'm going to tell you
about a couple additional text
input helpers which have
different types.
So each of these has input,
but then they have type.
For example, the first
one has password.
The browser is going to see that
typed password, and it's
going to know that it should
have dots instead of the
actual password, so people
can't read your screen.
Next up is the number_field
helper, which in some
browsers, it's going to give
you a number field on the
side, and some, it even
gives you commas
in your number fields.
Then you have a range_field.
Again, some browsers choose to
implement this as a slider.
Most browsers aren't going to
do anything special with the
email_field.
Maybe, eventually, they'll
do some client side
validation on email.
But where this is, I think, most
useful, is when you have
mobile browsers, because mobile
browsers will give a
different keyboard.
You tell someone to type in an
email address on your iPhone,
it's going to look like this.
Same deal with url_field.
On most desktop browsers, it's
not going to do anything
special, but on your iPhone,
it's going to look like this.
And then, finally,
telephone_field.
Again, it looks like this
on your iPhone.
Next up, I want to introduce
you guys to nested routes.
Let's jump back into
our routes.rb.
Here you can see we have
resources :zombies and
resources :tweets.
Some of the URLs that we might
get based on these routes--
well, to find a tweet, we would
have /tweets/2, and to
find all zombies tweets, we
might use /tweets?zombie_id=4.
This should feel a little
fishy to you.
It's not so good.
It's not very RESTful.
Tweets shouldn't really exist
without a zombie, so we can be
doing better RESTfully here.
So how do we do that?
How do we maybe use the
nested resource?
What we're going to do here is
we're going to switch it
around, so we're going to have
resources :zombies do
resources :tweets.
OK, so we sort of nested
tweets inside zombies.
This gives us access
to different URLs.
So here we can say,
/zombies/4/tweets/2, and then
to find all zombies' tweets, we
can do /zombies/4/tweets.
A couple things we need to do
to make this work throughout
our Rails application, we're
going to need to update our
controller and update all
the links and form_for.
So let's go ahead
and do that--
see what it looks like.
So here's our two actions, and
here are the parameters that
it's sending in.
So you can see, based on these
parameters, how it's sending
in the zombie_id versus
the tweet id.
The tweet ID is just
ID, whereas the
zombie ID is just zombie_id.
So here's our TweetsController.
Inside of our TweetsController,
we're going
to have our show action
to show a tweet.
And before we get into
our show action, we
can find the zombie.
Every action in this controller
is going to be
associated with a zombie, so
let's find the zombie.
Let's wrap that in a method
called get_zombie, then we can
call that using a before_filter
at the top of
our controller.
So we're going to fetch
the zombie before we
get into the action.
Then once we get into
the action, show.
We can call tweet =
zombie.tweets.find to find the
tweet for that zombie.
Wrapping it like this calling
zombie tweets is basically
using the scope of that zombie
to make sure that the tweets
we have access to under that
zombie are just the tweets for
that zombie.
Now, let's try to find all
the tweets for Zombie 4.
This is going to call the
index action in our
controller.
And inside there, all we do is
@tweets = @zombie.tweets because
we're finding all the tweets
for that zombie.
So that resources line is
nested, which is going to
create some different looking
routes for us.
How do we figure out
what they are?
Well, we run rake routes.
So here's what the rake routes
file looks like.
We have zombie tweets in
many different places.
We can use this print-out to
figure out how to link to
zombie tweets, so here's how
we get to zombie tweets.
We can get a new tweet using
new_zombie_tweet_path.
Here's how we do an edit.
Notice here we need to send in
both the zombie and the tweet.
Here's how we show a specific
tweet for a zombie.
And here's the short version
of doing that--
basically wrapping both
variables in an array.
We can also use that array
when we go to write the
destroy link.
Where might we see these
links in action?
Well, let's jump into
our index view.
Here you can see we're iterating
through all of the
different tweets, and we can
"Show", "Edit", "Destroy", and
"New", all using these new
routes that were created from
our nested route.
Another view we're going
to have to change
slightly is our form.
So we look inside of our form
here, and we need to include
not only the tweet, but also
the zombie in an array.
Let's jump back into the
TweetsController.
So here you can see our standard
create method that
our scaffold created for us.
We need to modify this to
reflect our new routes.
First, at the top, we can change
this so that it has
@zombie.tweets.
Then we can say redirect_to
@zombie, @tweet--
render json, @zombie, @tweet--
location, @zombie, @tweet.
And that's all we have to do.
We're almost done
with this level.
All that's left is talking about
partials and a couple
view helpers.
You may already be familiar
with partials.
And the most common partial
out there is this form
partial, which was created by
our scaffold for what we need
to create and update--
the tweet.
We can tell it's a partial
because it has that underscore
method there.
And if we look inside of our new
view, we can see where it
gets inserted.
And here is the edit view, and
we can see where it renders
the form into our edit view.
Next up, we're going to talk a
little bit about security.
You don't want people
to be able to do
this in your website--
put in malicious JavaScript and
then get it to execute on
other people's browsers when
they view the page, right?
Your user input need
to be escaped.
Hopefully, it does something
like this, where it escapes
that script to use the proper
escaping there.
Well, back in Rails 2, when it
came to user input, by default
when we printed something to
the screen, it would be
unsafe, like this.
We always had to remember to use
that h command to properly
get things to escape.
But in Rails 3, all variables
that we print out to our views
are going to be escaped
by default.
This is great.
You're less likely to shoot
yourself in the foot.
However, there are some cases
where you do want to print out
user-generated HTML and
JavaScript to the screen, in
which case, you just need
to use the raw command.
So raw's not going to
escape anything.
It's going to print it out.
So here we have some view code
where we're printing out all
of the tweets--
putting them each in a div.
Each div has a unique
ID because maybe
we're doing some AJAX.
Well, you should be familiar
with the div_for helper.
So check it out.
We can write this using the
div_for helper like so, and
it's going to do the
same exact thing.
What it's doing under the
covers, as well, is it's
calling the dom_id on our active
record object, and
that's how it's getting
the ID, which it's
using in the div.
Hm.
This will come in useful later
when we're writing some AJAX,
and we're writing some
JavaScript, and we need to
maybe do something to that
specific div, we're going to
call dom_id for that specific
object, get back the dom_id
that we want to make
disappear or reappear.
Next, we're going to take a
look at a couple string
helpers, starting
with truncate.
So, in this case, we're taking
"I need brains!" and
truncating it to 10
characters, which,
unfortunately, is going to
print out "I need bra".
Zombies don't need bras, so
what we're going to do
instead, we're going to have one
more parameter, so it's no
longer any bra.
We're going to add
a separator.
So this is saying, basically,
make sure the last character
is a space.
So, in this case, it's just
going to print out "I need",
which is better.
Next up is the pluralize helper,
where we can send in a
number of things and then a
word, and if it's one item,
it's going to say,
"I see 1 zombie.
If it's two, it's going to
say, "I see 2 zombies".
ActiveSupport adds a bunch of
string helpers, one of which
is titleize.
So if we want to make sure all
of our names on our websites
are titleized, we can call
titleize and it'll print out
"His name was Ash William".
The next helper we're going
to look at is to_sentence.
So this takes an array, and
it's simply going to put
commas and an and.
So, in this case,
we have Captain,
Soldier, and Brain Taster.
There's also time_ago_in_words,
which is really useful
for date/time fields.
So we can say, "He was buried
alive 2 days ago".
If you're dealing with money,
number_to_currency is pretty helpful.
It'll format things properly.
And lastly, number_to_human
is really nice when you're
dealing with large numbers.
So we can just put in a bunch of
numbers and it'll translate
that to, "Ash is 13.2
billion years old".
The best way to learn about more
view helpers is to simply
take a read through the Active
Support Core Extensions guide.
There's a ton of great material
in there.
So you've reached the
end of Level 3.
You've done a great
job so far.
You definitely deserve
some brains.
But, first, in code challenges,
you'll apply what
you've learned.