[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome to Rails for
Zombies 2, Level 1.
In this episode, we're going to
be going over some of the
things we left out in the first
set of Rails for Zombies
videos, covering things like
creating a Rails app, the
command line, database
migrations, the Ruby 1.9 hash
syntax, as well as a little bit
about Bundler and database
configuration.
If you haven't yet, I highly
recommend you get Rails
installed in your laptop, or
in your computer, whatever
you're using, so that you can
run some commands and follow
along as we teach them.
I'm not going to go into the
nitty gritty details of
installing Rails on
every platform.
I'm just going to mention that
if you're on Windows and you
don't have it installed
yet, head over to
railsinstaller.org.
There's instructions there, a
downloader, you'll be up and
running in no time.
If, however, you're running OS X
or Linux, I highly recommend
going over to railstutorial.org
and just
going through the
first chapter.
It'll get everything
installed you.
You'll even get an application
deployed on Heroku.
So once you have Rails
installed, if you run Rails
from any particular directory
that's not a Rails app, it's
going to give you the syntax on
how to create a Rails app
with a bunch of different
options.
You can skip ActiveRecord,
specify what database you want
to use, specify what JavaScript
framework you want
to use, couple runtime options,
and then finally give
you an example of how to
create the Rails app.
Let's go ahead and create our
first Rails app by running
rails new TwitterForZombies.
When we run that command it's
going to create a bunch of
files for us in a bunch
of directories.
Some of these directories should
look familiar from
Rails for Zombies 1, like
your Controllers,
Models and Views directory.
At the end it's going to
run bundle install.
What bundle install is going
to do is go out to the
internet and download any
external dependencies that
your Rails application
depends on.
You don't need to worry
about this too much.
We'll come back around and
talk about Bundler later.
So we've create our Rails app.
Now let's jump into
the directory.
So we're going to cd into the
directory, and if we run rails
from inside the directory we're
going to be given a list
of commands that we can run on a
Rails app, starting with the
generate command that generates
a new code, the
console command which we will
use to debug a little bit
later, the server command, of
course, to start our local
development server, and the
dbconsole command to jump into
a console for a database.
If we want more information
about any these commands we
can run them with the
-h option.
But, first things first,
let's get our
development server running.
So we're going to run
rails server.
It's going to give
us an output.
And if we go to localhost:3000
in a browser we're going
to get the Welcome
to Rails screen.
We can also run rails server -h
for more options, like if we
wanted to run this server
on a different port.
The shortcut for this command,
which you'll probably be
running more often,
is just rails s.
Next up let's take a
closer look at the
rails generate command.
If we run it without any options
we're given a list of
generators which we can use
to generate some source
for our Rails app.
A shortcut for generate is
rails g, and let's go ahead
and use that to generate
a scaffold.
So a scaffold, if you're not
familiar, is the basic
building block for most
of our Rails apps.
We specify a resource and it
builds us a view to list out
the items, edit the items,
create new items,
and delete the items.
So here's the syntax.
And we're going to go ahead and
create rails g scaffold
zombie, because we want
to create Zombies.
We're going to give it a name,
which is a string.
A bio, which is a text type.
And an age, which
is an integer.
When I say types, I'm referring
to database types.
And here's a list of all the
other database types which we
might find useful here.
When we generate a scaffold it's
going to create a bunch
of files for us.
Let's take a look at a few.
You can see here it's generating
a migration for us,
the Zombie model, it's going
to add resources :zombies to
our routes.rb.
It's going to create our
Zombies controller.
It's also going to create our
views, which should look
familiar from Rails
for Zombies 1.
You have our index view,
edit, show and new.
There are a couple other files
it's going to create like
helpers, tests, and assets,
and we'll see
some of those later.
But first, let's jump
in and take a closer
look at that migration.
When we say migration what
we're talking about are
database migrations.
This is how we make
changes to our
database from inside Rails.
And if you remember from Rails
for Zombies 1, Rails is going
to automatically create for us
a primary key called ID.
It doesn't even show that
in the migration.
It's just sort of assumed that
every table is going to have a
primary key of ID.
The last thing you'll see in
this migration is this
t.timestamps.
This t.timestamps line is
the same as saying datetime
:created_at and datetime
:updated_at.
These are magical
fields in Rails.
They get populated for you
automatically and you can use
them in your views.
When a model is created the
created_at gets set and every
time it's updated that updated
gets set for you.
To give you a better idea why
migrations are so useful
here's a commercial I created
back in my Rails Envy days.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
Hi.
I'm Ruby on Rails.
And I'm PHP.
So whatcha got there?
These are a bunch of SQL files
all the developers on
the team sent out.
And I'm really frustrated
because they just overwrote
all my database changes.
Oh, man.
That sucks.
You feel my pain, right?
Well, actually, Ruby on Rails
features something called
Migrations.
This allows developers to make
database changes independently
without stepping on
anybody's toes.
You still have to write tons
of SQL though, right?
Well, no.
Migrations actually use Ruby, so
it's database independent.
Wow.
That sounds really good.
I think I'll give that
a try, actually.
You know what, on my way home
from work tonight I'll stop by
Toys R Us and pick
one of those up.
While I'm there I'll get Barbie
to give me a ride in
her pink Cadillac all the way to
your offices in the Land of
Make Believe where you can
help us finish up my
application, and we'll all
live happily ever after.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
So database migrations are how
we version our database, keep
track of changes, so we don't
have to send around SQL
scripts and end up stepping
on each other's toes.
So back in our Rails app
we have this migration.
If we start off server at this
point, uh oh, we're going to
get an error.
It's not going to work.
It gives us an error, it gives
us the line of code where
there's an error.
If we looked at that line of
code we would see zombies =
Zombie.all.
Oh, so it's querying for the
zombies table, but it's not
yet in the database.
Well we forgot to run
that migration file.
To run migration files, we
run rake db:migrate.
Not only is that going to run
our current migration, but if
there's any other migrations
that other people on our
project committed, it's also
going to run all of those.
Here's the output we would see
from our migration and if we
run our Rails server again, now
if we go to /zombies
we can get a list of
the zombies and
start creating them.
Now that we have a zombie table
and a zombie model,
let's jump into the console
and play around with it.
So we use the console to
debug our application.
So we can go in here and just
start running Rails commands.
So here you can see I'm
running Zombie.create
(name:"Eric Allam", age:27)
That's going to actually show us
the SQL that's going to be
running inside of our Rails app,
and it's going to give us
back the zombie object
it created.
Now remember, when you used
tryruby.org everything in Ruby
has a return value.
That's that hash rocket symbol
you see right up there.
You can see that this
command returns an
instance of the zombie.
We can then run Zombie.first to
get back the first Zombie
which in case is the zombie
we just created.
We can change the name
of the zombie.
And then, finally, we
can save the zombie.
It's going to show us the SQL
that it uses to do that.
And it's going to return true
because it successfully saved
the zombie.
Now you may have noticed, when
we created this Zombie Eric
here, that we used a slightly
different syntax.
We actually used a different
hash syntax.
Remember, a hash is a collection
of key value pairs,
and a key can be almost
anything.
A key can be a string.
Here's the old syntax with
the hash rocket.
A key can be a number.
A key can more commonly
be a symbol.
You'll notice all of these
different syntaxes I showed
you here are compatible with
both Ruby 1.8 and 1.9.
And if we're using Ruby 1.9,
this last hash can also be
written as name colon.
It's a little bit of a shorter
syntax, two less characters,
and throughout this entire
tutorial we're going to be
using this new Ruby
1.9 syntax.
If you're just getting into
Rails now you should
be using Ruby 1.9.
Don't even bother
with Ruby 1.8.
Just use Ruby 1.9 and then
you'll get access to this hash
syntax you see here as well.
So here again is the code to
create Zombie Eric using the
Ruby 1.9 hash syntax.
And here it is using the Ruby
1.8 syntax, but really, it's
not Ruby 1.8 syntax.
You can still use the same
syntax, this sort of old hash
syntax, in either
Ruby 1.8 or 1.9.
It's up to you which one
you like better.
You can use either but in this
tutorial, like I said, we're
going to use the new way.
If you take a look inside
the controller that the
scaffolding created for us you
can see that in the respond_to
block over here it says
render json: @zombies.
That's using the Ruby 1.9
nine hash syntax.
And it does the same thing
as the old syntax.
So we have our zombie table
but we want to make some
changes to the database.
How do we do that?
Well, we do that by generating
a migration.
We're going to call
our migration
AddEmailAndRottingToZombies.
We're going to specify the
columns we want to add.
In this case, the email column,
which is a string, and
rotting, which is a boolean.
When we want to add a migration
that adds columns we
can use this title format
and it'll write all
the code for us.
So we say add anything to, and
then the table name, we have
our column names
and our types.
And that's going to generate a
migration for us which looks a
little bit like this.
As you can see here it's adding
two columns to our
zombies table.
And email column and
a rotting column.
But what happens when we want
to add some table options,
some column options.
For a default we can just
write default false.
A couple other migration options
here besides default,
we can also add a limit, specify
that it can or can't
be null, we can specify which
position of the table to put
the column, as well as add a
unique constraint to ensure
that this column is always
unique at the database level.
Now that we have a migration we
need to run rake db:migrate
to add those columns
to our database.
Rake db:migrate is
not only going
to run our new migration.
But if I checked out somebody
else's migrations, it's going
to run those too.
Some other rake commands you
need to be familiar with start
with rake db:rollback.
What rake db:rollback is going
to do is look at our most
recent migration and undo it
at the database level.
It's going to roll it back.
This can be really useful if,
let's say, I haven't committed
my migration yet and I want to
make some changes and then
migrate again.
It also is really useful when
you think about deployment.
If I deploy my application, I
run a migration and whoops, I
didn't want to run that,
something went wrong.
I can quickly type rake
db:rollback, it'll rollback
the migration, and I can make
any changes that I need to
from there.
Another useful rake command
is rake db:schema:dump.
And this gets run automatically
every time it we
run rake db:migrate.
See, after you have a Rails app
that's lived for three or
four years, you have a lot--
end up with a lot of
migrations.
I mean, over 100 migrations.
And it's unrealistic for
somebody new who checks out
your Rails app, a new developer,
to have to run all
those migrations.
What you find is that migrations
start to get
brittle after a while.
This is why we have a schema.rb
and it looks
something like this.
As you can see here it has our
entire database structure.
So the next time you check out
somebody's Rails app, and you
need to get up and running and
create the database, what
you're going to run
is rake db:setup.
That's going to create the
database if it doesn't exist
yet, it's going to run the
schema and create the database
using that schema file, and then
it's going to run any seed
data which you need in there.
So we know how to add columns
to our database.
But how do we remove them?
Well, let's go ahead and
generate another
migration for that.
We'll call it
RemoveAgeFromZombies.
The column we want to
remove is the age
column, which is an integer.
And we are using another
pattern here with the
migration name.
Remove something from
table name.
That's going to generate
a migration for us.
It's going to obviously have the
remove column command, but
if you look at that remove
column command you'll notice
it doesn't have enough
information in
it to roll it back.
Sure, we can remove the column,
but when we want to
add it back, what type was it?
So in this case we also
need to have an add
column command in here.
Now remember in the previous
migrations we
had a change method.
Instead of a change method
we're going to have an up
method, to migrate up.
And a down method so that our
application knows what to do
if we need to roll this
migration back.
A couple other migration
commands include
rename_column, rename_table,
drop_table, change_column, and
change_column_default.
So we know how to add columns,
we know how to remove columns.
What about everything else?
Well for everything else we're
simply going to create a
migration and name it anything
that we want.
So, in this case, let's drop the
zombies table altogether.
That's going to generate a up
and down method for us.
And we're going to
have to write it.
You can see here I've
written it for us.
We have a drop_table in
the up and we have
create_table in the down.
For more information on database
migrations head over
to guides.rubyonrails.org.
Over there there's a Rails
database migrations guide
which has tons of information
about migrations.
So when we created our Rails app
it ran bundle install and
installed a bunch of external
dependencies.
How did it know which
dependencies to install?
Well that came from the Gemfile
which is at the root
of our directory.
So here you can see a listing
of all of our Rails app's
external dependencies.
And whenever we want to make
sure we have these installed,
or go out and install
new ones, we can
just run Bundle Install.
And, remember, that got called
by default when we created our
first Rails app.
For more information on Bundler,
obviously I don't
have time to go into all the
nitty gritty, head over to
rubyonrails.org.
In the screen cast section there
you'll find a screen
cast on Bundler I created.
Also you can go straight over
to the Bundler website at
Gembundler.com.
By default our Rails
application
uses a SQLite database.
One way we can tell this is on
the previous slide where we
saw our gem dependencies, it had
listed gem "sqlite3"
So it's using a SQLite
database.
But how is our database
configured?
Well that happens in our
config/database.yml.
Let's take a look inside.
Here you can see we have
a configuration for our
development, test, and
production environments.
How might we change this
out for MySQL?
Well, we simply would have to
change this configuration,
we'd give it the MySQL adapter,
the database name,
the username and password for
our database, and we would
replace the SQLite driver with
mysql2 inside of our gem
file, run Bundle Install and
then we'd be using MySQL.
That's all we're covering
for level one.
Now it's your turn to take this
information and learn by
doing in the challenges.