[MUSIC PLAYING]
Good job getting through all
the level one challenges.
And now, we're on to
level two, Models
Still Taste Like Chicken.
So we're going to be going
through some model best
practices, starting with Named
Scope, Callbacks, some new
Relationship Options, Includes,
and then finally,
has_many :through.
Throughout these slides, you're
going to see some
symbols that look like this--
one for bad code, one
for good code.
That's for your reference.
If you go through the slides
later and you need to figure
out which is the bad code, which
is the good code, just
look for these symbols.
You also might see some zombies
wandering through
these slides.
They don't mean anything
in particular.
And you might also see some
brains which means don't get
too hungry, but it is organic
and no sugar added.
So let's jump into
Named Scope.
So here we have a
RottingZombiesController.
Inside here, there's an index
action where we're querying
for all of the zombies where
rotting is true.
Now, we're very often in this
application going to be
querying for rotting zombies, so
you think maybe there's a
better way to do this.
Well, there is.
We're going to take that
where method there.
We're going to move that
into the Zombie model.
Inside the Zombie model, we're
going to say scope :rotting.
So we're creating
a Named Scope.
The name in this case
is rotting.
Then back in our controller,
we can simply do
Zombie.rotting.
It's going to call that
method and return
all the rotting zombies.
Now let's take a look at a few
more examples of Named Scopes,
starting with fresh which gives
us all the zombies that
are less than 20 years of age.
We can also get all of the
recent zombies sorted by
created_at, limit only
three of them.
So we can chain these
things together.
We can also use method chaining
to create queries.
So we can say
Zombie.rotting.limit(5).
We can say Zombie.recent.rotting
and then
finally,
Zombie.recent.fresh.rotting if
we want to chain them
all together.
In a moment we're going to
talk about Callbacks.
But right now, we have
an objective.
We need to write some code to
check to see when the zombie
age is greater than 20, set
rotting equal to true.
First, we're going to see how
we might implement this,
badly, in our zombies
controller.
So let's jump into the
zombies controller.
So here's your typical update
action which was generated
from our scaffold.
In here, we're going to say if
@zombie.age > 20,
set @zombie.rotting = true
And you can see I've got that
symbol up there to signify
that this is bad code.
But why is it bad?
Well, there are many other
places that we're updating
zombies and might be
changing the age.
And if we do that in other
places, it's not
going to set rotting.
It's only going to set rotting
here in the update method.
So how can we do better?
Well, we're going to take this
logic, and we're going to move
it into the model.
So here we are in the
Zombie model.
We're going to wrap it in a
method called make_rotting,
and then, we're going to tell
it to call this method every
time it saves zombies-- in this
case, before it saves it.
However, this code
as it's written
wouldn't completely work.
We still have some invalid
variables in there.
We have those instance variables
which came from our
controller.
So let's get rid of the bad
code and rewrite this.
We're going to write if age
> 20 then
self.rotting = true
And now it's going to work.
Now, if you haven't written many
model methods, this might
look a little odd.
Why do we have self dot in front
of rotting and not age?
Well, it turns out when we call
age there, we're reading.
So it's going to
look for an age
variable inside that method.
It's not going to find it, and
then it's going to look at the
scope of our model--
so of the instance.
So it's going to pull
the age attribute.
With rotting though, we're
actually setting a variable.
Since we're setting the
variable, if we didn't have
self dot, it would set the
variable using the scope of
just the method, and we wouldn't
have access to it
outside of the method.
So here we specify self.rotting,
so it knows
we're talking about the
attribute in our database.
There's one other way we can
improve this code, refactor it
a little bit, and that
is by simply doing
it all on one line.
And we can say
self.rotting = true if age > 20
There are a bunch of
different model
callbacks that we can use.
But before I show you them,
we need to make sure you
understand that returning
false in any of these
callbacks will completely halt
whatever you're doing.
So here, we have a Brain
model, and we
have a taste method.
The taste method
returns false.
In Ruby, we don't really
need to have that
return the method anywhere.
We can just say false.
This method is going to called
before save, which means it's
going to stop.
It's going to stop the
save from happening.
So if we jump into the console,
we create a new
brain, and we try to save it,
it's going to return false.
We're never going to be
able to save a brain.
So you just have to be careful
of return values when you're
doing callbacks, because if you
return false, it's simply
going to stop.
Also, if you're a zombie,
be careful of fire.
Fire bad.
Bad zombie.
Here's a list of all the
callbacks that you get access
to from inside an Active
Record model.
You can see here we've got both
before_save, after_save,
before_destroy, after_destroy.
A couple points to
be made here--
you can use multiple callbacks,
even of the same type.
So I could have a bunch of
different before_save methods
if I wanted to.
And as we mentioned before, if
any of these return false,
then it's going to stop.
And if it's a before_create or
before_save or before_update,
well, it's not going to get
saved to the database.
To give me a couple of examples
of callbacks in real
Rails apps, you might have,
in your user model, an
after_create
:send_welcome_email.
So every time you create a user,
after it's saved, send a
welcome email.
You might also have before_save
: encrypt_password
so that when someone types in a
new password and they create
an account, they can save the
password, create a salt maybe.
And lastly, you might also
have before_destroy
:set_deleted_flag.
So you may never want to
actually really delete a user
out of your database, in which
case you might have a deleted
at date/time field.
So inside your before_destroy,
you might actually set that
date/time field and then return
false, which would halt
that destroy from
ever happening.
So it wouldn't actually destroy
it from the database,
but you could still
call destroy.
It would halt it, because
it would return false.
All right, we're about halfway
done with level two.
Next up, we're going to
be talking about some
relationships.
Remember relationships, back
in Rails for Zombies 1?
We talked about belongs_to
and has_many?
Now we're going to be talking
about has_one.
So our example here is we have
a zombie which may or may not
have a brain.
You can see a zombie
has a brain.
This one has half a brain.
This one has no brain.
So how do we do that
in our code?
First step, we're going to
generate a new model.
So we could say rails
g model brain.
Our brain is going to have a
zombie_id which is an integer.
That's how we know which zombie
this brain belongs to.
We're also going to have a
status which is a string, the
status of the brain, and
of course, flavor.
Flavor is very important
for zombie brains.
So when we run this command,
it's going to create a
migration for us.
It's also going to
create our model.
Let's jump into this
migration.
Inside this migration, we're
going to see that it creates
the brains table and all of the
columns that we specified.
We're also going to add
one small snippet of
code to this migration.
We're going to specify a foreign
key index on zombie_id
to keep our database
efficient.
If you don't know what a foreign
key is, maybe read up
on databases.
When we're ready to create this
table, we're going to, of
course, run rake db:migrate.
Now that we have the database
table, we have to represent
that relationship inside
of our model.
So here's the Brain model, and
here's the Zombie model.
Inside the Brain model, we
simply say belongs_to :zombie,
and in the Zombie model,
we say has_one :brain.
It's as simple as that.
Let's jump into the console now
and play around with this
relationship.
So here's our last zombie.
Let's grab that.
We can then create a brain by
just calling z.create_brain,
sending in the attributes.
And that will return the
brain we just created.
We could also just call z.brain
on our zombie, and
that's just also going to
return that same brain.
But what happens when
we destroy a zombie?
Does the brain go with it?
Well, let's take a look.
So we're going to grab
the first zombie.
There's our zombie there.
We're going to grab the
brain of that zombie.
There it is.
We're going to then destroy
the zombie.
It's destroyed.
There we go.
And then finally, we're going
to find the brain, and the
brain is still there.
The brain is still exists.
We need to destroy the zombie
brain with the zombie.
Well, how might we do that?
To figure out to do that,
we're going to go to
railsapi.com, and we're going
to search for the has_one
relationship.
In there, we're going to see a
lot of different relationship
options, including the
dependent option.
How do we use that?
Well, let's give it a try.
So in the zombie model, we're
going to say has_one :brain,
dependent: :destroy.
Well, let's jump back
into the console and
see what this does.
We fetch our zombie.
And then when we destroy the
zombie, we can see in the SQL
that it generates, that
it destroys both the
zombie and the brain.
Active Record relationships
have a bunch of different
options you can use, not only
dependent: :destroy, but you
can also change the foreign key
index if you want to have
a different foreign key.
You can even change the primary
key if you want.
You can also specify validate:
true on a relationship.
So in this case, if we had
validate: true on brain, when
we saved a zombie, it would also
validate to make sure the
brain validates as well.
If not, it wouldn't save it.
It would return false.
And there's lots of other
relationship options.
Check the documentation.
Next up, we're going to talk
about the include method.
You can see up here,
we have a view.
We're listing out the name and
the brain flavors for each of
our zombie.
What might the code look
like for this?
Well, here we are in
the controller.
We're getting all
of the zombies.
Inside of our view, we're going
to list out each of the
zombies, list out their name,
and call zombie.brain.flavor
to get the flavors
of their brains.
And if we look back on our
server to see what SQL was
running, we would see this.
This is not so good, right?
It's doing a query for each
brain for each of the zombies.
We call this sometimes
an n plus 1 query.
It's a bad thing.
It's not very efficient.
It doesn't scale very well.
How do we get around this?
Well, this is where the include
keyword comes in.
So we're going to say zombies =
Zombie.includes(brain).all.
What SQL does it run?
Let's take a look.
You can see here it's getting
all the zombies, and then it's
querying for all of the brains
for all of these zombies.
Much more efficient.
Lastly, we're going to talk
about the has_many :through
relationship.
And in this case in our example,
our zombie may play
multiple roles in
our zombie army.
We have a captain, a scout, a
soldier, and, of course, a
brain taster.
And a zombie can have
multiple roles.
So let's go ahead and implement
this relationship.
So we obviously have a Zombie
table, and we have a Role
table which could be
scout, captain,
soldier, and brain taster.
Based on the knowledge you have
thus far, you might think
that we should just add a
role_id to the zombie table
and then have zombie
belongs_to roll.
However, the problem with this
is it's only going to work if
a zombie has a single role,
and we want our zombies to
have multiple roles.
So how do we do that?
Well, we're going to
need another table.
We're going to need an
Assignments table which sits
in between Zombie and Role.
Inside that Assignments table,
we're going to have a role.id
and a zombie.id.
Through the role.id, Assignments
is going to belong
to Role, and through the
zombie.id, Assignments going
to belong to Zombie.
On the other side of the
relationship, we're going to
say Zombie has_many assignments
and Role has_many
assignments as well.
Before we jump into has_many
through, let's create the
migrations for these tables.
So here we have
CreateAssignments, we have a
zombie.id which is an integer, a
role.id which is an integer.
Lastly, we're going to have two
foreign keys-- a zombie.id
and a role.id.
We also want to create the Roles
table which is going to
be really simple.
It's only going to
have a title,
like captain or soldier.
Now let's jump into our model.
So here we have the Assignment
model which is going to
belongs_to :zombie and
belongs_to :role.
We'll have our Zombie model,
Zombie has_many :assignments,
and of course, Roll has_many
:assignments.
Now, here's where things
get interesting.
We need a way to represent
the relationship
between Zombie and Role.
That's where that has_many
:through comes in.
So we're going to say Zombie
has_many :roles, through:
:assignments.
We can represent the other
side of the relationship.
We can say Role has_many
:zombies, through:
:assignments.
OK.
Now that we've declared these,
let's jump into the console
and see what it looks
like when we
start coding some rails.
So we can say Zombie.last.
So we're going to fetch
the last zombie.
We can then give a zombie a
role by doing z.roles <<
Role.find_by_title("Captain").
It's the same thing as
just doing push.
It's just an array.
That's going to query for the
Role, and then it's going to
insert a row into assignments
to represent that.
We can also call z.roles to get
all the zombies' roles.
And that's going to do a single
query doing an INNER
JOIN on our database using both
the Assignments and the
Roles tables.
So we've reached the
end of Models
Still Taste Like Chicken.
Now, it's your turn to get
your hands dirty with the
challenges.
Good luck.