(SINGING) Put down your brains
and your entrails.
It's time to stop and learn
some rails, 'cause we got
something new to grab--
"Rails for Zombies"
by Envy Labs.
Hey, look, you made it all the
way to Level 5: Rendering
Extremities.
In this level, we're going to be
taking a look at controller
rendering options, some custom
RESTful routes, rendering
custom JSON, which is really
useful if you're creating an
API, and then finally,
we'll be diving
into a bunch of AJAX.
First, some review.
Here is our ZombiesController.
There's our show action.
There's no there's no responds
to in there.
So by default, it's going to be
looking for a file in the
Zombies directory called
show.html.erb.
So we're looking
to render that.
If that's only thing that
we're rendering,
that's all we need.
But what if we want to respond
to both HTML and JSON?
What do we need to
change then?
Well, that's where we do need
that respond_to block.
So let's write that here--
respond_to
format.html
so that's saying, yes,
this can respond to
HTML if it's requested.
That little comment there
show.html.erb, that's not
doing any configuration
at all.
That's just a reminder for us
to let us know that that's
what it's going to
be looking for.
And then maybe we also want to
respond to JSON, so we say
format.json, and then send in
the @zombie, and it's going to
properly do the JSON version
of that zombie object.
What if, though, the zombie
is dead again--
we want to render dead_again--
that dead_again.html file?
What do we do then?
Well, what we can do is
we can create a block.
So let's do format.html, do.
We're going to check the
decomposition to see if it's
dead again.
If it's dead again, render
out the dead_again view.
And we don't need an else
because if it doesn't hit that
conditional, it's simply, by
default, going to render out
the show.html.erb--
cool.
What if we realize after we
write this code that we don't
need JSON at all.
This is a web application.
It's only ever going to
respond to browsers.
We don't need the JSON
version of it.
What do we do then?
Well, at that point, we can
get rid of that respond to
block again.
So we can get rid of the
respond to block--
just have this.
OK.
Well, what if we only need
JSON, on the other hand?
What if we don't need
HTML at all.
Now we just need JSON?
How might it change?
Well, we don't need to add
the responds to block.
We only need to add render
json: zombie.
The moral of the story is that
if our action only needs to
respond to one thing, we
don't need to have
that responds to block.
And since we're talking about
JSON, when we're returning
JSON when using an API, we also
need to make sure we're
returning the correct
status codes.
Some common status codes include
ok, which is the
default, created,
unprocessable_entity.
There's also unauthorized,
processing, and not_found.
You may see these
in the scaffold
that's created by default.
In there, you might see
unprocessable_entity used when
we're returning the errors
for the zombie.
You also might see status:
:created returned when we're
creating a new zombie.
This is also returning another
header called location:.
It's just an API best practice
that if you're creating a new
resource, you return a location
which has the URL of
where to find that resource.
Let's customize our
API a little.
Let's create a custom action
in our Zombies controller
that's going to return the
decomposition status, and if
it's dead again, then also
return the status code
unprocessable_entity.
Well, how might we do that?
Well, it's going to
take two steps.
First, we need to add
a new member route--
a custom route--
and then we're going to create
a new action in the
ZombiesController.
So let's jump into it.
The customer route we want is
going to look like this, so we
can go to zombies/4/decomp, and
get back the JSON of the
decomposition status.
One way we can create this
custom route is by using the
match command, which we saw
in the previous "Rails for
Zombies," so something
like this.
We can do that, but there's
a better way to do it.
We can go into the resources.
You can see here, here's our
nested resources, and we can
specify get :decomp,
on: :member.
This is going to create a custom
RESTful Route, and it
does the same thing as that
match line up there.
Then we can run $ rake routes.
It'll give us back the routes,
the path, the method, the URL
that gets generated, and the
action that gets called, which
might be good to reference.
We can link to it using this
route helper if we want, so we
can just say,
decomp_zombie_path.
Before we move on, let's take
a deeper look at these two
types of custom routes that we
can use with our resources.
There's a member route, which
acts on a single resource, and
there's the collection route,
which acts on a
collection of resources.
Let's take a look at
a couple examples.
So here's our example.
We're getting the decomposition
state.
We have to send in the resource
that we want the
decomposition state from,
and then that gives
us this route helper.
Well, if we wanted to update
the decay on a specific
zombie, update is to put,
so we could say
put decay, on :member.
This is our URL.
And there is our route helper.
If we wanted to get a list of
all the freshest zombies, we
could create a collection route
called get :fresh, on:
:collection.
It would create this
URL, and here would
be the route helper.
If we wanted to create a search
on the zombies, we
could call post :search, on:
:collection, so it's going to
act on the collection
of those resources.
This is the URL, and here's
the route helper.
Some examples of using
this in our views--
we could have link_to 'fresh
zombies', fresh_zombies_path.
And if you we a search form,
it could look like this.
Let's jump back to our
challenge now.
So we figured out how to
add that member route.
The next step is we need to
create a new action inside
ZombiesController.
So here we are in our
We have a decomp action.
It's going to fetch the current
zombie, check to see
if decomposition is equal
to 'Dead again'.
If it is, then we're going to
render out the JSON with
status: :unprocessable_entity.
Otherwise, just render out the
JSON with status: :ok.
This is going to render out
JSON that looks like this.
And we don't want to render
out everything.
We only care about that decomp
value right there, so we're
going to have to modify this
code a little bit.
So let's take a deeper look
at the to_json syntax.
If we only care about the name
of the zombie in our JSON, we
can run to_json(only: :name).
If we want the name and
the age, we can
just send it in array.
If, instead of including things,
we want to exclude
things, we can say (except:
[:created_at, :updated_at,
:id, :email, :bio]).
That would print this out.
And we can also include
relationships.
Remember, zombie has a brain.
We can tell it to include that
in the JSON that it creates.
So, in this case, it
would include this.
Check out that brain
towards the bottom.
I noticed here that it is also
including zombie_id, which
we also might want to hide.
It might be a good idea.
But let's just continue on.
What if we want to make this
last line the default JSON
response when we call
@zombie.to_json?
How might we do this?
Well, we're going to dive
into the Zombie model.
Inside there, we're going
to define as_json, set a
parameter called option
that defaults to nil.
We'll call super(options
and then our hash.
What this is doing is it's
checking to see if we sent in
specifically what we want back
in from the JSON, and if we
have specifics about what
we want, use that.
Otherwise, if we just call
to_json, use this hash.
So let's jump back into
our challenge now
with this new knowledge.
Here's our decomposition
action again.
If zombie_decomp is 'Dead
again', render out only:
:decomp with status:
:unprocessable_entity.
Otherwise, just render
out :decomp.
By default, the status is going
to be OK, so I don't
need to mention it in
this second render.
Here's the JSON that it's
going to print out.
And now, we're about
halfway through.
We've gotten through rendering,
custom render
routes, custom JSON, and now,
we're on to the fun part--
writing some AJAX.
When I talk about AJAX, I'm
talking about making actions
in the browser, so when we click
a link or submit a form,
the page doesn't refresh.
Stuff happens, it contacts
the server--
doesn't refresh the browser.
For example, the first challenge
we're going to look
through is when delete is
pressed on this list, we want
that item to fade out
automatically,
not refresh the browser.
How do we do that?
Well, a couple different steps--
first, we need to make
that delete link
a remote call.
Then we're going to allow the
controller to accept that
JavaScript request.
Then we'll write the
JavaScript to
send back to the client.
So let's jump into it.
So here is the index view.
We're going through each of
the zombies, doing that
div_for you saw earlier--
link_to Zombie.
We've got "actions" 'edit'
and 'delete'.
So in this case, it's :delete
we want to look at.
All we have to do to make
it a remote call is add
remote: true.
That's all there is to it.
If you take a look at what this
generates in the client,
you'll see that all it's doing
is adding another one of those
HTML5 elements, data-remote.
Rails, of course, is using
that unobtrusive JavaScript
file we saw earlier to
hook into that and
make it an AJAX call.
So we've made the link
a remote call.
That was our first step.
We're done with that.
Next step-- we need to allow the
controller to accept the
JavaScript call, which
is a lot easier
than you might think.
So let's jump into the
ZombiesController.
Here is our destroy action.
This is the default scaffolding
destroy action--
nothing fancy about it.
All we have to do here is write
format.js, and that
tells our action that it can
respond to JavaScript.
That's all we have
to do there.
Next step-- the third step--
we need to write the
JavaScript to send back
to the client.
So let's jump into.
That we would put in the
destroy.js.erb in there.
We just call dom_id on the
zombie to get the div_id where
that zombie lives, and
call .fadeOut(); so
we can fade it out.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at what this view looks like.
So here's a little screencast.
We hit delete, and
it fades out.
We can hit delete on Tony.
It fades out.
And let's do one more--
delete and it fades out.
Pretty cool.
So we can destroy zombies
using AJAX.
Let's add a form so that when we
type in a zombie name here,
we can hit that create zombie
button, and it'll
automatically populate
that list without
refreshing the page.
Couple steps involved here.
We need to write format.js
in the controller--
simple as that.
Refactor the view-- we're going
to refactor the view a
little bit, and then
create the form.
And then lastly, we're going
to create the JavaScript.
So let's dive into it.
Here we are in our
ZombiesController.
This is the default create
action you get with your
scaffolding.
All we need to do here, again,
is add format.js.
Next step--
we need to refactor the view
and create the form.
So here is our is our
zombie list again.
We're going to refactor this.
We're going to create
a partial.
It'll make it easier
for our AJAX.
So we're going to take out the
div, put the div into a _zombie
partial, then inside of our
loop, all we have to do is
render zombie.
Hm, this is a little bit
different than our form
partial we saw earlier.
There's no quotes
around zombie.
What's happening under the
covers is that Rails is
looking at that zombie Active
Record model, looking at the
class, and then looking for a
partial for that class, which
by default, is going to
be the Zombies file
in the Zombies directory.
We can actually refactor
this loop to
do just render @zombies.
So those two things there,
they're the same thing.
Rails is smart enough to know
that we have a group of
zombies who want to iterate over
them and render out the
zombies partial.
Now, let's write the AJAX form
for creating the zombie.
So here, we have
form_for(Zombie.new, remote: true).
That's how we make
it an AJAX form.
Inside there, we're going to
have div class="field" and
the submit button down
there in the bottom.
That's all there really
is to it.
Now, let's create
the JavaScript.
So inside the create.js.erb,
we're going to go inside that
zombies div, and we're going
to append a new zombie.
We're going to call it
escape_javascript(render zombie).
We have to escape it properly
because we're putting all this
HTML right into this
JavaScript.
Then we're going to specify the
div for the zombie we just
created and highlight
it, so it's going to
highlight in yellow.
But what about when
the name is blank?
We do have a validation on name
for our zombie, so we
need to have some sort of
feedback to let people know
when they try and submit the
form when it's blank that
that's not working.
So we're going to add
to the JavaScript.
We're going to check to see if
the zombie is a new record.
If it's a new record, that
means it did not save
successfully, in which case, we
want to highlight the form.
We're going to highlight
it in red.
Otherwise, go ahead and append
the new zombie to the list.
Since we're using the highlight
effect here, we're
going to have to add jquery-ui
to our JavaScript libraries.
To do that, we're going to jump
into the application.js,
and all we have to do is
require jquery_ui.
That's all there is to it.
Now, here's a screen cast
of it in action.
So we click Create Zombie
and it doesn't work.
It gives us that red.
We can then start adding
zombies, and they get added
right on to the list of the
zombies and highlighted.
Two more challenges left.
In this one, we want to create
a form which allows us to set
a custom decomposition phase
on the zombie show page.
To do this, we need to create
a custom route for our
action-- a new custom route.
We need to define the form,
create the action in the
controller, and then write the
JavaScript, which we're going
to send back to the client.
So first things first, let's
jump back into our routes.
Here we have our routes file.
Inside there, we're going
to update the
decomposition status.
So we're going to
do a put action.
Call it custom_decomp,
on: :member, since
it's a member route.
Then let's define the form.
Inside the show action is where
we want to define the
form, but I also want to show
you that we have a span here
called decomp, and this
is where it shows the
decomposition phase.
This is the span we want
to update with AJAX.
Let's go and create the form.
We're going to wrap the form in
a dive called custom_phase.
We call form_for.
We need a custom URL here.
We want to go to our
custom_decomp_zombie_path.
We need to add remote: true
to make it an AJAX form.
We're going to give it a
Custom Phase title, a
text_field, a submit
button, and
that's pretty much it.
So we have the custom route.
We've defined the form.
Next up, we need to create the
action in our controller.
Let's jump into our
controller.
So here's the custom_decomp
action.
In here, we're going
to find the zombie.
We're going to set the
decomposition status, and then
we're going to save
the zombie.
And we don't need
a respond_to.
We're only responding
to JavaScript.
That's all.
So we don't need a
respond_to block.
Now, let's write the
JavaScript to
send back to the client.
First, we're going to set that
decomposition span to the new
value of our decomposition.
Let's go ahead and highlight
that, so it sticks out-- calls
our attention.
Then if the zombie decomposition
is "Dead again",
go ahead and fade out that
form we just created.
Let's check this
out in action.
So, here, we're going to
set a Custom Phase.
You can see when we add
that, it highlights
it and updates it.
And now when we put
Dead again, it
makes the form disappear.
Now, it's time for our
final challenge.
And we're basically going to
do the same thing we did in
our previous challenge, except
this time, we're only going to
communicate with our server
using JSON, and then we're
going to write some client side
JavaScript to communicate
with our server using JSON.
So it's kind of like we're
creating an API on the server,
and then writing JavaScript to
communicate with that API.
To make this happen, we're
going to define the form.
It's going to be a new form.
We're going to modify the
custom_decomp action so that
it responds to JSON, and then
we're going to write the
client side JavaScript,
and we're going to use
CoffeeScript to do so.
First up, let's define
the new form.
We specify form_for @zombie,
custom URL just like before,
except here, we're not putting
in remote true.
We give it a title,
text_field, and
the submit button.
Now, let's modify the advanced
decomp action.
In here, we're going to have a
respond_to block, and tell it
that it responds to JavaScript
and now JSON.
If it wants JSON, we're
going to render out
just the :decomp field.
Lastly, we're going to write
some client side CoffeeScript.
So here we are inside of
our zombies.js.coffee.
We've got (document).ready.
Grab that form.
When somebody submits the form,
prevent the form from
submitting.
Grab the form URL because we're
going to want to use
that later.
Grab the custom decomposition
value from that input field.
Then we're going to
do an AJAX call.
The type is going to be "put".
Remember, it's a "put" action.
We're going to call the
URL from the form.
We're going to send
in some JSON.
This is just plain old
JSON right here.
We specify the data type, and
then if this request is
successful, we're going to set
the new decomposition, give it
a highlight, then fadeOut
the custom phase form if
json_decomp equals
"Dead again".
Let's take a look at this
form in action.
So I can set the Custom Phase as
Smelly, as Putrid, or even
as Dead again.
And if I set it as Dead again,
and I hit Set, it makes the
form disappear.
So you've reached the end of the
videos, but your adventure
isn't over yet.
You've got some pretty
sophisticated challenges to
get through, and then once you
get through those, don't
forget, you've got that outro
video, where we'll tell you
where to go to learn more about
each of these topics.