Put down your brains
and your entrails.
It's time to stop and learn
some Rails, 'cause we got
something new to grab.
Rails for Zombies
by Envy Labs.
You made it all the
way to Level 4.
We're going to be talking
about asset
packaging and mailing.
So we're going to start out by
learning how to send emails
from inside of our Rails apps.
Then we're going to be looking
at the asset pipeline.
The asset pipeline is
new to Rails 3.1.
It's a bunch of really
new cool stuff.
We'll figure out how that works
with the asset tags.
Rails 3.1 also ships with
CoffeeScript and Sassy CSS
turned on out of the box.
We're going to get a taste of
each of those and then take a
look at the JavaScript manifest
file, which is
created for asset packager and
figure out how to use that
using something called
sprockets.
And that's about it.
So let's get to it.
In our application, we want to
create two different emails,
one for when the decomposition
state changes and one for when
we lose our brain.
So to do that, we're
going to use the
Rails generate command.
Again, we're going to say,
rails generate mailer.
We're going to call it
ZombieMailer, that's our
mailer class.
And then we're going to specify
two different emails,
the decomposition change email
and the lost brain email.
So we run that command.
It's going to create for us
the Zombie Mailer and two
views, which represent the text
version of our emails.
If we open up the ZombieMailer,
by default, before we
change anything, this is what
we're going to find.
In there, it's going to set
a default from address.
We're going to have
two methods.
One of them is going to
have decomp_change.
And you can see here,
it has a instance
variable called greeting.
And just like we have instance
variables in our controllers
to signify what we want access
to in our views,
same thing with mail.
When we actually create instance
variables, to signify
what we want access to
in our mail views.
So here we have a greeting, and
then we have this mail to:
command, which, obviously,
sends the mail.
And there's options
in here, and by
default it has a to address.
Let's customize this for our
particular ZombieMailer.
So first thing we're going to
do is, we're going to add a
zombie parameter.
The zombie parameter there,
we're going to send in the
particular zombie
that wants the
decomposition change email.
We're going to set that to
an instance variable.
So we have access to
that in the mailer.
Then we might also want
to show the last
tweet from the zombie.
So let's include that.
You might have attachments.
This is how you include
attachments, and then we can
say, mail to this particular
zombie, their email address,
and specify a subject
as you see here.
There are lots of additional
options you can send in to
this mail command like from,
cc, bcc, or reply to.
Any of these can also be put up
at the top of the file in
the defaults.
Now, let's create the content
of our email.
So we're going to open
up this view here.
We're going to say, greetings
@zombie.name.
Your decomposition state
is now blah, and your
last week was blah.
That's all there is to it.
If we want to HTML emails, we
just have to change it from
.text to .html.
And then we can write the HTML
email like you see here.
If we want both text and HTML,
well, we just create two
different files.
It's going to create a
multipart email for us, and
if it accepts HTML, it's
going to show HTML.
Now, let's figure out how
to send the email.
So we're going to jump into
our Zombie model.
Inside there, we're going to
have a private method called
decomp_change_notification.
The purpose of this method is
simply to send the email.
We're going to call
Zombiemailer.decomp_change self.
Remember, that method takes a
zombie parameter, and we're in
the Zombie model,
so we can just call self, it
will send the zombie right in,
and then we just need to call
deliver, and it's going to
deliver the email for us.
We're going to want to call
this method after save.
So we're going to
say, after_save
decomp_change_notification.
But we only want to happen if
the decomp has changed.
This decomp change method is a
helper method that is included
with active record by default.
When an attribute is changed,
you can call that method and
it will return true or false.
So by default, Rails is really
good with handling one off
emails, like a reset password
email, welcome
email, or even receipts.
But when it comes time to take
care of mailing lists, and
subscriptions, and
unsubscribing, and white lists
and blacklists, and all that
sort of stuff, in my opinion,
you're better off using
an external service,
one like Mad Mimi.
So if you wanted to use Mad
Mimi, you would add the Mad
Mimi gem to your gem file
and run bundle install.
You then just instantiate the
Mimi object sending in your
account email an API key.
You can then subscribe people
to mailing lists.
So in this case, I'm subscribing
Gregg@envylabs to
the newsletter.
I can remove Gregg from the
list by just calling
remove_from_list.
And I can get a list of all of
the subscriptions that Gregg
has with this command here.
At codeschool.com this is what
we use to do our monthly
newsletters.
And you may remember on the
sign up form, we have this
check box here.
When you keep that checked when
you sign up, we basically
do an API call.
We call add_to_list,
and we add you to
the newsletter list.
The great thing about going
with Mad Mimi is that they
have this great in-browser
interface for creating
beautiful newsletters, beautiful
emails, HTML emails.
You can see here's the Code
School email that we built
from inside Mad Mimi.
We build it, we select the
subscription list, and we just
hit send, and Mad Mimi
does the rest.
Now, we're going to be talking
about the asset
pipeline in Rails 3.1.
So back in Rails 3.0 and prior,
we would keep all of
our style sheets, JavaScripts
and images in their own
directory in the
public folder.
However, as applications get
bigger and you've got bigger
Rails apps, what you start to
find is that these folders
like the JavaScript folder
starts to feel like a bit of a
junk drawer.
Here's an example of a
JavaScript folder from a real
application.
And the JavaScript files you see
in here, some of these are
custom for a particular
Rails app.
Some of them are shared
libraries.
Some of them are vendor
Some of them are framework
libraries.
As you can see, it starts to
feel like a junk drawer.
So how do we fix things
in Rails 3.1?
In Rails 3.1, we have an asset
directory in our app directory.
We have an asset directory, lib,
and in vendor, we also
have an asset directory.
Inside each of these asset
folders, each of them can have
a style sheets directory, a
JavaScripts directory, and an
images directory.
So what's with the different
locations?
Well, in the app directory,
that's where we put all of our
apps-specific code.
In our lib directory, that's
where we put like shared code
that I might have between each
of my Rails apps, and in my
vendor directory, that's where I
put all my third-party code.
Like if I had a date picker or
a calendar, or some sort of
slide show, just some open
source library, I would put
that inside of my JavaScripts
directory, in
my vendor folder.
To get access to the files in
these directories, I only use
one path, that's the
assets path.
So if I go asset/custom or
asset/rails for an image, it's
actually going to check all the
different paths for this
particular asset.
To include that asset in my
Rails app, well, I can use the
javascript_include tag if I
want for a custom piece of
JavaScript and that just
creates this code.
I could use stylesheet_link tag
and then specify style,
and that would print out this.
I could also, for an image, use
the image tag helper, and
it will print out that.
Now, in production, it's
actually going to take the
file name and create a
fingerprint or MD5 hash, which
is going to be appended to
the file name like so.
Doing this allows for better
client-side caching.
So when you think about it, this
file name isn't going to
get changed until the contents
of it changed.
Otherwise, it should be
completely cached.
See, the way we were previously
doing it with
Rails, is we we're adding a hash
like this except well, we
were often doing it after the
file name in parameters, which
wasn't so good.
And we were changing it every
time we did a new deployment.
But you may not need to refresh
your Rails image if it
never changes.
So now we have a way to version
each of our assets and
cache them better on
the client side.
But what about in our
style sheets?
It's not uncommon at all to
see images referenced from
inside of our style sheets.
How do we take advantage
of this new
fingerprint caching mechanism?
Well, what we need to do
is add .erb to all
of our style sheets.
With this, we can write some
Rails code inside of our style
sheets, such as asset
path just like this.
That's going to generate this
nice asset path which includes
that fingerprint.
Rails 3.1 ships with SASSY
CSS by default.
SASSY CSS is just an improved
version of CSS that gives you
some additional features such
as nested rules, variables,
mixins, selectors, inheritance,
and more.
Let's take a look at a
quick example of how
we might use it.
So here we've got some CSS, and
you'll notice in each of
these pieces we've got
form.new_zombie,
form.new_zombie.
We're repeating ourselves.
Well, this would be a great
chance to use some nesting.
So check this out.
We're going to take form.new,
we're going to merge it up
into the top, properly nest
the CSS, and there we go.
It's a lot cleaner.
Next step, let's take a
look at CoffeeScript.
CoffeeScript is a programming
language that compiles into
JavaScript.
It's really nice, and you get
it by default in Rails 3.1.
So let's take a look at an
example where we might use
CoffeeScript.
We're not going to jump right
into CoffeeScript.
We need a good example.
So here is our zombie form.
Inside there, we've got a bio
field, and what we're going to
want to do is create a link
called show_bio_field when we
click Show Bio Field,
it's going to make
that field appear.
Here's a reminder of the CSS we
saw a second ago that bio
field is going to start
out as invisible.
And let's write the jQuery
first, not the
CoffeeScript first.
Let's write the jQuery first
to make this work.
So on document ready, we're
going to add code so that when
the show-bio link is clicked,
it's going to prevent the
default action, so it's not
going to follow the link.
Then we want to hide the link,
and then finally, we want to
show the text area.
So this would work just as it
is, but now let's take that
jQuery and let's convert
it into CoffeeScript.
So there's our document
ready, on click event.
We want to prevent default,
hide this, and
then show the bio.
It's nice to compare the two
side by side isn't it?
You can see some of the
benefits of using
CoffeeScript.
We no longer have any
of the brackets.
And in that interest, you want
to make sure you're using
either two spaces or
tabs to indent.
And we don't have any
of those semicolons.
But it's still very readable
as jQuery.
Remember back in level one, we
created a scaffold, and it
generated a bunch
of files for us?
Well, we have a couple files
that it created that
I didn't show you.
We've got a CoffeeScript file
and a SASSY CSS file.
Pretty cool.
Now, if you didn't want to run
SASSY CSS or CoffeeScript in
your Rails application, all
you'd have to do to remove it,
is take out those lines
from your Gemfile and
rerun bundle install.
That's all there is to it, and
the files that would get
generated wouldn't have those
extensions that you see there.
So every time we run scaffold,
it's going to create for us
another one of these
CoffeeScript files, and that's
where you would put all the
CoffeeScript for those
particular actions.
But do you then have to include
these in your Rails
application?
Maybe write something
like this?
You might think you do, but
you actually don't.
You see, the application.js
that was created with your
application when we created it
in the first place, uses
something called sprockets to
include all these files.
See, in the application.js,
there's a manifest of all the
JavaScript libraries we're
going to be using.
So let's take a look inside of
our application.js file.
In there, we're going
to see a new syntax.
You see that / / equals?
That's sprockets, and what
that's telling our application
is go grab the jQuery framework
and include it all
right here at this point
in this file.
It's kind of like
a Ruby include.
Then we have require jquery_ujs
to include all the
unobtrusive JavaScript that our
Rail application needs,
unobtrusive JavaScript that
does all of our Ajax.
It also does those form
conversions for the put and
delete methods.
Then we have require_tree.
That's going to require all
other JavaScript files in this
directory, in this assets
JavaScript directory.
That's how all those files with
scaffold created for us
getting included right here.
So all these JavaScript files
get put into this one file
called application.js, And in
production, have a look.
It's going to add that
fingerprint for us again so
that if our JavaScript files
don't change, the client
doesn't have to re-download
our JavaScripts.
Two more quick things.
There's a new rake task called
rake assets precompile.
You're going to want to run that
in production, and that's
going to precompile all these
assets, all of your
JavaScript, all your style
sheets, and images, so that
way the first request doesn't
have to do it.
And also in production,
it's going to minify
all your code.
So it's going to compress all
the JavaScript and all the
CSS, turn them into small file
names, take out all line
breaks so that it can
load really fast
on the client side.
But what about when you have
JavaScript in some of the
other asset directories, like in
the lib asset directory or
the vendor asset directory?
How do you include those
in your application.js?
Well, in this case, you can just
do required shared, and
require friend.
And these can be used to
specify order as well.
So whatever order these are in,
that's the order in which
they're going to be
appended together.
Not only are we using
sprockets now in our
JavaScripts file, we're
also using it in our
stylesheets file.
So let's take a look inside
of our application.css.
In here, we have require_self
and require_tree.
You already saw require_tree.
Require_self specifies
where to insert the
content in this file.
So if we had some style sheets
in here, this is going to get
included before everything
else.
Where is this really useful?
Well, if we had a reset style
sheet, we might want to make
that the first thing
that gets included.
So let's do the reset, then the
stuff in this file, and
then everything else.
This again, is going to compile
everything into the
application.css, and in
production, it's going to add
that fingerprint.
For more information on the
asset pipeline, there's a
great Rails guide on the topic,
which will walk you
through everything that I
talked about and more.
That about wraps it
up for Level 4.
But be sure to go do the
challenges and come right
back, because we've got some
really cool stuff in Level 5.
We've got some AJAX flying
around and JSON.
And we're going to be talking
about building APIs, and
really valuable stuff bringing
it all together.
So stay tuned and good luck
on the challenges.