Congratulations.
You've made it to the end
of Rails For Zombies 2.
You deserve a lollipop with
a first prize on it.
Or, or wait.
How about a heart on a stick?
Yeah, that's more zombie like.
Oh, wait.
Oh, wait, better yet, how
about a brain pop?
Here's what's crazy.
There's really such a thing
as a brain pop.
Everything I'm about to talk
about, including the brain
pops, can be found on the
links in the sidebar,
including a Rails For Zombies
2 t-shirt which looks like
this on the front and
this on the back.
We also still have Rails For
Zombies one t-shirts available
if you want to go retro.
You've come pretty far learning
Rails, but you're
probably wondering
where to go next.
Well, it's a good question.
I'm going to give you
lots of options.
First up, you may want to
download the source for the
completed course Rails app.
This is a functioning Rails app
that contains all the code
samples you saw in the slides,
and everything you completed
in the challenges.
If you've already created a
Rails app or two on your own,
or, you know, you go and do
that, you might want to come
back and check out our Rails
best practices course.
We go over ways to keep your
application organized and more
maintainable.
When it's time to create email
subscriptions on your Rails
app and do mass mailing, don't
forget to check out
madmimi.com and use the
Mad Mimi Ruby Gen.
You might notice below you have
some prizes, including a
link that will get
you one month of
RailsCasts Pro for free.
In case you're not familiar,
Ryan Bates releases one free
Rails screencast over on
rails.com per week.
And recently he decided to
introduce a pro subscription
where he's putting out more
advanced screencasts.
$10.00 off the
railstutorial.org's PDF
screencast bundle.
You see, Michael Hartl created
this great Ruby on Rails
tutorial, which if you click
this book button right here,
you can read for free.
The whole thing online.
If you want to support him,
though, if you go back to the
front page and scroll down,
you'll see that the PDF is
available for $26.00 the
screencast $85.00, and both
the screencast and the
PDF for $95.00.
And here's the cool thing.
If you use the discount code
codeschool, you can get $10.00
off the bundle, which means it's
the same price as getting
just the screencast, so you
might as well get that.
Also, a great resource
for learning Rails
are the Rails guides.
Really.
Take the time, read through
these, they are full of great
information.
Also, Ryan Bates' railscast.com
is a great
resource for learning all sorts
of things about Rails
and Rails libraries.
I'm also a really big fan of the
Agile Web Development with
Rails book.
That's how I learned Rails
with the first edition.
Now it's in its fourth
edition, and it even
covers Rails 3.1.
Also got to make sure you know
about Ruby 5, that's Envy
Labs' twice weekly news podcast
where we cover the
latest news in the
Ruby community.
You can find it on iTunes, and
it's a really good thing to
listen to you, like, say, when
you're mowing the lawn,
driving your hot dog,
or washing your cat.
And if you're not an audio
person, that's OK.
You can subscribe
to the RSS feed.
It's full of a lot of
information you should know as
a Ruby developer.
Lastly, got to let you know
about Top Ruby Jobs.
If you're looking for a Ruby job
now, or you're trying to
recruit a Ruby developer,
check out Top Ruby Jobs.
And now we've reached
the credits.
First we need to thank everybody
at Envy Labs.
There's now, at this point when
I'm making this video,
there's 20 people here, and each
of them contributed in
some way to this video,
most definitely.
Got to thank Oliver Tosh,
who did all the film.
Production Tyler Koeller, who
did the intro video, and
Everett Simpson, who did
the jingle that's
stuck in your head.
And of course, I need
to thank you.
Thank you for sporting Code
School, getting all the way
through the course, learning
some Rails.
If you want to show
your appreciation,
please give us a review.
Click on that review button on
this page, and let us know
what you think.
This also might be a good
opportunity to tell all your
Twitter friends about your
awesome accomplishment.
See that Twitter link
over there?
If you have any feedback, feel
free to tweet @codeschool, and
definitely follow Code School
if you want to be aware of
additional courses that
we're going to create.
There are definitely more Rails
ones in the pipeline.
So, I hope you have a great
week, and thanks for playing.