The Elements panel is great for
debugging HTML and CSS,
but if you're writing a complex
web application, odds
are you're using some
JavaScript, and when it comes
to JavaScript debugging, that's
where the Chrome Dev
Tools console comes in.
The Chrome Console is one
part log and one part
command line interface.
It allows us to easily interface
with our app to run
JavaScript commands and display
log messages for help
with debugging.
We can bring up the Console
by simply clicking on
the Console tab here.
On the command line, we can
write any JavaScript we like.
As you can see, I can even
press Tab to do some
auto-completion.
Here we wrote the JavaScript to
return to date header from
the page using its ID.
We can then run commands
on that object
right here in the Console.
The Chrome Console also provides
many ways for us to
log events happening inside of
our application, starting with
the Console Log command.
Here you can see we're simply
sending a string into the
Console log method and it
simply prints it out.
This can be a very useful way
to debug an application by
putting a bunch of Console log
commands inside of, maybe,
your JavaScript functions.
And those don't just output
strings, you can also put
JavaScript objects inside of
those Console log commands.
Let's take a look at that.
The Console object itself is a
JavaScript object so let's get
a little meta and write our
Console object to the Console.
As you can see, the Console
object is displayed in a tree
like structure that looks
similar to our DOM in our
Elements panel.
If we expand the prototype, we
can see all of our Console's
available functions.
There's a bunch of helpful
methods listed here, and you
can learn more about
them using the link
underneath the video.
But let's take a look at the
Assert method, which will look
familiar if you do a lot
of code testing.
If we pass a true Boolean
expression to assert, such as
asking is one equal to one, it
will continue on without
raising an error,
as you see here.
But if we give it a false
expression, it's going to
raise an assertion
failed error.
And as you can see here, our
Console is smart enough to
print out this error in red so
that we pay attention to it.
We'll talk more about debugging
errors later in
chapter three, but for now,
let's jump into some
challenges.