Another benefit our console
gives us is a handful of
helper methods that make it
easier to work with our
application.
Say we want to perform some
operations on the heading at
the top of the page, which
has an ID of Title.
We could laboriously
type out a call to
document.querySelector, but the
console provides us with a
shorthand way of doing this,
a function named with the
dollar-sign character sometimes
called bling.
Just typing bling with the Title
ID will save you a lot
of time and keystrokes.
You should be aware that many
JavaScript libraries come with
their own version of bling.
So if you load jQuery, for
example, it's going to
override the console's bling
with the jQuery bling.
In our sample app, we
are using jQuery.
So when we use the bling, even
if we send it an ID, it's
going to return us an array of
dom nodes instead of one.
So to get the same result, we
have to explicitly select the
first element of the array
using square brackets 0.
Now what if I want to use the
bling to grab an element from
the page and then figure out
where that is inside of my DOM
inside the Elements panel?
We can do that by grabbing an
element and passing it into
the inspect method.
That node is then selected
inside of our Elements panel.
We can also do the reverse.
Let's say you've selected a
node inside the Elements
panel, and you want to work
with it on the console.
Chrome keeps a history
of your selections.
The most recent one is stored
in the bling 0 variable.
So if we enter that, we get
the node we last selected.
If you'd like to view the dom
node you selected before this
one, you can actually
type bling 1.
Bling 2 will then go two
selections back in the
history and so on.
All right.
I hope you're ready to try out
some of this new bling in the
Challenges.