You're watching Discover
DevTools.
I'm Greg Pollack, and this is
Level Four, where we're going
to be taking a closer look at
debugging our applications.
As we saw in the last chapter,
the Chrome console will log
out any errors that our
application throws.
However, Chrome also comes
with some great debugging
tools so you can dive deeper
into these errors.
In the last chapter, you may
remember that we were getting
an error page when
we loaded it.
The events method was
returning null.
Let's try to fix that directly
in our code by checking to see
if events is equal to null, and
if it is, we'll set it to
an empty array.
With that done, if we go back
and refresh the page, we'll
see that our page loads
without errors.
Why don't you try this over
on the Challenges?