I'm Greg Pollack, and
you're watching
Rails 4: Zombie Outlaws.
In this level we're going to
be going over some new Ruby
features that affect rails,
thread safety, and routes.
Rails 3 introduced the match
keyword to map custom routes.
So here, as you can see we're
mapping a route to a specific
controller, in this case the
items controller, and the
purchase action.
However, when we use that match
keyword, it's matching
on every HTTP method.
So get, post, put, and delete.
This leaves us vulnerable
sometimes to cross site
scripting attacks.
So here we can see, we have a
cross site scripting attack
where a hacker might have
embedded this link in a
different web page.
People click on it and it
purchases an item, which
obviously isn't good.
The link is routed through
a get request.
And in our case we want them
to make this only post.
If you had a route like this
in Rails 4 and you tried to
start up your application,
you're going to get an error
that looks like this, Saying
that you need to specify your
HTTP method.
So let's go ahead and
rewrite this.
We can specify that this
is a post request in
two different ways.
First, by replacing match with
post or secondly, by using the
via keyword and specifying
via: :post as an option.
Additionally, if you did want
to route to accept all the
methods, you could specify via:
:all for all of the methods.
Let's say we have a Rails
application with resources
items in our routes file.
Now if we print our routes from
the command line, they'll
look something like this.
You'll notice we have that
put method down there.
Well it turns out if we look
inside the rest specification,
the put method requests that
the entire entity be stored
under the supplied URL.
That typically means
the entire request.
But in a Rails app, we only
might be interested in
updating parts of
our resource.
That's why in Rails 4, if we
print our routes, we'll see a
new method patch.
Patch is for updating
parts of a resource.
This is nothing new.
This is something that's existed
inside the HTTP 1.1
specification, we're just
now using it in Rails.
So now when we go to generate
an update form, we of course
use the form_for helper,
as you see here.
An HTML that it generates is
going to use the patch method.
Now, not all browsers support
the patch method, which is why
you can see here that our form
uses the post method.
And then Rails writes out this
hidden method field, which
specifies the value of patch.
And of course, when Rails
receives that request, it sees
that hidden method parameter
and will use patch as the
method of our requests.
We can also use patch in all
our controller test.
Sometimes a routes files can
have lots of duplications.
As you can see here we have
messages, posts, and items and
they all have comments,
categories, and
tags as nested resources.
How might we dry this up?
In Rails 4 we can dry this up
using the concern method.
So at the top of a routes file
we might specify a concern
called sociable which contain
three different resources,
comments, categories,
and tags.
To use this concern in our
resources all we need to do is
specify concerns, sociable.
The will add our three resources
under each of them.
This of course reads better and
it's easier to maintain.
Sometimes we also might want
to pass options into our
concern block.
To do this we add an options
argument to the
block as you see here.
Then we need to call our
concerns inside of a block.
And then we can pass
any arguments in to
that options block.
In this case, we only want the
resources under items like
comments, categories, and
tags to be created.
To keep our code organized, we
might want to extract our
concerns definition
into an object.
That object will need
to respond to call.
And we can even put it
in a separate file.
So in this case we created
a class called sociable.
This responds to the call method
and inside of that we
map our resources.
Back in Ruby 1.8.7, if we called
ID on nil, it would
return the number 4.
This is because objects in Ruby
all have an internal ID.
So if you called ID on zero or
true or false, you'd get back
an ID and also a warning.
You would get back a warning
that object ID will be
deprecating.
Instead you'll want to use
object ID if you want to get
access to this internal ID.
So in Ruby 1.9.2 or higher
versions, we can use this
object idea if for some reason
we want to get access to this
internal I.D. However, if we
call nil.id, it's going to
return a no method error.
But what does this have
to do with Rails?
Well let's say we're looking
up a post with a specific
title and we return.first
to get the first post.
And it returns nil as
you can see here.
If we call ID on that post, well
on the previous side we
saw that nil did have an ID, but
in Rails 3 it would return
a runtime error, saying that
you called ID for nil which
would mistakenly be 4,
if you really wanted
that use object_id.
This error came from the whiny
nil feature in Rails 3.
However, in Rails 4 we have to
use at least Ruby 1.9.3.
So now when we mistakenly call
ID on nil, it's going to
return that same no
method error.
Back in Rails 3, thread safety
was disabled on production.
If you wanted to go into your
production.rb, you could
simply un-comment
config.threadsafe to make it
thread safe.
However, in Rails 4 this
configuration option is
deprecated.
So if you created a new Rails
4 app and you looked inside
your production.rb, you would
see two new options which
enable thread safety by
default on production.
The first is cache classes
equals true.
This prevents class reloading
between requests and ensures
rack lock is not included
in the middleware stack.
So that your threads
don't get locked.
And our second option is
eager load equals true.
This insures that all of our
code is loaded before we
create new threads
as we need them.
To get the most out of thread
safety, make sure you're using
a multi-threaded server
like puma.
You've reached the
end of level one.
It's time for you to start
coding up some Rails 4 in the
challenges.
[GUN SHOT]