I'm Carlos Souza, and
you're watching
Rails 4: Zombie Outlaws.
In this level, we're going to be
talking about active record
and active model.
So back in previous versions
of Rails, you might have
gotten used to writing the old
style finders, say, using
Post.find and then specifying
that you want to find all and
then passing a hash with
the conditions.
These old style finders are now
deprecating and you should
just use the active relation
API instead.
Rewriting that to Post.where
author is admin.
If you really need to use the
old style finders, then you
can still use them through the
activerecord-deprecated_finders
gem.
Dynamic finders that return
collections are also
deprecated.
In this example, we're using the
magic finder
find_all_by_title and passing a
single argument.
Instead, we should just use
the active relation API
post.where title equals Rails.
The same thing for
find_last_by_author in this case.
You should just use the active
relation query specifying the
last element.
Dynamic finders that take a
single argument are not
deprecated.
In this example, find_by_title
will work fine in Rails 4.
However, there's a new way to
do this query using the new
find_by method that takes a hash
as an argument, which is
now the preferred
way to do this.
Dynamic find_by finders that
take a conditions hash are now
deprecated.
In this example, using the
find_by_title passing the hash
as the second argument is not
supported in Rails 4.
And again, you should use the
find_by method passing the
single hash as an argument.
Another reason why you should
prefer the find_by method is
because it allows dynamic
input more easily.
In this case, we could get the
post params back from some
other method and pass it down
to the find_by method.
And if you look at the
implementation of the find by
method, you'll notice that
find by is only a wrapper
around the where method that
returns the first occurrence.
So find by takes pretty
much the same
arguments that where does.
Lastly, dynamic finders that
create new records are also
deprecated.
In this example, find_or_
initialize_by_title or
find_or_create_by_title were both
deprecated in favor of the new
find_or_initialize_by and
find_or_create_by methods that
both take a hash
as an argument.
There's yet another alternative
to this method
introducing Rails 3, however,
there's a couple of gotchas
with this alternative.
Let's take a look
at an example.
Here, we're calling
first or create on
the return of a query.
What's going to happen here is
that if there's no existing
post with the title of
Rails 4, then it'll
create a new post.
However, if you happen to have
any call backs defined for
create, say, after you create,
any query that runs on that
same model will run within
the context of the scope.
In this case, we're querying
for all posts
where author is admin.
However, this query is going to
run within the context of
the initial query so it's
actually going to select all
posts where author equals admin
and title equals Rails
4, which is kind of an
unexpected behavior.
So this is another reason why
should prefer the new method
find or create by.
In this method, if there's no
existing post with the title
for Rails 4, then it's simply
going to create a new post
with the title for Rails 4 and
it does not affect scoping of
queries that run within
the callback.
And as you can see here, the
query insider after create
method is going to simply look
for all posts where author
equals admin.
We also had the update attribute
method which would
take two arguments and in Rails
3, we had the addition
of update column method
that would do
basically the same thing.
The basic difference between
these is that these on the
right here, they skip validation
all together.
Rails 4 adds a new alternative
to the update attributes
method simply called update,
which behaves the same way and
is not the preferred way to
update attributes for a model.
And for these guys on the
right, we have an update
columns method which takes a
hash as an argument and simply
builds a SQL statement
and executes it
straight into the database.
Again, skipping all the
validations for that model.
So back in Rails 3, you might
have used the scoped method
that basically allows you to
dynamically build queries
depending on certain
conditions.
In this example here for an
index action on a controller,
we're calling tweet.scoped which
does not run the query
and it returns an active
relation object.
And based on certain
conditions, we
can call other methods.
In this case, tweets.recent in
case we have a params recent.
Rails 4 deprecates scoped and we
should now just simply use
the all method which does not
run the query right away and
returns a relation object that
we can call other methods on.
So in this example, what we get
back from tweet.all it's a
chainable method that, depending
on the conditions,
we can call other methods on.