I'm Gregg Pollack and
you're watching
Rails 4, Zombie Outlaws.
In this level, we're going
to be going over strong
parameters and remote forms.
When building web applications,
it's important
to ensure the malicious users
can't insert sensitive data
into your database by putting
in form fields
like you see here.
This is the typical scenario
where you are creating a new
user and someone tries to make
them an admin user by maybe
using dev tools or inspector
in the browser to add a new
field like admin 1.
In Rails 3, the model is
responsible for white listing
parameters that get sent in
from forms using attribute
accessible.
This allows us to specify which
attributes can get set
by mass assignments like update
attributes, as you see here.
So with this white list, if we
sent in the user name, it
would work, but if we sent in
the user name and that admin
field, well it wouldn't work.
It would cause an error.
With Rails 4, we've moved the
responsibility of white
listing parameters from the
model to the controller.
So in the model we no longer
need to specify attribute
accessible.
So now in our controller we
have to specify which
parameters are required and
which are permitted.
Let me show you how
this works.
Here's the parameter hash that
our application is receiving.
If our code simply had params
require user, that's saying
that we're requiring the user
key to be inside of our
parameter hash.
Require works just like
a validation.
We're validating that the key
exists and if it does, it's
going to simply return an empty
hash because we haven't
allowed any parameters
to pass through yet.
If our parameter hash doesn't
contain user, it's going to
throw an error and return a
400 status code response.
Obviously, we want
the user name.
And this is where the permit
method comes in.
So here's our parameters.
If we call params require user
permit name, it'll validate
that the user keyword exists and
permit the name parameter
to pass through.
However, if we have a malicious
user that sends in
that admin key you see there,
the permit method is going to
strip out any invalid
parameters, in this case,
admin and only give
us the name.
Permit also filters out invalid
parameter types.
Here's all the parameter
types that it's going
to accept by default.
Also by default, all unpermitted
parameters will
get logged.
However, if you'd like it to
raise an exception when this
happens, you can edit your
configuration inside your
application.rb and
set it to raise an
error when this happens.
For more information about
strong parameters, check out
the link down here.
You might find that these new
strong parameters cause some
duplication of code inside
your controllers, maybe
something like this, where we're
requiring and permitting
the same parameters in both our
create and update methods.
One way we can DRY up this code
is by extracting it into
a common method, in this case,
our user params method.
Then inside of our create and
update methods, we simply call
user params.
If you still need to use
attribute protected and
attribute accessible inside your
Rails 4 application, you
still can but you're going to
need to install it as a gem.
For a while now, Rails has come
with good form security
and it looks something
like this.
When you generate a form,
Rails creates a unique
authenticity token inside
of that form.
Then when it gets submitted,
it validates that token and
only if it matches, does the
form properly go through to
your Rails app.
This way, malicious users don't
have a token and can't
submit form data.
This also helps you prevent form
spam, robots hacking your
web pages because they need an
authenticity token every time
they submit that form.
They can't just submit the
form over and over again.
In Rails 3, if you have a remote
form, so remote: true,
as in it's going to use Ajax
for the form, inside of the
HTML that it generates, it's
still going to have the
authenticity token
inside of it.
However, the Ajax request isn't
going to even use it
because that same token is
actually found inside the meta
tag on your page and that's
where the unobtrusive
JavaScript that ships
with Rails is
going to read it from.
In Rails 4, by default, if we're
using a remote form, the
authenticity token is no longer
going to be inside of
the form HTML that's
generated for us.
This is nicer because for remote
forms we weren't using
it anyways.
However, if our browser has
JavaScript turned off for some
reason, the form is no longer
going to work, but that might
not be a big deal to you.
However, if this is a big deal
to you, you can re-enable this
authenticity token for remote
forms by adding this
configuration line.
So what happens when
an application
gets an invalid token?
Well here you can see we're
sending an invalid token to
Rails 3 and by default, it's
going to reset the session and
log this warning.
With Rails 4, we've been given a
little more control over how
our application behaves
when this happens.
By default in application.rb,
we're going to see
protect_from_forgery
with: :exception.
This is the default.
And of course, it'll raise an
invalid authenticity token
when we receive an
invalid token.
We could also change this to
:null_session which would empty
our session but not trigger
the error, or we could use
:reset_session which will create
a new session for this
user destroying the old one.