I'm Gregg Pollack.
And you're watching Rails 4:
Zombie Outlaws. In this
level, we're going to be talking
about filters, session
and custom flash types.
So you're probably
familiar with
action controller filters.
Sometimes we use them to
set instance variables.
Sometimes we use them
for authentication.
But the word filter doesn't
really accurately describe
what we're doing.
We're not filtering any data
inside of our filters.
That's why in Rails 4, we have
a new syntax for this, or an
alternative syntax.
We can say "before_action," like
you see here, which kind
of describes what we're doing
in a more accurate way.
As I mentioned, this is
an alternative syntax.
You can still use all those
filter methods, but now they
have equivalent action methods
as you see here.
Let's take a minute to
talk about session
and how we use it.
When we're dealing with login,
we might have a Sessions
Controller.
Inside there, when somebody
logs in, we might set the
Session User ID equal to
that particular user.
That way, when that user comes
back to the website, we can
read that user ID back
out of the session to
get the current user.
But what is really going on
under the covers here to
persist that session variable?
By default, Rails uses a
Cookie Session store.
So on the first request after
the session gets created, the
application will send the
session data back to the
browser in the form of
a cookie that gets
stored in the browser.
And then all of the next
requests that browser does,
it's going to send that cookie
back to the app.
The app then reads the
information out of the cookie
back into that session, which
allows it to read the user ID
as you see here.
So back in Rails 3, that cookie
that gets created which
contains the session variables,
is digitally signed.
What this means is that a user
could not alter this data.
However, they can read it.
So if we use some Ruby code as
you see down here, we can read
out the user ID of
one, two, three.
So this is mostly secure.
But Rails 4 adds another
layer of security by
encrypting the cookie.
So here you can see in Rails 4,
the cookie gets encrypted.
And now if we try to read
content from that encrypted
cookie, well, we just can't.
Rails uses the secret_key_base
to encrypt this cookie, which
is inside of your
secret_token.rb.
So if your application is stored
on a public repo, you
probably don't want this checked
into source control.
So you might want to do
something like this in
production, where you're storing
the Secret Key Base
inside an environment
variable.
Now let's take a look
at Flash types.
As you may already know, we
use Flash types to send
messages back to our user.
In this case, we're saying
"item created."
Then inside of our show.erb,
we specify where we want to
print out our Flash message.
And then it prints it in our
resulting HTML, maybe looking
something like this.
In more recent versions of Rails
3 and in Rails 4, we
don't even have to use Flash
Notice and Flash Alert inside
of our ERB files.
For short, we can do just
Notice and Alert.
However, we can only use these
helper methods on registered
flash types.
In Rails 4, we now have the
ability to specify our own
custom flash types.
So here, we're specifying
flash types "grunt" and
"snarl" inside of our
application controller.
Then inside of or controllers,
we can set these Flash types,
either by setting them
explicitly or even using the
redirect syntax.
Then inside of our ERB files,
we can print them out using
the Helper methods.