I'm Greg Pollack and
you're watching
Rails 4 Zombie Outlaws.
In this level, we're going to
be going over ETags, Dalli,
and Cache Digests.
One of the new features in Rails
4 is declarative ETags.
But in order to understand how
to use them, you need to
understand what ETags are.
And since that's something
that not everybody
understands, I thought I would
give a brief introduction.
If you already know what
they are, feel
free to skip on ahead.
Rails 3 and 4 apps by
default use ETags.
But what does that mean?
Well here's the default ETag
behavior, here we have our
client, which is probably a
browser that requests a web
page from our Rails app.
Our Rails app renders out the
entire response body.
Then it creates an ETag by doing
an MD5 hash on the
entire response body.
The code looks something
like this.
Then it sends back to the client
the response body and
the ETag as a header field.
The client is going to
cache the response
and store the ETag.
Then the next time we request
that same page, the client is
going to send the ETag in the
if none match header.
Don't ask me why the header that
it sends to the browser
isn't called ETag.
It's called, if none match,
that's just what we use, it's
weird, just get used to it.
Once the Rails app receives the
request, it renders out
the entire response body.
It then creates a ETag
in the same way.
It then compares the ETag that
was sent over with the one it
just generated.
If the ETags match,
the body is not
sent back to our client.
It is simply sent the status
code 304 not modified.
That tells our client's browser
that nothing on the
page has changed since the last
request and it can load
the entire page from
their cache.
ETag stands for entity tag and
it's simply a key we use to
see if the page has changed.
If we take a look under the
covers at the headers that our
browser is sending and
receiving, we can see on the
first request that it
returned 200 OK.
Which means the entire body was
included in the response
and cached by our browser.
You'll notice at the bottom
here, we can see the actual
ETag that was sent with
this response.
Here we can see on the second
request that we sent the ETag
in the, if none match header,
down there at the bottom.
And the server responded
with a 304 status
code meaning not modified.
And our browser loaded the web
page from our local cache.
As we mentioned, by default
Rails calculates the ETag by
generating the entire response
body and then generating an
ETag which it sends back
to the client.
This is great on the client side
because if it gets that
304 not modified code, that
means it can load the entire
page from the local cache, and
it doesn't have to re download
everything.
However, on the server side, we
have to re render the page
every time to generate the ETag
which isn't that efficient.
If only there were a way to
generate a more specific ETag.
That's where
fresh_when comes in.
Here inside of our items
controller, we're going to set
a custom ETag.
We can do that by using,
fresh_when.
What this is going to do is
it's going to set the ETag
equal to the cache key of
that particular item.
The cache key as you can see
here is a combination of the
model name, the ID, and
the updated at field.
It then gets the MD5 hash of
this key and that's what it
uses as the ETag.
So let's go through
our client-server
scenario one more time.
This time when our server
receives the request, it's
going to create an ETag right
there in the controller.
Then render the body.
And then finally, send the
response with our ETag based
on the items cache key.
Then if we access the same page
for a second time, it's
going to send the ETag
back to the server.
Rails is going to create the
ETag in our controller again.
Compare the ETag to the one
sent over by our browser.
And if our ETags match, it's
going to send a 304 back to
our browser, and not bother with
rendering out the body of
the web page.
So this fresh_when command
really does two things.
First, it creates
the ETag for us.
And then it checks to see if
the client sent an ETag with
the request, if that
matches the ETag
that it just generated.
And if it does it
sends back 304.
Otherwise it will continue
rendering out the web page.
If we have multiple actions in
our controller that use ETags,
they might start to look pretty
similar, and we might
be duplicating some code.
So how might we re factor this
repetition? Well this is where
declarative ETags come in.
It allows us to declare a ETag
at the top of our controller.
We could even declare multiple
ETags at the top of our
controller.
So here we're declaring both
current user ID, and current
user age, and this is going to
get combined onto our ETag.
So as you see in the bottom
here when we do fresh_when
item, this is the same as doing
fresh_when item, current
user ID, current user age.