I'm Greg Pollock, and
you're watching
Rails 4, Zombie Outlaws.
And in this level, we're going
to be talking about
ActionControllerLive
and Turbolinks.
Let's say we have an Items
Controller, and we have a lot
of people connecting to see
the list of Items from our
Items Controller.
And when one person adds a new
Item, we want that to be
reflected on everyone's list.
This is kind of similar
to a chat room.
Right?
Where you have multiple people
connected to a chat room, and
when one person says something,
you want to
broadcast that message
to everyone.
How might we implement
this in Rails?
Well one way is to implement
polling.
Right?
Each of these people could be
checking the server to say,
hey, anybody said anything?
Any new Items?
But obviously that's
not very efficient.
We could also keep a connection
open and stream new
requests as they come in.
But controllers, and the way
Rails is built, isn't
necessarily good at that.
However, this is where
ActionController::Live comes in.
If we add this one line to our
controller, we get the ability
to do streaming inside
of our Actions.
WEBrick, the default server,
buffers output, which would
break streaming.
So if we're going to play around
with this feature, we
need to use a different server
like Puma, or Rainbows.
And to do that, we just
need to put it
inside of our gem file.
Now to do some streaming inside
of our controller
inside of an action, in this
case our show action, we need
to set a content type header,
which will tell our browser
that we're sending
an event stream.
And then, since we're
including
ActionController::Live in our
controller, we get access to
the stream object
in our response.
So in this case, we're going
to create a loop.
So three times we're going to
Write the string, "Hello,
browser!" and then sleep
for one second.
And then finally, at the
end, we're going
to close the stream.
So if we navigated to this URL
we would see, Hello, browser!
Hello, browser!
And again, Hello, browser!
It's really important that we
always remember to close the
stream, otherwise, it's going
to stay open forever.
Now let's jump back to our Items
example, where we have a
list of items, and we want them
to get updated as they
are created.
Here is our ERB file with our
unordered Items list.
Now we need to write some
JavaScript that will connect
to the server, and whenever
a new Item is created,
add it to that list.
Luckily, JavaScript has a
library called EventSource,
which will allow us to specify
a path to connect to.
Then we can add an
eventListener.
So whenever a new message comes
from that EventSource,
we can pass in a callback
to be executed.
The callback, itself, is pretty
self-explanatory.
It takes the event as an
argument, and then we can just
construct a new list item using
the event data, and
append that onto our list.
It's really important that
we set the content-type,
otherwise streaming
won't work.
And, we also have to
set this header
before we start streaming.
So if we did something like
this, where we tried to set
the header after we started
streaming, well, it wouldn't
work, because all the headers
were already sent.
To fix this code, we just need
to set the header before we
start writing to the stream.
Using streaming can be really
useful when paired with a
messaging system, like
Redis, for example.
Here's what using Redis
might look like.
First we set the header, then
we'll connect to Redis and
we'll subscribe to the "item
create" channel.
Then once a message arrives,
we want to write out to the
stream the data that
we received.
Lastly, we'll just
close the stream.
Next up, we're going to talk a
little bit about Turbolinks.
But first, let's take a look at
two screen casts, one that
doesn't use Turbolinks
and one that does.
Here's the one that doesn't.
As you can see, every time we
click a link, it does a
complete page refresh.
We can see that.
We can see a little bit of
visible lag between pages.
And now let's do the same
thing with Turbolinks.
As you can see, the lag seems
to have gone away, and the
pages load lightning fast.
But how is this happening?
Without Turbolinks, when you
click on the link it needs to
reload the entire page.
Even when you're using
ETags, for example,
which we learned about.
And the server returns a 304
Not Modified, and the
page gets loaded from cache,
it still has to redraw the
entire page.
Now with Turbolinks, which our
Rails 4 applications will use
by default, when we click on a
link it uses AJAX to go and
fetch the page, download it, and
then it only updates the
title and the body in the page
which was previously rendered.
So it doesn't redraw the
entire page, it simply
replaces the title, and replaces
the body with the
content that it fetched
from the new page.
None of the assets, or style
sheets, or JavaScript files
get reloaded.
So you've lots of people on your
website, and they're not
re-downloading any
of these assets.
Well, how do we make sure the
browsers know when you do go
and update that JavaScript
library or that CSS library?
This is what the
data-turbolinks-track option is
for, which you'll see by
default in your Rails 4
applications.
This tells your app
to keep track of
changes in these files.
So if you do a deploy and one
of these files changes,
Turbolinks is going to tell the
browser to do a full page
reload, so you can get
the new files.
All this functionality is
encapsulated inside the
Turbolinks gem,
which you're going to see inside
your gem file, and your
application.js by default.
So obviously, if you don't
want Turbolinks and this
additional functionality,
just remove them.
So we're using Rails 4 in
our new application with
Turbolinks, and we have a little
jQuery code, which
looks like this.
So when we click on an item
we get an alert box.
Let's see this in action.
So, we go here, we click on the
check box and it didn't
work the first time.
Not until we reloaded
the page.
And now it does.
When we first loaded up the
Index page, the page loaded,
and the document ready
event fired.
It looked for anything
with that ID to hook
on the Click event.
Didn't find anything.
Then when we clicked on Edit, it
used Turbolinks to load up
the new page, put the new
content in there with the
check box, but the document
ready event didn't fire again.
It only runs once.
When we refreshed the Edit page,
the DOM event fired, and
that time-- the second time
we loaded the page--
it did work.
So how do we fix this
with Turbolinks?
Well Turbolinks has a series
of events that
we can listen for.
One of them being, the page:load
event, which fires
every time we load a new
page using Turbolinks.
So if we wanted this to work, we
could simply listen for the
page:load event, and call the
Initialize method, every time
it's triggered.
Another work-around for this,
aside from listening to these
new events, is to include the
jQuery Turbolinks gem, if
you're using jQuery.
This will bind the document
ready event to
the page:load event.
So document ready will get run
every time a new page is
loaded via Turbolinks.
You just want to make sure, if
you use this library, that you
require it immediately after
your jQuery library inside
your application js.
Another work-around for this
is to simply bind events
straight to the document,
like you see here.
This will work when the page is
reloaded, or when you load
new pages using Turbolinks.
Just to recap, when we're on a
page with Turbolinks and we
click a link, the moment we
click that link an Ajax event
is fired to the server.
However, this page
stays the same.
It still has the old content.
Once we get a response back
from the server, it's then
going to swap out the old
content with the new,
instantaneously.
That's why it's so quick.
However, there still might be
some latency involved there.
The server might not be so
quick, which might not be a
good user experience.
They click the link and
nothing happens.
So if we're worried about
latency, we might want to add
some loading indicator to our
page, so that our users know
that something's happening.
Let's add a loading message
to our page.
So to do this, we're going
to add a new div.
And we're going to define a
style, which, of course, by
default is hidden.
Then there's two Turbolinks
events we're
going to listen for.
First we listen for fetch,
that's when a new page is
being retrieved.
So if we go to fetch a new page,
we're going to show the
loading div.
Then once that response has
been received and the page
gets updated, the page:change
event fires, and we want to
hide our loading div.
By default, Turbolinks is going
to hook onto all of the
links in our application.
But we might not want that.
If we have links that we want to
force a full page refresh,
we can specify the data-no-turbolink
option in that link.
We can also use this attribute
on containers, and then all
the children inside that
container will be opted out of
Turbolinks.
So in this case, those
links are going to
force a full page refresh.