[SINGING]
jQuery will help you build your
dotcom, find an element
inside of the DOM, AJAX
traversal manipulation, event
handling, and animation,
providing you with
versatility, an API with
extensibility.
jQuery is something
you can't ignore.
Write less.
Do more.
I'm Greg Pollack, and you're
watching Try jQuery.
This course should take about
three hours to get through.
It's going to start with a bunch
of videos, and following
each video, you're going to have
a Code Challenge in the
browser, where you actually
have to prove that you
understood what you
just learned.
After you get each question
right, you're
going to earn points.
And then at the end of each
level, you're going to earn a
badge, finally earning the
course badge, which will be
displayed in your Code
School profile.
In order to take this course,
you need to be familiar with
HTML, which is how we create
content inside web pages, CSS
which is how we style that
content, and maybe a little
bit of JavaScript.
But if you're not familiar with
JavaScript yet, don't worry.
We'll be going over it as we
go through the tutorial.
Now before we start looking at
code, we need to make sure
everybody knows what jQuery
is and what it can do.
Here's a few examples
at Code School.
When somebody clicks the login
button on Code School, the
login form appears and
can disappear once
they click that again.
Over on the Code School payment
page, people can
select between paying yearly and
monthly, and the price is
updated accordingly.
Also in this page, we can toggle
different CSS classes,
based on which button somebody
presses, as you can see here.
Five common ways you might use
jQuery include finding
elements on an HTML document,
changing that HTML content,
listening to what a user does
and reacting accordingly, like
when they press a button,
animating content on the page,
and talking over the network.
So if you want to communicate
with a server, without having
to refresh a whole browser
page, you can
do that with jQuery.
Here's some HTML from a web page
And you can see here it
has a title, an h1,
and a paragraph.
And our objective is to modify
the h1 element using jQuery.
To do this we first need to find
this element, and then we
need to change it.
So how can we write some jQuery
to find that h1 inside
of our HTML?
Well in order to do that, we
need to understand a little
bit better how our browser
organizes the HTML it receives.
It does this in something
called the
Document Object Model.
This is a tree like structure,
created by browsers, so we can
quickly find HTML elements
using JavaScript.
In this tutorial, we'll refer
to the Document Object Model
as the DOM.
When we go to a URL, and our
browser starts receiving HTML
from that web page, it loads
it piece by piece into the
DOM, like so.
As it receives each element,
it starts building nodes
inside of our DOM.
So here, you can see it has an
HTML node, which is underneath
the document node.
You might say HTML is a child of
the document node, and the
document is the parent
of the HTML node.
Then we have a head node, then
underneath that a title node.
And that title of jQuery
Adventures--
we're going to call that a
text node, which lives
underneath title.
Then we have the body
node, which is a
sibling to the head node.
Underneath that is an h1 node,
with a text element of where
do you want to go.
And lastly, we have a paragraph
node, which also has
a text node under it.
In order to interact with the
DOM, all browsers use
JavaScript.
That's the standard language
that gives developers a way to
interact with our DOM.
So here we have a web server.
It has a JavaScript file.
It also has some HTML files
on it, as well.
Over on the other side, we
have our web browser.
The web browser might request a
web page by going to a URL.
The web server is going to
send back the HTML you
requested, along with any other
files needed to load
that page, including in this
case, some JavaScript.
The web browser is then
going to load that
HTML into the DOM.
And then once loaded, we can
execute the JavaScript that
was sent over to interact
with the DOM.
So you might be wondering, why
don't we use JavaScript to
interact with every browser?
Why do we even need jQuery?
Well, the catch here is that
each browser has a slightly
different DOM interface.
This is where jQuery comes in.
So you can write one piece of
code which can communicate
with all modern web browsers.
In order to access the DOM using
jQuery, we'll put some
code inside of this jQuery
function you see here.
To access the DOM using jQuery,
all we need to do is
specify the document key
word you see here.
But how can we search through
the DOM and find that h1
element we were looking for?
To figure this out, let's
jump back into our HTML.
And we need to think a little
bit about how we would use CSS
to decorate this web page.
If we wanted to decorate the
h1, we might write a CSS
selector, which looks
like this.
In this case, it's increasing
the font size of the h1.
To make the paragraph font color
blue, we would specify p
.
We use these same CSS electors
to find elements
from inside the DOM.
So if we wanted to find the h1,
we could simply specify
jQuery ("h1");.
Notice that h1 is wrapped in
a string with two double
quotation marks.
To find the paragraph from the
DOM, we could simply write
jQuery ("p");.
There's a shorter way we
can write this code.
Instead of specifying jQuery,
we can simply
use the dollar sign.
It's going to mean
the same thing.
So we know how to find the
h1 using that $("h1");.
But how do we modify
that element?
So remember, this is our DOM
representation of this HTML.
To find the h1, as we saw a
minute ago, we simply write
$("h1");, and that returns
the h1 element.
If we wanted to return the text
inside that h1, we would
simply call the text method,
like you see here.
It would return where
do you want to go.
In order to modify the element's
text, we can simply
send a string into
this text method.
Here, when we send where to, you
can see that it replaces
that text element in the
Dom with where to?
And if we were watching this
web page in our browser, we
would see the page
get updated.
Now there's one thing you need
to be wary of when you're
running jQuery that interacts
with the DOM.
The HTML might be getting sent
over to your browser, and that
JavaScript might
fire off before
the DOM is done loading.
In this case, the DOM hadn't
finished loading yet, and so
when it went to change
the text in the
h1, it didn't work.
So we need to make sure the DOM
is finished loading before
we try to interact with
any HTML on the page.
It turns out that when the DOM
is finished loading, it
triggers an event.
It says, "I'm ready."
So we need to be
listening for that signal.
And we only want our jQuery
code to run once that DOM
ready event has been
triggered.
The code looks something
like this.
We write jQuery(document).ready
and
then we have a function.
And anything inside of that
function is only going to get
run once the document
is ready.
So our completed code, while
we're fetching the h1 and then
changing the text element,
is going to look
something like this.
We're waiting until the document
is ready, and then
we're fetching the h1, and then
changing the text node.
Before we get into the
challenges, let's take a quick
tour of the challenge
interface.
Over on the left side of the
screen is our Table of
Contents, showing
us six levels.
When we're in each level, we can
see the different sections
of the level and
little buttons.
The Play buttons represent a
video, and the Prompt buttons
represent a code challenge.
You're more than welcome to
jump around between levels
sections and challenges.
Down below, we have a Download
button to grab all the slides
for the course, which can be
really useful if you want to
put them on a second monitor
for reference.
Also at the bottom here, we'll
see listed our total number of
points and the progress bar to
see how much we've completed.
The Table of Contents is useful
for navigation, but if
you want to get yourself a
little more screen room, you
might want to minimize it.
On the right side of the page
you can see the challenge
title and text.
Sometimes a challenge will
link to external jQuery
documentation, as you
can see here.
We then see the rendered HTML
page we'll be interacting
with, using jQuery, and
below that, the HTML
source of the page.
Notice this HTML has a lock
next to it, meaning that
you're not going to be
able to edit it.
At the bottom of the
page, you'll see
our JavaScript console.
This is where you'll want
to start coding.
And the first few challenges,
you'll
practice using selectors.
Notice how when I type div, the
div HTML is highlighted in
the source.
Similarly, if I type p to select
the paragraph, I can
visualize the selection.
And if I scroll up a little,
we'll see the paragraph
element in the rendered HTML
is highlighted, as well, to
help us solve the challenge.
If you need reference to the
slides, and you don't already
have them downloaded, you
can view them here
in the slide tab.
And if you get stuck at any
point, you can always ask for
a hint in the Hint tab.
Hints are free, but if you want
to show the answer, it'll
cost you 75 points
off your score.
Next, I want to call your
attention to this little Split
Screen button on the
right side, here.
If your monitor is big enough,
this allows you to view both
the source code and the slides
at the same time.
Let's go ahead and solve this
challenge by typing in the
right answer in the console and
hitting Enter or Return.
Awesome, now we can continue
on to the next challenge by
clicking the Continue button
or hitting Alt-Return or
Option-Return.
Here's an example of a challenge
later in the course
which doesn't use the console,
and instead, we need to write
a couple lines of jQuery
on the editor, which
is no longer locked.
To submit the code, we just hit
the Submit button on the
bottom right.
On these challenges, you'll
probably want to make sure you
go split screen, so you can see
both the JavaScript and
the HTML source at
the same time.
Well it's time for you to get
your hands dirty in the
challenges.
And I'll see you in
the next video.