Good job.
So you've written some
of your first jQuery.
And you might be wondering,
how do I get
jQuery onto my web pages?
Well, first step is to go to
the jQuery.com webpage,
download jQuery.
You can load it into your HTML
page, using this script tag
you see here.
But in order to start using it,
you're probably going to
want to create another file,
maybe called application.js.
Include that inside your HTML.
And then inside your
application.js, meaning
JavaScript, you can
start writing your
jQuery right there.
In this section, let's look at
a few more ways we can find
elements in the DOM.
So here's some new HTML.
You can see, it has a UL, or
unordered list, of different
travel destinations.
How might we change the text of
every li on this web page?
Well, first we need to
find all of them.
And then we need to
modify their text.
Let's take a look at the
DOM on this webpage.
First, let's figure out what
the DOM looks like.
So there's our tree.
To select all these li's,
we don't need
three lines of code.
We just need one.
We just specify li,
just like that.
And it returns a jQuery object
of all of the li's.
If you want to change their text
nodes all to Orlando, we
simply send in the
string Orlando.
There we go.
If we're building a big webpage,
it's not unheard of
to have many different li's
inside many different lists
and many different paragraphs.
But we might not want
to select all of
them all of the time.
So how do we fix that?
Well, we can use many different
CSS selectors to
select particular parts
of the DOM.
So just like we were able to
select p, to select all of the
paragraphs, in CSS, if we wanted
to style an element
with the ID of container, in
jQuery we just specify
#container.
In CSS, to style an element with
the class of articles, we
just use .articles.
And in the same way in jQuery,
to fetch all of the elements
with the class of articles,
we simply put .articles.
So let's jump back into our
HTML and figure out how we
might select that unordered
list with the ID of
destinations.
Let's find it using the ID.
All we have to do, in this
case, is specify
#destinations.
And that will select the element
that has that ID.
Notice here, one of our li's
now has a promo class.
How might we select
just that class,
using the proper selector?
In this case, we would
just specify .promo.
And that would select all the
list elements that have the
class of promo.
In this case, there's
just one.
Why don't you try your hand at
using some specific selectors.
And I'll see you in level two.