[SINGING]jQuery will help
you build your dot com.
Find an element inside
of the DOM.
AJAX traversal manipulation,
event
handling and animation.
Providing you with versatility,
an API with
extensibility.
JQuery is something
you can't ignore.
Write less, do more.
I'm Greg Pollack, and you're
watching Try jQuery, And this
is level two, where we're going
to be searching through
the DOM using more
CSS selectors.
So here's the HTML we used
in our previous level.
And remember, we were able to
select the unordered list with
the ID of destinations.
But how might we select the
list items inside of that
specific unordered list?
We can do that using the
descendant selector.
So here is our DOM again.
And we can simply write
"#destinations li" to
select all the list items
underneath the element with
the destinations ID.
So here the parent is
destinations, and the
descendant is the LI.
Let's make our HTML a little
bit more complex.
As you can see here, now we have
an unordered list inside
of our unordered list.
And we want to find only the LI
elements that are children
of the destinations UL.
Just the children, not the
children's children.
To solve this, would we use
the descendant selector?
Well, let's see what
happens if we do.
If you use #destination li
like before, it
selects all of the list items
underneath that UL, which is
not what we want.
In order to find only the direct
children, we need to
use the child selector.
Let's see what that
looks like.
To select the direct
descendants, we specify
#destinations, then we
use the greater than
sign, and then LI.
You'll see in the DOM that that
Paris list item does not
get selected, because we're only
going after the direct
descendants.
#destinations is
the parent here.
The child here is LI, and that
greater than sign is what
tells jQuery that we're
looking for the direct
descendant.
Now, what if we want to select
multiple elements?
Let's say we want to select
elements with either a promo
class or a France ID.
To do that, we can simply list
".promo, #france"
Using a common like
this allows us to
select multiple items.
Now, what if we only wanted to
select the first item in that
unordered list?
We can do that using the
pseudo selector.
In this case
#destinations li:first
This will select the first
item in the list.
As you might imagine, to select
the last item in the list
we simply use
li:last.
If we wanted to select every
other list item, we might want
to use the odd pseudo class.
So in this case, it would only
select the middle list item.
This might not seem intuitive
at first, but you have to
understand that the index for
these list items starts at
zero, like so.
So that's why the odd only
selects the middle item.
If we used even, it would select
0, 2, 4, 6, and so on.
Time for you to use some of
these selectors in the
challenges.