Up until now, we've used
CSS-like selectors to select
different parts of the DOM.
However, sometimes it's faster
to use something we call
traversing.
Let's take a closer look.
Here we are, back in our HTML.
And we want to select all
the list items again.
But this time we don't want to
use a descendant selector.
How can we do this
using traversing?
Here's our DOM again.
And in the previous level, we
selected all the li's by
writing #destinations li.
To use traversing, we can call
#destinations and then call
the Find method on the DOM
object, which gets returned,
sending in the li parameter so
that it finds all the list
items underneath the
Destinations element.
When you're finding elements
using traversing, it typically
has two parts.
The first is the selection, in
this case #destinations.
And the second part is
the traversal, in
this case find li.
Traversing, as you can see,
takes a little bit more code.
But to find specific elements
in the DOM, it's
a little bit faster.
So remember how we used the
first pseudo class to find the
first item in that list?
Well, to do that using
traversing, we can simply
specify the first
method, like so.
As you might imagine, instead
of using the last pseudo
class, we can use
the last method.
So we know how to find the first
element and the last
element with traversing.
But how might we find the middle
element in this list?
We can do this using
a technique
called walking the DOM.
So if we called li.first,
it's going to give us
that first list item.
And if we wanted, we could chain
another method onto it.
So we could call li first.next,
and that would
return the middle list item,
which is what we want.
This technique of calling
multiple methods together is
called method chaining.
If we wanted to, we could keep
on chaining more and more
methods onto this.
So if we called first.next.prev,
which stands
for previous, it would go back
to the first list item.
Sometimes we're going to want
to walk up the DOM.
We might be able to select
a child element.
And then we want to walk up
the DOM, to its parent.
How might we traverse
up the DOM?
So here we've selected
the first list item.
But what we might be interested
in is the parent.
To get the parent, we
would call first
to get to list item.
And then we can simply call
parent, which is going to
select the unordered list,
which is what we want.
Sometimes we might want
to walk down the DOM.
So we might have a parent,
but we want to
walk down to its children.
So how do we traverse down?
Here's that unordered list,
which has another unordered
list inside of it.
Now, if we only wanted the
direct children of the
destination's unordered list,
we could do that using
traversing by calling
#destinations and using the
children method, specifying
that we only want the
children, which are
list items.
Earlier in this level
we used find.
If we use find here, it
would have selected
all of the list items.
However, we only wanted the
direct descendants.
That's why we're using children
here and specifying
that we want all the children
that are list items.
All right, well, it's time for
you to play around with
traversal in the challenges.
And I'll see you
in level three.