Our code has worked great so
far, but what if we add
multiple vacations?
If we then click the Get Price
button, we can see that all of
the buttons disappear.
And we see all of the prices.
Well, that's not so good.
So how might we fix this?
Here's our DOM, this time
with multiple vacations.
And here's our code.
When we go to append the price,
it's going to find all
of the li's with the
classification and append the
price, the same price,
to all of them.
It's also going to return all
the buttons, when it searches
for a button, and then call
.remove, effectively removing
all of them.
One way around this problem
is by using a
keyword called This.
You see, inside of our Event
Handler, when we use This,
we're referring to the item
that triggered the event--
in this case, the button
that was pressed.
So inside our Event Handler, you
might think we could call
this.remove to remove
the button.
But that wouldn't quite work,
because when we call This,
it's not a jQuery object.
We need to convert it first.
So we'll wrap that in a dollar
sign and parentheses and call
this .remove, and that's going
to remove only the button that
was clicked.
So let's write that code
in our function.
And now we're only removing the
button that was clicked.
So if we go back to our code
and click Get Price, we can
see that each button is removed
when it should be.
However, it's still adding the
price on every list item.
So how might we fix that?
We can use this again and call
$(this).after(price) to put the
price after this
current button.
So let's go ahead and move
that into our code.
And now it's going to
add the price as a
sibling, after the button.
Notice here in the DOM, we've
moved the button into a div.
So the DOM has changed
slightly.
And now when we run this code,
well, the price is going to be
inside of that div, which
we may not want.
So how would we write this code
so that if the DOM gets
changed to like this, it's still
going to print out the
price where it should be?
So we want to keep the price
as a child of the li.
So we can't use after price.
Well, one way we could solve
this, using traversing, we
could call parent.parent.append,
which
would seem to put it
in the right place.
But again, it would break
if we changed the DOM.
We could also find parents to
find the vacation class above
the current button and then
append price onto it.
But this doesn't work,
because it could
return multiple vacations.
The best way to solve this
problem is to use .closest and
then send in .vacation.
What this is going to do is walk
up the DOM to find the
ancestor with the class of
vacation and then append onto
that the price node.
It's also worth mentioning that
closest is going to find
zero or one node when it
searches for ancestors with
the proper class, whereas
parents is going to search for
all of the ancestors with
the proper class.
So let's go ahead and put this
line of code back up into our
Event Handler.
And now it's going to add the
paragraph at the bottom of the
vacation class.
Let's take a look.
So now when we click each
button, each of them will show
us the price properly.
And now it's time for you to
get into the challenges.
And I'll see you in the last
section of level three.