So back in our demo, in our
vacation packages, you can see
we click on each button and it
gives us a price, but all the
vacations always have
the same price.
How might we give them
different prices?
Well, here's one way
we could do it.
Here's our HTML, and we're going
to specify the price by
adding a data price attribute
to the HTML.
The data tag is an HTML5
attribute you can add to any
of your elements to provide
additional information about
the objects on your page.
To interact with these
attributes, we can call data,
than specify a name to get out
the information, and we can
also set these attributes by
providing a name and a value.
Here's an example of reading
out that data.
We can fetch the nodes with the
vacation class from the
dom, get the first one of those,
then call data and
specify the price name.
Now, it'll return the price
that we see here, $399.99.
Now, let's go back to our old
code and refactor it to use
this data price attribute.
To do this, we're going to start
with a button that was
clicked, which is represented
here by this, we're going to
find the closest ancestor,
which has the
.vacation class.
And then, finally, call the data
method to get the price
value out of the dom.
We can then use that amount
when we construct our
paragraph dom node, which shows
the price, like so.
Let's take these two lines and
put them inside of our code.
So each vacation now, will
have its own price.
However, there's some
duplication
that's going on here.
You can see that we're fetching
the vacation class
here and then again
down below.
So let's eliminate
this duplication.
We can do this by creating a new
variable called vacation,
which will fetch us the closest
vacation, and then we
set the amount, we can simply
call that variable dot data,
and then when we append, we
can, of course, use that
variable again.
Now, if we use this code inside
of our function, no
longer are we repeating
ourselves, and we're only
querying the dom once for this
element, which is going to
make it a little bit faster.
Now, if we jump back into our
browser, when we click Get
Price, we see that each of our
vacations has its own price.
This works great, but what if
we start adding different
buttons to our web page?
This click handler is going to
be called for all of them, so
we need to make this
more specific.
Well, we could use
a CSS selector.
We could say dot vacation
button, so it's only going to
listen for click events
on buttons inside of
our vacation class.
But there's a better way to
write this, we can simply
fetch the nodes that have the
vacation class and then call
on, we want to listen for click
events, and then we'll
specify which elements inside
the vacation class we want to
listen for.
In this case, button elements,
and then our third argument
becomes our event handler
function.
This technique is called
event delegation.
We're only targeting
buttons if it's
inside a vacation class.
So now, if we jump back
into our browser, our
buttons still work.
Sweet.
But, oh, we've got some filters
up there, On Sale Now
and Expiring Soon.
Let's make those filters work.
Here's the HTML for
the filters,
they're inside of a div.
They're buttons as well, so we
want to make it so that when
we click On Sale Now, it only
shows On Sale vacations and
when we click Expiring it only
shows expiring vacations.
So to do this, we're going to
write two different event
handlers for the buttons, and
we'll highlight vacations with
these traits.
Here we are inside of our
application.js.
First, we're going to fetch the
div with the filters ID,
then we're going to use event
delegation to listen for click
events for the on-sale
filter class.
And inside of the event handler,
we're going to first
find all vacations that are on
sale, and then we're going to
add a class to these vacations
so they highlight.
Here's the dom for our
vacation list.
You can see that some of them
have two classes, vacation and
on sale, and some of them just
have one, being vacation.
So how might we select the ones
that are just on sale?
Well, we can do this using
a CSS selector.
We could just do dot vacation
dot on sale, however, let's do
this using traversing, so we'll
call dot vacation, and
then we'll filter those
vacations to return just the
ones that have the
on sale class.
Let's move this code up
into our function.
And now, the second step, we
need to add a class on to
these vacations.
To add a class using
jQuery, we can use
the addClass method.
Similarly, we can use
the removeClass
method to remove a class.
So first, we'll grab all of the
vacations which have the
class vacation and on sale,
and we'll add the class of
highlighted onto all of them.
So let's move this back up
into our code, and as we
mentioned, filter finds the
right vacations and addClass
adds the highlighted class to
all of those vacations.
We can do the same thing for our
expiring filter, listening
for clicks on that expiring
filter button.
Then when it's clicked, we will
filter all the vacations,
which also have the expiring
class, and add the class of
highlighted.
Let's take a look at
this in action.
We click on two and we can see
them highlighting, but, well,
everything's highlighted now, so
if we continue to click the
buttons, nothing more happens.
So we need a way to unhighlight
all of these vacations.
One way we can do this is when
a button is clicked, first
thing, we'll look for any
highlighted classes, and we'll
remove that class of highlighted
from them.
So we're getting rid of all
highlighted classes from our
page before we then go and
add highlighted back
to the proper vacations.
So here we go, back on the page,
and now when we click
through our On Sale and Expiring
Now vacations, the
proper ones are highlighted.
You've reached the end
of level three.
Time to go to the challenges,
and I'll see
you in level four.