[SINGING]
jQuery will help you
build your dot-com.
Find an element inside
of the DOM.
Ajax traversal manipulation.
Event handling and animation.
Providing you with
versatility.
An API with extensibility.
jQuery is something
you can't ignore.
Write less.
Do more.
I'm Gregg Pollack, and you're
watching "Try jQuery." This is
level three, but we're going
to be talking about working
with the DOM. Let's take a look
at the web page that we're
going to be working with.
Here you can vacation
packages.
In this case, a Hawaiian
vacation.
And we have that button.
And when we press that button,
it changes to the price of
that Hawaiian Vacation.
In this case, $399.99.
Let's figure out how to
write the jQuery to
make that button work.
So here is the DOM of our web
page, as you can see.
We need to do two things.
First, we need to append
a new DOM node to the
bottom with the price.
And then secondly, we need to
remove the button altogether.
So how might we do this
using jQuery?
You might notice, here we're
inside of our application.js,
where we're going to write
all of our jQuery code.
And the first thing we start out
with is our document.ready
function, as you see here.
Inside of there, the first thing
we want to do is create
a new paragraph with
the price.
So well, one way we could do
this using JavaScript is we
could var price = "from
$399.00", which is the text.
However, we want to create HTML
here, so you might think
that we would just do
From $399 and wrap
that inside of a paragraph.
But that still wouldn't
be right.
In this case, we want to create
a new DOM node by
sending the HTML into
the jQuery function.
This will create a DOM
node and set it equal
to the price variable.
However, it does not add this
new node onto the DOM.
It's not attached
anywhere yet.
That's going to be
our next step.
Now let's move that price
variable into our
application.js, and there's a
couple different ways that we
can add that node
into our DOM.
We could use the append method,
the prepend method,
the after method, or
the before method.
And we're going to go into
more detail what each
of these would do.
First, we need to select a node
out of our DOM, which
will serve as a reference point
to put our price node,
in this case, before.
So we're grabbing the vacation
class element.
And then before the vacation
class, we're adding the price
node. This is where I would add
the paragraph, which in this
case, is not what we're
looking for.
So let's try a different
method.
What if we tried adding the
price after the vacation node?
In this case, it would be put
it down here at the bottom,
which is also not what
we're looking for.
We could try using the
prepend method.
In this case, the price node
would be added as the first
child of the LI with
class vacation.
That still is not quite right.
In this case, I think what we're
looking for is append.
Append is going to add that
price node as the last child
of our list item.
OK.
So we're appending the price
in the right location.
The only step left is
to remove the button
node from the DOM.
To do this, we simply
fetch the node and
call the remove method.
That will remove it
from the DOM.
So now with that code, when we
load up the page, the DOM is
going to load.
And as soon as it's loaded,
it's going to add that
paragraph and hide the button.
So we're going to see the price
like you see there.
Now obviously, this
isn't complete.
We want to make it so that when
we click the button, it
changes, which we'll get into
in the next section.
And before we get there, there's
four other methods you
should know about.
There's the appendTo, prependTo,
insertAfter, and
insertBefore.
These methods are different
because of the
order of the syntax.
So in this case, if I wanted to
do the same thing we were
doing before with append,
I would write
price.appendTo vacation.
So the reference point
comes at the end.
Some people think this
is more readable.
I'll leave it up to you.
You can do it anyway you want.
And now it's time for you to
get into the challenges.