Now that you know how to remove
and add DOM nodes to
the page, let's take a look
at how we do interaction.
Here's the code that we
use to listen for when
the document is ready.
Inside there we pass in
an Event Handler.
That Event Handler
is a function,
which looks like this.
And we send in all of the code
that we want executed inside
of that function.
Put them both together, and you
get the code that we're
now familiar with.
The ready method takes one
argument, which is that Event
Handler function.
Now it's time to figure out how
to make that button work
so that when we click Get Price,
it shows us the price
of that vacation.
Here's the DOM for our page.
To listen for an event on the
button, we first need to get
the button out of the DOM.
We're going to want to use the
On jQuery Object method.
It takes an event and
an Event Handler.
So here we're going
to say On, Click.
And then our second parameter
is an Event Handler.
So this code is going
to return all the
buttons from the DOM.
We call the On method sending
in the Click as the first
argument, which we'll watch for
any clicks that happen to
any of those buttons.
And then when they're clicked,
it's going to run the code
inside of our function.
Let's take that code and
move it inside of
our Document Ready.
So our function inside of our
Document Ready runs when the
DOM is ready.
And then our code inside of our
Click Handler runs when a
button is clicked.
Now all we need to do is
add in the code from
our previous section.
And now every time the button is
clicked, it's going to add
the paragraph and then remove
the button, as it should.
So let's go ahead and
see that in action.
When we click the Get Price
button, it first adds the
paragraph with the price
and then removes
the Get Price button.
Why don't you try making some
buttons work in the
challenges.