So we know how to do mouse
events, but what about
keyboard events?
Let's say we have a web page
like this, and notice here, we
have the quantity of tickets
that we need, we have a cost
per ticket, and when we change
the quantity, we want the
total price to be automatically
updated.
How might we do this
with jQuery?
We'll let's take a
look at the HTML.
You can see here we have a div
of classification, which also
contains the price for
this vacation.
We have the amount of money per
ticket, we have our input
field, and then lastly,
at the bottom, we
have our total price.
We need to make it so when the
input updates, we calculate
the total price and update it
at the bottom of the page.
Obviously, we need to be
listening for some sort of
keyboard event, so that when
somebody types a key, we get
that quantity and we calculate
the total price.
So here, we can listen on the
quantity, but what is going to
be the event we're
listening for?
Well, here's a list of
keyboard events.
You've got things like keypress,
keydown, keyup, and
also, here's a list of form
events, because that input is
a form field.
So we could be listening
for blur, select,
change, focus, or submit.
Check out the documentation if
you want to learn more about
what each of these does.
In our case, though, we want to
listen for the keyup event.
So when somebody stops pressing
a key, or a number in
this case, we want to then
calculate the total price.
So let's put keyup there at the
top, and inside of that
event handler, we want
to do three things.
First, we want to get the
price for the vacation.
We can get that out of
the data element.
Then, we'll get the quantity
they entered
in the input field.
And then finally, we'll set the
total price to price times
the quantity.
Here's the dom on the side,
and to fetch the price--
this should be nothing new--
we're going to get
this object.
So this is the input element.
We're going to search for
ancestor, the closest ancestor
with the class of vacation, then
we're going to get the
price from the data attribute.
That's going to return
$399.99.
However, this is going to return
a string, but we want
to do math on this variable.
So one way that we can convert
this into a number is by
adding that plus to the
beginning of this statement.
That's going to convert the
string into a number, which we
can use later to do our
multiplication.
So we have the price, but we
need to get the quantity that
the user entered.
Now, remember, it's the input
field itself that is
triggering the keyup event.
So we can probably use this
to get that input field.
However, we need to get the
value out of that input field.
Luckily, we have some
helper methods.
We can use val to set the input
value or just .val to
get the input value.
So you might think we can call
this.val, but remember,
this is not a jQuery object
yet, so we need to write
$(this).val(),
which will
properly return two.
But this returns a string and
again, we need a number.
So we use that same convention
we saw a minute ago and add a
plus to the beginning of this
statement, like you see here.
This returns us the
number two.
We'll bring that back up into
our code, and the only thing
we have left is to multiply the
two numbers together and
set that equal to the total
value on the page.
In this case, we'll fetch the
span with pound total as the
ID, and set the text to the
price times the quantity.
And luckily for us, we can pass
a number or a string when
we're setting a dom text node.
All right, so now we have a
completed text, and whenever
that quantity is changed, the
keyup event will trigger, and
our total will get updated.
So here's our webpage again,
and now, if we update the
quantity, we can see the total
getting updated at the bottom
of the page.
Time for you to implement some
key events, and I'll see you
in the next section.