Here's the page we're going to
be working with for our last
section here.
As you can see, we have multiple
vacations, and when
we click Show Comments, we want
to show the comments for
that vacation.
Specifically, we want
them to fade in.
So how might we do that?
Here's our DOM, and the first
thing we want to do is to make
sure that the comments UL is
hidden when we load the page.
So we make it display none
inside of our CSS.
Then we want to add behavior
so that when we click this
link, show comments, that it
shows the proper comments
underneath that link.
Inside of our application.js
we have
our document ready.
Inside that, we're going to
fetch a vacation class, listen
for our click event on the link,
which has the expand
class on it, and then run
our event handler.
There's two things we
need to do inside
of our event handler.
First, we need to find the
comments UL, which is below
our link, and then, we need
to show it, in this
case, fade it in.
To find the appropriate comments
list, we need to do
some traversal, like we did
on previous sections.
So the link that was clicked,
we're going to start with
that, or in this case,
this, because it
was what was clicked.
And then call closest to
search up through its
ancestors to find the vacation
class, and then call find to
search down through the
DOM to find the
appropriate comments list.
So we found the comments list,
now we just need to fade it
in, and there's a couple
different fade
methods that we can use.
We have fadeIn, fadeOut, and
fadeToggle, which will toggle
between the two.
In this case, we want to use
fadeToggle so that when we
click on the link, it'll
either fade them in
or fade them out.
So let's see this in action.
As you can see, we can click on
one of the links, and then
it fades in the comments.
And we can click on it
again, and it will
fade out the comments.
However, if we click on a link
near the bottom of the page--
did you see that?
The page jumped back up to
the top of the page.
That's kind of annoying,
and how do we fix that?
In order to understand how we
fix that, we need to grasp
what's happening when
the event occurs
inside of the DOM.
So here's our link, and when an
event occurs, we get this
little event bubble.
We'll call it a bubble.
And it's going to start right
there on our link, and then
it's going to go up to each
parent node to let it know,
hey, a click event happened.
Eventually, it's going to get
to the top, and then, well,
because we have an href here
with a hash, it's going to
follow that link when it gets
up to the browser, which is
going to do the default
behavior, which is pop it back
up to the top of the page.
So we need to figure out a way
from preventing that default
browser behavior.
The first step down the road to
fixing this is to add the
event parameter inside
of our event
handler, as you see here.
We're going to need
that in a minute.
One way we can try to fix this
is by using stopPropagation.
What that's going to do is when
the event happens and it
tries to bubble up,
it's not going to.
It's not going to bubble
up to other ancestors.
However, stopPropagation does
not prevent the default
behavior from the browser, and
we're still going to pop up to
the top of the page.
So this is not our solution.
Instead, we're going to call
event.preventDefault to
prevent the default
behavior of
the browser- in this case, when
the event happens, it's going
to bubble up and when it reaches
our browser, it's not
going to follow the default
behavior, which is popping up
to the top of the page because
our href was a hash.
So now, when we go back to our
web page, we can see that we
can fade in comments and fade
out comments, and we're no
longer popping up to the
top of the web page.
So now, it's time for you to get
into the challenges, and
I'll see you in level five.