[SINGING]
jQuery will help you build your
dotcom, find an element
inside of the DOM, AJAX
traversal manipulation, event
handling, and animation
providing you with
versatility, an API with
extensibility.
jQuery is something
you can't ignore.
Write less.
Do more.
You're watching Try jQuery,
and this is level four.
In this section, we're going to
be going over this web page
you see here.
We've got one vacation,
and we want to look
at the flight details.
So we'll click the Flight
Details button, and it'll give
us more information
about that flight.
So how might we implement
that?
Well, let's take a look
inside the HTML first.
Here is our confirmation
list item.
Inside of that, we have a button
labeled flight details.
And then we have an unordered
list, which has those extra
details, which get shown when
we click the button.
So clicking this button will
show the ticket here.
To set this up, we're first
going to set a CSS style on
the ticket class to display
none, so that it starts out as
hidden when we first
load the page.
There's three steps to
making this work.
First, we're going to watch
for the click event, then
we're going to find the ticket,
and then show it.
First thing we need to do is
write our event handler.
We'll grab the confirmation
li.
And then when there's a button
inside of that which gets
clicked, we're going
to run some code.
In our case, we want
to grab the button.
We're going to search up through
the ancestors of the
button to find the closest
confirmation class, then we're
going to search back down
through the children to find
elements with the
ticket class.
To show this ul, we're going to
use the slide down method.
.slideDown() would show it,
.slideUp() would hide it, and
then .slideToggle() well, is
going to toggle between the
two states.
So let's do .slideDown()
like so.
So let's go ahead and try this
in our browser, but it doesn't
seem to be working.
We're going to have to figure
out how to debug this
JavaScript.
And one of the most basic ways
we can start debugging is with
the alert function.
You're probably familiar
with this.
You call alert in JavaScript.
And you get this
little pop up.
This is JavaScript, not
necessarily jQuery.
And then another useful thing to
know about debugging is if
we fetch a DOM element using
jQuery, and call .length on
it, it will give us how many
nodes are on that page.
So if there was three list
items, it would return three.
We can combine these two to see
if there's any buttons on
the page when this
alert gets run.
So we fetch the buttons
and call .length.
Oh, what we found here
is that it's zero.
So it's not finding
any buttons.
That's probably because we're
not wrapping this code in a
DOM ready function.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Now we're using
(document).ready() just like so.
And now when we load our page,
ah, our alert pops up one.
So it did find the button.
So let's go ahead and jump back
into our web page, and
yep, when we click Flight
Details, it
properly slides down.
Time for you to jump into the
challenges, and I'll see you
in the next section.