In this section, we're going
to look at some more events
that we can listen for
on our webpages.
So here, inside of our webpage,
we want to make it so
that when we hover over that
little price tag that it also
displays the flight details.
So how would we do that?
Well, you've already seen most
of the code that we need to
make this happen, namely
grabbing a DOM element, using
the on method, passing in the
h3, because we would want to
listen for events on h3.
And then we just need to slide
down the ticket confirmation.
Some of the mouse events
you can listen to.
Click, you're obviously
familiar with.
But there's a bunch
you can use.
In this case, we want to use
mouseenter, which fires when
the mouse is first positioned
over the element.
So let's move mouseenter up
into the code, just like so.
This is going to show the ticket
when it's positioned
over that h3.
So let's take a look
on the webpage.
And you'll notice, when we hover
over that ticket icon,
it shows the details.
And still, if we click on the
Flight Details button, that'll
also show the ticket
confirmation.
This code that we've written has
some duplication going on.
And we don't like duplication.
So how would we get rid of it?
Well, we could move the contents
of each of those
Event Handlers into its own
function called Show Ticket,
just like so.
Then we'll move that up to the
top and change our Event
Handlers so that the third
argument is simply that
function that we just defined.
You'll notice here that even
though we're passing in a
function, we don't put
parentheses at
the end of the name.
If we did, it would call the
function immediately.
And we want it to call only when
the event is triggered.
And so now back on our webpage,
we can see that both
of these events still fire
properly and call that same
function, which we defined.
Time for you to try this
in the challenges.