[SINGING]
jQuery will help you build your
dot-com, find an element
inside of the DOM, AJAX
traversal manipulation, event
handling, and animation,
providing you with
versatility, an API with
extensibility.
jQuery is something
you can't ignore.
Write less.
Do more.
You're watching Try jQuery, and
this is level five, where
we're going to start by talking
a little bit about
taming CSS.
So we've got HTML, we've got
CSS, and we've got
JavaScript.
And if we want to change the
style of something, what
should we use?
We can use both CSS
and JavaScript.
Let's try using some
JavaScript.
So here we've got a page
where we've got
different vacation packages.
Let's make it so when people
click on the li element, that
it changes the style.
So here we are inside of our
application.js, and we're
listening for click events
on the vacation class.
There's a few different methods
we can use to get and
set the CSS.
We can set it by specifying
the attribute and a value.
We can get its current value by
specifying the attribute,
and we can also send
in an object.
Let me show you what
that looks like.
In our example, we could set the
background color for this
current li to this hex code.
We could also set the border
color to one pixel solid with
this color.
We could also do this in one
line by method chaining these
both together like so.
However, the cleanest way to do
it would be to simply send
in a JavaScript object, in this
case, having a series of
keys and values with just
one argument, which
is that JavaScript object.
Now when our vacations are
clicked, we want to show the
price for that vacation.
So we're going to take this,
which is the current li that
was clicked.
And we're going to find inside
of it the price class.
And then we want
to display it.
One way we can get it to display
is changing it from
display none to display block.
However there's a better
way to do that.
jQuery gives you two methods,
one called show
and one called hide.
And they basically do the same
thing-- they change it between
display none and
display block.
But they're a little
bit easier to use.
So here we call the show method,
and it's going to
display the price for us.
And there we go.
Now when we click on the li,
it highlights a vacation
package and shows the price,
as we can see here.
This might feel a little
bit dirty to you.
That might be a good feeling.
Because you might want to keep
all of your styles inside of
your style sheet and not
in your JavaScript.
So how might we do that here?
Let's refactor this
code to do that.
So let's create two
new classes.
We have a style on the
highlighted class and a style
on the price inside the
highlighted class.
Now in order to make these style
changes, all we have to
do is add this class
to our li.
So let's go ahead and
do that, and now our
code is a lot cleaner.
Plus, it's much easier to
manipulate the style, because
all of our styles are in CSS.
One more feature we want to add
here is when we click on
the li for the second time, we
want the price to go away.
So how do we remove the
highlighted class?
Well remember, not only do we
have .addClass() or
.removeClass(), but we can
also do .toggleClass().
So let's go ahead and do that.
We'll add .toggleClass()
highlighted.
And then it will add the class
if it doesn't have it.
And if it does, it will
properly take it away.
And here we are back in
our web page, and as
you can see, it works.
Time to get in the challenges,
and I'll see
you in the next section.