So we've taken a look at styles,
but jQuery also gives
us the ability to do
some animations.
How might we use an animations
on this page?
Well, maybe what we should
do is make each of those
vacations jump up a little
bit when we select them.
Let's figure out
how to do that.
So here we are back in our code,
and maybe what we should
do is have the LI that was
clicked move up 10 pixels,
negative 10 just like that.
jQuery actually has a method
called animate that we can
send in CSS styles, and it will
slowly animate from its
current state to the style
that we give it.
So in this case, we would write
animate top negative 10
pixels, and it will animate from
0 pixels to negative 10.
Let's put that in our code.
Now, let's see what
that looks like.
So we click on it, and each
of these items goes up.
And well, it doesn't
go back down.
They just go up.
So obviously, we're going
to have to deal
with that in a minute.
When this event handler is
called, we only want to make
it animate up if we just added
the highlighted class.
However, if we just remove the
highlighted class when we
toggled, we want it to animate
back down to zero.
So we have an if statement
here, if vacation class
highlighted, then animate
up, else animate the
vacation back down.
So let's go ahead and move
that up into our code.
And have the second animate
line there, where we're
animating it back down to zero,
but we still need to
figure out what goes inside
of our if statement.
We've got just some
pseudo code there.
Well, jQuery gives us a method
called hasClass.
We can check to see if a node
has a specific class.
So in this case, we'll call
this dot has class
highlighted, and if it
returns true, we know
that it has the class.
So let's move that back up
into the if statement.
And now, if it has the class,
it's going to animate that up,
and if it doesn't, it's going
to animate LI back down.
So here we go in our browser.
We click it once,
it goes back up.
We click it again, and
it goes back down.
Now, this is a little
bit slow.
We might want to speed up or
slow down the animation in
certain circumstance.
How might we do that?
Well, we can specify the speed
by adding a second argument.
In this case, if we did comma
400, that means it's going to
animate in 400 milliseconds,
and this is
actually the default.
So if we don't specify a
speed, by default, the
animation is going to take
400 milliseconds.
We could send in the argument
of fast, which would be the
same thing as specifying
200 milliseconds.
We can also specify the argument
slow, which, in this
case, would be 600
milliseconds.
And we can also use that speed
argument in other methods,
like slideToggle, fadeToggle,
slideDown, slideUp.
They all work.
So let's speed up
our animation.
This time making it fast,
just like you see here.
Now, when we go back into our
browser, we can see the
animation is definitely
a little more snappy.
Now, once again, we have CSS
inside of our JavaScript, and
again, it might give you that
not so fresh feeling.
So how might we get this
out of the JavaScript?
It turns out we can do this
animation in CSS by specifying
a transition like
you see here.
So we're specifying here that if
the top element is changed,
it should transition
in 0.2 seconds.
Then, when we add the
highlighted class, we're
specifying the top is negative
10 pixels, which will cause
the animation to happen.
You've got to be careful when
using this however, because
it's only going to work with
browsers that support CSS
transitions.
One way we can support
additional browsers is by
specifying the browser prefixes
as you see here.
So this is something you have to
be aware of if you want to
use these types of CSS
animations, and there's lots
of information out there on the
internet that will tell
you which ones you can use,
which ones are dangerous, and
there might be a code school
course or two on the subject.
So here we are, back in our
browser, and as you can see,
we can click, and we
still get that same
nice animation effect.
All right, you've reached the
end of the videos, and now
it's time for you to get
into the challenges.