[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome to Level Six
of Assembling
Sass: Math & Color.
In this level, we'll be going
over basic arithmetic with
Sass, as well as color,
shortcuts, and functions.
Sass gives us a number of ways
to perform operations on
numbers, including addition,
subtraction, multiplication,
division and modulo.
If you're not familiar with
the modulo operator, it
returns the remainder
of an operation.
So 12 mod 3 returns zero,
because 3 goes cleanly into
12, while 12 mod 5 returns 2,
since the remainder of 12
divided by 5 is 2.
By default, Sass returns up to
five digits after a decimal
point for us when performing
number operations.
Now, with Sass, division
is the trickiest of the
operations, because like the
comma issue we ran into
earlier with variable arguments,
the slash is a
valid character in some
CSS, like our
font declaration here.
We're able to trigger
division in one of
three ways using Sass.
Either one of the values can be
a variable, we can wrap the
operation in parentheses, or the
division operation can be
part of a larger arithmetic
operation.
When we add strings together in
Sass, we concatenate them,
or mash them together.
And whether or not the final
result has quotes is dependent
on whether or not the left hand
string had quotes or not
going into the arithmetic
operation.
When performing arithmetic in
Sass, it's going to attempt to
combine any units that
don't match.
So in this case, we have pixels
added to points, and
Sass can make that conversion
for us.
If we use the relative ends
though, instead, it's not able
to make that conversion,
and the Sass
compiler throws an error.
Sass isn't able to set a hard
pixel value to em since it's a
relative unit.
There are a number of predefined
utility functions
in Sass to help us with
math operations.
We have the ability to round to
the nearest whole number,
round up to the nearest whole
number, round down to the
nearest whole number, get the
absolute value, pick out the
minimum or maximum value of a
list, and return a percentage
based on a number input.
We can call these functions in
the same way that we did
custom functions like our
fluidize function earlier.
So using the ceiling function
here on 1.2, output's 2.
As I mentioned before, we're
able to replace our fluidize
function with a built in
function of percentage.
Here, using percentage, I can
pass in the target and the
context as a division operation,
and the output is a
percentage.
It's worth noting with this
operation, if you find
yourself using the same context
multiple times, you
can go ahead and set the context
to a variable and then
re-use that in the percentage
function as you move through
your style sheet.
Here's how Sass improves our
ability to handle color.
Not only are we able to set
color values to variables to
recall them later, we're also
able to use pre-built color
utility functions that we'll
go into soon to alter our
colors, as well as use
shorthands for easy
representations of certain
types of colors.
First up, we're able
to perform math
operations on our colors.
Here, we're setting a color base
and performing addition
to another hex value.
When this compiles, we go from
our initial dark gray swatch
to the swatch shown next to
our new background color.
We're also able to perform
subtraction, multiplication,
and division to any
color value.
This is a neat trick, but
it's not something I
would normally use.
Later on in the level, we'll
be going into color utility
functions that give us a more
predictable and maintainable
version of doing this
sort of operation.
When storing color values and
variables, inevitably, we'll
run into this situation where
you want to use that hex value
in an RGBA operation.
Normally, we'd have to manually
find the RGB values
for that hex value to use
RGBA and get it partial
transparency.
However, in Sass, we're afforded
a shorthand way of
doing RGBA in which we can pass
that variable directly as
the first argument in RGBA.
We aren't just limited to
passing variables as that
argument though.
We're still able to pass any
type of color as the first
argument in RGBA, and it'll
automatically do the
conversion for us.
Now, we'll go into those
aforementioned color
functions, and the significance
of these really
can't be overstated.
They allow us to make
alterations to color that are
predictable, maintainable,
and remove the need for
third-party apps like Photoshop,
and finding slight
alterations to the colors we
already have the values for.
First up, we'll set a color
value of dark gray again and
look at lighten.
So the lighten color utility
function allows us to pass an
argument of a color and an
argument of a percent, and it
will lighten that color by that
percent, winding up with
this swatch.
We're also able to darken
in much the same way.
We pass the color value and a
percent, and it darkens the
color for us.
Similarly, we can change the
intensity of the color via its
saturation.
Here, we're starting off with
a green swatch, and we will
saturate it by 20% using the
saturate function, giving us a
more intense color.
We can also desaturate it using
the desaturate function,
giving us a less
intense color.
We're also able to mix two
color values together.
Here, we're going to take a blue
and a yellow and mix them
together to form a green.
The mix utility function takes
an optional third argument,
which changes the percentage
of the first
color that's used.
So in the second case, we're
going to change the amount of
yellow used to 30%, meaning 70%
of blue is used, and we
wind up with a more
teal-ish color.
Other color utility functions
include gray scale, which will
return the gray scale
value of our green.
We're also able to invert our
green, giving us the opposite
of each of the R, G, and B
values of our initial color.
And we can use complement to
find the opposing color wheel
value of the color we pass in.
We started you off with some
of the more useful color
utility functions, but there
are a lot more, so we
definitely recommend visiting
the Sass documentation to see
the rest of what
colors can do.
That does it for Level Six.
It's time to apply what you've
learned in Math & Color to
the challenges.
We'll see you again
in Level Seven.