[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Assembling Sass
and this is Level Seven:
Responsive.
In this level, we're going to
go into how Sass helps us in
our responsive design workflow,
including optimizing
media queries, and some
pitfalls inherent with
responsiveness.
Recently, responsive design has
really gone from a good
idea to a common practice.
And a lot of elements of Sass
help us deal with that.
The basis of responsive design
centers around fluid widths,
which we went into with that
percentage function, and media
queries, which we'll
explore more now.
If you haven't taken our
Journey Into Mobile course,
this is a great time to visit
that course to learn more
about responsiveness.
But we'll just be taking a look
at the very basics of it.
As a refresher, here's how we
can, in its most basic state,
define a media query.
We have a sidebar declaration.
And then within our media query,
which checks to see
whether or not the viewport
has at least 700 pixels of
width, sets another sidebar
declaration that changes the
properties slightly based
on that condition.
While this bit of code is
correct, as you can see we're
repeating the sidebar
declaration in two places.
So it's not quite as optimized
as it can be.
With Sass, we're able to nest
that media query inside a
sidebar and it'll automatically
compile out to
the proper CSS for us.
Now though, we'll continue
to optimize our
media queries via @content.
So the @content directive allows
us to pass a block into
a mixin, rather than
just arguments.
Here we have our sidebar and
our nested media query.
So in here, we're going to
create a new mixin called
respond-to.
And that's just common
naming practice.
And that respond-to will be
included inside the sidebar
declaration.
We're not passing an argument
into respond-to, we're opening
and closing a declaration.
And those properties
will be passed to
the mixin via @content.
So now back in respond-to
we add our @media query.
And inside of there we put
@content so the properties
passed into the respond-to
block are output where
@content is in our mixin.
This works in outputting the
code we already had but again,
we're manually setting
this media query.
So we want to make this a bit
more flexible for later.
Before we move on, let's just go
over this really quick one
more time to make sure we're
all on the same page.
Step one.
In our sidebar declaration, we
have our @include respond-to.
And we have a block that it's
passing, similar to the way an
argument passes up
to our mixin.
@content makes use of what's
passed for step two.
And ultimately in step three,
the output of that mixin is
put back into our sidebar
declaration.
This code isn't very useful to
us, though, because we have
one hard-coded media query that
would be used each time
we call our respond-to mixin.
So let's expand on
it a bit more.
One common practice is to
create a set of named
breakpoints.
We can pass a media argument
to our respond-to, add a
condition to check what
the media value is.
In this case, we're
checking to see if
$media is equal to tablet.
If $media is equal to tablet,
then it outputs that media
query as normal.
And from within our @include
respond-to, if we pass tablet
then the compiled version
uses the media query.
With this method, we could add
additional else-if checks to
see if any other breakpoints are
true, and set a series of
fixed breakpoints to use based
on the media type we pass in
as an argument.
However, that's not quite
flexible enough for us.
Usually we want our content to
dictate where our breakpoints
are, and we wouldn't be able to
pass a specific value into
our respond-to mixin.
So let's revise this
a bit more.
We're going to pass a
query argument into
our respond-to mixin.
And we're going to rewrite our
media query to continue to be
min-width, but take that query
argument as a value of our
min-width query.
And then from our @include
respond-to in the sidebar
declaration, we can set that
query-value argument to
whatever we'd like and use it
anywhere in our style sheet to
change that min-width value.
Here we're passing 900 pixels.
So when it compiles, our media
query will have a minimum
width of 900 pixels.
That's better, but we're still
restricted to using min-width
for all of our media queries.
Let's expand on this
a little bit more.
We're going to pass two
arguments now into our
respond-to query, including
a value and that query.
So within our media query,
we'll pass the value, colon,
the query value, still using
our @content block.
And then when we define our
@include for the respond-to,
we'll pass two arguments.
The first here being
max-width.
And the second being the value
we'd like that max-width query
to be equal to.
And it compiles.
Now we're using a max-width
media query and we have a
separate 600-pixel value.
We can now use this for all
sorts of media queries,
including max-width and minimum
device pixel ratio.
To wrap up, let's talk about a
few responsive pitfalls when
using Sass.
First up, any declarations that
are defined outside of a
media query cannot be extended
into that media query.
For now, we get a deprecation
warning if you try to do this.
However, future versions of
Sass are just going to out
right throw a compile error.
We are, however, able to extend
items within the same
media query to each other
without any problems,
like you see here.
And finally, even though our
media queries might have the
same values, Sass does
not combine them.
In this example, we have a
nested media query in both
sidebar and callout with a
minimum width of 700 pixels.
And even though those media
queries could be combined in
normal CSS, Sass doesn't do
that combination for us.
Sometimes the answer is to go
ahead and write that in normal
CSS as a combined media query
so we avoid having multiple
similar media queries to find
throughout the style sheet.
Congratulations.
You've made your way through
all seven videos
in Assembling Sass.
It's time to move on to the
last set of challenges.
Good luck.