[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome to Level Four of
Assembling Sass: Extend.
In this level, we'll be talking
about the extend
directive, pitfalls associated
with it, and
the placeholder selector.
Remember this bit of button code
back in the mixin
level?
So we have btn-a and btn-b,
and the problem was that
they share three of the same
properties in both instances.
So we said we were able
to simplify it using a
comma-separated selector.
We can have Sass instead track
and combine these selectors
for us using the extend
directive.
We define btn-a as usual with
its inherent properties.
But then inside of btn-b,
we use the extend directive
followed by the selector we'd
like to extend, in this case,
the btn-a class.
And when it compiles, it
compiles down to that
comma-delimited selector that
we were looking for.
Without the properties in each
declaration, here's how the
selector combination happens.
What happens when
we have nested
selectors and we use extend?
In this example, we're extending
content in our
callout declaration, but content
has an h2 scoped and
nested inside.
When this compiles, not only is
callout added to content,
but a scoped version
of h2 is also added
to callout, as well.
If we take out the properties,
here's how that selector
combination works.
Extend is incredibly powerful
in that we can combine
selectors with like styles for
anywhere in our style sheet,
but it has some inherent
problems that
come along with this.
Here we have our btn-b
extending our btn-a, but
later on, we might want to scope
a change to btn-a
like sidebar here.
So sidebar has a scoped version
of btn-a and
changes btn-a. But since
btn-b extends btn-a,
when it compiles, that change
to btn-a also extends to
btn-b, which may
not be desired.
Since btn-b is extending
btn-a, any changes you make
the btn-a will also be
changes made to btn-b. If
the selectors that are generated
aren't needed, we're
creating some stylesheet bloat,
but we can fix that
using placeholder selectors,
which we'll go
into in just a minute.
When I write Sass, I make sure
I always check the compiled
CSS output because we can't be
guaranteed that Sass is going
to output perfect
CSS every time.
Now let's learn about
placeholder selectors.
So placeholder selectors in
Sass are denoted by the
percent sign.
And they're sort of like
partials in that they can be
extended, but they never become
selectors of their own.
So back to our button code
where sidebar has a scope
change to btn-a. We can move
everything that's shared
by btn-a and btn-b up to a
button placeholder selector.
Then inside of btn-a and
btn-b extend that
placeholder selector so btn-b
is no longer directly
extending btn-a. And when
this compiles, that change to
btn-a inside of sidebar
doesn't carry over to btn-b.
Placeholder selectors are
extremely useful when it comes
to CSS styles we want to reuse
throughout our style sheet.
In this case, we have the HTML5
boilerplate version of
image replacement as a
placeholder selector and we're
able to extend it anywhere
we need it.
So when this compiles, only the
selectors that need to use
ir are comma separated
in the final output.
Take heed that versions of IE
prior to 9 have a hard limit
on the number of selectors
you can use in a file.
So if you're using lots of
extends and lots of imports,
you might reach the 4,095 total
selector output limit
that there is.
If you do, anything
beyond that is
just going to be ignored.
That does it for level four, so
it's time for you to write
your own extends.
I'll see you on the other
side of the challenges.