[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome to Level Five of
Assembling Sass: Directive.
In this level, we'll be
talking about control
directives that Sass allows us
to use, like functions, if,
each, for, and while.
As a quick refresher before we
jump into functions, you might
remember a bit of responsiveness
that we talked
about back in Journey
Into Mobile.
Whenever we define a fluid width
for something, we use
the formula of target
divided by context.
So if we have a target size of
a side bar at 350 pixels, and
our parent containers context
is 1,000 pixels, then our
formula here allows us to find
out that we should set the
fluid width to be 35%.
With Sass we can automate these
sorts of calculations,
so we're going to define
a function
first using @function.
And then we give it a name,
sort of like a mixin.
In this case we'll call it
fluidize, but unlike a mixin,
even if we don't have any
arguments to our function, we
need to have opening and closing
parentheses following
the name of the function.
Inside of the function we can
determine a return value.
The value that will return
whenever we use this function.
For now, we'll just set
it to a straight 35%.
From within our declarations
we can call the function by
using the function name.
And again, even if we don't have
any arguments, we need to
have opening and closing
parentheses.
In its current state this isn't
a very useful function.
We're always returning
the value 35%.
But let's improve it by
incorporating the formula we
saw at the beginning
of the level.
First, we'll add target and
context arguments to our
fluidize function.
Then in the return value we'll
incorporate that fluid width
formula of target divided by
context, and multiply that by
100% to get our final
return value.
So within sidebar we can say,
fluidize, pass arguments for
target and context, and
then our output
is the same as before.
Later, we'll talk a bit more
about how Sass can improve our
responsive design workflow.
But for now, it's worth noting
that functions have the same
rules for arguments
as mixins do.
The next control directive
in Sass we'll be taking
a look at is if.
So with if we can conditionally
output code.
Here we're going to set a theme
variable to the string
of dark, and then within our
header we can say if theme is
equal to the dark, output this
bit of code making the
background black.
Since theme is indeed dark
when this compiles the
background of black
will output.
There are a number of
comparisons available to us in
Sass, including equal to, not
equal to, greater than,
greater than or equal to,
less than, or less
than or equal to.
With the last four only
applying to numbers.
Let's continue to expand
this example.
Changing our theme variable
value to light means that our
background no longer outputs.
We're also able to add
a fall back to this
conditional using @else.
So if the if above it evaluates
to false or null,
the @else condition
will be output.
When this bit of code compiles,
since the theme is
no longer equal to dark, the
second condition of background
white outputs.
We can continue this chain
using @else if to add
additional comparisons prior
to reaching our fall back.
In this example, we'll
add an else if
theme is equal to pink.
So if we change that theme value
to pink, a background of
pink is output in our
final compiled CSS.
The third control directive
we'll look at Sass is each.
And each allows us to iterate
over a list performing an
operation on each item
in the list in turn.
We're going to start off with an
author's list that contains
the values of Nick, Aimee,
Dan, and Drew.
To iterate through each item
in this list we're going to
start our each loop with
@each, followed
by $author in $authors.
Authors represents
the list above.
While author is the instance
variable for that
version of the loop.
To illustrate that a bit,
here's what the author
variable will represent
for each loop.
The first time through author
will stand for Nick.
The second time through for
Aimee, so on and so forth.
Inside this loop we'll print out
a bit of styles based on
the current author.
First, we'll set up a selector
that is author hyphen an
interpolated name of
the current author.
And inside of that, we'll set a
background image with a URL
interpolated also with the
name of the author.
The compiled version of this
utilizes each author's name in
turn to create new selectors
with new background image URLs
based on that current
looped author.
Our next control directive
is for.
And similar to each, it's going
to perform a loop, but
it's more number based.
We'll define our for
loop with @for.
Give it an instance variable of
i, which will represent the
current loop value.
And then say from what number
to the n number.
In this case, we're saying
from one through three.
So in these loops i is going
to represent 1 first
time through, 2 the second
time through, and 3 the
third time through.
Then inside of this for loop,
we can define some
styles to be output.
First we'll create a item hyphen
interpolated version of
the current i value.
And we'll multiply the current
i value by 30 pixels.
So on compile, we have a list of
items that use the i values
as a hyphenated portion
of this selector.
And the top value has been
multiplied by 30 pixels for
each i value.
So for, and by extension while,
which we'll go through
into a second here, are similar
to each, but we have a
bit more control.
With while, unlike for, we have
to manually update that
instance index variable.
To start off a while loop first
we're going to define
that instance variable.
Up top we'll say that
i is equal to 1.
Then we can start our while loop
by saying, at while, and
then providing a condition.
First up, we'll be replicating
our for loop.
So our condition here will be
while $i is less than four,
we'll be executing
a bit of code.
Inside, we have the same
bit of code that
was output with for.
So the item hyphen interpolated
$i, $i multiplied
by a specific pixel value, but
with while we have to manually
update $i or else it
will loop forever.
If we didn't add this $i: $i + 1,
then i would stay one, and
while would always be true, and
we'd have a infinite loop.
So using this where we are
adding one to $i each time, our
$i value goes from being one,
to two, to three, and the
fourth time it attempts to go
through, $i will be four, which
is not less than four.
So that bit of code
won't be executed.
And as you can see when this
compiles we have the same
output as we did with
our for loop.
Let's take a look at a reason
to use @while over @for.
We're going to start off with
two instead as our main
instance variable.
Then we're going to change our
while condition to be less
than or equal to six.
And our $i is going to
increment by two
each time it loops.
The first time through $i
will be equal to two.
The second time through four.
The third time through six.
And finally, it's going to be
eight, so the fourth time
through that code won't execute
since eight is not
less than or equal to six.
The output of this code only
targets the even values, so
we're able to modify our @while
to only target specific types
of values with different
iterations than @for.
We've introduced a lot of
directives in this course, but
let's be clear when we should
actually use each one.
Mixins should be used when we're
defining similar sets of
properties that have small
variations that we can change
with arguments.
Extend should be used
when we have
properties that match exactly.
Things that are copied from
declaration to declaration.
Functions, on the other hand,
are operations we need to use
multiple times that just
return a value for us.
Let's take a look back and see
how we can improve our button
mixin now that we know
control directives.
We'll start off with our button
mixin, and now we're
passing a color and a rounded
argument into the mixin.
Our color is output as the
color, but we're going to add
an if condition here to see
whether or not we should
output a rounded value.
If rounded is equal to true,
we're going to output a border
radius of four pixels, and by
default rounded is true.
To use this mixin in btn-a
here, we're going to use at
include button, and we'll pass
arguments of black and false.
Since we're passing false, it
will override the default
value of true.
And since rounded is not equal
to true inside of our mixin,
that border radius will not
be output on compile.
If we leave off a second
argument, rounded defaults to
true, and that border radius
will be output for us.
But what if we didn't want the
radius to be on there by
default, and wanted more control
over what the value
was when it was included.
First up, we'll change
our rounded
default value to false.
And now, we'll change our if
value to simply if rounded.
With this version of our if
conditional, it checks to see
whether or not that variable
is false, or null.
If it's not, then the condition
inside will be output.
And now we're using an actual
value of rounded, so we can
define that from within
our mixin call.
In btn-a, if we don't include
a value for rounded,
it will simply output with a
color, and there will not be a
border radius.
In btn-b however, we'll
add a value for rounded.
Now the condition will
evaluate as true.
And that border radius will get
that rounded argument that
we're passing.
In this case, four pixels.
You're all set on control
directives in Level 5.
Now it's time to test your
knowledge of them.
Good luck.
And I'll see you in Level 6.