[MUSIC PLAYING]
I'm Nick Walsh, and welcome to
Assembling Sass, Level One,
Foundation.
In Level One, we'll be
discussing why adding Sass to
our workflows is advantageous,
and then talk about how we can
change our CSS to the Sass
syntax including comments,
importing, and nesting.
So first up, let's talk
a bit about CSS.
Not CSS was designed to be
simple and largely it is.
But at size, we start to
run into some issues.
Throughout our large style
sheets, we'll have slight
variations of colors, numbers,
and properties that become
incredibly difficult to change
over time, like if we wanted
to change all shades
of blue to a red.
Also, we have problems curbing
repetition as our stylesheet
size grows.
It's harder and harder to know
where to put new styles as
things get very large.
Also, base CSS has no good way
to go about handling multiple
stylesheets.
So either we have to take a
performance hit or we have one
really large stylesheet.
So because of these problems,
Sass comes in very handy.
Now Sass stands for
Syntactically Awesome
Stylesheets.
And it looks a lot like CSS, but
adds a lot of extra stuff
on top to help combat these
aforementioned issues.
Now Sass is a preprocessor, kind
of like CoffeeScript and
Haml, if you're familiar
with those.
So we're going to be starting
with a Sass file.
When we save it, it'll run
through a Sass compiler.
And finally, a CSS file
will be output so the
browser can read it.
So real quick, a bit
of history on Sass.
Sass was created by
Hampton Catlin.
He's also the creator of Haml.
And he wanted to bring the terse
syntax Haml brings to
HTML to CSS as well.
The primary developers on the
project have been Nathan
Weizenbaum and Chris Epstein.
And if you're fortunate enough
to work in Rails, it's already
baked into the asset pipeline.
Now a lot of people write
"SASS" in all caps.
So it's important to note, if
you want to be taken seriously
when saying "Sass," only
capitalize the first letter.
Hampton has said before he likes
to intentionally not
have shouty acronyms
on his projects.
Let's start off talking a bit
about file extensions.
.scss or Sassy CSS is
the default file
extension for Sass.
CSS doubles as a valid SCSS.
So when starting off, you're
able to take any CSS you would
normally write, save it as
.scss, and it compiles
normally into Sass.
Also, there's a second syntax
called the indented into
syntax that's available
with Sass.
But in the course, we're
going to stick to the
default of Sassy CSS.
So in this course, we're going
to be discussing a lot of SCSS
code and then seeing what it
compiles down to in CSS.
Whenever we have to show
SCSS code, it will look
something like this.
And then when we compile it
down to normal CSS, we'll
represent it like this.
Don't worry too much about
the stuff in here
you don't know yet.
We'll be covering what
all this means
later in the course.
So as we said before, since CSS
doubles as valid SCSS, we
definitely recommend that you go
ahead and write styles like
you're used to and slowly
incorporate new
techniques as you go.
You might get a little bogged
down if you try to incorporate
everything at once.
So our first conversion from
CSS to Sass is going to be
through comments.
In Sass, we're afforded a second
way to denote comments,
double slash single
line comments.
These type of comments in
Sass aren't compiled
down to normal CSS.
So in this case, we see we
have normal CSS comments
following our single
line Sass comments.
And when it's compiled down to
normal CSS, the Sass comments
no longer appear.
These comments come in
exceptionally handy when
you're trying to separate our
your CSS document, as those
cosmetic comments
aren't necessary
for the final product.
As we mentioned before, it's a
bit difficult to deal with
multiple files in CSS.
We're afforded either using
multiple link tags or using
the @import rule.
But historically, we've avoided
using the @import rule
because it's not very
performant.
The stylesheets can't download
in tandem and we have to wait
for everything to load
before any styles are
shown to the browser.
When we use Sass though,
the @import
rule is slightly different.
We can import files that end in
.scss or .sass, and that
importing happens during compile
time instead of on the
client side.
Also, using the @import rule
with Sass, we don't have to
include a file extension.
In this case, we have our
application.scss file and
we're importing the
buttons.scss file.
During compile time, the
application.scss file compiles
down to application.css.
And during compile, the
buttons.scss file is imported
into application.scss, which
ultimately becomes part of
application.css.
However, when we have a separate
buttons.scss file,
the compiler goes ahead and
makes a separate buttons.css
file even though we're already
importing it into application.
Now if we only want to include
buttons.scss as an import of
application, this is
a bit of a problem.
We don't need that
extra stylesheet.
To combat this is Sass, we're
able to create partials.
So we can rewrite our
buttons.scss file as a partial
by starting it with
an underscore.
Once we add the underscore,
it's still imported into
application.scss normally,
but a button.css file
is no longer created.
So back in our application.scss
file, we don't have to change
anything with our import.
The import looks for the files
that I've specified here in
the comments, so we're
still good to go
with our new partial.
Now that we laid the groundwork,
let's start
getting into the really
useful bits of Sass.
First up is nesting.
So as you start writing CSS,
you're going to notice some
patterns with your selectors.
In this case, we have a
content declaration.
And we also have scoped p
and h2 declarations to
go along with it.
So let's go ahead and convert
this over to a Sass file by
copying the same
contents over.
Using Sass, we're able to nest
these properties instead of
defining them separately.
So we have our content
declaration.
And then inside of that,
we're going to nest
our h2 and our p.
At compile time, it's going to
go ahead and scope those as we
initially had in
our normal CSS.
Less common, but occasionally
useful, is the ability to nest
certain types of properties
with matching namespaces.
In this case, we have our text
decoration and text underline
properties nested together.
And when it compiles, it will
compile down to those specific
properties.
We can use this for things like
border and font as well.
Another useful feature while
we're nesting is the ampersand
or the parent selector.
So normally, if we have our
callout block scoped inside of
our content block, it
adds a space it
creates that selector.
If we use the ampersand in front
of our callout block,
when it compiles, it uses that
reference to our initial
parent selector, content, to
create a compound selector
with no space in between.
The difference between these two
declarations, as you may
know, is that the first callout
that's scoped inside
of content looks for a container
that has a class of
callout inside of a container
that has a class of content,
whereas the second looks for
a container that has both
classes at the same time.
Using the parent selector is
exceedingly useful in cases
where we need to have pseudo
classes and pseudo elements
like anchors.
Here, I want to set an active
state and a hover
state for my anchor.
So I can use the parent selector
to go ahead and
reference that anchor as we move
down and set new styles
for those states.
So with this parent selector
reference, we're not limited
to using it as the first
part of a selector.
With this bit of basic CSS, you
can see we have a sidebar
declaration.
And then later, we went
to scope it to user
to change it slightly.
However, we're changing sidebar
in a second scoping,
things are disconnected, and
really it's not quite as
coupled as we want it to be.
So using our parent selector
reference, we're able to nest
this change into our sidebar
declaration in Sass.
We can go ahead and scope that
user's change inside.
Our ampersand character
for the parent
selector references .sidebar.
And we use the user selector
first, so that when it
compiles, it compiles
that same bit of
CSS that we had before.
So take note that when you nest
and combine the parent
selector, the parents selector
reference context carries
through depending
on your nesting.
So this ampersand here, since
it's found inside of a nested
h2 and our sidebar declaration,
has the reference
of sidebar h2.
So when we compile it, as you
can see, it compiles down to
.users, .sidebar, h2 because
of that nesting context.
So as you can see, nesting is
very easy and really helps
clean up our code, but
it's dangerous.
Sass adds a lot of extra
functionality and is very
useful, but it doesn't help
us write good CSS.
You should always check your
nesting to make sure you're
not adding nesting levels
unnecessarily, as that will
increase the specificity of your
selectors far too much.
And here's what I
mean by that.
In this case, we're nesting
everything down to the hover
state for our anchor.
When you see the compiled
CSS, we have a
four level deep selector.
And this specificity
is incredibly
hard to override later.
So as a tip, try limiting
your nesting the
three or four levels.
And if you have to go deeper,
consider refactoring your code
to make use of extra classes.
All right, you've made it the
end of Level One and it's time
to get started on
the challenges.
Make sure you reference the
slides as you move through the
challenges.
And definitely feel free to use
the hints if necessary.
We don't want you to get stuck
in any one place for too long.
Good luck.