[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome to Assembling Sass,
Level Three: Mixin. In Level
Three, we'll be discussing how
to use and set mixins, as well
as how to use arguments
with our mixins.
First up, let's take a look
at some normal CSS.
Here we have a pair
of buttons.
And this isn't very good CSS
because we have three
repeating properties in
each declaration.
To help combat these sources of
repetition in CSS, we can
use a mixin.
So a mixin starts with @mixin.
And then we give it a name.
In this case, we'll
call it button.
And then inside of the block,
we write whatever
properties we like.
And in this case, we're going
to carry over the shared
properties between those
two buttons.
Once we've defined our mixin,
we're able to use it by
calling @include within any
statements we'd like.
So I'm using @include inside of
btn-a, calling the name
of our mixin.
And when it compiles, the
properties that are within the
button mixin are going to be
copied into our btn-a
declaration.
Similarly, in button b if I
also use @include, when it
compiles down, those same
properties will be included in
the btn-b declaration.
When you're using mixins, make
sure that your mixin
declaration comes before these
includes, especially if you're
importing files that have
mixins in them.
If you try to use a mixin
without having it defined
before the include,
Sass is going to
throw an error at you.
On another note, we're
using @include,
that's calling a mixin.
While @import, that we defined
earlier, is importing the
contents of a file into
our Sass file.
So looking back at the CSS we
generated in that previous
example, while we've made it
easier for ourselves on the
Sass side, the generated CSS
is still the same thing.
We're copying those same three
properties into both of our
buttons, and our CSS is
still not efficient.
For now, it's easier to write
this as normal CSS using a
comma-separated selector between
our two buttons for
the shared properties.
So let's stop for second here.
I showed you an example, but
ultimately it wound up being a
bad example of mixin.
In this case, what is a mixin
a really good for?
Let's take a look at
this bit of CSS.
We want to change our
box sizing property.
But to get the best coverage as
far as WebKit and Mozilla
browsers, we have to include
those vendor prefixes.
It can get old really quick if
every time we want to change
box sizing we have to include
three things that
are almost the same.
To combat this, we can start off
by defining a box-sizing
mixin in the same way that we
defined that button mixin and
including all three
vendor prefixes.
Then, within our content block
we can say @include
box-sizing, and those properties
are copied over.
However, as we said before,
here we're just using the
mixin to copy properties, it's
not an efficient use of CSS.
The power of mixins comes from
our ability to pass arguments
into the mixin.
After we define the name of
the mixin, in this case,
box-sizing, we can open and
close parentheses and pass in
any arguments that we'd like.
In this case, we'll call
our argument x.
And then within the mixin, we
can go ahead and use x in any
property we'd like.
Now in our @content declaration,
we're going to
@include our box-sizing mixin.
We pass border box as a
string into the mixin.
Border-box is set
as the x value.
And then everything inside of
the mixin is output into our
content declaration.
So now we have an appropriate
use of mixin.
We can define a callout, use
@include box-sizing, and pass
content-box, a second possible
value for box-sizing, and when
that outputs, it uses that
value as x instead.
Taking our argument passing one
step further, we're able
to define default values
if we'd like.
Looking back at our box-sizing
mixin, we can add a colon to
the end of our x argument and
then add the string of
border-box.
If nothing is passed for x, then
border-box will be used
by default.
Now with our content
declaration, if we simply
include box-sizing and don't
pass an argument, the
border-box value is used by
default, and it outputs using
that value.
With our callout declaration,
however, we have to still pass
content-box as an argument for
it to be output like before.
And as you can see, this
overrides the default.
Let's continue adding complexity
to our arguments by
adding more than one.
By using a comma-separated list,
we can pass more than
one thing into a mixin.
Then, we use that mixin in
with our @include, we'll
simply use a comma-separated
list of arguments to pass more
than one thing ultimately
to our mixin.
Here, you can see our mixin call
here took two parameters
and then used them
both for output.
And for some reason, we call our
mixin, but don't include
the total number of arguments
that the mixin is expecting.
It's going to throw an error
at us when we compile.
If we go ahead and add a default
value to our second
argument, when we call the mixin
we aren't required to
include all of those
values unless we
want to override one.
Now, as you can see, only
including one argument still
allows us to compile, and the
default value is used where we
didn't override it.
When including default values
and creating optional
arguments in our mixins, any
optional arguments need to
come at the end of our
chain of arguments.
Here, if we move our optional
argument up front and then try
to only pass one value, the
compiler is going to throw an
error at us.
Let's go ahead and switch that
back around so that it works
again, and talk about
keyword arguments.
If we're passing more than one
argument into a mixin,
sometimes it can get confusing
what order they're
supposed to go in.
And it's very finicky
if we pass things
in the wrong order.
We can use the values of the
arguments in our mixin to
create key value pairs
in our call like so.
And this allows these keyword
arguments to be
passed in any order.
Some CSS can be problematic
when defining multiple
arguments however.
Here we have the transition
property.
And in the transition property,
it's possible to
have commas separating different
input values for
transition.
If we try to pass these
comma-separated valid CSS
values into mixins, we're going
to run into some issues.
First up, we'll write a
transition mixin similar to
our box-sizing mixin that takes
care of any browser
prefixes that we might have.
Then, if we try to include that
comma-separated CSS value
we showed on the previous slide,
it's going to have a
bit of a problem.
It thinks we're passing two
arguments, even though we're
only passing one, because
of the comma.
To fix this, we can create
a variable argument.
So to create a variable argument
in Sass, we had three
dots to the end of the argument
definition in the
mixin definition.
Here we'll three dots
to the end of val.
And when we pass that
comma-separated value into the
mixin, it uses it as a single
argument and outputs correctly.
We're also able to make use of
variable arguments in reverse.
Here we're looking back
at that button
mixin we defined before.
And if we have a list variable
that we defined back
in Level Two that has two
values, comma-separated, we
can pass that into our mixin
using a variable argument
properties...
When it gets sent into the
mixin, the mixin will split
those values into their
applicable arguments and use
them as necessary.
Let's take a look at some bad
mixin code and figure out how
we can make it better.
We have a mixin that allows
us to pass a color.
And it changes that
side's border.
Here we have three others that
allow us to change any side of
a border we like based
on passing a color.
So in our button declaration,
we're going to change the
right side border color based
on the argument we
pass into the mixin.
However, this is horribly
inefficient.
We have a separate mixin for
each side of the border.
Using interpolation that we
learned back in Level Two, we
can clean this up a bit.
We're going to redefine
our highlight
mixin simply as highlight.
We'll continue to pass color as
an argument, but we're also
going to add side
as an argument.
Within our mixin, we can use
interpolation to interpolate
the value of our side
argument into the
border color property.
Now when we use it within our
button, we'll pass which side
we would like to change.
And ultimately, we simply need
to pass the right string, then
we have one mixin that
can handle any side
of our border color.
That does is for Level Three.
It's time for you write some
mixins of your own.
And I'll see you
in Level Four.
Good luck.