[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome to Level 2 of Asembling
Sass: Variable.
In Level 2, we'll be discussing
how to set and use
variables, the types of
variables we can set, scoping
variables, and interpolation.
So eventually, the CSS spec
will natively support
variables, but for now, Sass
affords us a way to use these
bits of re-callable
information.
In Sass, we define a variable
with a dollar sign
followed by the name.
So here, you can see we're
defining a base variable and
giving it a color value.
So then within our Sass code, we
can call $base by just using
the name in any value, and that
color code that we gave
it initially will be
inserted when we
compile to our CSS file.
Optionally, we can use
the default flag
when we define variables.
Normally, if we define a
variable, then call it again
to define a new value, that
first value is overwritten.
In this case, using title and
then defining title again
immediately thereafter
changes that value
to the second value.
So when we use it and when it
compiles, that second value is
the value that's used.
When we use the default flag,
however, on that second
variable definition, it checks
to see, first, whether or not
a value already exists.
So, in this case, since "My
Blog" is already set to title,
the second value of "About Me"
doesn't override "My Blog."
Let's take a look at how
this might be useful.
If we're defining more modular
Sass, like a buttons partial,
here, that we'll be importing
into application later, if we
want this partial to be
hands-off, to have a bunch of
code that we're not going to
touch later, we might define a
rounded variable with a default
flag, so that we can
override it if we want.
But, if nothing else is provided
in the file that it
will be imported into, then it
will go ahead and set itself
based on a value
not being set.
So back in our application.scss
file, we can
go ahead and set a rounded
variable, we can import
buttons, and since we're
overriding that default, it
will go ahead and use that
new value when it
compiles down to CSS.
There are a number of different
types of values we
can store as variables,
including booleans, like true
and false; numbers, with or
without units; colors,
including just straight name
colors, like purple, RGBA
values, and hex values; strings,
with or without
quotes; lists, which kind of act
like a raise, either they
are comma separated or have
spaces; and null, which we'll
go into later as far
as conditionals.
We are about halfway
through variables.
Let's talk a bit about
scoping variables.
Here, we're able to define
variables within a CSS
declaration.
We're defining our border color
within the paragraph
declaration, then using it.
However, if we try to use
that variable in our h1
declaration, it doesn't have
access to that initial border
variable, and when we
compile down, it's
going to throw an error.
So any variables that we set
within a declaration aren't
available outside
a declaration.
However, if we define a
variable outside of a
declaration and change it
within a declaration, it
changes that variable
globally.
Let's take a look at
an example of that.
First up, we'll define a
color-base with a color value, and
then within our sidebar
declaration, we're going to
change that value and use it.
When that compiles, we can see
that our changed value is
what's used for that sidebar
background color.
Later, however, when we try to
reuse that variable in a
different declaration, like
paragraph, here, that changed
value is going to
be used as well.
Changing it within a
declaration changed it globally.
So last up, as far as
variables go, is
interpolation.
Now, we can use the Ruby-esque
method of using a hash
followed by an opening and
closing curly brace to add our
variables to either selector
names, property names, or
within strings.
Here, we're setting a variable
to the string of top.
And then if we wanted to use
that as a property inside of
our super declaration, we can
go ahead and interpolate the
value of our side variable as
the property within there.
When this compiles down, since
side is equal to the string of
top, that string is inserted
into that interpolation, and
that's the property that's used
in that second position
within super.
Also, we're able to interpolate
this value of the
side variable into a selector.
So, second here, we have
a callout, hyphen, and
interpolated value of side.
When this compiles down, we
can see it compiles to
callout-top,
with top being the
value of our side variable.
We find it useful to
be very considerate
in naming our variables.
If we use things that are more
semantic, like color-base, we
get a lot more mileage out of
it than something like
color-blue as we move Sass from
project to project.
That wraps up Level 2.
Good luck with the challenges,
and we'll see you in Level 3.