[SINGING]
Your client side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add
structure but it
won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models that
you cannot lose, we'll
render out your models with
the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the Anatomy of
Backbone JS at Code School.
You're watching The Anatomy of
Backbone Part Two, and this is
Level Six where we're going
to be going over app
organization.
All of the Backbone objects
we've defined thus far have
been in the Global Namespace,
which can lead to problems.
First, it can lead to
naming collisions.
Second, we're having to put
the type of object it is
inside the name, which
just feels wrong.
And then lastly, the
maintainability of the app is
going to be difficult.
One way we could solve this
problem is by creating a
single global object where
we store everything.
So here you can see we've
got Models, Views, and
Collections, and then we
simply put our Backbone
objects inside of those.
So App.Models.ToDoItem,
App.Views, App.Collections,
App.Views, and we can just store
one off objects like our
router at the top level.
Now when we go to instantiate
these classes, we simply add
the Namespace, in this case
App.Models.ToDoItem.
Now let's talk about links.
We might have links in our
existing HTML that we want to
call Backbone actions.
So one way we could do this
is by using jQuery.
So every time a link is
clicked, we'll prevent
default, and then we'll
navigate to the
target of that link.
However, what if we wanted
Backbone to handle
our links for us?
The first thing we can do to
make this cleaner is to move
this jQuery code inside of our
App Global Object, maybe
inside of a start function
like so.
This also might be
where we put our
Backbone.history.start function.
And to start our application, we
can simply call App.start.
However, the way we're listening
for events here is a
view concern.
Backbone is capable
of handling it.
So let's move this inside of
our View Event hierarchy.
To do this, we're going to make
our application itself a
Backbone View.
This allows us to use the
Backbone Events handler.
So inside here, we can
specify the event
when a link is clicked.
To instantiate the app, we're
going to send in the entire
document body so it will
listen for events
anywhere on the page.
Since we only want to create
one instance of this App
class, we can simplify this
code a little and actually
instantiate this view right
after we define
the class, like so.
Notice the parameters are now
at the bottom of this code.
Now to start our application
running, we simply need to
call App.start.
Here's our link HTML again, and
here's our Event Handler.
So this is going to capture
all links on the page.
But sometimes, we may not want
to capture all events.
For example, this Support link
here, that might be a link to
a different web page that
doesn't use Backbone.
We might want to refresh
the entire page.
So how do we specify
which links we
want Backbone to handle?
One way we could do this is by
adding a data attribute.
So here we have
data-internal=true, and then
inside our Event Handler, we can
specify to only listen for
links that have this
data element.
Since we have a view that
encompasses our entire
document body, if we want, we
can put some template code
into this App View which has
some of our initial HTML.
This is why sometimes when you
go to websites that use
Backbone and you view the
source, there's not much HTML
on the page.
It's probably because it's
getting loaded initially by a
view that encompasses the
entire document body.
So to do that here, we have
a basic template.
We're going to render it, and
then call the Start function.
It renders out some initial
HTML to the body.
Inside of the start method
is also a good place to
instantiate our Collections,
our Views, render out our
Views and append that to
the page, and then
fetch the todoItems.
This works fine, but if you're
loading a page for the first
time, you're actually doing two
requests to load the page,
one to load the initial HTML,
and then you're doing an AJAX
request to fetch all the data.
But what if you could put
that initial data
also inside your HTML?
That would be quicker, and you
wouldn't have to do that
callback for all of your data.
The first step to do something
like that is to simply put
your data inside of a variable
inside of the HTML that we're
initially sending over.
In this case, we have
a little bootstrap
variable with our data.
We're going to send that
bootstrap variable into our
start function.
The start function receives a
bootstrap parameter, and then
we send that into our Collection
to initialize all
of our todoItems.
That's all there is to it, and
we've sped up our application
because it no longer has to do
that AJAX request to fetch all
the To Dos after the
page is loaded.
Let's have you organize some of
our Backbone code, and I'll
see you in the final level.