Your client-side JavaScript
is to starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add
structure, but it
won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models,
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want
your JavaScript to
end up like a mess.
It's time for the Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
You're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone, Part Two.
And this is Level 4--
Varying Views.
Typically, when we create views,
we send in the model
they're associated with.
So here, you can see we
pass in the todoItem.
And then basically, what
we call todoView.model.
It's the same thing
as just todoItem.
And then, when we set
a collection,
we send in the todoItems.
Here again todoView.collection
is equal to todoItems.
But what other options can we
pass into initialization?
Let's look at a few useful
reasons to do this.
So here's our todoView.
And we have a template,
we have a
typical render function.
When we instantiate this view,
we send in the proper model.
And in our HTML, we already have
a todo div where we want
to put that todo.
So we might just grab that out
of the DOM, change the HTML to
this todoViews element.
This is going to print out a div
within a div, because the
default element for a
view is a div, which
obviously is not good.
So how might we use the
existing div here
instead, and not to?
To fix this, we can instantiate
the view with
another parameter, here passing
in the existing el,
which in this case
is our todo div.
Now to render out the view,
all we have to call is
todoView.render, and it will
properly use the existing div.
Another use for passing extra
options into your views is if
you have additional JavaScript
objects that might be useful
inside of those views, such
as currentUser here.
So if we pass in currentUser, we
can access that by calling
toDoView.options, which is
going to give us back a
JavaScript object with all
of the different extra
options we passed in.
This also can be useful if you
want to access extra options
in your initialize function.
So here you can see we're
setting the options.user equal
to this.user property, which
will make it easier to access.
Sometimes your Backbone views
might be in charge of printing
out user generated content.
But you need to be careful
because people may try to put
malicious JavaScript inside
of your model values.
And you don't want to be
printing that out to the
screen, like so.
One way you can fix this
is by using the
model inside your template.
So we'll need to send the
entire model into the
template, and then once inside
there, we can call escape
method, which will properly
escape the value.
So in this case, it'll print
out our escape code, which
will keep our page safe.
Here we have a view that prints
out a description.
And we want to make it so that
every time the description is
changed, it updates the view,
and highlights it.
So if we set the description,
it's going to trigger the
change:description event.
But what if we wanted to change
the description, but
not call that event handler?
How might we do that?
We can do that by sending
in an extra parameter--
in this case, silent: true.
This will update the
description, but it won't call
that change event function.
But what if we do want to update
the view, but not do
the highlight?
So we just want to run the first
line of that function,
and not the second where
it gets highlighted.
In this case, we can pass an
additional option into that
change event function.
We're going to call a
highlight: false.
We just made that up.
That'll get passed inside
the options object.
And we can simply add
a conditional.
So if options highlight is not
equal to false, then we do
want to highlight
the description.
This is useful if you want
finer-grained control over
your event handlers.
So here's our todoView.
And you can see here the model
is going to notify the view of
changes so that it
can re-render.
But what if we want to
remove the view, but
not delete the model?
So we just want to hide the view
for some reason, take it
off of our page, but we're
not deleting the model.
Well, if we call just
todoView.remove, that's not so
good, because the model still
holds a reference to it, and
it's going to try to update
it when it changes.
So we need to turn off
that model event.
And in older versions of
Backbone, this is how we would
do it, which is, well,
not that pretty.
However, there's a better
way to do this now.
Instead of telling the model
to notify the view when
there's changes, we're going
to tell the view to
listen to the model.
So we do this by calling
listenTo,
sending it the model.
Give it the event we want to
listen for, and then the
function to call when
the model changes.
Then if we want to stop all of
the listeners, we can simply
call todoView.stopListening.
And when we call remove,
it automatically calls
stopListening.
So it's not going to be
listening for model events
anymore because the view no
longer is on the page.
It's time for you to explore
some various views in the
challenges.