[SINGING]
Your client side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to
add structure.
But it won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models.
And you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
I'm Gregg Pollack.
And you're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone, Part Two.
In this first level,
we're going to be
going into more models.
So just to review,
we're getting our
truth out of the DOM.
Backbone provides the client
side application
structure for our app.
We have models that represent
data, views that
hook up to the DOM.
And then Backbone also takes
care of synchronizing the data
back and forth from
the server.
Jumping back into our Backbone
app that we've been creating,
here is our TodoItem,
which is a model.
And then we give
it a urlRoot.
And we're assuming that that
attaches to a Rails RESTful
endpoint, the Rails Flavor of an
API, which our application
isn't always going to have that
standard API, which we're
actually going to cover
in this level.
How do we deal with that?
So then to get the
TodoItem with ID equals
1, we run this code.
And then we call fetch, which
fetches this JSON data, stores
that inside of our model.
But what if when we call fetch,
our API is different
than the standard Rails
interface, and it's sending
back something that
looks like this?
Well inside of Backbone,
there's a parse method.
This is what it looks
like by default.
We don't have to define it.
But this is what its behavior
looks like.
And with that default code, if
we call todoItem.attributes,
when we got this JSON array--
well, it would be empty.
So how do we deal with that?
To fix this and properly parse
the JSON, we are going to
define the parse method
inside of Backbone.
And inside there, we simply have
to write response.todo.
Instead of passing the response
directly through, we
intercept it in this method and
call .todo, so that the
proper JSON objects get
sent into Backbone.
Now we called that attributes,
we can see that our Backbone
model returns the
proper values.
What if instead of fetching the
JSON, we wanted to create
a model with some pre-existing
data like this?
But notice this is that weird
different format again.
In this case, if we call
.attributes, we can see that,
well, it didn't work.
It didn't properly go through
the parse method.
To fix this, we can add
another option to our
constructor--
in this case parse: true.
This will tell the model
to run the JSON
through the parse method.
And it will properly parse
the attributes.
But what if the API we're
working with sends back a
different property name?
You can see here that we
have d-e-s-c instead of
description, which is what
we're expecting.
To deal with this inside the
parse method, we can simply
define response.description
and set that equal to the
description that got sent
in from the JSON.
And we need to make sure
we delete the old
name for that property.
Then we just return
the response.
And now when we call
.attributes, we get back the
proper JSON object.
So we have our todoItem.
And if we update one of the
attributes and we call save,
that's going to call toJSON
and send that back to the
server using a put.
But the API we've been working
with is expecting the JSON in
that different format
we saw a minute ago.
So how do we modify that
JSON before we send
it back to the server?
We can fix this by overriding
the JSON method.
So here is the default behavior
of the JSON method.
And then here's the default
output, which in this case is
not what we want.
So to fix this, as you might
imagine, we just need to
override the toJSON method.
So here you can see we're simply
wrapping the attributes
inside a todo property.
This properly outputs what
our API is expecting.
But of course, we
forgot one part.
What about the description
becoming d-e-s-c?
To fix this inside of our JSON,
we can simply set the
d-e-s-c property.
And then we're going to use the
underscore library's pick
method, which allows us to send
in a JavaScript object
and pick out the properties
that we want to
be included in it.
So we'll have an object with
just the d-e-s-c and status
property, which then allows us
to create the proper object
that our API is expecting.
But there's a problem
with this though.
Now we can't use toJSON
in our view to
render out our template.
Well how would we fix this?
Here's the code inside of
our render function
where we call toJSON.
So we can't use to
JSON anymore.
To fix this instead of using
toJSON, we can use
model.attributes, which will
give us back the JavaScript
object we're looking for.
toJSON should only be used for
serializing the data back
to the server.
One more thing we might have
to deal with in an
unconventional API is a
non-standard ID attribute.
So here when we call fetch,
you can see that our ID
attribute is _id.
So if we try to parse this and
call .id on the model, we
would get back undefined.
To fix this, we simply need to
specify the ID attribute
property inside of our model.
Once we do that, it's going
to properly parse this
field as the ID.
That's the end of level one.
It's time for you to get your
hands dirty in the challenges.