[SINGING]
Your client-side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add
structure, but it
won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models
that you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
The Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
You're watching The Anatomy
of Backbone, Part Two.
In this level, we're going to be
going over some customized
collections.
Let's review how we work with
Backbone Collections.
Here you can see how we
define a collection.
To populate a collection,
we call fetch.
This is going to return an
array of JSON objects.
And then if we call
todoItems.length, we can get
back how many models are
in a collection.
Once again, what do we do when
the API we're working with
returns a non-standard
response?
Perhaps something that
looks like this.
Here, you see we have a total.
We have the number of
items per page.
We even have a current page.
And then, todos data is wrapped
inside of a todos property.
Under the covers, Backbone
Collections also has a parse
method, which looks like this.
And with the current code, if
we called toJSON, well, it
doesn't know how to
parse this object.
To fix this, once again, we can
redefine our parse function.
We're going to want to store the
per_page, page, and total
properties.
So we can just do
that like this.
And then we simply want to
return the todos array.
These new properties can simply
be accessed by calling
.perPage, .page, or .total.
And these aren't special
properties.
They aren't defined
anywhere else.
Remember, we're working inside
JavaScript, so we can just
randomly define new properties
inside of a JavaScript object.
And now, if we call toJSON,
it works as intended.
So working with this API,
when we call fetch, it
returns this JSON.
Now we're properly parsing it.
But what if we wanted
to turn a few pages?
What if we wanted to get
page number six?
We would need to call a GET
request with a parameter.
In this case, page equals 6.
But how would we do that
inside Backbone?
We can do that by sending an
additional object into fetch.
In this case, we're going to
specify that we want to send
additional data on to the
request, and that data is
going to be page six.
This will construct the proper
URL and do the request.
However, since we're setting the
current page when we first
fetch the collection, we could
make this code a little more
dynamic, and call fetch on
the page which is our
current page plus one.
This would get us the next
page of todo items.
Now we know how to fetch the
next page, but how would we
put this next page link in
our app and make it work?
Here's some code you
should remember
from the first course.
Inside of a review, we have an
initialize function, which
listens for the collection
reset event.
We have a render function,
which calls addAll.
The addAll function empties out
our elements, and it goes
through each item in our
collection, calling addOne
for each todoItem.
Lastly in the addOne function,
we create a todo view for each
todo item, and then render that
out and append that
to the collection element.
So how do we use this collection
view to render out
a next link?
One way we could do this is by
adding a template into this
collection view, which
will render out the
link that we want.
Then inside of our render
function, after we add all the
todoItems, we can append the
HTML from this template,
sending in the proper
page that we want
this link to go to.
That's all we need to do here.
But we should still jump
into the router and
add this page URL.
Before we do that, let's quickly
review our router.
So here we have just
one route.
We have the index route.
Inside of our initialize
function, we're instantiating
the collection and the
collection view, rendering out
that collection, appending it
to the app div, and then
defining the index route
function, which will just
fetch the todo items.
So at our page route,
we simply add
this path to our routes.
And then to find the page route
function, notice this
has a parameter it gets from
the path called page.
And then we simply fetch the
todo items, sending in the
proper page.
Let's take a look at this
code in action.
So here, you can see
our todo list.
When we click next page,
it brings us to the
next page of todos.
We can even click Back if we
want to, or Refresh, because
every time we click
next page, it's
updating the URL properly.
Backbone provides an easy way
to sort your data using the
comparator property.
So here inside of our
collection, if we say
comparator status, so now when
we call fetch and we get the
data, Backbone is going to
sort our models into the
specified order.
In this case, sorted
by status.
To do more complex sorting, we
can set the comparator equal
to a function.
This function will take in two
parameters which are two
different models.
We can then compare two
items on that model.
In this case, we're comparing
the status, so we'll sort
status in reverse order.
And once we call fetch,
then use the
comparator to sort our models.
What if we wanted to count how
many models in our collection
are complete?
Well, one way we can do that
is by defining a completed
count function.
Inside of that, we're going to
want to use the where function
to filter all of the items in
our collection that have
status complete.
And then we can call length on
that returned array to give us
the number of complete items.
So if this was our collection
data, and we called completed
count, we would get
returned one.
That's the end of level two.
It's time to code up some
collections in the challenges.