[SINGING]
Your client side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to
add structure.
But it won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
You're watching the anatomy
of Backbone, Part Two.
And this is level five where
we're going to be
working with forms.
Up until now, we haven't talked
about forms at all.
And obviously we want to
add new to do items.
So one way we might think to do
this is to create an HTML
form and hook it up
with some Ajax.
Let's see what that
would look like.
Here we have our HTML with
our default description.
And if we were using plain
jQuery, we could simply hook
onto the click event, call
prevent default so the form
doesn't submit, grab the URI
from the form action, get the
description out of the input
element, and then do an Ajax
post with these values.
This would work.
But doesn't Backbone take
care of this Ajax
data thing for us?
Shouldn't there be
a way to do this?
Well there is.
Let's figure it out.
Let's start from the bottom
up with the model.
So if we have a model with a
proper urlRoot, we can then
call to do item and send a
default description in if we
want when we instantiate this.
Then when we save it, we can
pass in the values we
want to set it to.
And when we call save, it's
automatically going to do that
Ajax request to create
a new todoItem.
So there's our Ajax call.
But how do we create the form?
Well, our form should simply
be another view.
Here's what its template
might look like.
It's simply the form.
And here's our normal
render function.
To create this form, we first
need to create a to do item.
We'll send that to do
item into the form.
And then we'll simply render
it out on our web page.
Notice the value has the default
description which got
printed out using
our templates.
So this prints out the
form to the page.
But if we clicked the button,
nothing would happen.
Because we're not listening for
any events on that button.
So inside of our TodoForm
view, we're going to listen
for the click on the button.
And we'll call our save
event function.
Inside that function, we want
to prevent the default
behavior of the form.
We'll grab the new description
from the input field.
And then finally call save on
the model, which will do the
Ajax request.
This works fine.
But it's only going to work when
we hit the Submit button.
What if we wanted to be able to
type out our new to do and
simply hit Enter?
Backbone comes with a special
event called Submit, we can
use here, which will call save
either when we hit the button
or when we press Enter.
So now we can create
new to do items.
But what about editing
a specific one?
Well, we can actually
reuse the same view.
To do that, we first fetch the
to do item we want to edit.
Then we create a new to
do form and send in
the existing model.
And then just render
it out to the page.
That's all there is to it.
And it will automatically use
the description on that
existing to do item.
But there's one more step before
this all really works,
and that is to update
our router.
Here's our existing
TodoApp router--
nothing new here--
where we instantiate our to
do items, send them to the
collection view.
And then insider index
function--
fetch the to do items and render
it out to the page.
Let's add a route to render
the to do form with an
existing to do item.
So in the routes, we'll specify
todo, slash, the ID
that we want to edit,
slash, edit.
That'll call the Edit
Event function.
And inside that, we'll simply
get that todoItem model out
of our collection and send
that into the TodoForm.
Then we'll simply render out
that form to the page.
What about the new form?
First we're going to
add a new route.
So when someone goes to
todo/new, it's going to render
out a newTodo.
And that new to do function is
simply going to create a new
todoItem and send that into
a new TodoForm view, and
then render that out
to the page.
Now back in our TodoForm when
we successfully save a to
do item, we're going to want to
go back to our index route.
But we're only going to want
to do this when we
successfully save.
If there's an error, we don't
want to go back to the index.
So let's change this up a little
bit and add a call
back, so when the save is
successful, then navigate to
the index path.
But what happens if the to
do item doesn't save?
What if there's maybe some
sort of validation error?
Well we can add one
more call back.
This will be the error
call back.
And in this case, we're
going to want to
parse out the errors.
And we'll just alert
them onto the page.
Let's check out our new
to do form in action.
So here if we click on New
Todo, here is our form.
If we try to submit it without
anything, we get a validation
error-- description
can't be blank.
Now if we create a proper to
do item and save it, ah, it
gets added to our list.
If we wanted to edit this form,
we can click this edit
link which allows us to update
the specific to do item like
you see here.
Forms are an important part
of any web application.
So it's time for you to
do some of them in the
challenges.