[SINGING]
Your client-side JavaScript
to starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble a
bad spaghetti code.
And it is time add structure,
but it won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data and the models
that you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
You're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone Part 2.
And this is level seven,
where we're going to
be customizing Backbone.
So here we are back in
our TodoItemView.
And notice here that we're using
a banana instead of our
typical template keyword, just
to remind you that views don't
care how you use templates or
what kind of template you use.
It's very easy to use other ones
such as handlebars, EJS,
or Google Clojure Templates.
We're going to take a look
at a couple alternatives.
So here's an Underscore
template where we have
description, and assigned_to
as variables
that get filled in.
And then the equivalent Mustache
template would look
something like this.
Notice we're using curly
braces here.
Mustache doesn't allow for
arbitrary JavaScript.
So you've got to do things
slightly differently.
Let's take a closer look.
So if you want to use Mustache
inside your view, you're going
to want to call Mustache.compile
and then
include the string that has
your Mustache HTML in it.
Mustache.compile returns a
function, just like to
_.template does.
So as we saw a moment ago, if
are view sends in this data,
with underscore, this is how
we put it into our HTML.
And with Mustache, we use
the curly braces.
But how would we
render an array
names inside of Mustache?
Here's our array.
With underscore, we would use
JavaScript, calling the _.each
method, which is a
little verbose.
Mustache, I think, is a
little bit cleaner.
We simply specify names, and
then inside of that, we have
our little loop, and we just
have to do curly braces with a
dot, specify we want to print
out each item in that array.
But what if we had an
array of objects,
like this, with people?
Well, in underscore, we would,
again, go through each of
them, like so.
And with Mustache, we would
do this, where we
just specify the keys.
As you can see, it's a little
easier to read.
Let's take a look at a few more
mustache conventions.
So if our view sends in data,
completed false, and we only
want to show done if completed
is true, we do this in
Mustache which would print out,
"Are you done?" because
completed is false.
If our array of names was blank,
and we had the same
Mustache code you saw a few
slides ago, it would simply
print out the uls, and no lis.
And if you wanted to print out
some HTML if completed was
false, we could do it like
this, using that carrot.
So in this case, it would print
out, "Are you done?
Nope!" Mustache allows you to
send functions into it if you
need more complex behavior
inside your template.
So here, we have a header
function which simply wraps
our rendered text
inside of an h1.
Here's what our template
would look like.
So it's going to render
Hello, name.
Name, in this case, is Eric.
And then it's going to wrap
that inside of an h1.
By default backbone has a very
RESTful persistence strategy.
So when we go to Read data, we
call fetch, which causes a Get
request to happen.
When we need to update, we call
Save, which triggers a
Put request.
When we need to delete, we call
destroy, which triggers a
delete request.
And when we need to create, we
simply create a new TodoItem,
like you see here, Save
it, and it's going to
do a post to /todos.
But what if we wanted to
override the default behavior
and make it so that our backbone
model was read-only?
Remember how we overrode the
parse method in level one to
override the default behavior?
We're going to do the same thing
here to make a model
read-only by overriding
the sync function.
The sync function has
three parameters--
method, model, and options.
In this case, we're going to
check to see if the method is
equal to read.
If it is, we do want to
sync with the server.
And if it isn't, we're
simply going to
error out to the console.
The method parameter is either
going to be read, create,
update, or delete.
And when we call fetch now,
it's going to work.
But if we call save, that's when
it's going to print out,
" cannot update a TodoItem
model." So now, we know how to
override the default behavior
of our persistence strategy,
but what if we wanted
to create our
own persistence strategy?
Perhaps we would have a switch
statement, which does certain
things when create, read,
update, or delete are sent in
as the method.
Let's do this making a
localStorage persistence strategy.
So in case you're not familiar
with localStorage, this is
browser-side storage that
most browsers have.
You can call setItem to
set a key and value.
For example, we can set
animal as the key
and dog is the value.
And then, when we call getItem
animal, we get back dog, as
you would expect.
We can remove an item.
If we try to get an
item that doesn't
exist, it returns undefined.
And lastly, we can use a nice
object syntax, where we
specify the key between brackets
and set that equal to
the value that we want.
We can obviously read
this back out
using the same format.
Here's all the browsers that
support local storage.
So we really are talking about
storing this data on
somebody's browser.
Let's implement this local
storage persistence strategy,
starting with the
create method.
So if the create method
is sent in, we
need to create a key.
In this case, we're simply
going to prefix it with
TodoItem and then
send in the ID.
Then we're going to set
that with this key and
stringify the model.
This automatically calls the
toJSON function on the model
and then turns it into a string,
which we can store in
somebody's browser.
So now, when we create a new
TodoItem, like so, it's going
to store it in the browser.
And if we use something like
devtools, we can actually
inspect it, and see, like this,
that it's stored the
value like so.
Now, to implement the Read
method, we need to construct
the key again, get the result
from local storage using the
key, then, if that result
does exist, parse that
string back into JSON.
Then we need to check to see the
success callback exists.
And if it does, return
the result.
Now we can create a new
todoItem, call fetch, which
will read this todoItem
out of local storage.
And then if we call
todoItem.attributes, we can
see that our localStorage
strategy worked.
If a key doesn't exist in local
storage, we might also
want to do something on error.
So here, we're going to
check to see if the
error callback exist.
And if it does, then we're going
to error out, "couldn't
find TodoItem." Now, if we
create a new TodoItem, and we
attempt to fetch the value, and
we pass in an error call
back, that error callback will
be run and, in this case,
print an Alert message.
So now you know how
to create a local
storage persistence strategy.
But if that's what you really
want, somebody's already
created that for you.
If you go to this GitHub URL,
you can simply include this
JavaScript in your code and
specify when you create a
collection that you want to
use this localStorage.
And it will automatically take
care of reading, creating,
updating, and destroying out
of local storage for your
Backbone models.
Only a few more challenges
before you
complete this course.
We'll see you in the
wrap up video.