[SINGING]
Your client side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to
add structure.
But it won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
You're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone, Part Two.
And in level three,
we're going to be
talking about real routes.
If our to do application was
able to search, we might have
a router that looks like this,
where we have search and then
query option.
And then also our search
results might
have multiple pages.
So we need to specify that.
Here's our search route
function where we have two
parameters, query and page.
And we're simply going to log
those out to the console.
So if we navigate to
search/milk, the result is
going to be milk, comma,
zero, obviously.
And if we navigate to
search/milk page two, we get
back milk, comma, 2.
So good so far.
But there's a way that we can
get rid of some of this
duplication.
And instead of listing out these
routes in two different
lines, we can do them in one.
We do this simply by
using parentheses.
Parentheses give us an optional
part of our route.
So now the same routes
still work.
But we can define them
in a single line.
But what if we wanted this
route to also match
search/milk/p2 and have
that trailing slash.
It's not uncommon to want to
have your URLs be able to take
that trailing slash.
We can do this by adding another
optional part of our
route, which just has the slash
in between parentheses.
So now when we go to this route,
it's going to work.
When people use our search
form, they might type in
multiple words.
This is going to get encoded
in the URL like so.
But it's actually never going
to get decoded in our app.
And we don't want to have to
search for
So how do we decode that?
Well it's pretty simple.
We just need to add a line,
decodeURIComponent, and send
in the query parameter.
This will properly decode
this string, so we
can search for it.
Also in our router, here's
how we show a todoItem.
And right now the function
itself is simply going to log
out the ID that we send in.
So if we go todos/2, it's
going to log out, 2.
But what if we sent in a non
numeric parameter, in this
case notanid?
Well it's going to trigger
that same function.
And it's going to look for
an ID with notanid.
So how might we filter this
route, so that it only accepts
numeric IDs?
To do this, we can use a regex
and call todorouter.route,
specify the regex that we want
and specify the route function
we want it to call.
This would work.
Now when we call todos/notanid,
it wouldn't
trigger the show route.
Obviously this code
isn't optimal.
We're defining a route from
outside of the router.
And we want to define all of our
routes inside the router.
However, a JavaScript object
like we've been using to
define our routes can't accept a
regular expression as a key.
So the way to do this is inside
of the Initialize
function as you see here.
This allows us to keep the
route inside the router.
We can use some pretty advanced
regular expressions.
You see that code up there?
I don't even know
what that means.
But it's advanced.
So this matches a bunch of
different search routes.
Doesn't match some other ones.
And in order to figure out how
to do the regular expression
stuff like this, check
out this URL.
The router allows us to have
some catch all routes.
For example if we wanted a route
that gets called when
none of our other route
paths get matched, we
could do *path.
And that would call the
notFound request function, in
this case just saying sorry,
there's no content here.
So we navigate to nothinghere,
which
doesn't match a route,
it's going to give us
this alert message.
One way this can be useful is to
get the different parts of
a file path.
So our route is file/*path.
That calls the file request
function, which in this case
is just going to split out the
path and log them all out to
the console.
So if we call file/this/is/a/file,
we get back
each part of that path, this
is a file, in an array.
Why don't you jump into some
real routes in the challenges?