I'm Carlos Souza and
you're watching
Rails 4, Zombie Outlaws.
In this level, we're going to
be looking at more additions
to active record and
active model.
Back in Rails 3, one way you
could write scopes was by
passing your relation to either
scope or default scope,
which was known as eager
evaluated scopes.
They're now deprecated
in Rails 4.
If you try using them, you're
going to come across this
deprecation warning.
You should now use the proc
object syntax instead.
And for the default scope, you
can either pass in a proc
object or a block.
To understand the reason behind
these deprecations,
let's take a look at
the following code.
Here, we're passing a condition
to the scope where
we have a date inside.
The issue here is that two weeks
ago is only going to be
resolved when the class is
loaded and not every time that
we run this query so the
date will never change.
In the second example, although
the first scope for
recent is correct, the fact that
we're using the second
scope with the relation and
calling the recent on that
which is forcing the previous
scope to be resolved and,
again, forcing two weeks ago
to always be the same date.
And that's why in Rails 4, you
should always use the proc
object as an argument
to scopes.
Now let's take a look at a
Users model that has a
visible post method that returns
a collection of posts
based on the user role.
So when the user is a country
manager or reviewer, it's
returning a subset
of the post.
However, when it's a bad user,
we're using an empty array to
represent an empty collection.
So the problem here is that if
visible post return an empty
array, and then we try to call
recent on that, we're going to
run into a no method error
because there's no method
recent for an array.
One way you can fix this is by
checking the return value from
visible posts.
If there's any element on the
return that we get from
visible post, then we' go
ahead and call recent.
Otherwise, we, again, return
an empty array just to make
sure that the caller for this
code doesn't also break.
So this code isn't
looking too good.
Let's see how we can solve
this in Rails 4 using the
Post.none method that returns an
active record relation and
never hits the database.
So in this case, we can remove
all the conditionals and
simply call recent
on the result.
Here's the possible outcomes
for the visible post method
and we can see here that at the
end it's obviously calling
post.none.recent which will
return an empty collection.
Every method that we call on
this chain will never hit the
database because we've
called post.none.
In Rails 3, if wanted a query
for all posts where the author
was not equal to the one that
we're passing as an argument,
we could write something like
this which works fine for most
of the values that we pass
in except where it's nil.
When the author is nil, it's
actually going to generate
this incorrect SQL syntax which
will now blow up but
will return an incorrect
result.
As a workaround, we can check
for the value of author and if
it's nil, then we write
the proper SQL syntax.
In Rails 4, we can use the not
method which will negate the
query and will automatically
check for when the author is
nil and it will generate
the proper SQL syntax.
Here we have a User model with
the default scope that orders
the results by name.
If we wanted to call order
again, which do you think
would take precedence?
Turns out that in Rails 3, the
first call to order, in this
case the one that's found in
the default scope, takes
precedence.
Any additional calls to order
will get appended to the end
of the SQL statement.
In Rails 4, this behavior's
changed.
Now it's reversed.
New calls to order will
take precedence
over existing calls.
In Rails 3, if you wanted to
specify that an order was
descending, you would have to
pass a SQL string like this.
In Rails 4, now you
can pass a hash.
So this is the SQL that
it generates.
Notice that the default sorting
for name is ascending.
Also in Rails 4, order can
now simply take a hash.
In this case, created at
desc will generate
the following SQL.
Let's look at the following
scenario.
Say we wanted to query for posts
and also include their
comments, however, we wanted to
filter the posts for where
their comments had the name
equal to the string 'foo'.
This code in Rails 4 shows a
deprecation warning because
Rails has to look inside of that
SQL string to figure out
what table this refers to.
This code is brittle and
it's not guaranteed
to work in the future.
In Rails 4, you must use the
references method to
explicitly tell when you're
referencing a
table from a string.
In this case, you're referencing
comments.
Some cases do not require us to
use the references method,
for example, when we're using
hash based conditions.
And in this case over here,
we're not using any
conditions.
We're simply ordering
the results.
So we don't have to use
the references method.
Back in Rails 3, active model
was introduced, which pretty
much allowed us to treat any
Ruby class like an active
record object without
necessarily having a database
table behind it.
In this example, we have the
support ticket class.
And by mixing in certain modules
from active model, we
can treat objects from this
class like an active record
object and use it in form
helpers and also call methods
like valid, errors, and
to param on them.
In Rails 4, we can include the
ActiveModel::Model module--
yes, ActiveModel::Model which
will basically mix in the same
modules that we saw before,
but obviously,
writing a lot less code.
And if we look inside of that
module, we can see that the
implementation is pretty
straightforward.
It simply includes the
module that we saw in
the previous slide.