[SINGING]
Wanted and captured without
bail, locked and forgotten in
a rusty jail.
Zombies attacked, the
townsfolk fled.
Those who were left
became the undead.
He's the zombie outlaw.
And he's fighting the law
that left him for dead,
for dead, for dead.
My name is Carlo Souza, and
you're watching Rails 4,
Zombie Outlaws. In this level,
we're going to be
looking at views.
Say we have an Owner class
which has many items.
And each item obviously
belongs to an owner.
In Rails 3 and 4, if you wanted
to build a Select box
for owners, you could do it
with a single method call,
just by passing the collection
of owners.
We can do this using the
Collection Select method, as
you can see it over here.
But what if we need radio
buttons or check boxes?
Well in Rails 3, if you wanted
to do this, we needed a loop
and build each of the individual
HTML elements.
Now in Rails 4, we have the
collection_radio_button
methods that behave just like
the collection_select and
takes the same arguments.
Also, if you have the
many-to-many relationship, you
could use the collection_check_boxes
method to dynamically
build check boxes
for your models.
At some point, you might used
the date_select form helper
that generates a set of select
boxes that looks
something like this.
The HTML behind them, it's
kind of verbose.
And he uses three individual
arguments to
represent the date--
one for the year, one for the
month, and one for the day.
Rails 4 now, gives us the Date
Field form helper, which
generates a much better
looking HTML element.
Notice that uses the type
"date." And since it uses a
single HTML element to represent
the date, it also
returns a single parameter
to our application.
If you're using a browser that
supports this HTML5 type date,
then you're going to see
a calendar that looks
something like this.
Otherwise, if your browser
doesn't support this type,
then you're going to fall back
to a text field that looks
something like this.
So for now, it's best to stick
with a third-party library,
like jQuery-ui Date Picker,
for example.
Now let's take a look at this
Index action from our
controller that uses the Respond
To block to return an
HTML or JSON response based
on the request.
If a request comes in asking
for JSON, this is what a
response would look like.
But what if you need to
customize this JSON response?
Well, one way to do
it is to use the
Jbuilder template handler.
This way, we can use the
Jbuilder API to build our
custom JSON structure that gets
returned from the request.
In this case, here's what the
output would look like.
Rails 4 now gives us another
template handler that allows
us to write pure Ruby.
In this case, we're using Ruby
to build what our response
could look like.
And we're explicitly calling
to JSON on our collection.
In order to use the Ruby
template handler, all you have
to do is to add the .ruby
extension to your view file.
And here's how the output
would look like.