[SINGING]
He was wanted and captured
without bail, locked and
forgotten in a rusty jail,
zombies attacked, the
townsfolk fled, and those who
were left became the undead.
He's a zombie outlaw, he's
a zombie outlaw, and he's
hunting the law that left him
for dead, for dead, for dead.]
I'm Gregg Pollack, and
you're watching
Rails 4, Zombies Outlaws.
In this level, we're going to be
going over some new testing
features in Rails 4.
In a default Rails 3
application, here is what the
test folder structure
looks like.
It should look familiar.
Things have changed a little
bit in Rails 4.
Here's what the test
folder structure
looks like by default.
First thing you might notice
here is that no longer do we
have a functional directory.
Those were typically
where we'd put our
controller tests, right?
So why not call that directory
controllers, like we are now.
We also don't have the unit
folder anymore, so we're going
to take the helpers folder and
move that up to the top level.
Also you might notice that we
have a models directory.
Makes sense.
That's typically where we
put our model tests.
We still have the same fixtures
and integration test
folders, and we have
a new folder,
which is just for mailers.
To run our tests in Rails 3,
we would typically run rake
test:units to run our unit test
and rake test:functionals
to run our functional tests.
But now with the new directory
structure, this doesn't make a
lot of sense anymore.
So now we can run rake
test:models to run all the tests in
the models directory, rake
test:controllers, rake
test:helpers, and rake
test:mailers.
The old rake task will still
work with this new folder
structure running the
appropriate tests.
However, these new commands will
only work with the new
folder structure, obviously.
Let's say we create a new
migration for Rails app, like
so, but we don't run
that migration.
If we then go and run an
individual test, like you see
here in Rails 3, it's going to
go ahead and execute it.
No warnings, no nothing.
It's going to run the test.
The test might pass or it might
break because we haven't
run that migration.
Luckily in Rails 4, by default,
if we have migrations
we haven't run yet, and we try
to run an individual test,
it's going to give us a pending
migration error, as
you see here.
The reason for this default
behavior Rails 4 is that if
you look inside your
test_helper.rb, you'll see
this line at the top that says
"check pending." so that means
every time you try to run a
test, it's going to check for
any pending migrations.
Rails 3 by default shipped
with performance testing.
Bet you didn't know that.
But in Rails 4, they
took it out.
But those of you did use this
feature, all two of you, you
can reinstall it by adding it
to gem file, running bundle,
and then you can generate your
performance tests this way.
The default testing framework
in Rails 4 is now MiniTest.
It used to be Test Unit.
But don't worry, the syntax
hasn't changed.
This new library is a little bit
more lighter weight, and
it uses the same API.
There is one nice new feature
in MiniTest, though.
If we're in our test file here,
and want to skip a test
for some reason, we can
simply add the skip
keyword, as you see here.
Another feature of MiniTest is
that we can specify test
options where we're using the
verbose option, which is going
to show runtime and skip status
for each of our tests.
This can be really useful if you
need to track down a slow
test in your test suite.