Rails 4 now defaults to using
a different memcache client,
one called Dalli.
Dalli is a high-performance pure
Ruby client for accessing
memcached servers, and it
has some benefits.
It's faster than the previous
memcache client.
It provides proper failover
with recovery
and adjustable timeouts.
It's easier to integrate
with monitoring
tools like New Relic.
It's threadsafe.
And it's backwards compatible
with the previous memcache
client API.
I'm really sorry that I read
from the screen like that.
You'd never want to do that
with presentations.
But now you know the benefits,
and it's up
there on the slide.
Let's continue.
To use the new memcache
client, you
don't have to do much.
Inside the configuration, well,
it defaults to using
Dalli, so you don't have
to change the default
cache_store.
However, you will need to add
it in your gem file like so.
If not, you'll see this
error message.
In case you're not familiar with
the Rails caching API, it
looks something like this.
And this is nothing new.
It allows us to read and write
key values from our cache and
call the fetch command
which checks to see
if there's a value.
And if there isn't, it will
properly set it based on what
we pass in the block.
By default in your
production.rb, it sets perform
caching to true.
So if you want to play around
with this in your development
environment, just make
sure you set
perform caching to true.
A new, exciting Rails 4 feature
is cache digest.
But again, in order to
understand what that means, we
need to make sure that we
understand fragment caching
and russian doll caching.
So if you don't know
this, don't worry.
We're going to go
into an example.
So here we have a project page
that has multiple documents
listed on it, and each
of our documents
has multiple comments.
Here's what the ERB
might look like.
At the top level, we render
out the project documents.
Then this looks for a
document partial.
The document partial renders
out some documents.
Inside there, you can
see we have a render
document.comments.
This, by default, is going to
look for a comment partial in
the comments directory.
And it's just going to render
out each of the comments.
If a lot of users access this
page, we might want to
implement some fragment
caching.
But what does that do?
Let's take a look at how
that might work.
On our first request, the client
is going to request the
page from our Rails app.
It's going to do that expensive
template rendering,
and we want to store pieces of
the page or fragments into our
server side cache.
We'll then send back the
response to the browser.
Now the second time someone
accesses that page, we no
longer have to do that expensive
template rendering.
We can simply access the
fragments from the cache and
return that to our browser,
which is going to take a lot
less time than rendering out
all those templates.
To start implementing fragment
caching, we're going to go
into our comment partial and
wrap our list item in a cache
comment do block.
Here is our comment class.
It's simply an active
record object.
And the first time this partial,
gets rendered it's
going to check for
the cache key.
Remember the cache
key from earlier?
It's basically the model name
and the ID and updated at.
Then, if it doesn't find the
cache key in our server side
storage, it's going to render
out the template and store the
resulting HTML inside
of our cache.
Then the next time this partial
gets accessed, it's
going to construct that cache
key, check to see if that
cache key exists in our
server side cache.
It's going to find it.
And it's simply going to return
that HTML, and it
doesn't have to render what's
in between our block.
Let's go through the sequence
of events one more time.
So the first request--
let's say it goes
to comment 2--
it sets the cache, because
that doesn't exist in the
cache storage.
The second request reads
from the cache.
Now if comment 2 gets updated
somehow, it's going to set the
updated at field, as Rails
does by default.
Then the third request that
comes along is going to look
up the cache key.
It's not going to find that
it matches, so it will
regenerate the cache.
This works great, but what if
we make a change to the
comment template?
Here you can see we've
added comment.author.
Well when that third request
comes in, it's going to check
the cache key.
The cache key hasn't changed
because the comment in the
database hasn't changed.
It still has the same ID and
the same updated at field.
So it's going to show
the old template.
So we need a way to
deal with this.
One way to solve this problem is
to add a version number to
how the cache key is created,
as you see here.
Now, if we change the comment
template, we simply need to
increment that version.
And then when we deploy and
it goes to render out that
template, well, the cache key is
going to be different, and
it's going to render it again.
Fortunately for us in Rails 4,
we no longer need to version
our templates.
With Rails 4 when we update
our comment template, it's
going to know that
automatically, and it's going
to change the cache key so that
we can refresh the cache.
Seems like magic, doesn't it?
So how does this work?
Well, it turns out that with
Rails 4, there's another
argument added to the end
of the cache key.
When it goes to create a cache
key for this comment, not only
does it have model name, ID,
and updated at, but it also
takes a look at the template
itself that we're going to
render, does an MD5 of it,
and adds that to the end
of this cache key.
This way, if that template
changes, well, it's going to
generate a different
cache key.
So now let's go back to our
original example where we have
a document, and a document
has many comments.
This time, we're going
to have caching at
two different levels.
We'll have caching at the
document level, and we'll have
caching at the comment level.
So what happens when this
page gets rendered?
The first time it
goes through, it
fetches document 1.
Then inside of document 1, it
goes to render the comments.
It's going to render
comment number 1.
It then is going to set the
cache for comment number 1.
Then it's going to go ahead and
render out comment number
2 and set the cache for
comment number 2.
And then it's going to
go back up to finish
rendering out the document.
Once that's done rendering, it's
going to set the cache
for the HTML inside that
entire cache block.
Then, if a second request comes
along to get the first
document, well it's simply going
to read it straight from
the document 1 cache.
It's not going to bother hitting
the comment caches
because those are inside
of the document cache.
So what happens when comment
number 2 gets
updated in the database?
Well the next time a request
comes in, this time for
document 1, well document hasn't
changed, so it's simply
going to read that straight out
of the cache, which isn't
good, because it's showing
the old comment number 2.
So how do we get around this?
One way we can get
around this is by
updating the comment model.
You see up above where it says,
belongs_to document?
We can simply add the
option touch: true.
This time, when comment 2 gets
updated, it's not only going
to set the updated at field for
comment number 2, but it's
going to also set document
1's updated at field.
So now when the third request
comes in for document 1, it's
going to create a new cache key,
rerender the content for
document 1.
Comment 1 hasn't changed,
so it's going to read
that from the cache.
Comment 2, however, has changed,
so it's going to
reset the cache there as well.
This works great, but what would
happen if we changed the
comment template here?
How would the document cache
key know that the comment
template has changed?
Well it turns out Rails
4 cache digest
takes this into account.
How does it do this?
Well, if we look under the
covers, we'll see that when it
creates an MD5 hash of a
template, it actually combines
any inner templates inside
of this cache block.
So here, when we create the
cache key for document, it's
combining both the document
template and the comment
template to come up
with the MD5 hash.
This way, if any of the
templates are changed, the key
for the document will be
different, and it will
regenerate the cache.
This works great, but there
are some caveats.
If you're using a utility method
or, say, a scope to
load in comments, it's
not going to work.
The cache digest won't work.
You need to explicitly set the
partial, like you see here, to
get cache digest to
work properly.
Optionally, you can use this
comment syntax which will tell
cache digest where to look
up the comment partial.