So you're probably wondering,
what is Rails For Zombies?
Well, the short answer is that
it's an interactive tutorial
to teach the basics of web
application development in the
browser using Ruby on Rails.
But here's the long answer.
In the world of technical
learning, you've got books and
you've got screen casts, neither
of which has any
interactivity.
But come on, this is the
Nintendo generation.
Give me a damn joystick.
Plus, then there's the
configuration issues.
No matter how easy it is to set
up your computer to code
rails, you'll likely figure out
some way to screw it up
and it may not even
be your fault.
When you're diving into
something new, it needs to be
fun and not give you the feeling
that you've been
thrown into the deep end.
By the time you get
to the water, you
should be booking it.
Ruby on Rails is supposed
to be all ponies
and rainbows, right?
So you should at least have
rainbow colored floaties or be
armed with maybe some pistols
or maybe even a shotgun.
Oh yeah, a shotgun.
But speaking of shotguns, you
have to be asking what does
this have to do with zombies?
Well, that's where our example
application comes in.
You see, Twitter is always a
good example for beginners.
However, that's been overdone,
so we need to
find something new.
Recently I've learned
about zombie walks.
It's where people in big cities
dress up like zombies,
meet in a single location, and
wander the streets as the
living dead.
It actually happens all over
the country, and in Seattle
they had over 4,000 zombies
walking through downtown.
But again, what does this have
to do with Rails for Zombies?
Well, if you do that zombie
walk and you find some
delicious brains, you're going
to need a way to tell your
fellow zombies about it.
Thus, the application
we'll be building
is Twitter for Zombies.
Makes perfect sense, right?
So how does this zombie
thing work?
Well first, if you're not
familiar with the Ruby
language, head over to
tryruby.org and follow through
the Ruby tutorial there.
Then head back over to
Railsforzombies.org and click
the Start Course Now button
on the homepage.
You'll be taken to the first
video lesson for the course.
You can skip to a chapter
at the top if you
want to skip ahead.
And when you're done, just click
on the big green button
to start the challenges where
you'll have to do some coding
to get to level two.
In the challenge interface,
you'll see your total points,
the points you can earn from
this challenge, and the
challenge instructions.
To solve the challenge, you'll
need to write some code using
our in-browser code
editor here.
If you don't get it
right, you'll
see some error messages.
And if you're stuck, you can
take a look at some hints to
help keep pushing you forward.
Once you type in the correct
answer, you'll get a
congratulations screen where
you can continue on to the
next challenge or try
some extra credit.
The extra credit isn't verified,
it's just an
opportunity to practice
your rails coding.
Once you're ready to move on, on
the left side of the screen
you can jump around to
the other challenges.
Where you watch the video
lesson, learn the interface
shortcuts, or download
the video lesson
slides for later reference.
Once you finish Rails for
Zombies, you'll receive a
badge for your public profile,
unlock the final video.
And finally, you'll receive $5
in Code School cash that you
can use to enroll in Code School
and get access to Rails
for Zombies 2, Rails Testing for
Zombies, and Testing with
Rspec, along with all our other
courses and Code TV
screen casts.
Rails for Zombies is graciously
sponsored by New Relic.
Providing rails developers the
tools they need to monitor
their application performance.
Enough talk, it's time to learn
some Rails for Zombies.