I'm Gregg Pollack, and you're
watching Rails for Zombies,
Episode Three.
[MUSIC  PLAYING]
In this episode, we're going to
be learning about the view,
which isn't always so pretty,
especially when
you're eating brains.
Now when a web request comes to
our Rails stack, it's going
to be going through four
different components.
We've already talked about the
component on the bottom, which
are the models.
But now, we're going to be
talking about the view, which
is right about there.
Let's take a look at the
directory structure of our
Twitter for Zombies
application--
might look a little
bit like this.
You can see we have
an app directory.
Inside that we have views.
Inside that we have the
zombie directory
and a tweets directory.
Inside the tweets directory, we
have an index.html.erb, and
a show.html.erb, one which shows
all the tweets and one
which shows a particular
tweet.
The file extension here
is .html.erb.
erb, I know what you're
thinking, it stands for Edible
Rotting Bodies.
No, no, not quite.
It actually stands for Embedded
Ruby, basically, Ruby
inside HTML.
Now let's take a look at
the show tweet action.
Here's what it might look
like in the browser.
So we're showing the status of
a particular tweet, and we're
showing which zombie
created the tweet.
Now Rails introduces two new
HTML tags, which we are going
to be using inside
of our erb files.
First, we have the
tag.
So anything in between this
tag is going to get
evaluated as Ruby.
Then we have the
version of this tag,
which is going to evaluate
the Ruby.
And whatever that returns,
it's going to print
out onto the page.
Now if we open up the
show.html.erb, here's
what we might see.
You'll notice that we've
got some basic HTML
elements for a header.
We then have a
tweet = Tweet.find(1)
that should look familiar.
We're pulling in that tweet,
evaluating that Rails code.
We then have a header, which
is the tweet status.
And we then say, posted
by tweet.zombie.name.
Oh, look out, here comes the
Zombie, and he's telling us
that our code sucks.
It does suck a little bit.
It sucks in two different
ways.
One of which is, obviously, if
you look at this code over
here, you'll notice that we have
some header code and some
footer code.
And, obviously, if we continue
down this path, we would have
to copy and paste that
across all the pages,
which is not good.
So the first thing that we're
going to do is we're going to
take that header and the footer,
and we're going to put
that into a file called
application.html.erb, which is
in our layouts directory.
So we've got sort of core show
content down here, and we've
got the layout up here.
There's one thing we
have to add to this
layout, which is a yield.
So this is saying to Rails, at
this point, when you see this
yield, put the show view
code right in there.
So if we go back to our
directory layout, you'll see
that we're going to add a
layouts directory, and inside
there, our application.html.erb,
which is
our main layout for the site.
There's a couple other things
that you're going to see in
the default Rails layout.
You're going to see a style
sheet link to tag, a
JavaScript include tag,
and a csrf meta tag.
Now we're going to go through
each of these items so that
you understand what they
mean, starting with
stylesheet_link_tag.
Basically, what this is
saying is include all
of the stylesheets.
It's going to look inside the
public directory, inside the
stylesheets directory, and all
the stylesheets that's
going to include them, and
render out something that
looks a little bit like this.
Next up is the
javascript_include_tag.
So it's going to be including
all of the default JavaScript.
Where is it including it from?
Well, it's going to look in
the public javascripts
directory, and, by default, in
a Rails app, it's going to be
including all of these
JavaScript files, which you
may recognize as being the
prototype JavaScript framework.
Now don't worry, if you're a
jQuery or a MooTools fan, you
can very easily replace these
defaults with your JavaScript
library of choice.
Next up is the cross site
request forgery meta tag.
This will prevent zombie hacker
sites from submitting
comments spam into
your website.
You'll notice that, if you look
at the source of your
Rails page, that it's putting
these csrf param and csrf
token meta tags right
in at the top.
And then it's going to
automatically include these in
every form in your application
to make sure that you don't
get hacked.
Next, we need to talk
a little bit about
root path and images.
So when somebody goes to your
Rails app and puts slash
something and types something
besides the root, the first
thing it's going to do is
check inside your public
directory to see if it exists.
If it doesn't, then it's going
to go and try to execute
inside Rails.
A good example of this
is your images.
If that file exists, it's
going to render it.
Now we're going to learn
how to create links
in our Rails views.
So here's part of our view where
we're printing out the
zombie name, but what if we
wanted to link to the Zombie
Show page to get more
information about that
particular zombie.
In that case, we have our Ruby
percent equals tag, and we're
going to say link_to
tweet.zombie.name.
And then the path is going to
be zombie_path(tweet.zombie)
So we have our link text and
then we have our link path.
This is going to render out
some pretty common HTML.
And there's another way we can
write this which is a little
bit simpler.
We can simply put the link text,
and then just put the
actual object to show,
which, in this
case, is just a zombie.
Rails can automatically look at
that model and figure out
what the right path is to view
that particular zombie.
This helper method link_to has
a lot of different options.
And you might be asking, how
do you figure out what all
those different options are?
Well. there's a couple
different ways you
can figure that out.
The first one is, you can
look in the source.
So you could type, get clone
and clone the Rails source.
And then go into your Rails
directory and open whatever
text editor you use, and then
search for def link_to to
figure out where that method
definition is and
read through it.
The second option you
have is to look at
api.rubyonrails.org.
These are the API
docs for Rails.
And, obviously, you could use
your browser to search through
all of those.
The third way is by going
to apidock.com/rails.
These are searchable,
online-only
documentation with comments.
The fourth way is to look at the
Rails Searchable API Doc
at railsapi.com This you can
also download, or you can just
use it online.
It has a really nice Ajax
search feature.
And it's really easy to get
through and read the code.
So here you can see, we've
looked for link_to.
And one of the options under
link_to is to have a confirm
box when somebody
clicks the link.
So if we add confirm, are you
sure, to our link, when
somebody clicks on it, it's
going to pop up a JavaScript
alert that says, are you sure?
So we just got finished going
through the show action to
show a particular tweet, but
what might the index action
look like where we list
out all the tweets?
Well, it might look a little bit
like this in our browser,
where we're listing the
tweets just like that.
And here's what the code
might look like.
So, the header, we're
listing tweets.
We're starting a table.
We then say Tweet.all.each
to iterate
through each of the tweets.
And there's our basic
code block.
Inside there, we're going to
print out the tweet status,
and the tweet zombie name
for each of the tweets.
Just to review what each piece
of this code returns, when we
call capital tweet, we get
returned a class, which we
then call all on.
.all returns an
array of tweets.
Now as we iterate through each
of them, we store each of
those tweets inside the
lowercase tweet.
What if we wanted to make
these both links?
We would link to the show tweet
and link to the show
zombie actions.
Well, we would add link_to, then
we'd specify the tweet.
And then we would add
a link_to, and
then specify the zombie.
Let's go and build out a little
bit of functionality.
Right now, if we don't have any
tweets, it has nothing.
What we want to do is print
out no tweets found.
So here's our code down here.
First thing we're going to do
is we're going to move out
tweet.all and store that
in a tweets variable.
We're going to move that tweets
to be what we iterate
through when we call dot each.
And then, at the bottom, we're
going to say, if tweets size
equals zero, then print
out no tweets found.
We can simplify this code a
little bit by calling
.empty?
And if that's true, then it'll
print out no tweets found.
As you can see, it does here.
Now what if we wanted to add
edit and delete links to the
list of tweets, so we could
very quickly edit them and
delete them?
What would the code
look like then?
Well, here we're going to
add a link_to "Edit"
And we're going to say,
edit_tweet_path(tweet)
And to add a delete link, we
say link_to delete, specify
the tweet, and then give
it a method of delete.
Now I'm going to give you a
quick summary of all the
different paths you might use in
your link_to in Rails, and
maybe also in the lab that
you're about to do.
So to list all the tweets,
you're going to
use the tweets_path.
That's going to generate
a tweets URL.
To link to a new tweet form,
you'd use the new_tweet_path
to generate this URL.
For the remainder of the paths,
you're going to need to
reference a specific tweet.
So here we're getting a
tweet with ID of 1.
To show it, we're simply going
to pass in the tweet object,
which will generate this URL.
To edit it, we're going to put
in edit_tweet_path (tweet).
And we're going to
get this URL.
And to delete the tweet, we're
going to simply specify it,
specify the method as delete.
And that's going to generate
the path tweets/1.
That brings us to Zombie Lab
Three, where you can get your
hands dirty trying out
some of this code.