I'm Gregg Pollack, and you're
watching Rails for Zombies,
Episode Two.
[SINGING]
Put down your brains
and your entrails.
It's time to stop and learn some
Rails because we've got
something new to grab.
It's Rails for Zombies
by Envy Labs.
In episode two, we're
going to be looking
at, of course, models.
So in the previous chapter, we
had this bit of code,
Tweet.find(3)
And somehow that mapped down
here to this database table.
But there's obviously something
missing in between
these two pieces of code that
map one to the other.
And that's where
models come in.
In this case, we have a Tweet
model, which is just a plain
old Ruby class.
So what's happening here, when
we call that capital Tweet,
that's going to be looking
at this Tweet class.
This inherits from
ActiveRecord::Base.
Basically, that maps the
class to the table.
So it's going to go look in the
database by default for a
plural tweets table,
just like that.
Let's take a closer look at
what's going on when we
execute that find code.
So I'm going to call
Tweet.find(3)
Tweet in this case is a class.
We're calling a method, find
three on the class, which goes
to the database, finds
the row that has the
Tweet with ID of three.
It then populates an instance of
this Tweet, puts that data
into an object, and then stores
that in the t variable.
Now, you may have noticed with
lab one that it was possible
to create a zombie with
no data in it.
And in this case here, we can
create a Tweet with no data in
it, which isn't so good.
We obviously need some way
to validate our model.
We can do that in Rails by
adding a bit of code.
Here, in our Tweet class, we can
add validates presence of
status to ensure that a status
is put into the model before
it gets saved.
If we were to test out this new
class, if we did t = Tweet.new,
we would get back
a new Tweet object that
hasn't been saved yet.
We'll call t.save on it.
It's going to return false
because it was unable to save
it to the database because that
validation did not pass.
If we call t.errors, we
can get back a hash of the
errors that came back.
And if we call t.errors[:status]
that particular
key, we can get back just
that particular error.
Rails by default comes with a
ton of validations that you
can use, from numericality,
to validating uniqueness,
confirmation, acceptance,
length of, format,
et cetera, et cetera.
With Rails 3, we now have
a new syntax for doing
validations.
Instead of doing them one line
at a time, we can say
validates :status,
:presence => true.
So here you have the attribute
and the validation.
We can also say validates :status,
:length =>
But of course, to simplify all
this, we can write both of
these on a single line.
Here are the other validations
you saw previously, but
showing how you might use them
with this new syntax.
Now it's time to talk a little
bit about relationships
because they always travel in
packs and because, you know,
you need to have multiple tables
and their relationships
with each other.
So as you saw with our previous
example, you might
have noticed that the Zombie Ash
had two different tweets,
and we were listing
his name twice.
That's obviously not
very efficient.
Well, what we're going to do
here is break that out into a
separate zombies table.
But now we obviously need a
way to map which zombies
tweeted what.
The Rails way of making the
association is to add a zombie
underscore ID column to
the tweets table.
We then specify the ID of the
zombie that made the tweet,
and we can then map the
tweet to the zombie.
So now if we add a tweet, one
that maybe says your eyelids
taste like bacon, we can specify
which zombie that
belongs to.
So looking at this database
table, we might say a tweet
belongs to a zombie.
Inside of our model, to map that
correctly, we simply add
belongs_to :zombie.
It's important to notice
here that we're
using zombie singular.
We say belongs_to :zombie because
one tweet belongs to
one zombie.
So now we've mapped the
relationship in one direction.
How do we map it in the other
direction and basically say a
zombie has many tweets?
Well, if you take a look at the
model here, to map that,
we simply write
has_many :tweets.
So now that we have the mapping
correct for each of
these models, let's
start playing
with them on the console.
So we're going to fetch a
zombie, then to create a tweet
for that zombie, we're going to
call Tweet.create, send
in a status, and specify
the zombie.
You'll notice in this second
line the tweet gets saved and
gets stored in the t variable.
We can then call t.zombie to
get back the zombie object
for that tweet, and call
t.zombie.name to print out
the zombie that made that tweet,
in this case, Bob.
To explore the other side of
the relationship, we can go
and get a specific zombie.
We can count the number of
tweets on that zombie, and if
we just call ash.tweets, we
get back an array with all
of the tweets that that
zombie has done.
Now it's time to get back into
the code with Zombie Lab
Number 2.