I'm Gregg Pollack, and you're
watching Rails For Zombies,
Episode Four.
(SINGING) Put down your brains
and your entrails.
It's time to stop and learn
some Rails. 'Cause we got
something new to grab, Rails
For Zombies by Envy Labs.
In this episode we're going to
be looking at controllers.
So here's our application
stack, as we saw before.
Down at the bottom we
have the models.
Over here we have the views,
and now we're going to be
looking at the controllers.
So remember in the previous
episode this guy came out and
said hey, this code sucks
a little bit.
And we fixed the one
reason why it
sucked, we used the layout.
But the second reason it sucks
is because we're not
effectively using a
controller yet.
So when a request comes into
Rails, it's first going to hit
a controller before it then
renders out the view.
The source for this controller
is located in the app
controllers directory, and its
name in this case is going to
be tweets_controller.rb.
It's no coincidence now that our
path has tweets in it, our
controller name has tweets in
it, and our view directory
name has tweets in it.
This is just another one of
Rails' intelligent defaults.
Inside that tweets controller
we've got a class TweetsController
which inherits from
ApplicationController.
Also inside this file we'd
probably find a show method.
Also no coincidence that
the show method maps
up to the show view.
Now, how can we fix this code
and make it better?
Well, we're going to take the
code that basically finds a
tweet, and we're going to move
it up into the controller.
So another Rails best practice
is to keep all of your model
calls in your controller.
This is just so that your views
don't end up with a lot
of Ruby code inside of them.
So the first thing that happens
when a request comes
in is it goes into the tweets
controller, executes all of
the code in the show action,
and then it goes to
render the show view.
Uh-oh, here's the
zombie again.
And he's saying look out, what
about variable scope?
Because you might wonder, this
tweet variable, it's inside
that show method.
How is it that the view
get access to that?
Wel, it's a good question.
This is where instance
variables come in.
So in Rails, what we do is we
put this little @ symbol next
to the tweet variable, and that
signifies to Rails that
this is a variable that we want
to have access to from
inside of our views.
So there you can see we have
the @ symbols next to every
time we use that
tweet variable.
Let's venture out of the common
defaults in rails for
just a moment.
What if we wanted to render
out a view called status
instead of show?
Well, then we would have to add
a little bit of code to
let Rails know that the
action we want to
render is called status.
This is just one small example
how if you go outside of the
Rails defaults, there's always
ways to override it.
This code is fine if we want to
always show the tweet with
ID equals one, But obviously
people are going to want to
show other tweets, and they're
going to specify the ID in the
URL just like this.
So how do we change the code
to adapt for that?
Well, it turns out that using
this convention it's going to
store that number in a hash
called params with the key in
the ID field.
So when our request comes in,
basically it's going to have
that params hash, and inside
that hash it's going to have
an ID of one.
So one's going to
be the value.
So inside of our show action we
do params, ID, and then it
will look up the proper tweet.
Whenever we send in query
parameters in our URL or using
a post, Rails is going to
store that inside a hash
called params.
So here we have the params hash
again, and if we needed
to access the status value, we
could simply create a new
tweet and set the status
to params[:status]
Often in Rails, inside this
parameter hash you see
multiple hashes.
So here you can see we have a
hash that has a tweet, and
inside that tweet hash
we've got status.
So here if we wanted to create
a tweet using that value, we
would do params[:tweet][:status].
You'll notice, though, that
when we call this create
method, that we already
have a hash in there.
So we can simplify this simply
by saying params tweet.
Now, what if we wanted to show
our tweet in XML or JSON?
Let's say for web services
to consume.
Here's the XML we might expect
from a tweet, and here's the
JSON that we might expect
from a tweet.
Now there's some URLS we're
going to use for this.
We can go to .xml to get the
XML, .json to get the JSON.
These are just Rails defaults.
Inside the show action
we've got to add a
little bit of code.
We're going to add a
respond_to block.
And inside there we're
going to say this
action responds to HTML.
It also responds to XML,
and then renders the
XML from the tweet.
And it also responds to JSON by
doing rendered JSON tweet.
That's all we have to do, and
now Rails is going to render
out the tweet in XML or JSON.
There's going to be a set of
common actions you're going to
see in your Rails controllers
a lot if you're developing
Rails apps.
Let's go through them
one at a time.
You have your index action,
which is going to list all of
the tweets.
Your show action to show
a single tweet.
You have a new action to show a
new tweet form, edit to show
an edit tweet form, create to
create a new tweet, update to
update a tweet, and destroy
to delete a tweet.
Now I'm going to be walking you
through how to create a
little authorization
in our application.
So if I click that edit button
on the tweets page, it's going
to call the edit action.
Inside of the edit action, I'm
obviously going to need to
retrieve the tweet that
we want to edit.
It's then going to render the
edit view by default.
And there is the edit
form that we
would see on our screen.
Now the next time I click the
Edit button, what I want it to
say if I don't have
authorization is sorry, you
can't edit someone
else's tweet.
So how might we get to
the point where we
can make that happen?
Well, here's the edit action,
and I'm going to introduce
some new concepts.
First of all, the session.
So session basically works
like a per user hash.
So per request, it sort
of saves that for
that particular person.
Often saves it in a cookie.
So here we're checking to see
if the person's zombie ID
inside their session is not
equal to the zombie ID of this
particular tweet.
So if this tweet doesn't belong
to us, then we're going
to create a flash.
A flash is what we use to send
messages to the user, so we
flash the notice onto the screen
that says sorry, you
can't edit this tweet.
After we set the message, we
want to redirect the user back
to the tweets path.
So we say redirect_to do a 501
redirect and render out a
separate action.
Rails 3 has a new syntax so that
you can do the redirect_to
and the notice in
the same line.
Now before we check this out
the browser to see if it
works, we're going to jump
back into the layout, and
we're going to add
an if statement.
So if flash notice exists, then
print out the notice onto
the layout.
Now if we go back to the
list tweets page, we
hit the Edit button.
If we're not authorized,
it's going to give
us the proper notice.
Now if you go back into the
tweets controller, you might
notice that edit is not the
only action that needs
authorization.
The edit, update, and destroy
all need the same
authorization.
Well, how do we not repeat
ourselves in our controller?
Well, if you looked inside each
of these actions, you
would see that each of
them pulls the tweet.
They call tweet find and they
pull the current tweet.
Well, in Rails, how
do we dry that up?
Well, we're going to take that
code, move it up, and create
its own method.
Wrap it in its own method
called get_tweet.
We then say before
filter get_tweet.
That tells the controller, call
this method before every
action, and we can specify.
Call it only with edit, update,
and destroy methods.
Now let's go back and grab
the authorization code.
So we've got our session
code right here.
We're going to wrap that in a method
called check_auth, and now just
like before, we can specify
before filter check_auth only
on edit, update, and destroy.
So now we have authorization
across all three actions,
which leads us into Zombie Lab
4, where the bodies start
piling up and the zombies tweet
even more frequently.