I'm Gregg Pollack, and you're
watching Rails for
Zombies, Episode 5.
Put down your brains
and your entrails.
It's time to stop and learn
some rails, 'cause we got
something new to grab.
Rails for Zombies
by Envy Labs.
In this episode, we're going to
be talking about routing.
So let's take one more look
at our component stack.
So when a request comes in,
we've got our controllers, our
models, views, and now, we've
got our one last component,
which is routing.
Let's take a look back at
all of our links here.
In order to properly find all of
these paths for our link_to
and all of these actions, we
need to define our routes.
We do that in a file located
in our config
directory called routes.rb.
If we looked in there, we'd
find something like this.
We'd find that we have a
ZombieTwitter::Application.routes
.draw command.
It's sort of namespaced to our
application, and inside there,
we have resources tweets.
This basically creates what we
call a RESTful resource.
It's this resource command
which gives us all of our
paths that we've seen
previously.
Basically, when we have tweets
paths, it links to the tweets
URL, which goes to
the index action.
When we use tweet in our
link_to, it goes to this URL,
which goes to the show action.
When we do new_tweet_path, this
goes to that URL, which
goes to the new action, and the
edit_tweet_path goes to
this URL, which goes to, of
course, the edit action.
And there's a bunch more
routes that this generates,
which we're not going to
go into right now.
So how do we do some
custom routes?
For example, if we wanted
new_tweet to go and render the
same thing as tweets/new.
Well, tweets/new goes into our
tweets controller and calls
the new action.
So in this case, our controller
name is Tweets,
and our action name is new.
To create that custom route,
we write match new_tweet =>
Tweets#new.
The tweet new is our path,
obviously, Tweets is our
controller, and new, of
course, is our action.
So if we go to new_tweet in our
browser, that's going to
bring up the same view that
we would see if we went to
tweets/new.
Next up, how do we make it so
that if we go to /all, it goes
to the same action as tweets.
Well, if we look in our
controller, tweets calls the
index action.
So our controller
name is Tweets.
Our action name is index.
To make this happen, we do
match 'all' => Tweets#index.
But what if we want
to go to this all
route inside of a link?
What do we do? tweets_path
isn't going to work.
Well, what we need to do here,
is specify as all_tweets.
What this will allow us to do
is specify all_tweets_path
inside of our link, and it's
going to link to the
appropriate place.
So as you can see, when we go to
/all, it's going to show us
a listing of all the
different tweets.
Well, what if we want to change
that behavior and
instead of rendering out
the list, redirect
to the tweets path.
How do we do that?
So again, we want /all to
redirect to the tweets path.
So we say match all
match 'all' => redirect('/tweets')
We can also redirect outside
of our website.
We can do match google
redirect to Google.
Simple enough.
What about our root route?
So when people just go to / then
their application, what
if we want that to render
out tweets?
We simply specify here
root :to => "Tweets#index"
So here we have the controller
and the action.
And if we want to put that in a
link, we simply do root_path
inside of our link.
Now, let's get into some
route parameters.
So what if we want to be able to
send in a zip code to find
all the zombie tweets in
a particular zip code.
How might we do that?
Well, first of all, what would
it look like in our
controller?
So maybe in our index
action, we check for
the zip code parameter.
If it exists, we query for all
the tweets where the zip code
equals that.
Otherwise, we list all the
tweets and then, of course,
just render out the page.
The route that would make it
happen would look like this.
'local_tweets/:zipcode' =>
'Tweets#index'
So by putting that :zipcode
in there that says
whatever gets sent in here for
the URL, put that into the zip
code parameter.
Also if we specify a name, so we
say as local_tweets, we can
then use link_to and do a
local_tweets_path and then
send in the zip code.
Now, if you use Twitter a lot,
you might notice this format
where basically they have
twitter.com/username.
How might we implement that
using our new route knowledge?
So basically, again, we want to
allow the user name to show
all the tweets for
that zombie.
So if we go to /greggpollack,
it will
show all of my tweets.
To create the route, we do
match ':name' => 'Tweet#index',
:as => 'zombie_tweets'
which would then allow us to do
zombie_tweets_path('greggpollack')
inside of our link_to.
Then inside of our controller,
might look
something like this is, where if
the parameter name exists,
then query for that zombie
and then get all of
that zombie's tweets.
So now, if we want to view a
particular zombie's tweets,
for example, Ash's tweets, we
simply go to /Ash, and we're
shown all of Ash's tweets.
Well, that pretty much wraps
up this fifth episode.
Now, it's time for Zombie Lab
5, where the zombies get
bloodier and the brains
get tastier.