Hello, I'm Gregg Pollack,
and you're
watching Rails for Zombies.
(SINGING) Put down your brains
and your entrails.
It's time to stop and learn
some Rails because we got
something new to grab.
It's Rails for Zombies
by Envy Labs.
In order for this video to make
sense, you're going to
need to know a little bit
about the Ruby language.
If you don't know anything
yet, pause this video, go
tryruby.org, go through that
tutorial, and then come back
and start the video.
So in this first episode,
we're going to
be deep in the CRUD.
We're going to be talking
about CRUD.
Now, bear with me if you're
an expert in some of these
languages and some of
these concepts.
We'll get to the advanced stuff
soon enough, but we need
to make sure everyone's
on the same page.
So we're going to be creating
Twitter for zombies.
That's your application.
If you don't know why, go
back to the front page
and watch the intro.
But let's jump into
it for now.
So here we have our first
database table.
It kind of looks like
a spreadsheet.
We're calling it tweets.
It has four rows, and it
has three columns.
Now, we might put a label on
each of these columns.
The first one is the ID.
The second one is status.
And the third one represents
the zombie,
like Ash, Bob, Jim.
These are our zombies.
Now, our first zombie challenge
is going to be to
retrieve a hash of the tweet
with ID of 3.
Now, I'm not going to show
you the solution.
What I'm going to show you first
is the result, what we
want to get back in
the database.
In this case, we want
to get back a hash,
which looks like this.
Now, you should be familiar
with what a hash is, but
here's a small recap.
So if we do puts b[:status], we're
going to get back "I just
ate some delicious brains."
If we do puts b[:zombie], we're
going to get back "Jim."
And if we do this at the bottom,
we're going to get
back "Jim said I ate some
delicious brains."
Because you know, zombies
love eating the brains.
Now let's get back
to our database
table and our challenge.
So there's our challenge
again.
Now, I'm going to show you the
actual solution, the code that
we want to write.
We want to write
t = Tweet.find(3)
So what that's going to do is
get us back that hash, and we
can then do puts t[:id] gets
us 3, puts t[:status] gets "I
just ate some delicious brains,"
and puts t[:zombie] gets
us back "Jim."
Now, there's another way we
can write this in Rails.
Instead of puts t[:id], we
can do puts t.id.
Puts t[:status], we can have puts
t.status, and so on
and so forth.
So we can use these to find our
solution instead of using
the hash keys.
Here's what our answer
might look like with
those pieces of code.
There's one Rails convention
here that
I want you to notice.
Notice we have capital T in
Tweet in the code solution.
And what's happening on the
back end here is that it's
going to lower case that,
pluralize it, and then it's
looking for a table called
tweets in our database.
It's time to jump
in to the CRUD.
And by CRUD, I mean Create,
Read, Update, and Delete.
Now, let's figure out how we
can do each of these inside
our Rails application.
First, in the create,
we do Tweet.new
We can then set the status
and call t.save
to save the item.
For reading, we then do
Tweet.find(3), just like you
saw a moment ago.
For updating, we're going
to find the tweet.
Then we can set of values
on it and save it.
And then for delete, we can find
the tweet and call t.destroy
to delete it
out of a database.
Now we're going to go through
each of these in a little more
detail, and I'm going to show
you some alternate syntaxes.
But first, with create, notice
that we're not setting the ID
on the object here.
That's because Rails is going
to take care of that for us
and properly increment
the ID and
store that in the database.
Another way we can create a new
tweet is simply by sending
in a hash of the items
that we want to set.
We can then save that.
We could also write this all on
one line by calling
Tweet.create.
So that's going to set
these attributes
and save the object.
Next up, for reading, there's
lots of ways we can read data
out of the database.
We can find a particular
item with an ID number.
We can find a bunch of items and
it will return an array.
We can find the first one.
We can find the last one.
We can find all of them.
We can count them.
And the interesting thing about
count here is that it's
actually doing this
the correct way.
It's not going to the database,
pulling everything
out, and then counting it.
It's actually going to be doing
a count query on the
database and returning
that number.
We could also get all the
zombies and order them by the
zombie name.
We can limit the number to 10.
We can say get us all the
zombies where the zombie name
equals Ash.
Or we could put all these
different methods together to
do something we'd like to
call method chaining.
Next up, we have update.
So you remember with update,
we find the tweet, we set
something, and then
we save it.
Alternatively, we can set the
attributes value and send in a
hash and then save it.
We could also call
t.update_attributes, which not
only will set the items,
but will also save it.
Next up is destroy, because
zombies like destroying
things, especially brains.
So as you saw before, we can
find an item and destroy it.
We can also write this
on a single line.
And lastly, if you want to
destroy all the tweets, we can
just call Tweet.destroy_all
So we've already reached
Zombie Lab 1.
This is where you get to start
coding and implement some of
the stuff we've already
learned.
So go and have some fun with
your new zombie friends.