Congratulations.
You've slain the zombies,
completed the labs, almost
saved the princess, but she
was in another castle, and
acquired some Rails knowledge.
All right, so you've found
yourself on the wrap-up page.
On this page you're going to be
able to review the course
if you want to give
us some feedback.
All the links that I'm about to
be talking about are going
to be found right here
on the sidebar.
And at the very bottom you're
going to see some badges that
you've earned, although
they're going to look
different than the ones here
because you've got newer,
cooler ones.
And then of course your prizes,
which you probably
have $5.00 in Code
School cash.
So what is it good for?
Well, you might want to go and
play through Rails For Zombies
2, the sequel to this course,
which has even more zombie and
Rails goodness.
Also, you can take that $5.00
and put it towards your first
month of code school
enrollment.
What that's going to give you
is access to all of our
courses for free.
We've got lots of content, from
Git to Backbone, to Node,
to CoffeeScript, to JQuery Air,
well, JQuery, to HTML5
CSS3, there's a CSS--
I can't speak.
There's a CSS cross country
course, which will give you
some CSS best practices.
And then of course
the Rails stuff.
Besides Rails For Zombies 2, we
also have Rails Testing For
Zombies, and Testing With Rspec,
Rspec being one of the
more popular Ruby testing
frameworks.
So from here, also if you want
to grab a Code School shirt or
Rails For Zombies shirt, we
also just recently created
some Rails For Zombies posters
while supplies last.
Like, movie posters.
Also, I want to make sure
you know about Ruby 5.
Here at Envy Labs we do this
twice weekly podcast called
Ruby 5 where we talk about the
latest news in the Ruby and
Rails community.
We have a really active
community, lots of libraries
being created, lots of news.
And this is just a short five,
six, seven minute audio
podcast to keep you up to
date on a weekly basis.
Good to listen to while you're
on the subway, traveling in
the car, or doing
your laundry.
Yeah.
Oh, if you're not an audio
person as well, you can also
just subscriber to the RSS feed
by hitting the RSS link,
and you get sort of audio
descriptions, audio
descriptions, that doesn't
make any sense.
Text descriptions of everything
that we talk about
on the podcast.
Also, Top Ruby Jobs.
If you're looking for a Top Ruby
gig or Top Ruby talent,
over on toprubyjobs.com, you can
post a job or look for a
job, and that gets covered
on the podcast.
Also, if you're a teacher and
you want to teach Rails For
Zombies to other people, there's
a blog post where I
actually allow you download
the keynote slides.
So you could basically teach it
at your own pace using the
keynote, and have your students
go on their laptops
or computers and actually do the
challenges, so just ignore
the videos.
Of course, gotta thank Envy
Labs, our web consultancy for
creating Rails For Zombies
and bringing it
out there for free.
Yeah, here's sort of
a team, who we are.
We're basically a web
application development
consultancy.
Gotta thank Eric Allam, he
did a lot of the work
on Rails For Zombies.
But if you have a big web app
project out there and you need
some help, or you need
a team to do it,
maybe drop us a line.
Also, you can follow Code School
at the Code School
Twitter account, and then
finally I have to thank, well,
I've got to thank you, first,
for going through the course
and spending your time learning,
but also New Relic.
New Relic sponsored this so that
we were able to give it a
new skin and sort the hints and
the points and all that
good stuff.
New Relic is what we use on all
of our projects to monitor
web applications and make sure
they're monitoring the
performance.
Make sure they're performing.
And this is what it looks
like for Code School.
Here's Code School's
dashboard.
We keep a close eye on this to
make sure that, well, it's
functioning and it's
responsive.
And we recently put together a
video talking more about how
we use New Relic in our software
development process,
which you're going to see now.
And I'll leave you with that.
Hi, I'm Nathaniel Bibler, and
at Code School, we actually
use New Relic in a lot
of different ways.
First, we use New Relic
extremely heavily at a new
course release.
The way the Code School course
architecture is set up, each
course actually runs as
its own application
on their own servers.
So New Relic actually shows
us exactly how much of our
servers we're using, and
indicates to us whether or not
we need to scale up new
resources, scale back to
adjust our actual usage
to cost accordingly.
Meaning when we put a big
marketing effort behind a new
course release, we actually get
a lot of people on that
site right away, and they
tail off of over the
next week or two.
So that actually lets us see how
many people are actually
using the site, what the load is
on the servers, and adjust
our cost accordingly so that
we're actually getting the
most for our money.
Secondly, we use New Relic
to actually monitor our
background jobs or asynchronous
jobs.
Specifically we actually have
our own billing system which
runs our own subscription
charges.
These are actually run as
background jobs, and we can
inspect those jobs on New Relic
to determine how long it
took those jobs to run, whether
or not there were
exceptions, and actually
identify specifically where we
might be having a problem,
because they actually split
apart those Ruby processes to
say, well, you spent 30% of
your time in the network,
10% of your
time in Ruby, or whatever.
Next we actually use a newer
feature of New Relic, which is
end user monitoring.
What that allows us to do is
actually see what the end user
perceives of codeschool.com.
What that means is we can
actually see on average how
long it took somebody in, let's
say the UK to load our
landing page.
And they'll actually split apart
for us to say, well, you
know, there was seven seconds
of network time.
There were three seconds of page
render time, et cetera.
That actually allows
us to do some
really interesting things.
For example, when we first
started using it on Code
School, we learned that on
average across the water.
It was taking more than 10
seconds to actually load our
landing page, largely due
to network usage.
And so what that actually
indicated to us was we needed
to use a globally
redundancy CDN.
So we switched over to using a
CDN, and again, through New
Relic and user monitoring, we're
actually able to see
that the load time went down
from about 12 to 13
seconds to just four.
Still not great, but
significantly better.
And finally, we actually used
New Relic's deployment
recording feature.
What that allows us to do is
look back in history and see
how we were performing at any
given time and relate that to
deployments.
So we can actually see, OK,
well, our site has gotten
slower on this particular
page.
Well, when did that happen?
Why did that happen?
We can actually go to New Relic
and look back over time
and say, oh, well on this
particular day, or after this
particular deployment, there was
a significant change for
requests to this page, so that's
a good indication of
where the bug might lie.
At Code School, the user
experience is really important
to us, and New Relic has
everything we need to monitor
performance, both on
the server side
and the client side.