If you've been a web developer
for a while, odds are you
remember the bad, old days of
web-development debugging.
If you get a JavaScript error in
your web page, well, maybe
the browser gives you a line
number, maybe it doesn't.
And maybe that line number
brings you to where the error
actually happened.
Same thing goes for style
sheet debugging.
You have a CSS property,
and why isn't it
showing up on the page?
Well, you go back to your file,
you update it, check the
browser, back to the file,
update it, check your browser.
Luckily, these days, we have
Chrome Developer Tools.
Developer Tools allows you to do
things like live edit your
HTML and CSS right there
in the page.
It comes with a powerful
JavaScript debugger and also a
bunch of tools to optimize
your website performance.
It makes programming for the
web, dare I say, easy.
I'm Greg Pollack.
And in this course, we're going
to be walking through
all the major features of
Chrome Developer Tools.
Now we're going to start with
some of the basics, which you
already may be familiar with.
So feel free to skip ahead to
the next couple chapters to
get into the more advanced
material.
Meanwhile, Level One, we're
going to be jumping into the
Elements panel.
Throughout the videos and the
challenges, we're going to be
working with the Scheduling app,
which we've been working
on that you can see here.
But we want to make some changes
to this application.
First thing we want to do
is open Developer Tools.
To do that, we look for the icon
on our browser with the
three lines on it.
Then find the Tools menu
item, then click on
the Developer Tools.
If you're not already familiar
with the keyboard shortcut to
call up Developer Tools and to
close Developer Tools from
within your browser, take
note of it here listed
next to the menu item.
It'll be much more convenient to
open it using that keyboard
chart next time.
By default, DevTools will appear
at the bottom part of
your Chrome window, and we can
close it at any time, either
by clicking that X icon in the
top left or simply by using
our keyboard shortcut.
So here is our Calendar
application.
We want to make some changes to
the HTML structure of it.
Now we could go back on to our
server and make the changes
there and then refresh our
browser, but maybe we just
want to play around and
live edit the page.
To do that, we want to make
sure we're in the Elements
panel you see here.
In this panel, you can see a
bunch of HTML on the left side
and a bunch of CSS
on the right.
But what you're really seeing
there on the left side is a
representation of the DOM or
Document Object Model.
You can think of it as a
collection of the different
elements in your HTML put into
sort of a tree format.
So if you want, you can press
on those little triangle
shapes, and it'll show you
more or less code in that
document tree.
If you're looking at your
rendered HTML page, and you're
wondering, well, what HTML
created that particular
element, what you can do is
right click on the element--
in our case, we're going to
right click on the button--
and select Inspect Element.
As we open the Elements panel,
if we don't already have it
open, and show us that
particular element highlighted
inside the DOM.
You might also notice that it's
showing us the CSS for
that element on the right side,
but we'll get more into
that in the next level.
Another way you can select an
element is by clicking the
magnifying glass in the bottom
left of the screen to enter
the Element Selection mode.
Then when you hover over the
page, you can see the
different element boundaries.
And when you left click on
one, it will select that
element in the Elements panel.
Now let's go ahead and make
some live changes.
For example, let's change
the text on our button.
To change that text, all we have
to do is double click on
it, type a new title, and then
we can just hit Enter when
we're done or click somewhere
else on the page.
If we right click on a
particular element, we're
given a bunch of different
options, including the ability
to add or edit attributes.
Let's go ahead and add an ID
attribute to this element.
Pretty easy.
Also in this menu, we can choose
to edit a node as HTML,
where we can change any part
of the element or add
additional elements.
Finally, if we click and drag an
element, we can change its
location on the page.
It shouldn't come as a surprise
that you can select
any element and hit the Delete
button to remove that element
or even right click and select
the Delete menu item.
Well, now it's time for you to
practice using some of these
techniques in the Challenges.