So we've learned about making
real time updates to the DOM,
but what if we want to
make changes to our
style sheets or CSS?
Well, that's where
the right side of
Elements panel comes in.
The styles view does
a lot for us.
First off, it displays the
computed CSS styles for any
given element.
See, on any element, you might
have multiple styles coming
from multiple files, multiple
style sheets, and they get
computed into a listing
that you see here.
The styles view also allows
you to enable and disable
style properties, add new
ones, edit rules on
pseudo-classes, like your
active and hover state.
And finally, it provides a bread
crumb trail so you can
figure out what file
a style came from.
Here you can see, I have the Add
Event button selected on
the left side.
And on the right side, I can
see all the CSS rules being
applied to this button,
starting with the most
specific rules first.
So if I had any inline styles,
they would be displayed here.
And then, there's a label that's
showing us the first
set of CSS rules coming from the
new class since our link
belongs to that class.
You see all those check boxes
next to those styles?
Well, they do what you would
expect them to do.
If you unclick a style,
it stops getting
applied to that element.
This is really useful
in debugging.
If you're wondering what style
is messing up your page, you
can just start disabling the
styles until you figure out
who the culprit is.
We can also change the
style values by
double clicking on them.
So now, our button text is
aligned to the right, as you
can see above.
Or we can remove a property
entirely by just deleting the
value, and now our text
is over on the
left side of the button.
If you want to add a style to an
element, just make sure it's
selected and just hit the
Plus button here.
We then, will want to specify
the CSS selector, which, as
you can see, is defaulted to the
dot new class since that's
what we have selected.
We can then start typing a new
style, and look at that.
It actually allows us to auto
complete each of the
properties and values
using the Tab key.
Now, what if we wanted to change
our Add Event button so
that it changes to a different
color when our
mouse hovers over it?
It might be kind of hard to
hover the mouse over it while
we're trying to use Dev Tools.
But, there's a solution
for this.
If we click on this icon, on
the right side here, we can
force the element we have
selected, the button in this
case, to be in the
active, hover,
focused, or visited state.
In this case, we want
the hover state so
we'll check that off.
And as you can see here, the
button text up above is
underlined.
We can also see the style for
the hover state, which makes
underlined right here in the
bottom right of the screen.
If you want to change the
background color on hover, we
can just add the style here,
and immediately see that it
turns black in the web page.
When we're ready to actually
watch it work, we can uncheck
the hover state and
play with it.
Yep, looks like it works.
Black is obviously not a great
color for this hover state, so
let's change it.
But this time, instead of typing
a value, let's click on
that color swatch right there.
When we see that, we can get
this nice color picker so we
can choose our color this
way, and come up
with a better match.
Lastly, our style view allows us
to know where a particular
style came from.
You might notice that in our CSS
panel, each CSS rule has a
file name listed on the right
side with a line number.
When you click on this file,
that opens up the CSS source
in something that resembles
an editor.
This is actually the source
view panel, which we'll be
going over in the
next chapter.
So let's not get ahead
of ourselves.
First, it's time for you to play
with the style view in
the challenges.