All of the changes we've been
making to our web pages using
the Elements panel have been
temporary, meaning as soon as
we refresh our page, boom, all
of our changes are gone.
If we really want to make
modifications to our web page,
well, we have to make changes
to the source files.
This is where the Source
panel comes in.
You can edit your file right
there in the web page, it kind
of looks like an editor.
You can export that to disk when
you're done editing, and
you can also see a revision
history so you can see all the
changes that you've made
to the file over time.
As we saw at the end of the last
chapter, clicking a file
name in the style section of
Elements panel will open that
file in the Sources panel.
I think the text on our Add
Event button should be a
little bit bigger.
So let's go ahead and
edit it right here
in the Sources panel.
As you can see, while I'm
editing the CSS, the page
instantly reflects the changes
that I'm making.
You may notice that we now have
a star next to the file
name here in our
Sources panel.
That means we need
to save the file.
So we can hit Control S, or
Command S if we're on a Mac,
and it will Save the file.
Now, it's just saving to
our browser's storage.
It's not saving to our original
source files.
To see all of the modifications
that we've made
here in the browser, we can
right click on a particular
file and select Local
Modifications.
This will show us a list of time
stamps and when we open
them up, we can see the
different changes that we've
made along the way.
So here we can see the font
sizes change from 1.6 EMs in
red to 3 EMs in green.
You also might notice that each
revision has an Apply
Revision Content button
next to it.
If we click that, the changes
from that revision will be
applied to the current revision
and a new revision
will be added with those
changes at the top.
Unfortunately, I'm not very
happy with the changes that
we've made here, but
fortunately,
there's a Revert button.
I can click that, it's going
to blow away all of my
modifications, and put
the file back in
its original state.
Sometimes you're going to make
a lot of changes here in Dev
tools and you're going to want
to save that back over the
original source file.
Luckily, we can do that.
To do this, you can simply right
click on the source file
you want to save and
click Save As.
In our case, we're going to go
into our project folder and
simply overwrite the original
source file.
There's no substitute for
practice so it's time for you
to jump into the challenges.