So here we are back in our
Calendar application.
We've got the console panel
open, and you'll notice when
we refresh the page, we're
going to get an error.
We can learn more about what
caused this error by clicking
on the little triangle next to
it, and it'll show us a stack
trace of the calls that led to
the error, along with a file
name and line number.
If we click that line number,
the JavaScript file will open
up over in our Sources panel,
and we're brought right to the
line number where the error
occurred and even shown the
error message itself
right here.
If you take a read through the
JavaScript, it looks like
we're trying to call
the length property
on the events array.
But according to our error, the
events array is null, and,
obviously, you can't call
length on a null object.
So what's setting the
events array?
Well, it looks like the events
variable gets set when we call
calendar.events.
So it must be that method
which is returning null.
Here it might be useful to test
to see if that method is
actually returning
a null array.
Let's jump into the console
and run the command.
To open up the console this
time, we're simply going to
click this icon in
the lower left.
It's a little bit
of a shortcut.
Now I can make a quick call to
calendar.events, and yep, it's
returning null.
So we know where our
problem lies.
The function here is returning
null because we
don't have any events.
But we're going to want to
change this code so that if it
doesn't have any events, instead
it just returns an
empty array, which we'll get
into in the next chapter.
But for now, let's jump into
some more challenges.