But now, if we try to create
another event, it's still not
working, and it looks like
we created another error.
Let's dig deeper and click on
the file name on the right to
see what's going on.
Oh, it looks like Save Event is
calling that same calendar
events methods, which, as we
know, will return null.
And as the error reads,
we can't call the
push method on null.
How might we confirm that
this is actually
what's going on though?
Well, we're going to have to
jump into the code and pause
the code as it's executing, so
we can examine the state of
the variables.
One way we can do this is by
clicking on the Pause On
Exceptions icon in
the bottom left.
You see it down there?
Once we have the Pause icon
pressed, the next time an
error occurs, the code is
going to be paused.
While it's paused, we can just
hover over each variable, and
it will show us the value.
Here's the event object we're
trying to add, which has a
name of 5k run.
The events variable is supposed
to hold our events
list, but as you can see, it's
currently null as we suspected.
Now, if we refresh the browser
again with Pause On Exception
selected, something unexpected
is going to happen.
It looks like we paused
somewhere inside of our Jquery
library, and it looks like it's
the minified version of
Jquery, meaning that all white
space and unneeded characters
have been removed.
Minifying your JavaScript
libraries like this, is going
to make it load quicker
in any browser.
But it's also going to make it
more difficult to debug.
Fortunately, Dev Tools has a
pretty print mode, which you
make it readable again.
You see those brackets down
there at the bottom?
If we click that, our code
becomes a lot more readable,
and we can see that the code
that's causing the exception
is inside a tricatch block.
This means it's a caught
exception, which we're not
going to want to pause on.
This is why Dev Tools has a
second mode for your debugger
that will pause only uncaught
exceptions.
All we have to do to activate
it is click that button a
second time.
Now, if we reload the page again
and try to create an
event again, you'll see it
skips directly to our own
caught exception.
This is what we wanted.
That's twice now that
we've had problems
with the event function.
So let's take a look inside that
code, and see if we can
figure out what's going on.
I'm going to scroll down to the
function in the code and
set a debugger break point by
clicking on the left margin on
the first line of
that function.
Then, if I try to create an
event and again, the execution
will pause as soon as it hits
that break point, like so.
The line you see highlighted
here hasn't
actually been run yet.
We can confirm this by hovering
over the events variable.
So we need to execute that
code to see what happens.
To do this, we'll need to use
the execution controls, you
can see over on the right
hand side of the page.
The first button you see here
is Resume, which will resume
the execution of the entire
page until the next break
point, if there is one.
The next button is Step Over.
This will run the current line
highlighted and step over to
the next line of code.
Then there's Step Into, which
will go down into whatever
function is being called on that
line, in this case, it
would be the Get Item Method.
Step Out will return
from the current
function into its caller.
The last button will deactivate
all break
points in our code.
What we want to do here is
execute the current line of
code and step over to the next
one, so I'm going to press the
Step Over button.
And now, if we hover over the
events variable, we can see
that it's been defined, and
it is, in fact, null.
Remember earlier how we were
checking to see if events that
got returned is null?
Well, this is probably a better
place to check for it.
So we'll check to see if events
is null, and if it is,
we'll parse the JSON.
Otherwise, we'll just return
an empty array.
We can test our new code by
simply refreshing the page,
and once again, it will stop
on our break point.
Now, if we step through a few
lines, we can see that our
events was equal to null
so we're going to
return an empty array.
Now, if we click Create New
Event, it's going to pause on
our break point again.
Then if we execute this line and
hover over our events, we
can see that it's still null,
so it's going to return an
empty array again.
And we're going to add a new
event to this array.
And now, for the first time
ever, we've actually added a
new event successfully.
And now that the event method
is fixed, we can go back and
remove that null check that we
did in the last level from the
Get Events for Date function.
Why don't you give this a
try in the challenges.