Now let's take a look at an
error that might pop up when
we read data from
local storage.
So here you can see I refreshed
the page, an
error popped up.
It looks like our application's
trying to call
the two lowercase method on
a value that's undefined.
If we refresh the page again,
you can see that it's paused
on our exception.
And if we hover over the name
for our event, we can see that
it is, in fact, undefined.
So what's going on here?
Well, let's take a look at our
events in local storage.
To do that, we'll first
have to click on
the Resources panel.
Then we can bring up storage for
the app on our development
machine by clicking
in the list here.
On the right, we can see our
stored items sorted by Key.
And there's our event, JSON.
It looks like our first event
has both a name and a date
attribute, but our second
only has a date.
So let's try adding
a name to it.
Now when we refresh the page, it
loads successfully because
our name is no longer null.
All right.
Now that we've shown you some
of the capabilities of the
DevTools debugger, it's time for
you to try it yourself in
the Challenges.