You're watching Discover
DevTools.
And this is Level Five, where
we're going to be going over
the Network panel.
Any given web page that you load
is made up of a bunch of
network requests.
You've got the HTML itself,
JavaScripts, style sheets,
images, maybe even some Ajax.
And each of these network
requests, well, the faster
they happen, the more responsive
your web page is
going to feel.
Now DevTools gives you the
Timeline panel which helps you
identify bottlenecks in these
network requests, which we're
going to take a look at now.
Here you can see we're back
in our Calendar app.
To see the Network panel in
action, we'll want to call it
up and then refresh
our browser.
From left to right, it's showing
us the name of each
resource; the HTTP method used
to get it; the response status
code, which return from the
server; the file type of the
response; what initiated the
request, in case we need to
track that down later;
the size of the
file; how long it took.
And over on the right side, we
can see a little waterfall,
which shows us when each
resource was requested and
when it finished downloading.
In case you're not familiar
with status codes, they're
pretty easy to Google.
And this one, 304 not modified,
means that my
browser has already downloaded
this resource before, and it
has a local or cached copy that
it's going to load up
instead of downloading
it again.
To get an idea of how fast my
page loads when somebody first
goes to it, I'm going to want
to reload all the resources.
To do this, I can hold down
the Shift key now
and then do a refresh.
This is going to re-download
everything.
I can see now that downloading
all the resources and
completing the request took just
a little over a second,
1.19 seconds to be precise.
We can also see that our
response statuses have all
changed to 200 OK, meaning
that they were all
re-downloaded.
When you're debugging the
performance of your web page,
you're going to want to disable
the cache, and there's
two more ways to do it.
First, you can do it by going to
the File menu and selecting
New Incognito Window, which
will not only use a fresh
cache, but it also won't
use any cookies
you may have stored.
You can also go down to the
bottom right, click the gear
icon, and open up the
DevTools Settings.
There, you can select the
Disable Cache check box.
Now let's take a closer
look at what's going
on over in our waterfall.
The translucent bar shows the
latency of our request--
how long from the start of
asking for a resource to the
start of when it begins
transferring it back to us.
The solid part shows us when
the browser started and
finished downloading
that resource.
The endpoint is when
all data from
that request was received.
You might be wondering what all
the different colors mean.
Well, it's colored
by the file type.
HTML is blue, up at
the top there.
JavaScript is orange.
Style sheets are green,
and images are purple.
The first request that we did on
this page is obviously the
HTML page itself,
the index.html.
And if you take a look at that
Initiator column, you can see
that all of the other resources
were pulled down
because we discovered them
inside of the index.html.
And you can actually click on
those, and it will bring you
to the line inside the
index.html where it discovered
that it needed that resource.
If we look over at the
waterfall, you can see that it
reflects exactly this--
the resources are only requested
after the index.html
is downloaded.
The blue line at the end of the
timeline represents when
the DOM content-loaded
event fired.
This gets triggered when our
browser is done parsing our
HTML file, but it still could
be loading resources.
The red line signifies the load
event or when all the
resources are done
downloading.
Sometimes there's
a notable delay
between those two events.
If we click on the file name of
a resource, we can get more
information about
that request.
We're shown all the headers sent
along with the request
and the response.
This can be really useful if
you want to make sure your
server has the correct
cache settings.
You can also preview the
resource contents here, which
for text files like HTML,
JavaScripts, or style sheets
are just going to show
you the contents.
For images and fonts, you'll
get a visual preview.
Now it's time for you start
playing with the Network panel
in the Challenges.