Now that we're familiar with
the Network panel, let's
figure out some things we can
do to speed up our web page.
Google has created a helpful
extension called PageSpeed.
This tool analyzes our
application and makes
suggestions for how we
can speed it up.
Just search for it
in the Chrome Web
Store to install it.
Once we have it installed, to
run it on our web page we'll
load up our page, click on the
new PageSpeed panel that we
have here, and click the button
to start analyzing.
PageSpeed will download our page
and run several automated
checks against it.
Looks like we've got
an initial score
of 79 out of 100.
Not bad, but we can definitely
do better.
Let's see if we can
pull up our grade.
We'll start with the item with
the highest priority,
minifying the JavaScript.
Currently, our application is
loading three JavaScript
files, as you can see here.
We can see how big they are by
looking over on the Network
tab, and together, they have
a size over 160 kilobytes.
They are fairly big.
They also require us to make
three separate requests to the
server, which also
isn't optimal.
The first optimization we can
make to each of these
JavaScript files is to
minify each of them.
This is going to remove extra
white space, reduce long
parameter names, and make other
optimizations to the
files to make them smaller.
Here you can see some code up
top that hasn't been minified.
Then, after minifying it, you
can see the code is going to
function the same but now it's
less characters, which is good
for speeding up your
page load time.
The next thing we can do is
take our three JavaScript
files and put them all
into one file.
Now the size is going to be
the same, whether it's in
three files or in one big one,
but it's only going to take
one network request to load
that file into our browser
rather than three.
And browsers themselves are
actually limited the number of
network requests they
can do at the same
time for a web page.
So obviously, the less network
requests our page has to do,
the faster it's going to load.
There are many different
libraries you can use to
combine your JavaScripts and
to minify them, but we're
going to use Google's
Closure Library.
Below this video, you'll find
a link to the official web
page to download this library.
You can download it in the form
of a Java JAR, and then
just run it from
your terminal.
We can also minify and combine
our JavaScript files using
this web app created by the
Google Closure team.
In order to use it, we need
to get the URLs of our
JavaScripts.
Now assuming your web app is
like ours and it's available
at a public URL, we can easily
get these JavaScript URLs by
going into our Network panel
and right clicking on each
JavaScript file name and
selecting Copy Link Address.
Then we'll just paste this
address into the Closure
Compiler and click Add.
We'll then go back and get the
next file, copy its address
and paste it, and repeat
for the third one.
Once we have all our files in
place, we click on the Compile
button, give it a few seconds,
and on the right side, you'll
be shown your minified
JavaScript and a link where
you can download the
compressed file.
We'll go ahead and save this and
change the name from the
default to app-min, meaning
minified, and save it to our
app folder.
Now we just need to replace
our old JavaScript sources
with this new source,
just like that.
Previously, to load our
JavaScript for this web page,
we had to load three files
totaling 160 kilobytes.
Now in our new version, we only
need to make one request
for 110 kilobytes.
That's a pretty nice savings.
Now it's time for you to jump
into a challenge and start
making some page optimizations.