After making this optimization,
if we look back
in our Page Speed extension,
we'll see that our score has
improved to 81.
Not bad, but we still have a
bunch of recommendations to
address, one of which is
to avoid bad requests.
As you've probably noticed by
now, we've been trying to load
an image that doesn't exist.
It has that 404 not found status
code, and it's colored
red here in our timeline.
If we check our source for
clock.png, we can see that
it's actually hidden in
the class of someday.
And if we check our CSS file,
we'll see that this class
isn't even set to display
on the page.
So it seems pretty
safe to remove.
Let's do that and delete
it from our HTML file.
And now if we refresh the page,
you can see that our
warning is gone.
Next up on the list
is to optimize
our style sheet order.
If we take a look at our HTML,
you'll see that we're loading
the JavaScript before the CSS.
And if you take a moment to
think about what a web page
needs to render on the page,
well, it's not going to be
able to render properly until
it's downloaded all the CSS.
Whereas JavaScript, in some
cases, might be a lot less
important because it might
just be dealing with user
interaction, not how it
displays the page.
So it's best that we have our
CSS file listed before our
JavaScript file, unlike
we see here.
So let's update our
HTML to fix that.
So now if we refresh our page,
we'll see that our CSS is
being loaded before our
JavaScript as it should be.
But that doesn't seem to affect
our page load time.
And if we look at the waterfall,
it seems like it's
still waiting to download the
JavaScript before it's loading
our web page.
But in our case, our JavaScript
is just dealing
with user interaction, so we
don't really care that much if
it loads after the page
gets rendered.
To put off parsing of the
JavaScript so the web page can
be rendered sooner, we can add
the async attribute to our
script tag like so.
Now it's time for you to jump
into some challenges and see
if you can find a
missing asset.