Lastly, it looks like we're
serving an image that hasn't
been scaled down to the size
that we're displaying it at.
That image there, we're getting
displayed at 35 pixels
by 35 pixels.
But we're downloading an image
that is much bigger and
leaving it to the browser
to scale it down.
In a perfect world, the image
that we downloaded would be 35
pixels by 35 pixels.
It's also a JPEG, JPEGs are
good for photographs.
But when we're dealing with
icons and other images with
large areas of solid color,
you might want
to use a PNG instead.
So I've scaled down the image
and I reexported it as a PNG.
Let's update the file
name in our HTML.
There we go.
The image was 19 kilobytes
before and now
it's down to two.
It's going to download faster.
Not only that, but it's
the right size.
So the browser doesn't have to
re-size the image and the page
is going to load slightly
faster.
You might also notice on
the screen that the
DOMcontentloaded event is firing
at 175 milliseconds.
This is because we set that
JavaScript to load
asynchronously a minute
ago, async.
And this event isn't going to
wait anymore for scripts to
load before it fires.
Now if we go back and check
on our grade, we're up
to 96 out of 100.
Not bad.
Our app is heading in
the right direction.
Now these techniques might not
apply to the applications
you're working on.
But hopefully you have the
knowledge now to optimize your
application using the page
speed extension.
Good luck in the challenges.