You're watching Discover
DevTools, and this is level
six, where we're going to be
talking about frames and the
CPU profiler.
As we saw in the previous level,
you can speed up your
web page by optimizing your
network interactions.
But sometimes, the problem
isn't your network
interactions.
It might be that you just have
some slow code that's running
on the browser side.
To optimize that, you can use
two tools we're looking at in
this level called the Frames
View and the CPU Profiler.
If you're a gamer like me,
you've probably heard of the
term frame rate.
This refers to the number of
images that gets rendered on
your screen per second.
So if I have a frame rate of 30
FPS, or frames per second,
that means there's 30 different
images that are
getting drawn onto my
screen per second.
And as my computer slows down,
it slows the rendering time
down, which means I might be
getting less frames per second
and it might start to stutter.
Especially as it gets below 10
frames per second, you're
definitely going to
be able to see it.
Even your browser has a frame
rate, and it can be slowed
down by things like JavaScript
execution, rendering of your
styles, and painting the
rendered page onto the screen.
This is where the Frames View
comes in, telling you when and
where your frame rate is
starting to suffer.
I've modified the Event Creation
button so now it has
an animation whenever
we create an event.
Let's see if that has any impact
on our frame rate.
So I'm going to open up the
Timeline tab and go to the
Frames menu.
We can record our frame timeline
by clicking on the
Record button here at the
bottom of the screen.
Now, let's try adding
a new event.
We click on the Event button,
try typing a name, click to
add, and there's our little
slide down animation.
As new events fire, our timeline
is updated, showing
how long each frame
took to render.
The ones that are under that
bottom line are around 16
milliseconds.
If each frame is 16
milliseconds, you can fit
about 60 frames per second,
which is a reading that you
see here on the right hand
side of our timeline.
It says 60 FPS or Frames
Per Second.
The second marker above
this says 30 FPS, or
30 Frames Per Second.
So if a frame takes longer than
33.3 milliseconds to run,
well, it's going to be above
that line and we're going to
see this huge bar, which
is not good.
Notice at the bottom of the
screen, we have check boxes
with Loading in blue, Scripting
in yellow, Rendering
in purple, and Painting
in green.
These are the colors you see
represented on the timeline.
This page was already loaded
when we started recording, so
there's not much blue, or HTML,
loading in our timeline.
We do have some JavaScript which
we can see in yellow.
And of course, the purple is the
rendering of the page or
the time we spent on style
recalculation and layout.
The transparent part of each bar
is the time spent idling
or on other uncategorized
tasks.
Low frame rates or laggy
animation can lead to a bad
user experience of an otherwise
beautiful web page,
so it's important to keep
an eye on this.
And so far, it looks like our
page here is loading under
this 60 frames per
second line.
Let's switch to the
next calendar day
and see what happens.
Whoa, you see that yellow
bar over there?
Not so good--
definitely less than 30
frames per second.
The color suggests that
JavaScript here is the
culprit, but there's a lot of
JavaScript in our application.
To narrow our search, we're
going to need the CPU
Profiler, which we're going to
get into in the next video.
But for now, why don't you jump
in to the challenges and
get familiar with
the Frames View.