So our app seems to slow down
when we switch between
calendar days.
This is where the CPU Profiler
comes in, which can show us
which parts of our JavaScript
are slowing the page down.
Let's create a profile by
clicking on the Profiles
panel, selecting Collect
JavaScript CPU Profile, and
click the Start button
at the bottom.
Now we're recording, so
we'll switch to the
next calendar date.
When it's finished, we'll hit
the Stop button here.
What we're then presented with
is a bunch of different
functions that were called
and how much CPU
time they each took.
Up at the top of this list, we
see a function called window
Calendar get events for
date, and this took
up 13% of the time.
We can dive into this function's
code by easily
clicking on the file name and
line number on the right.
It appears we're looping
through every single
millisecond of the day to see
if our event is happening on
that particular millisecond.
This is a pretty expensive
operation, and
it's probably overkill.
So let's refactor this code to
take a look at the first
millisecond of every day instead
of every millisecond
of every day.
All right.
Now that we fixed the code,
let's redo our profile by
going back to the Profile
panel, select Collect
JavaScript CPU Profile,
and click Start.
Then we switch dates, stop
when the operation is
complete, and click on the new
profile in the Profile list to
view the results.
I think, previously, get events
for date was right at
the top of the list.
And we can click back and forth
between the two profiles
to compare them.
Now it's not even
on the top 10.
Looks like we fixed it.
Let's go back into the CPU
Profiler and see if we can
make any more optimizations.
We'll start on the recording
and start
switching days again.
There are no second-long stalls
this time, but it seems
like the animation intended
for adding a new event is
being run for every event on the
page, and well, it's just
not very smooth.
On our timeline here, we can
find a few instances where the
JavaScript and the rendering are
much longer than 30 frames
per second.
We use our Display Event
function to add our
events to the page.
Here you can see we added a
conditional to determine if we
should add an animation
effect when we
display out the events.
In our Create Event function,
we called the display event
with the animated parameter
set to true.
We also call it in the display
date for each event
we add to the page.
Here you can see the animation
is set to true, but it really
should be set to false so it
doesn't call that animation
every time it renders an
event on the page.
It was likely this event that
was slowing the page down.
Let's correct this and switch
it to false so we don't
animate old dates.
Now let's switch back to
the Frames view and
make another recording.
We'll try switching dates
again, a couple
times for good measure.
Once we stop the recording, you
can see on our timeline
that scripting, rendering, and
painting for each frame is now
completing faster than
60 frames per
second most of the time.
The Frames view can
quickly alert you
to performance problems.
And then the CPU Profiler can
help you track down where your
slow JavaScript code
is happening.
And it's time for you to get
your hands dirty in the
Challenges.