You're watching Discovering Dev
Tools and this is level
seven, where we're going to be
learning about memory leaks.
You may have heard the term
memory leak before.
It usually happens when an
application takes up more and
more memory on your computer to
the point where it starts
to slow everything down and
maybe even crashes.
Well, you can even write
JavaScript code that can cause
memory leaks and without even
knowing about it, so that when
somebody's running your
application in a browser,
things might tend to slow down
as your application takes more
and more memory.
Well, let's take a look at the
memory section of the timeline
to see how we can identify and
diagnose some memory leaks.
I've added the ability for our
users to hide the add event
entry form by just hitting
the Escape key.
However, now we're getting
complaints from our customers
that after they use our page
for a long time, that it
starts to slow down.
This might be a memory leak.
Let's see if we can
diagnose it.
First, we'll go to the Timeline
panel and click on
the Memory section
on the right.
Just like in the previous
chapter, we need to hit the
Record button and then interact
with our application
a little bit.
I'll open and close the
form a few times,
then stop the recording.
The graph you see shows the
amount of memory allocated to
our application.
It looks like our application
is consuming more and more
memory the longer we use it,
which is a good sign for a
memory leak.
Healthy applications don't just
continuously grow in memory.
Why don't you give this a
try in the challenges?