So we know there's a memory
leak, but we need to figure
out what piece of code
is causing it.
Well, this is where heap
snapshots come in.
They show you a snapshot of the
current JavaScript objects
in memory, so we can figure out
where the leak might be.
To take our first snapshot,
we'll go into the Profiles
panel, select Take Heap
Snapshot, and press Start.
We're currently in Summary view
of our heap snapshot,
which shows us all our objects,
but this is quite a
large number to sift through.
Instead, let's take a second
heap snapshot, and then we'll
compare it to the first.
But before we do that, let's
go ahead and go through our
application and do the behavior
we think might be
causing that memory leak.
So we'll open and close
the form a few times.
Now back in the Profiles panel,
we can just hit the
Record button at the bottom of
the screen, which will take
another heap snapshot.
Then, to make this comparison,
we'll select the newest
snapshot, switch the view from
Summary to Comparison and make
sure it's comparing against
snapshot one.
Now we're looking at objects
that were allocated between
our two snapshots.
The detached DOM tree item
listed right here is
especially interesting.
If we expand it, we'll
see a large
number of input elements.
They're highlighted in red here
because they have been
removed from the DOM,
but they haven't
been garbage collected.
The memory that they were using
hasn't been freed up.
While there can be legitimate
reasons to do this, more often
than not there's
a memory leak.
If we dive into our source code,
we see the first signs
of our problem.
Whenever we're creating the
form for adding an event,
we're creating the inputs
from scratch.
And we're adding a function to
the window which listens for
the Escape key to be pressed
and then removes the form
fields by just overriding
the parent's HTML.
There's two issues with
this listener.
The first is that it simply
removes the input field from
the DOM when it overrides their
parent's HTML context.
That causes these elements to
be detached as you see here.
They're no longer connected
to the DOM.
Ordinarily, the garbage
collector would come along and
delete this node the next
time it cleans it up.
However, we also have the
reference to the input fields
within our function, which is,
in turn, attached to the
window object.
The garbage collector sees this
reference and doesn't
clean up the inputs
when it runs.
It just leaves them there until
such a time that the
page is closed or reloaded.
It is a memory leak.
Every time we hit the Add Event
button, it's creating
new input fields.
And then when we press Escape,
it's never cleaning them up.
So how do we fix this?
Well, it's probably optimal to
keep the input fields in the
DOM all the time.
Just have them there and show
them when we go to add a new
element and hide them when we
don't need them anymore.
Also, we should make sure
we're not creating new
elements outside the event
listener which we're using
inside the event listener.
So let's take our input fields
out of our JavaScript, and
we'll put them into our HTML.
We'll also move our Add Event
button into a separate
container, so it can be hidden
when we show the Create Form.
Now we'll go into our CSS and
make sure the creation form
isn't displayed initially.
It starts out as hidden.
Then back in our Create method,
we'll add the code to
find our hidden create
div and show it.
Then we'll find the Add
button and hide that.
Inside the Escape keyListener
below, we'll first get rid of
the code that overrides the
HTML, and then simply hide the
creation form and show
the Add Event button.
You might notice that we still
do have reference inside the
event listener of create and
add, even though they were
declared outside the function.
Let's fix that.
It'll be safer to do
a fresh look-up of
the nodes every time.
That way there's not an extra
reference to these nodes
inside our event listener.
Now let's see if
our code works.
Looks like our changes
are working.
Now let's see if we're leaving
detached DOM nodes still.
We'll return to the Profiles
panel, take
another heap snapshot.
Now we'll do that same activity
before that created a
memory leak.
We'll display and hide the
fields a few times again, then
we'll take a second snapshot,
select it, choose the
Comparison view, and
then compare to
the previous snapshot.
If we look at the objects
created between the first and
second snapshots, we can see
that we're no longer leaving
detached DOM nodes when
we hide our fields.
Sweet.
So now we've shown you how
to discover memory leaks,
pinpoint them, and
eliminate them.
It's time for you to try it
out in the Challenges.