[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS Cross
Country, and this is Level 3,
Box Bindings.
In Level 3 we'll be discussing
the box model, positioning,
and Z-Index.
So what is the box model?
Every element on the page is
outlined by an imaginary thing
called the box model, which
looks something like this.
The actual area around
the content is
called the content area.
Any padding we define outside
of the content is in what's
called the padding area.
The border appears around the
padding area, and any margin
that we have will be outside
of the border.
We can manipulate each of these
properties via CSS.
The total width of an item on
the page is going to be
dependent on the total of each
box model property, so in
defining the total box width
of an item, we have to take
all these properties
into account.
In looking at an element like
this, that has a set content
width, a set left and right
padding, and a border all the
way around, to determine the
total space it will take up on
the page we can add all these
properties together.
So first we'll add the
total content width.
Add together the left
and right padding.
Add the left and right
borders together.
And we'll get a total box
width of 125 pixels.
So this is the total width
this element will
take up on the page.
More often, though, you'll need
to determine the total
content width given the box
width and the accompanying
properties.
So, in this case, we have the
total box width from the
design, as well as the left
and right padding and the
total border.
By subtracting these values from
that total box width, we
can end up with our total
content width,
which is 310 pixels.
In dealing with setting
boundaries on our containers,
we need to know what happens
when content flows outside of
these boundaries.
So let's take a look at
the overflow property.
There are four main properties
for overflow, and we'll be
taking a look at each.
Visible is the default property,
and that's going to
allow any content that
extends beyond our
boundaries to be visible.
If we use the auto property of
overflow, that'll add scroll
bars whenever necessary so that
our container stays the
size that we set, but we can
still view any content that
would overflow.
If we set the overflow property
to hidden, then any
content that would have extended
beyond the container
will be cut off.
Finally, if we use scroll,
scroll bars will automatically
be added to the element,
regardless of whether or not
they need to be there.
Next, let's take a look
at positioning.
Now, there are four main
values, for the position
property in CSS.
Static, relative, absolute
and fixed.
Anything that is on the page
in the normal flow is
considered position static.
Anything that's set to something
other than static is
considered a position element,
and that'll be important for
properties later on.
Once something is positioned,
then we can set the top, left,
bottom, or right values in CSS
to move that item depending on
what type of positioning
we've applied.
First, let's take a look at
relative positioning.
With relative positioning items
will be rendered as
though they're static, but then
we have the ability to
use those top, left, bottom and
right properties, to move
it from where it normally would
have been rendered.
In this case, we want the 2 that
is within the superscript
tag to be rendered as though
it is an exponent.
Here's a bit of code from
the HTML5 boilerplate.
Don't worry too much about
what the first
three values do.
You can visit link one to
learn more about the
boilerplate.
But the final two properties set
this item to be positioned
relatively.
Then, using the top property,
move it up half of an em.
This allows the item to be
rendered first in normal
document flow, then be moved
from its normal position to
appear as an exponent.
Alternatively, using absolute
positioning takes an item
outside of the normal document
flow, and it allows us to
manually position it within
our document.
In this case, we want to move
our h3 byline absolutely to be
attached to the right side of
our article, rather than being
in the normal flow.
If we simply give this position
absolute, give it a
right value of 10 pixels, and
a top value of 10 pixels, we
might expect this to stay 10
pixels from the top right edge
of our article.
And if our window is the
same size of our
article, this is true.
However, if our window expands
beyond the normal article
confines, our absolutely
positioned byline is going to
move along with it.
Why is that?
When we're positioning something
absolutely, it's
going to be scoped to the window
unless it falls within
an element that is position.
So, in this case, we're
going to give our
article position relative.
If we have an item that needs
to be positioned, meaning it
has something other than static
for it's position
value, we can use relative if
we don't intend to actually
move the item.
Once we give this article a
position of relative, then,
regardless of the window
width, our absolutely
positioned byline is going to
stick to the article size
rather than stay with
the window.
With fixed positioning, we can
affix our item in the window
in a specific place where it
will stay, like shown, in the
same place regardless of
how the user scrolls.
Unlike absolute positioning,
we cannot scope this to a
specific container
on the page.
When dealing with multiple
position items it's
commonplace that these items
might begin to overlap one
another, so it's important to
take into consideration in
what order they'll overlap.
In this case, I have two images
that are overlapping
one another because they
are positioned.
If they have the same z-index
set, or if they have no
z-index set, the image that
appears second in the HTML
will appear to be
above the first.
So, in this case, our sled image
will appear above the
ski image since they both have
the same z-index value.
If I change the z-index value
to only apply to our ski
image, it will overcome the
default cascade order and
appear above the slide image.
Z-index will only apply to
elements that have a position
value other than static, meaning
they're positioned.
Remember that if you don't want
the item to move, but
simply need to give it
positioning, you can use
position relative.
There are a whole lot of other
considerations with stacking
order as they apply to things
like floats, normally
positioned elements and position
elements, so take a
look at link two if you'd like
to learn more about this.
So that does it for Level 3.
While you're off doing the
challenges, I'm going to get a
cup of cocoa.
Good luck.