[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS Cross
Country and this is level six,
Image Issues.
In this section, we're going
to talk about image use and
image cropping.
When dealing with images it's
important to consider whether
the image is part of the layout
or part of the content.
Let's look at an example.
Here we have a list of rental
products and I'm displaying
our image using a background
image.
This was fine in the beginning
because I had the image that
we needed, but what happens
if this list ever
needs to become dynamic?
How would we dynamically access
the background image of
a list item?
A better way to do this is to
write it as an inline image.
This way we can dynamically
access the source and all the
attributes.
You shouldn't always use
inline images though.
Let's look at an example of
a case when you shouldn't.
Here we have an h1 tag that's
immediately followed by a
divider image.
This works fine, but it's not
very dry because we'll
probably have to repeat it a lot
and it's hard to maintain.
A better way to define this
image is to define it in the
background of our h1 tag.
So just to review image use,
images that are part of the
layout should be included
as background images.
And images that are part of the
content should be included
as inline images.
So now that you understand how
to use images properly, let's
talk about some common issues
that can come up when images
become dynamic.
Let's look at our
list of rental
items that is now dynamic.
We need to consider what's going
to happen when these
images come in at
different sizes.
You've also probably seen
something like this before.
As you can see, setting a set
height and width on everything
is going to squish some
of our images.
A better way to handle this is
to use something called the
overflow crop method.
What we're going to do here is
apply a crop class to the
parent element surrounding our
image, which in this case, is
our list item.
We're going to set a set height
and width on that, and
then apply an overflow hidden to
hide the part of the image
that overflows our container.
So now you're going to see a
window that is cropped at a
certain size but the image
inside of that container will
be its regular size, and
it won't be squished.
Doing it this way works
fine, but it's
still not totally perfect.
Because as you can see, using
only the overflow crop crops
out part of the full image.
There's a better way that we
can do this that will scale
the image down to better
fit the container.
What we need to do is set a
width on our image and then
allow the height to
automatically scale.
Resizing the image and using
the overflow crop method
together will provide us with
a much better result.
But wait, if we go back and
refresh the browser, now we're
seeing an image that's coming
through that uses a portrait
orientation.
We haven't accounted for any
portrait oriented images in
our CSS, so we can go back
and do that now.
To account for portrait oriented
images, we just need
to switch the height
and width settings.
So we're going to set a set
height on it and allow the
width to automatically scale.
Unfortunately, now that we've
changed our CSS to account for
portrait oriented images, we've
broken our landscape
oriented images.
The best way to handle both of
these situations at the same
time is to scale your images
to become a square.
The square should be less than
the height and width of all of
your images.
There's really no perfect way to
resize images with CSS, so
your best bet is to try to
resize them server side.
You can also provide image
uploading instructions for
your users inside of your CMS.
If you're dealing with fluid or
responsive layouts, Richard
Rutter has a good technique
for dealing with those
provided at link number one.
You've reached the end of level
six, good luck with the
challenges.
Time for me to go
do some moguls.