[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS Cross
Country, and this is Level 7,
Sprightly Slaloms.
In Level 7 we'll be
discussing image
replacement and CSS Sprites.
Now that we know when to use
images in our layout, let's
take a look at a logo that's
being added as a background
image in our CSS.
In this case, Sven's Snowshoe
Superstore has been doing
extremely well and is now Sven's
Snowshoe Emporium.
So on their website we're going
to include their logo as
a background image.
This type of example works,
but we're using an empty
element for the anchor tag in
which the logo is being added.
This is not best practice as, if
CSS is turned off, or if a
screen reader is trying to read
this, they won't be able
to tell what content
is on the image.
Let's go ahead and add the text
that appears on the image
to our element.
Now, as you might expect, that
text appears over top of our
image, which isn't desired.
But how can we fix this?
By using the text indent
property of CSS, we can move
the text out of the view port,
so we can still have the
placeholder text but have the
image replace that text.
Let's move on to CSS Sprites.
Let's take a look back at that
imaginary place, Sven's
Snowshoe Emporium logo, and
let's say we want to add a
hover state, which has
a second image there.
We have the initial code, and
we're adding a hover and focus
state for that logo that'll
show a second image when
either of those states occur.
This works fine, but when the
hover or focus state triggers
that second image has
to be loaded.
So we're making a second HTTP
request, and since that image
is not preloaded, there's going
to be a flash while that
image loads, which will look
something like this.
To combat this, let's combine
both of those logo
images into one file.
That logo is going to look
something like this, where the
total height of our new images
is 200 pixels, and the height
of each logo is 100 pixels.
Going back to our example, we're
going to replace that
hover and focus state image
with background position.
What background position will
allow us to do is change the
orientation of our image
inside of the element.
So, in this case, we'll add a
background position of zero
and negative 100.
The first value in our
background position property
will be the x-axis shift,
and the second
value, the y-axis shift.
With this background position
applied, when the user hovers
or focuses on our logo, the
orientation of the background
image will shift up 100 pixels
so our second version is shown
to the user.
Also of note, in our original
logo declaration I didn't need
to set the background position
because it defaults to zero
zero, which is the correct
orientation for the default
state of our logo.
When using sprites we have the
advantage of not needing a
second HTTP request, and we
don't need to worry about
using crazy means to
preload our images.
There are many examples on
the web of using sprites.
Here a few examples for
Gmail and GitHub.
Let's take a look at a
bit more complicated
example using sprites.
In this case, we have two
separate icons, one for
Twitter and one for GitHub, and
both will have their own
separate hover state.
Each of the icon parts will be
100 pixels wide and 100 pixels
tall, making for a total
image width and
height of 200 pixels.
Here's the initial bit of
code for our icons.
Let's set up our base code to
have two list items with
anchors inside that are set up
next to each other with a bit
of spacing in between.
This example is assuming that
you're using some sort of
reset on our list items,
otherwise you will need to
separately reset the default
styles for li's.
When this renders, as you can
see, we're just seeing the
text in both of those anchors.
Let's move on to our
image replacement.
First, we'll set up the shared
styles for both the Twitter
and GitHub icons using
image replacement.
As you can see, now we have the
Twitter icon for both, but
we need that GitHub icon to
appear in GitHub's place.
Using the background position
property, we can shift our
sprite 100 pixels to the left so
that the GitHub icon in its
resting state will have
the correct image.
Now we can add both hover and
focus states to each of the
Twitter and GitHub icons so
that, on hover, the images
will shift down 100 pixels
to show their
hover state like so.
There are a number of great
tools online for dealing with
sprites, including Sprite Cow.
Go ahead and visit link one
to learn more about that.
One last consideration in
dealing with imagery placement
is the base 64 method of
encoding images directly into
our CSS, HTML or JavaScript.
Using this method with syntax
that looks something like
this, you can directly encode
the images into our code and
that allows us to not need
to use sprites or include
separate images.
But it's only available for
versions of IE 8 or greater,
and if you'd like to learn more
about this, go ahead and
visit link two below.
That does it for Level 7.
While you're doing the
challenges, I'm off to stand
in line at the chairlift.
Good luck.