[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS Cross
Country and this is Level
Four, Grooming Your Code.
In this section, we're going to
talk about different ways
that you can clean up your CSS,
including Staying DRY,
knowing and understanding
display types, and a little
bit about horizontal
centering.
One of the fundamental ways that
you can clean up your CSS
is to be DRY.
In programming , the DRY acronym
stands for don't
repeat yourself, as it's a
practice that will save you
tons of time in declaring and
maintaining your styles.
Let's look at an example.
Suppose you want to include a
font property in a number of
text related elements.
One way you can do this is
to define each of them
individually, but this isn't
very DRY, because as you can
see we're having to repeat
ourself three times.
A better approach is to pull
this definition up
into the body tag.
This effectively makes your
font family your base font
family and every element within
your application will
inherit the style from
the body tag.
Obviously, if you don't want
your entire application to
inherit that style, you can just
target a specific parent
container instead.
If you have a number of text
related elements that don't
all fall within the same parent
container, you can
still declare these
in a DRY way.
All you need to do is just
pull them into a comma
delimited list and a declare
them once there.
This will allow you to declare
them all at one time and make
it easier for you to change
them all at the
same time later on.
Another method but you can use
to DRY up your CSS is called
selector abstraction.
To define what that means,
let's look at an example.
Here we have two classes that
are using exactly the same
declarations.
Now maybe we define these at
different points throughout
our application development
and we never went back and
refactored them, so obviously
what we need to do here is
just pull them into
one single class.
So we're going to pull these
into a single class called
button and then we're just going
to apply that button
class to both of our
button elements.
But what happens if
our buttons are
only mostly the same?
So I have my two buttons here
and maybe I want the input
button or submit button to use
a gray background color.
Well, what I can do is keep
our shared elements in the
button class and then add a
subclass called submit and
then we're just going to apply
that submit class to the
element in addition to
the button class.
Now the Submit button will be
pulling its styles from both
the button class the
submit subclass.
It's important to note that
order matters here, so if you
remember back to level one we
talked about cascade order.
And the reason that the submit
subclass is able to write the
background color from the button
class is because it
comes second in the
style sheet.
Another easy way to DRY up
your CSS is using property
shorthands.
So let's look at an example.
Here we have our ski_poles
class, which uses a number of
margin declarations.
Well, a quick way to DRY this
up is to just use the
shorthand syntax for margins,
which would look
something like this.
If you're not familiar with
the shorthand syntax for
properties like margin and
padding, it can just take a
bit of memorization.
The order goes top, right,
bottom, left.
Now let's just all say it
together one time--
top, right, bottom, left,
starting at the top of a clock
and going clockwise.
Notice when we're declaring our
zero bottom margin here,
we're not writing zero pixels.
We can just write zero
because zero units in
CSS do not need units.
Here's a list of some common CSS
shorthand properties, and
feel free to refer back to this
list at any point during
the course.
Notice that the syntax
for each of
these is slightly different.
Moving on, we're going to talk
about display types.
The display property in CSS
affects how elements behave
together on a page.
Just to review, the display
values are none, block, inline
inline-block, and a bunch of
others that we're not going to
cover in this course.
Let's go to Sven's Snowshoe
Superstore for an example.
Here in our code we have an
anchor tag that I want to
convert into a button.
Here's an example of what I want
the button to look like.
Now, if I don't know much about
display types, there are
a few things that I might
do to create our button.
I'm probably going to float the
button left so that it'll
pick up the top and bottom
margin and padding.
Then I'm going to apply a width
of 100% to it so that it
clears to a new line and
fills the full width
of its parent container.
Because our button is now
floating, I'm also going to go
back to that our clear fix class
to the parent container.
As you can see, this is a lot
of extra CSS and markup just
to create a button.
To do this better, let's
talk a bit more
about display types.
The first display type
that we're going to
talk about is block.
Block elements will stretch the
full width of their parent
container, behave as though
there's a line break before
and after the content, and allow
you to manipulate the
full box model.
In contrast, inline elements
are typically found within
block level elements.
They do not take up the full
width of their container, only
spanning the width of the
content inside of them, and
they do not generate
a line break before
and after their content.
Another option that you have is
inline-block, which is not
a default display type but
is something that can
be applied via CSS.
Inline-block elements behave the
same as inline elements in
that they only stretch the width
of their content but
they also behave the same as
block level elements in that
you can manipulate the full
box model on them.
So knowing what we know now
about display types, let's go
back to our button inside of
Sven's Snowshoe Superstore.
We can remove the float left and
the width of 100% from our
declaration and just add display
block, which will
achieve the same effect.
Because our button is no longer
floating, we can now
remove the group clear fix
class from our parent
container also.
As you can see, this leaves
us with a much cleaner and
concise markup in CSS
for our button.
The last thing that we're going
to talk about in this
section is a bit about
horizontal centering.
This is going to be brief, but
horizontal centering is a
common problem that trips
people up, so it's just
important to talk about it.
Depending on the display type
of the element, there are
different ways to horizontally
center it.
Let's look at an example first
of horizontally centering a
block level element.
One way that we could do this
badly is to apply a set left
margin to it.
In this manner, we're sort of
eyeballing the center of the
page and it looks fine, so we
could just leave it like this.
But what happens if the width
of that container changes or
if our user is using a different
size monitor?
Our element is no longer going
to be horizontally centered.
The correct way to horizontally
center a block
level element is to declare a
width on it and then apply a
left and right margin of auto.
This will horizontally center
our block level element
regardless of its width
and regardless of
the size of the monitor.
To horizontally center an
inline or inline-block
element, it's very simple.
You just need to apply
text-align center and it will
center it inside of its
block level parent.
Great job.
You've reached the end
of level four.
It's time to go play through
the challenges.
I'm off to go warm myself
by the fire.