[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS Cross
Country, and this is level 8,
Pseudo Sitzmark.
In level 8 we'll be
discussing pseudo
classes and pseudo elements.
Let's take a look at a common
design pattern.
In this example we have a list
of items, each with a border
of their own on the bottom.
But we want the last list item
to have that border removed.
If we like, we can manually, or
through logic, add a class
to the last item to remove the
border for us, but that's
adding an extra step.
With pseudo classes we won't
need to add that logic.
We can go ahead and remove the
last class, then use the last
child pseudo class to target the
last li in our lists, and
remove the border for us.
With pseudo classes we're able
to conditionally target items
based on their position or
their current state.
All pseudo classes start with
a colon, and you're probably
familiar with a few very common
ones like we used
earlier with hover and focus.
Let's take a look at another
example where using pseudo
classes can help simplify
our CSS.
In this case, we want to zebra
stripe our list items to have
different background colors.
Initially, we can have logic
manually add these classes for
us, but again, this
is a bit unwieldy.
Using the nth child pseudo class
of CSS, we can target
the even item specifically
without need for that extra
class, and our zebra striping
is achieved for us.
With nth child we also
have the ability
to target odd items.
So, if I change out even for
odd, we can quickly switch
which items are zebra striped.
Using nth child gives us a few
more options in selecting
these source of lists.
We're able to include a bit of
math with the formula an plus
b, which allows us to select
items grouped by numbers a,
starting at element b, which
would be zero if we don't
include a b.
Taking a look at things
we've already seen.
We can use this formula to
replicate even and odd.
Using 2n we would select
all even elements.
While using 2n plus 1 would
give us all odd elements.
If you'd like to select every
third element, you can use 3n.
fourth element, starting with
the fourth element, you
can use 4n plus 4.
There are a number of useful
pseudo classes, and we'll
touch on a few here.
As we said before, you're
probably familiar with the
link pseudo classes like hover,
focus, active and visited.
We've also looked at last child
and, similarly, we can
use first child and
only child.
Along with nth child, we also
have nth of type, which would
allow us to only select siblings
of a certain type
within a matched list.
If you'd like to learn more
about pseudo classes and the
support in different browsers
go ahead and visit links one
and two below.
Lastly, let's take a look
at pseudo elements.
Let's say I have an article, and
I want the last paragraph
of each article to
conclude with the
snowflake UTF character.
If I'd like, I can include that
manually at the end of
each last paragraph, and
it would show up as so.
But, this is a bit unwieldy.
If I ever wanted to change it,
or I wanted to remove it, I
would have to manually go in
and remove all of these.
Using the last child pseudo
element I can automatically
select the last paragraph for me
in CSS, then add the after
pseudo element.
Now, the pseudo element after
will allow me to add content
via the CSS content property.
In this case, I'm using the
escape text value for my UTF
snowflake to add it after that
last paragraph occurs.
So there are a few different
types of pseudo elements.
I've mentioned after, but
there's also before, which
works in much the same way.
Both of these require browsers
version IE 8 and greater.
And each of these requires you
to have a content property,
whether or not it's empty.
Also, we have the first letter
and first line pseudo
elements, which allows us to
target either the first
letter, or first line of
a block of content.
Either of these needs the
content property as an
argument to be used.
Let's take a look at something
a bit more useful
using pseudo elements.
In this case I have a block
quote, and inside is a span
that's using imagery placement
to position an image, this
decorative quote mark, five
pixels outside the left of our
block quote, and five pixels
outside the top
of our block quote.
Now, with this, again, I'm using
an empty element that
has no replacement text and is
very unwieldy should I need to
change this in the future.
Instead, let's change this to
use a before pseudo element.
Using before I can use all the
same properties, except I'll
need to add my content
properties so this shows.
In this case, the content will
be empty, since this is just a
decorative element.
And now we won't need an empty
element, and this decorative
quote mark will still
be included as part
of our block quote.
Pseudo elements are extremely
handy because they effectively
give us two extra places
per element to
add style or layout.
If you'd like to learn more
about the cool things you can
do with pseudo elements,
visit link three below.
You've reached the end of the
videos and now you're ready
for some black diamond runs.
I'll be waiting for
you at the end.
Good luck.