[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS Cross
Country, and this is level
two, Clear Carving.
In level two we'll be discussing
clearing our floats
and inheritance and
specificity.
So now that we've discussed the
float property, let's talk
about clearing those floats.
If the other items inside of a
container are in danger of not
extending beyond that of the
floated item, the parent
container isn't going to stretch
to match the height of
any floated items.
So we'll need to clear a float
if any floated items might
extend beyond that of the other
content that's not floating.
Similarly, if all of the content
inside of a container
is floating, we'll need to clear
that container as well.
Now, there are three main
ways to clear floats.
So the first of these methods
to clear floats is clearing
with the subsequent element.
What we'll do here is target
an element that falls after
any floated content and give it
that clear both property.
Once we clear with the
subsequent element, any floats
from the previous container
won't overlap the elements
inside of that subsequent
element.
Now this works to a degree
but has a few problems.
If you have to change the
sequence of elements later on,
it's going to mess
up this clear.
Also, if the initial parent
container that has the floated
item has a background or a
border, such as this, this
type of clearing isn't going
to allow that border or
background to extend to the
bottom of the container.
So let's move to our second way
of clearing floats, via a
manual clear.
Now with a manual clear we're
going to add an empty element,
as a sibling of any
floated items
in that parent container.
And this is going to allow us to
clear that container prior
to it finishing out, and it will
look something like this.
Now this works perfectly in
extending the border or
background of the parent
container so it stretches to
the height of any floated
elements, but it
also has some problems.
In this case, we're adding
an empty element to
achieve this clear.
If down the line we wanted this
to no longer float, we'd
have to go through and remove
all of these extra HTML
elements because they'd
no longer be needed.
So let's move on to the third,
and recommended, way to clear
our floats, via the clearfix.
Now, here's a bunch of code, and
don't worry too much about
how it works yet.
We're going to go into some
of these concepts
later on in the course.
For now know that clearfix
was developed back in
2007 by Tony Aslett.
This bit of code is refined by
Nicholas Gallagher, and what
it allows us to do is add this
group class to the parent
container to have itself
clear any floated
elements inside of it.
So if we go back to our example,
by adding the group
class to the parent element, we
no longer need a subsequent
element or an empty element to
clear the floats, and this
container will automatically
stretch to the height of any
floated elements.
Let's move on to inheritance
and specificity.
Now, in CSS, you need to
remember that when you set a
property on a parent element,
any other children elements
inside that parent are going to
inherit those styles unless
you override it.
So in this case, by setting
a style on the parent, the
paragraph inside is going to
inherit the color as well.
If you need to override these
inherited properties you can
use what's called a
nested selector.
So, in this case, we're adding
a nested paragraph to our
initial selector and set a
second color that will
override that of the first.
If you've been dealing with
CSS for a while you're
probably aware of situations
like this, where an ID and a
class selector are both
contending to set the same
property on an element.
But which wins out?
You're probably aware that the
ID selector will win out here.
But without trial and error, is
there an easy way to find
out which would win?
In CSS there is.
The way we do that is
with specificity.
Now, specificity is referring
to the priority of our
selector, and that can be
represented by a common
delimited list of four digits.
The fourth digit refers to the
total number of element
selectors and our
CSS selector.
The third digit refers
to the total
number of class selectors.
The second digit, the total
number of ID selectors.
And the first, whether or not
we have inline styles.
But what does this look
like in practice?
Here I have an example of a
simple element selector.
So my common delimited
list has a 1
in the fourth position.
Next we have a class selector.
It has a 1 in the third
digit position.
We can find out which one would
win out if they are
competing to apply a property to
an element via this common
delimited list now, by comparing
whether or not they
have a digit in a
higher position.
If we have an ID selector, then
there'll be a 1 in that
second position.
And if we an inline style,
there'll be a 1 in the first
position, meaning this
overrules the
previous three versions.
The important value added to a
property in CSS is going to
override all of these previous
examples, so it's important to
remember that the important
value shouldn't be used unless
absolutely necessary.
Let's take a look at a few more
complicated examples.
In this first selector
we have two classes
and one element selector.
And in the second we have two
classes and two elements.
So in this case, since the
highest priority digit, the
class selector, has the same
value it'll default back to
the element selector to
determine that the second
version would win out if they're
trying to apply the
same style.
Remember, though, that just
having one ID selector will
override both of these previous
examples no matter
how many class and element
selectors they have.
It's because of this it's
recommended in many cases to
try to keep the number
of ID selectors you
use down to a minimum.
If you'd like to learn
more about this
visit link one below.
Here's an example of how to
deal with a specificity.
In this case, we have a
container with an ID and that
ID is setting a color on
both of its paragraphs.
If we have a paragraph that has
a featured class, and we
want to give it a special
color via that class, we
simply can't use a class
selector to change the color
that's inherited from the
ID and element selector.
Well why is this?
If we look at the specificity
numbers, we can see that the
initial selector is so much more
specific than our simple
class selector that the class
selector will not win out over
that initial color
declaration.
The first way we can fix this
badly is via the important
property that we just
talked about.
This will make this second
declaration override the first
but, like we said, we're
completely overriding our
cascade order and creating
a maintenance nightmare.
Let's take a look at the correct
way to override the
initial rule.
We can nest our class selector
inside of an ID selector and
the specificity will be
increased as so, so that it
becomes the version that
is used by the browser.
That does it for level 2.
Good luck on the challenges.
I'll be out carving
up the slopes.