[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS Cross
Country and this is level one,
Frost-Proof Fundamentals.
In level one, we'll be
discussing how to add CSS, our
basic selectors, the cascade
order, and the float property.
Now, if this is a bit review
for you, go ahead and skip
ahead to the challenges.
We're trying to make sure
everyone's on the same page
before moving to the more
advanced materials.
First, let's start with how
we can add CSS to our
application.
Now, the easiest way to do this
is via the inline style
attribute in our HTML, and it's
very easy to do, but it's
a maintenance nightmare.
Second, is adding our styles
via the document head which
also works, but if we have
more than one page in our
document also a maintenance
nightmare.
So the main way to add your
styles is via including them
all in external style sheet and
having a link in the head
of every page of
your document.
This is how we're going to treat
all the styles in this
course so assume everything
is on its own
separate style sheet.
Moving on there are three basic
selectors we're going to
cover in CSS Cross Country and
these are the element, class,
and ID selectors.
There are a number of more
selectors to deal with but
we're not going to cover them
in depth in the course.
If you'd like to learn more,
visit link one below this
video to learn more about things
like the child and
sibling selectors.
So the first of these basic CSS
selectors is the element
selector and just to review,
that's directly mapping the
HTML tag to your CSS
declaration.
We're also able to select items
via the class attribute
with a class selector.
Finally, the ID selector allows
us to select items via
their ID attribute.
We also have the ability to
combine more than one of these
selectors together to
create a compound
selector like this one.
So let's talk about
the cascade order.
In CSS there are two different
cascades to contend with, the
first being where the styles are
found in your application.
Now, in order of increasing
priority, styles found in the
external style sheet can
be overridden by
the same style set
in the document head, can be
overridden by the same style
set inlinen can be overridden
by items marked important.
We'll go into why important
is a bad idea later in the
course, but just know that
since we're including
everything as though it's an
external style sheet, we won't
have to contend with things
found in the head
or in inline styles.
So the second cascade we have
to contend with is where the
property is actually declared
in our style sheet.
In this case, we have two intro
declarations setting colors.
Via the cascade, the second
color set will be the one that
is applied to the element.
It's important to remember
that these properties are
additive if they
don't conflict.
When things are shown to the
user, everything is going to
combine together, so if we have
more than one declaration
setting different properties
these will add
together later on.
So to round off level
one, let's talk
about the float property.
Now, you've probably used the
float property at some point
and seen something like this.
In this case, we're going to go
ahead and float our image
to the left, and that's going
to have the rest of the
content wrap around
that image.
But what is this
actually doing?
Now, when we float something
it's going to take that object
out of normal document flow and
push it to the specified
edge of its parent container.
Any other sibling content in
that container is going to
wrap around our floated item.
Now, the float property allows
us to define whether that item
should be on the left or right
or, if we want to remove a
float, we can declare none.
Floated items are going to stack
up against one another
until they reach a parent edge
at which point, they'll break
down to the next
available edge.
So in this case, if we have
three containers floating up
against one another, but the
parent width becomes too small
to contain all three, the final
object is going to break
down to a new line.
You have to take care though
when you have multiple things
floating with different
heights.
In this case, since the first
items height is greater than
that of the other two elements,
when one of the
other elements breaks to new
line the first available edge
is up against that first
item rather than all
the way at the bottom.
It's also important to consider
that since we can
float things left and right at
the same time, the order in
which they appear in the HTML is
important to know which one
will break through new
line, if necessary.
In this case, we have two
images, one floating left and
one floating right, if the
parent container is too small
to contain both of them on the
same line since the sled image
appears second in our HTML it's
going to break down below
the ski image should any
collision happen.
When multiple items are floated
right and stacking up
against one another, these
items are going to
float right to left.
So the first item in your HTML
will be the one that's found
on the far right.
So that does it for level one.
If you haven't already, please
go ahead and download the
slides on the sidebar.
They're going to prove to be an
invaluable resource to help
you move through
the challenges.
Also, please use the hints
if you get stuck.
We don't want you to get
stuck on any one
problem for too long.
Good luck.