[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching CSS
Cross-Country and this is
level five, CSS Safety.
In this level, we're going to
talk about a couple of ways to
deal with user-generated content
and dynamic content,
including protecting your
layout and dealing with
specificity problems.
Let's look at an example
of a basic page layout.
Here we have a header, a
feature, and a body section.
And we've spaced these elements
apart by applying a
margin to the feature section.
This works fine, but what
happens if one of the sections
is removed?
When we remove the feature
section, you can see that this
breaks the layout.
This isn't so good.
This probably isn't the
best way that we
should define our layout.
A better way to space out our
three elements is to apply a
margin to all three of them.
That way, when we remove one of
the sections, you can see
that it does not break
the layout.
We have a consistent margin
throughout our entire page.
When defining margins on
subsequent elements, there's
an important thing that you
should keep in mind.
Something called margin
collapsing can come into play,
and it will affect your margins
in a way that you
might not expect.
For example, you might expect
to see a 60 pixel margin
between your header and your
feature section, because you
have a bottom margin of 40 on
your header, and a top margin
of 20 on your featured
section.
But what will actually happen
is the margin will end up
becoming the larger
of the two values.
So in this case, you will
actually end up with a 40
pixel margin, instead of a 60
pixel margin, because the
margins will collapse.
Likewise, where you might
expect a 30 pixel margin
between feature and body, you're
going to end up with 20
pixels, because that is
the larger of the two.
Collapsing margins will not
occur when one or more of your
elements has padding or border,
relative or absolute
positioning, or a float
left or right.
For more information on
collapsing margins, see link
number one below.
Now we're going to expand on
some of the specificity issues
that we talked about earlier
in the course.
When dealing with user generated
content, specificity
issues can come up often.
Let's look at an example.
Here we have some list items
that were defined according to
the specs of a mock-up.
This works fine, as long as this
list stays only within
the sidebar section.
But what happens if we want to
recreate this list item style
within a different section?
The only way that we can reuse
these styles is by copying and
pasting them, but that
isn't very DRY.
Instead, what we can do is
remove the specificity from
our declaration.
So instead of declaring sidebar
ul li, we can just
declare ul li.
This will allow us to apply this
style to any list item
throughout our document.
However, if we don't want it to
apply to every list item in
our document, what we can do is
declare a class that we can
apply to any unordered
list that we want
to inherit the style.
But wait, what about our
other list items?
Now that we have a class that we
need in order for our list
items to inherit the style,
what happens if unordered
lists are inserted by another
user, or another developer,
throughout the course
of the application?
After doing this, we still need
to go back and declare an
unspecific list item style.
This will allow us to have a
default style in place for any
list items that are added later
throughout the course of
the application.
This is a good time to
talk about resets and
normalization.
It's a good idea to have default
styles in place for
most of your HTML elements and
account for inconsistencies
across browsers.
Some good resources can be found
at links number two and
three below.
You have reached the
end of level five.
It's time to ski down to the
level five challenges.
I'll meet you on the slopes,
but first I have to go look
for my prescription goggles.