[SONG PLAYING]
Your client-side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add
structure, but it
won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for the Anatomy
Backbone.js at code school.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone.js.
My name is Eric Allam.
And in this level we're going
to be going over Level 4:
Models and Views and how they
work together in a little bit
more detail.
So let's review our model view
that Greg developed for us in
the last level.
As you can see, we have
our template here.
And we have our render
function.
And we can define a new instance
of that view passing
in the model, render it, and
then when we look at the
output of the element, we'll
have just simple
with an h3
So what if we wanted to add
a check box to this view?
So we can change the template
and add a input of
"type=checkbox".
And we're also going to make
sure that if the status of our
TodoItem is complete, we'll go
ahead and print ("checked").
So our check box is checked.
And then we'll finish off with
putting our description there
like before.
So we have our check
box in our view.
But now we want to update
our model when
that check box changes.
So how do we do that?
So if you remember this diagram
from Level 1, you can
see that our models provide
the views with the data.
And then it's the view's
responsibility
to build the HTML.
So we can also go
the other way.
When a DOM event happens, it is
the view's responsibility
to handle that and
update the model.
Now that the model has
the new data, it
can update the server.
Now let's jump back into
our TodoView class and
define a new event.
Whenever an input inside of this
view changes, we want to
call the toggleStatus function
which would look
something like this.
In our toggleStatus function
we have our model.
And we want to check if
its status is already
"incomplete." We'll set it to
"complete." And, otherwise,
we'll set the status
to "incomplete."
So as you can see, this isn't
the best code though.
We have a lot of model
logic in our view.
But we can fix that pretty
easily by a simple refactor.
We'll update our view's
toggleStatus: function to call
a model function of
the same name.
So we need to go back into our
TodoItem model and define this
toggleStatus: function.
As you can see, it's doing
the exact same thing as
it was in the view.
Although now we don't have
to call this.model.
We can just call this.get
and this.set.
And now our code is better
because our model logic stays
in the model and out
of the view.
As you can imagine, we could
call the model's toggleStatus
function from other places in
our app, and it would do the
right thing.
We want to sync this change to
the server whenever we call
toggleStatus on the model.
So there's a good place
to put our save call--
which we'll do to PUT request
to the todos/ID,
in this case 1.
Let's say that whenever our
model status is complete, we
want it to look like this with
a strike through and
a light gray text.
How do we do that?
Our designer has given us some
CSS to make this happen.
So to make this work, let's
change our template and add a
class on to our h3
And that class will be set to
whatever the model status is.
Now whenever our model's status
is set to complete, our
new styles will be applied
correctly.
But how do we update our view
when the model changes like
we've seen in the last
couple of slides?
We could go back into the view's
toggleStatus function
and just call render
after we've
toggled the model's status.
And that'll do what
we want, right?
But what would happen if our
model changed somewhere else
in our app, like in a sidebar
button that checked all
of our items off?
This wouldn't work.
We need some way to notify our
view whenever the model
changes and re-render.
Does that sound familiar?
We can use model events like
we saw in Level 2 to notify
the view whenever our
model changes.
And then, our view can re-render
and update the DOM.
Let's see that in action.
Back in our TodoView
class, let's add
an initialize function.
Now this function is going to
be called whenever a new
instance of the TodoView
is created.
Inside of this function
we can listen for any
changes on the model.
And when that change event is
triggered, we call the render
function on the view.
You might be wondering about
that third argument--
the "this" we're passing
into the on function.
Let's look at an example of
listening for the change event
of the model without passing
in that third argument.
And then we'll look at what
changes when we do pass in
that third argument.
So here's our render
function.
As you can see, we're using the
keyword "this" inside of
the function.
What the "this" refers to is the
context of the function as
it is called.
As you can see, we're going to
want the "this" to point to
our TodoView instance.
And usually this isn't
a problem.
But because of the way we listen
to the change event on
the model, when that change
event is triggered, the
render function is going
to be called with
the incorrect context.
In fact, it's going to be called
with the window context
which is the global object.
So now in our render function,
"this" will equal
"window" which is obviously
not what we want.
When we add that third argument
back in, its telling
Backbone that when it triggers
the change event and calls the
render function, it should set
the context of the render
function to the todoView
instance.
So when render is called, the
"this" will be set to the
TodoView instance, and
thus will work.
Just like we listened to the
model's change event and we
re-rendered the view, we also
are going to want to listen to
the model's destroy event
and remove the
view from the document.
To make this work, we have to
define the remove: function.
And all that does is remove
the element from the view.
Now let's watch this
in action.
I've already rendered my
TodoView onto the page.
And now I have my todoItem,
and I want to update it.
And as you can see, we're
updating the description to
"Pick up milk and cookies."
And when that
gets submitted our
DOM is updated.
And now I just want to
destroy todoItem.
And I want to see that go
away just like that.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
That about does it
for Level 4.
Have fun in the challenge
area.
And I'll see you back here
in Level 5 when we add
collections.