[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching The Anatomy
of Backbone.js.
And this is Level 1, where we're
going to talk about why
you might want to use
Backbone.js in an application,
and we'll walk through
a sample application.
We're going to create a really
simple todo app.
It's going to look something
like this.
Simple because it only can
have one todo item.
It's a feature, not a bug.
And we'll explain why
that is later.
So if we were to build this todo
app, and we want it to be
very responsive on the client
side, we might call getJSON to
fetch some JSON data, which we
can then load onto the page
for our first to do item.
The JSON return might look
something like this.
And we can use that to render
out our first to do item.
Now, this is all fine and good
until we start adding a lot of
functionality to our
application.
We might have a bunch
of JavaScript
functions flying around.
We might need to check
off the to do button.
We might need to
add deadlines.
We might want to reorder and
sort our one to do item.
Don't ask.
And before we know it, we might
have a very disorganized
application.
We might have all these methods
flying around and no
structure to it.
That's the first problem.
The second problem is that we
might lose the data structure
inside of the DOM.
Allow me to explain that in
a little more detail.
See, the data is coming from our
server back to the client.
There's our JSON again.
And we're going to load
that into our HTML.
You can see each of the pieces
are right there.
Now, this is fine if we
just want to load
stuff onto the page.
But as soon as we want to
interact with that data, add
functionality, check off to do
items, send data back to the
server, back to the client,
we need the JSON data.
We need, almost, a data
structure, or an
object, or a model.
This is where Backbone
comes in.
Backbone.js was created by
Jeremy Ashkenas, who believes
in getting your truth out of
the DOM, meaning don't lose
your data inside of the DOM
when you should, instead,
abstract it, maybe,
into a model.
Backbone.js provides a
client-side structure for all
those functions so we can
keep those organized.
It provides models to represent
the data structures
inside of our views.
It has views to hook up the
models into the DOM, which
we'll see later.
And lastly, it takes care of
synchronizing our data to and
from the server.
So here's our server
and our client.
And our client's a browser.
And we're going to add another
layer inside of
here called our model.
So let's create our
first model class.
It's going to be called
TodoItem, and it's going to be
extended from the Backbone
model base class.
Pay close attention here
to the capitalization.
We're going to capitalize the
first letter of each word when
we're declaring a class.
Now let's create a model
instance from our
class called todoItem.
We're going to send in
a JSON object for the
attributes of our model.
Notice, again, the
capitalization.
The first letter of the first
word here is lower cased.
Now let's move our model up to
the top and talk a little bit
about how we get and set
data into our model.
We can call a get function to
get data out of our model.
To set an attribute, we can call
the set method and send
in a JSON object.
To synchronize the data that we
have client-side with the
server, we can call
the save function.
Obviously, we're going to need
some configuration to really
make this happen, because we
don't know what the end point
on the server is for this
particular piece of data.
We're not going to get
into that this level.
That'll be next level, when
we talk more about models.
So on the client side,
we have models which
encapsulate our data.
Those models provide the
data for the views.
And it's the view's
responsibility to build the
HTML, which, then, we might
put back into the DOM.
To create a view class, we're
going to create a TodoView.
Notice, again, the
capitalization.
And that is going to
extend from the
Backbone view base class.
To create a view instance, just
like we created a model
instance, we're going to create
todoView, which is
going to instantiate a new
TodoView instance.
And we're going to send in the
model that we created on the
previous slide.
We need our view to render out
some HTML for our TodoItem.
To do that, we need to define
the render function.
Inside the render function,
we're going to get our
description out of the model
and create some HTML.
We're then going to set the
HTML of that view element.
Now, every view instance has
its own view element.
That's that EL for element.
So a single instance is
associated with an element,
which means it's a HTML
tag of some sort.
It could be a div, which
it is by default.
But it also could be a
paragraph, an li, a header, or
whatever you want it to be.
Now, when we instantiate
the view, we
call that render function.
We can then print out the
resulting HTML to the console
by just calling todoView.el.
So now that you've got a brief
glimpse into the model and
view layer inside Backbone, it's
time to get your hands
dirty with some challenges.
Don't worry about all
the details that
are going on here.
In level 2 and level 3, we're
going to go into models and
views in more detail.
For now, get your hands dirty
with some challenges and have
some fun putting up
some Backbone.
[MUSIC PLAYING]