[SINGING]
Your client-side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add
structure, but it
won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data and the models
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone.js.
This is Level 7:
Routers and History.
So we have a little problem
in our app right now.
As you can see, over to the
right of each item, we have a
little link.
And we want that link to take us
to a page that'll show just
that one item.
But we don't want to refresh
the whole page.
We actually just want to use a
little bit of JavaScript, as
you can see here--
using something like jQuery to
just show that one item.
Let's see what happens when we
implement this link using
plain jQuery.
When I click on the link, I am
shown just that one item.
But now let's say I want to hit
the Back button to go back
to the full list. Well when I
do that, I'm actually taken
out of the entire app
back to Google.
This is not what we want.
And, actually, Backbone has this
problem solved with the
router and history.
First, let's introduce
Backbone's router.
Now the router's job is to
map URLs to actions.
As you can see here, we're
creating a new router.
And we're going to pass
in a routes object.
This is going to map a URL
to a single action.
In this case, when the URL
todos, the action will be
index. And that index:
function is
defined on the router.
So when the URL in your browser
is say, /todos or
#todos, the index action
will be called.
If you're unfamiliar with that
hash mark syntax, we're going
to cover it a little
bit later.
Let's dive a little bit more
into that routes object.
As you can see here, we're
defining a new route,
and that's going to match
todos/:id and call the
show action.
But this id is actually
a parameter.
It can be anything.
For example, it could be
/todos/1, /todos/2,
/todos/hello.
And that parameter that is
matched will actually get
passed to the show action.
Let's look at a couple more
route matchers that you can
use in your routers.
Our first one here is going
to match search/:query.
For example, search/ruby.
And that'll pass that one
parameter into the action.
The second one will actually
match two parameters--
the first one being query
and the second one being
page, And both of those will
get passed to the action.
Same kind of thing with the
third example here where both
name and mode will get
passed to the action.
And then there's a wild card
matcher which will match
everything after a
certain point.
So in this example,
hello/world.txt will get set
as the only parameter
to the action.
Now you may be wondering how
do we trigger these routes.
Well we can use the router's
navigate function.
With that all we have to
do is pass in the URL
as the first argument.
And if we actually want to
trigger the action, we pass in
trigger: true.
If we didn't pass in trigger:
true here, the browser URL
would update, but our action
would not be called.
And, of course, we can just
use normal links.
Unfortunately, these aren't
actually going to work yet.
And before we show you how to
fix it, let's go back and see
how people have solved this
history problem before.
You may be familiar with using
the Gmail web client.
And they solve history by using
that hash mark thing
that I was showing
you earlier.
As you can see here, when I
click on the Starred, we're
not actually doing a
whole page refresh.
But we are changing the
URL to #starred.
And this way when you click
Back, it's not actually going
to take you back all the way.
It's just going to take you back
to where you were before
you clicked Starred.
Now Basecamp Next does this a
little differently but in a
similar way.
Instead of using that hash mark
that Gmail used, they
actually use a new HTML5
API called pushState.
And this lets them update
the browser URL.
And instead of using
a hash mark, it
uses the regular slash.
So it looks like a real URL.
Backbone will actually let you
do both of these approaches to
saving history in the browser.
But I would suggest
using pushState.
Now browser support isn't
great right now.
But it's really close.
And there's a lot of advantages
to using pushState
as I'll go over later.
Let's go back to our
Backbone code.
As we saw earlier, our navigate
and our links weren't
working yet.
Now to make these work, we first
have to use the backbone
history API.
All we have to do is call
Backbone.history.start():
And as you can see here, if
we call start with no
parameters pushState
is going to be off.
And our URLs are going
to have that hash
mark in front of them.
And this is not great.
Instead when you call
start you can pass
in .
And now when we navigate on our
router, we'll have a slash
in front of our URL instead
of that hash mark.
Let's take these concepts and
implement our Todo app router.
Here we're creating a router
class much like we did with
models and collections
and views.
When we create that class, we
pass in a routes object.
And we're going to start out
by defining the show action
which'll match on todo/:id
Now let's define that
show action
accepting the id as a parameter.
And we're going to call this
focusOnTodoItem function on a
todoList collection.
This focusOnTodoItem function
has already been defined.
And all it will do is to reset
the collection to show only
the TodoItem that matches the
id that is passed in.
But you might be wondering
where we're getting that
todoList from.
Well I'm going to define
an initialize
function on our router.
This function takes an options
object and will assign the
TodoList to the router
from the options.
Now when we create our
TodoRouter instance.
We pass in an object with
TodoList collection.
What happens if after the user
goes to the show action,
they hit the Back button?
Well they're going to end up
back on the root route which
has no URL.
So we need to define the root
route on our router.
We do that by just using an
empty string as seen here.
And we want to call the index
action when the root
route is matched.
Now when we define our index
action all we're going to do
is call fetch on
the collection.
And this will get all the
todoItems from the server and
display that to the user.
Now let's see our router
in action.
As you can see here, we've got
a list of todoItems. And when
I click on that link, I'm shown
just that one todoItem.
And our URL in the browser
has been updated.
Now when I hit the Back button,
I'm going to go back
to the root route, and my list
is going to refresh.
And I can click on other links
and go back and forth.
And the history works
as we expect.
To finish it all up, we can use
our router as a good place
to organize some of the code
that we've been writing.
Instead of defining a whole new
router class, since we're
only really going to have one
router instance, let's just go
ahead and create the router
instance directly.
Now we have our routes that
matches are root route to the
index action and our
todos/:id to the show
action just like before.
When we initialize our router,
we will go ahead and create a
new TodoList collection.
Then we will create our TodoList
view and pass in that
collection.
The last thing we need to do in
initialize is append that
collection views element
to our DOM.
We're going to define a new
function called start.
And all that's going to do is
call back our history start
with pushState: true.
Next our index function which
we've seen before, and our
show function as well.
The really neat thing about
using our router to organize
our code this way is when our
page first loads, we can use
the jQuery ready function.
And all we have to do is
call TodoApp.start.
And that'll start our whole
app and everything will be
initialized.
And we'll be good to go.
Well that's it for Level 7:
Routers and History.
I hope you enjoyed the course.
Now you have some
more work to do.
But I'm out of here.