[MUSIC PLAYING]
Your client-side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add
structure, but it
won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for the Anatomy
of Backbone JS.
At Code School.
You're watching the anatomy
of Backbone JS.
And this is Level Five:
Collections.
So far in our to-do app,
we've gotten a lot of
feedback from our users.
And they want to do more
than one thing at once.
So they want a to-do list
instead of just one item.
So how do we handle
this in Backbone?
We could create a couple model
instances and then
stick that in an array.
And then we could loop
over that array and
put them in the DOM.
But there's a better way
to do it in Backbone.
We could use collections.
Here we're defining a TodoList
collection class just
like we've done with
models and views.
The only thing we have to do is
make sure we specify which
model the collection
is managing, in
this case, TodoItem.
And then we can create a new
instance of the TodoList
collection and have this
manage a set of models.
Here are a couple things we
can do with collection
instances, like get the number
of models inside using length.
We can add a model instance
using add.
We can get a model instance at
a certain index using at.
And that will return
a model instance.
We can get a model instance
by its ID.
And we can remove a model
instance using remove.
But let's say we want to
populate a collection with
models in bulk.
How do we do that?
Well, collections have a reset
function where all we have to
do is pass in an array of
objects, and each one of those
objects will become
a todoItem.
Now our TodoList collection
has three todoItems in it.
But how do we populate our
TodoList collection with
data from the server?
First thing, let's go back to
our TodoList collection
class and specify a URL.
Now when we call the fetch
function from the TodoList
collection, Backbone will go
ahead and make a get to the
/todos URL and populate
our collection with
data from the server.
And now our todoList
has two items in it.
Just like we can listen to
events on a model, we can also
listen to events on our
collection instance.
Here we are listening to
the event name, event.
And whenever that event is
triggered, we're calling an
alert, just like in our models.
Collections in Backbone
also have special
events just like models.
For instance, we can listen
to the reset event on our
collection.
And that is triggered whenever
fetch or reset is called.
If we don't want the event to
be triggered, we can pass in
silent: true to fetch end reset,
and that won't trigger
the reset event.
We can also remove the event
listener with off.
Just like on model instances,
we can listen to an event on
the collection by passing in the
event name followed by the
function that we want
to be called when
the event is triggered.
Some of the built-in events that
Backbone provides us is
add, which is called whenever
a model is added to the
collection.
Remove, which is called when
a model is removed from the
collection.
And as we saw earlier, the reset
event, which is called
whenever the collection
is reset or fetched.
Now there's a special case
with the Add and Remove
events, as shown here:
When the event function is
called, it passes in the model
that was either added
or removed.
On collections we can also
listen to events that are
triggered on models.
So for instance, we can listen
to the change event on any
model that is inside
of our collection.
We can also listen to the change
attribute, the destroy,
the sync, the error,
and the all.
And those will all be triggered
on our collection
whenever they're triggered
on the model.
Now that we have a set of
models, we're probably going
to want to do some iteration.
First, let's set up our
collection using reset with a
couple of items. Now as you can
see here, we can call forEach
on the todoList, pass
in a function, and that
function will be called with
each item in the collection.
So here what we're doing is
alerting each model's
description, which will look
something like this.
Backbone provides collections
with many different iteration
functions, one of them being
map, which just like forEach
takes a function that is going
to be called with each item in
the collection.
But this time it's going to
build a new array based off
the return items of
that function.
So in this example, we're going
to have an array of two
descriptions.
We can also use the filter
function to create a new array
with only the items that return
true from the function.
There are many other iteration
functions you can use on
collections.
And these are provided by the
underscore library, the same
one that gives us our
template function.
And that's about it
for level five.
Have some fun in the
challenge area.
We'll see you back here for
level six when we talk about
collections and views
together.
[MUSIC PLAYING]