[SINGING]
Your client-side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to
add structure.
But it won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess it's time for the Anatomy
of Backbone.js at Code School.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone.js.
And this is Level Six:
Collections and Views.
In the last level, we learned
about collections.
But now we're going to
want to show those
collections to the user.
And that's where collection
views come in.
So in this level, we're going
to build something
that looks like this.
But first let's review
our model view.
As you can see, we've
defined it here
with the render function.
Then when we create a new
todoItem and pass it into a
new todoView instance we
can render it out.
And we'll get the HTML.
As you may have noticed, our
models and views have a one to
one relationship.
That means that our model
has one view and our
view has one model.
With the collection views,
that's not really the case.
Since our collection view has
many models, it's also going
to have many views.
That's because the collection
view delegates to the model
views to actually
render the HTML.
The collection view doesn't
render any of its HTML itself.
Defining a collection view is
just the same as a model view.
Here we're creating a TodoList
view and then creating a new
instance of that view.
But this time, instead of
passing in a model, we're
passing in a collection.
Let's take our first crack at
writing the collection views
render function.
So we have our collection
in render.
And we want to go through each
model in the collection.
And we're going to use
forEach for that.
Inside of our forEach loop,
we're going to create a
todoView for each model.
And then we're going to render
each todoView and take that
view's element and
append it to our
collection view's element.
There's a problem with
this code, though.
Earlier we saw when we listen to
events on a collection or a
model, we sometimes have to pass
in a context parameter.
And it works the same
way with forEach.
So here whenever this function
is called inside of forEach
it's going to have the
wrong context.
So let's do a little refactoring
to fix this.
First, we're going to add a new
function called addOne.
This is going to do what out
forEach loop was doing before
except now it's its
own function.
Then we update the render
function and pass the addOne
function to forEach.
We also have to add a second
argument to forEach to make
sure the context of addOne
is called on the view.
Let's see this render
in action.
First, we'll create a new
instance of the collection
view passing in our todoList
collection.
Then we render it.
And when we print it out to the
console, you can see that
we've got both model views
inside of the collection
view's top level element.
What's going to happen, though,
when we try to add a
new todoItem to our
collection?
Right now, it's not going
to update the view.
We have to change our collection
view first. Let's
add an initialize function
to our collection view.
And just like we did with the
model views, we'll listen to
the add event.
And whenever that add event is
triggered, we'll call the
addOne function.
And we won't forget our
third parameter.
Now when we add our new todoItem
to the todoList, our
view will be updated.
So now let's see
that in action.
Here we've already got a
couple todoItems in our
collection already
on the view.
And we're going to go on the
console and add a new todoItem
with a description and status.
And as you can see, the
view has been updated
with our new todoItem.
And let's just see that again.
Instead this time, let's change
the status to complete
and give it a different
description.
And we can see that it
works correctly.
Just like adding a new item to
the collection at first didn't
update our DOM, right now, if we
fetch a bunch of new items
from the server, our DOM isn't
going to get updated.
When we call fetch on the
collection, it's going to fire
the reset event.
We can listen to this event in
the collection view and call
this new function addAll when
that event is fired.
Now all we have to do is define
addAll, which pretty
much just does what render was
doing before and update render
to use the addAll function.
Let's see the reset
event in action.
So to start, we're going to
take our collection view.
And we're going to render it.
Then we're going to add the
collection view's top level
element into the DOM.
So now when we get our
collection and call fetch
on it, it's going
to fetch the new
data from the server.
And when that reset event
is fired, it's going
to update the DOM.
There is one problem, though.
Let's say we try to remove an
item from the collection.
Shouldn't that remove
it from the view?
Well, as you can see here, it's
not updating the view.
To fix this problem, we're
actually not going to need to
touch the collection
view at all.
And I'll show you how
using custom events.
We know that, when we remove an
item from the collection,
the remove event is triggered.
When we remove an item from a
collection, we don't actually
destroy the item.
If we do destroy it, it would
have removed it from the view.
But that's not what we want.
So instead let's use
custom events.
In our todoList collection,
we're going to define the
initialize function.
And we're going to say, whatever
the remove event is
fired on this collection
instance, call hideModel.
Now we define the hideModel
function.
And as you remember
from level five.
The function is going
to accept the
model that is removed.
So now, inside of our hideModel
function, we're going to
trigger a new custom event
called hide on that model.
And then we can open up our
TodoItem view and listen for
that hide event.
And whenever that is triggered,
we can remove the
view from the DOM.
Bringing it all together,
let's see
it work in our browser.
So here we have our three items.
And we're going to
remove the first item
from the collection.
In using those hide events,
it's going to remove the
single item from the view.
That's it for Level Six:
Collections and Views.
Good luck in the
challenge area.
We'll see you back here for the
last level, level seven,
where we'll be going over
routers and history.