[SINGING]
Your client-side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add structure,
but it won't
take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models,
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
You're watching the Anatomy
of Backbone.
And this is level two, where
we're going to take a look at
Backbone models in a little
bit more detail.
So remember from level
one, we defined a
model class, like so.
We then defined a model
instance like this.
Then to get an attribute,
we would call get.
To set an attribute,
we would call set.
So in order to do page loads,
the first thing we're going to
want to do is to fetch the JSON
data from the server.
How would we do that
in Backbone and
load it into our model?
So here's our
todoItem instance.
We can set the URL to get JSON
by setting the url property.
And then, we can populate the
model from the server by
calling .fetch.
This is going to go to that URL,
pull down the JSON, load
that into our model, and then
we can call get to get that
data out of our model.
Now the URL that we have
here, /todo, isn't a
very good URL, right?
Because we're talking about
one todoItem, and we're
calling /todo.
So how might we fix that?
How might we do this in
a more RESTful way?
Well, if we go back into how we
define our model class, we
can specify a URL root.
By default, it's going to
use that URL to get
data from our server.
And it's going to interact with
our server in a RESTful
way using sort of the Rails
flavored version of REST.
To fetch the todo with ID of
1, we simply send the ID
when we define our
todo instance.
To fetch the data for the to
do, we just call fetch.
That's going to do a get request
to the todo/1 URL.
It's going to return the
JSON and populate the
instance with that data.
To update the todoItem
on our client, we
call the set command.
And then, if we want to
synchronize that with the
server like we saw before,
we call the save command.
And in this case, it's going
to do a put request to the
todo/1 URL and send the
JSON parameters
with the model data.
What about when we want to
create a new todoItem?
What might that look like?
Here, we define a
new instance.
We set the data.
We're going to set
the description.
Save the todoItem.
And that's going to do a POST
request to /todos with the
JSON parameters.
We can see that this todoItem
was properly created on
the server, because when we call
get ID, we get back the
number two.
Then, if you want to destroy
this todoItem, we can simply
call destroy.
And that sends a delete request
to the todos/2 URL.
If we ever want to get the JSON
object out of our model,
like maybe when we want to
render it into the view later,
we can call toJSON.
Another nice option when we're
defining the TodoItem class
is the ability to specify
default values.
So here you can see, we're
setting defaults for both the
description and the
status attributes.
So now, when we create a new
todoItem, and we call get
description or get status, it
returns the default values.
One of the unifying concepts
of Backbone.js
is the use of events.
And the first place we see this
is at the model layer.
So here, you can see we're
defining an event.
Event can be named anything.
So here you can see we're
listening for an event called
event-name on our to
do item instance.
When the event-name event gets
triggered, we're going to call
a function here which
will call an alert.
To trigger this event, we can
just call trigger event-name.
This may look really familiar
if you already
write lots of jQuery.
Now Backbone models already come
with some special events
that will get triggered
on their own.
The most common one you're
going to see
is the change event.
So here we're saying listen for
some changes to our model.
And when that happens, call
the doThing function.
Our doThing function might
be declared elsewhere.
And you can see it just
gets called here.
If we called set on our
todoItem, and we changed an
attribute, this would
automatically get triggered.
If you wanted to set the
attribute without triggering
the event, we could send in the
silent parameter like so.
And if we want to remove the
event listener, we can just
call off instead of on.
To listen for an event, we
called the on function and
send in an event and a method.
What are the special events?
Well, the built-in events that
come with Backbone include the
change event that we just saw.
We can listen for a change
in a specific attribute.
We can listen for when the model
gets destroyed, when it
synchronized with a server,
when there's an error.
And finally, we can listen for
when any event is triggered
using the all event.
So now we've talked
a little bit more
about Backbone models.
It's time to jump into
the challenges.
And when you come back, we'll
talk about Backbone views.