[MUSIC PLAYING]
-Your client-side JavaScript
is starting to mold.
It's starting to resemble
a bad spaghetti code.
And it is time to add structure
but it won't take too long.
Gotta get your truth
out of the DOM.
Take your data into models
and you cannot lose.
We'll render out your models
with the help of the views.
And if you don't want your
JavaScript to end up like a
mess, it's time for
the Anatomy of
Backbone.js at Code School.
[END MUSIC]
You're watching The Anatomy of
Backbone, and this is level
three where we're going to take
a closer look at views.
So here, let's define a
SimpleView class, nothing in it.
Now, let's define an instance
from that class.
And at this point, if we print
out to the console the el
property, we're going to see
that it's simply a blank div.
Remember, by default, that
el is just a div.
Every view has a top
level element.
If we want to change that top
level element, we can specify
the tag name when we
define the class.
Here, we're setting the
tag name to li.
So when we print out the
el, we get a blank li.
That tag name can be any HTML
element that you want.
It could be an li, it could be
an unordered list. It could be
a section or an article
or a footer.
Now, let's jump back to our
TodoView where we're going
to set its tag name equal to
an article, its ID equal to
todo-view, and its class
name equal to todo.
If we printed out the el
property, it would look
something like this.
If we were using the jQuery
framework with Backbone-- and
you don't have to, but
you most likely are--
and we want to get the HTML from
our todoView, one way we
could do it is by calling this
function you see here.
However, there's a better
way to do in Backbone.
That el is a DOM Element.
So we can wrap that in the
jQuery function and simply
call .html on it.
Backbone actually gives
us a better sort of
shortcut to do this.
We can call simply
todoView.$el.html.
This is good because that el--
we don't know what the ID's
going to be.
What we construct out of our
view might be dynamic.
So it's much better to
simply use this.
Let's take a look at the view
code that you saw back in
level one that looks something
like this.
Hopefully, it makes a little
more sense this time
you're seeing it.
To construct your HTML, we
called the render function,
then we called
console.log(todoView.el) and
it printed out Pick up milk.
Let's revise the class
definition a little bit, first
adding the tag name,
ID, and class name.
You can see we're wrapping
with the el with a jQuery
function, and we just learned
there's a shortcut for this,
so let's modify it
accordingly.
To generate the HTML from our
view, we just call the render
function and we can
print out the el
property to the console.
We're generating our view HTML
by simply creating a variable
with all of our HTML, we're
appending it all together.
And you can imagine, if we had
a lot of HTML and a lot of
attributes we were printing out
inside of it, it would get
really hairy and ugly.
We can organize that by using
some sort of client-side
templating framework.
Backbone comes with
the underscore
library for doing this.
Not that the underscore
library's just for templating,
the underscore library actually
is a big utility
library that gives us some great
stuff, one of which is
the templating function.
To use the underscore library,
we just use the underscore and
we're going to use the template
function and send in
the string which is
our _template.
Then inside of our render
function, we're going to
create the attributes variable,
setting that equal
to the JSON from our model.
To render the template, we
just call the template
function and send in
those attributes.
Then if we render out the HTML
just like we did before, we'll
get the same result, this
time using a template.
Although the Underscore.js
library comes with Backbone,
that doesn't have to be what
you use for client-side
templating.
We could also use Mustache.js.
It might look something
like this.
We could use Haml.js.
We could also use Eco or any
other templating library.
But here's our template.
And we want to make it so that
when somebody clicks on that
h3, it pops up an alert.
If we were to do this in
jQuery, it might look
something like this where we
set a click listener on h3,
which will call the alert
status function.
However, this is typically
not how we do
DOM events in Backbone.
You see, in Backbone, views are
responsible for responding
to any UI interaction.
So these events are defined
inside of our views like so.
Instead of our view class
definition, we
have an events object.
We specify that when the h3
element is clicked, call the
alert status method.
We then define the alert
status function
inside of the view.
Now, you're probably wondering,
is this alert going
to pop up whenever I click
on any h3 on my page?
Well, no.
Backbone's smarter than that.
If you looked inside of a
Backbone code, you would see
that that h3 event is
scoped to inside of
this particular element.
It's actually calling the
jQuery delegate method.
So that means inside of this
element if there's any h3s
when they're clicked, call
the alert status.
Now, let's take a look at
a more complex event
declaration.
Here, we have a
DocumentView class.
Inside there, you can see I'm
defining multiple events.
At the top of event,
you'll notice it
doesn't have any selector.
As you can imagine with the code
that we saw previously,
what that means is if I double
click anywhere inside of this
element, it's going to call
the open function.
The format of events looks
something like this.
We specify an event, we specify
a selector, and then
the function to call.
If you're using jQuery, here are
all the different events
that you could listen to.
Remember, you can always create
custom events at the
model level or even at the view
level. That about wraps up
this level.
So have some fun with the
challenges and Eric Allam will
meet you on level four.