[SINGING]
While on jQuery Air, you'll
arrive super quick.
With our in-flight
service, you'll
learn code with a click.
Yes, now all this and more
taught by Greg Pollack.
We hope you enjoy your flight.
I'm Greg and I'll be
your Captain this
evening on jQuery Air.
Welcome to jQuery Air 2.
I'm Greg Pollack, and in this
level, we're going to be first
doing a little bit of review
on selectors to make sure
we're on the same page.
We're then going to talk about
name spacing using a dollar
sign, data tags, binding events,
unbinding events, and
then finally, we'll talk about
live and delegate.
So we're going to start out
looking at some HTML, and then
we're going to run some
selectors against it.
You may notice that this HTML
has an HTML5 data tag.
We can use this data tag to
store variables and little
pieces of data that
we may want to use
later in our jQuery.
To get the first item in
this list, we would use
this jQuery code here.
It would return the link.
If you wanted to get the text
to that link, we could do
this, and it would return
September 27.
To get the href of a link, we
could call attribute href, and
we get back this.
And then finally, if we wanted
to get the value of the data
tag, we could call data
'flights,' and that
would return 6.
What we're going to be building
together in this
level is something that
looks like this.
It's a little flight
reservation page.
So here, you can hover over each
of the tabs, and it tells
you how many flights are
available on that day.
And if I want to see the flights
on that day, I can
click on that tab, and then it
will go and fetch the flights
and show me what's available
for that
day along with prices.
So let's start building.
So here's the HTML that we saw
a second ago with all the
dates that we have
flights for.
Let's write some jQuery.
We want this to run only
when the document
object model is ready.
We're going to say, for each
link, preventDefault, so we
don't want it to follow
that link.
Then let's remove the active
class from the tab that's
currently active, and let's add
it to the class that we
clicked on.
We can clean up this
code a little bit.
We're going to take some of
this code and wrap it in a
function called changeTab, then
our click event is simply
going to call that function.
Instead of using document ready,
we're going to use a
slightly different syntax,
syntax that looks like this.
What this does is it executes
the DOM when it's loaded just
like document ready, but it also
ensures that that dollar
sign is namespaced to the jQuery
object, so if we're
using other JavaScript
frameworks that also use that
dollar sign, here we're going
to make sure that the code
inside here, that dollar
sign, refers to jQuery.
So let's jump into the browser,
and you can see here,
we can click on each
of the tabs, and it
properly gets selected.
But we might also want a default
tab, maybe that middle
one, September 29.
Let's make that the default.
So when we call up the page
for the first time, that's
already selected.
The way we're going to do that
is simply by grabbing that
link and calling the
click event on it.
You'll notice here, I'm using a
different selector you might
not have seen before, eq(2).
That's going to select
a third element.
The first tab would be eq(0),
the second tab would be eq(1),
and the third tab, which
we want, is eq(2).
So here, you can see in the
browser, September 29 is
selected by default.
We can click off of that, and
whenever we refresh the page,
it's going to select
September 29 again.
Next up, we're going to use that
data flights attribute so
that we can create a tool tip,
so when we hover over each of
the tabs, it'll show us
how many flights are
available for that date.
We want the tool tip look a
little bit something like
that, so let's take a look
inside of our code.
You can see here we have
our normal click event.
We already went over that.
We're also going to add a mouse
enter event, which will
call the showNumberOfFlights
function, and a mouseleave
event, which calls the
hideNumberOfflights function.
So first of all, in the
snowNumberOfFlights function,
we're going to grab the number
of flights out of the data
attribute, and we're going to
append a span with the number
of flights in it.
For the hideNumberOfFlights
function, all we're going to
do is call remove
on the tool tip.
So just remove that element.
We can refactor this
code a little by
using the bind command.
Since all of these events are
happening on the same element,
we can write it like this.
So we just say bind,
and then we have a
list of all the events.
In the browser, here's
what our tool tip's
going to look like.
So you can see here, we hover
over each of the tabs, and it
tells us how many flights
are available.
So we have tabs, but we need to
add some divs where we put
the flight data.
So let's go ahead and write them
out, as you can see here.
Right now, we're just going
to put the loading
text in each of them.
You'll notice that the href
matches the ID of the divs
down below.
This is no coincidence.
We're going to be using
that in just a minute.
Let's shrink down our HTML and
make some room for our jQuery.
Here's our changeTab function.
We've already walked through
this code, but now we're going
to add a hide call to hide all
the divs, and then we're going
to find the active div by
looking up the attribute on
the link that was just clicked,
and we're going to
use that to find which div
we should be showing.
We're going to refactor this
code a little bit by creating
a showFlights function.
We'll just send in the active
div to the showFlights
function, and that'll hide all
the divs and show the one
that's active.
So if we jump into our browser
at this point, we can see that
as we click the tabs, it
properly shows the div that
we're looking at.
Pretty cool.
So we're selecting the proper
divs, but we don't have the
flight data in there yet.
We want to be able to load that
in, and we want to load
it using AJAX, but we're not
going to cover AJAX until the
next level.
So for now, we're just going
to call the showFlights
method, and that's going to load
in the proper flights.
So let's jump back
into the browser.
So now, we have flights, and
we can click on each of the
tabs to select the flights.
Pretty cool.
You'll notice, though, that if
I click a tab, every time I
click the tab, even if it's the
active tab, it's going to
do another call back to the
server, another AJAX call,
which isn't so good.
To stop the event from
happening, we're going to
learn how to use the
unbind function.
So here, you can see I'm getting
the active link, and
I'm unbinding the click
event on it.
Since I'm unbinding the event,
when I click off of that tab,
I'm going to want
to rebind it.
So I'm simply going to
add click(changeTab).
It should be said that this
the same thing as saying
bind(click", changeTab).
It does the same thing,
just different syntax.
So if we go back into our
browser now, we can see that
when we click a tab and keep
on clicking on that tab, it
doesn't cause an AJAX request
to happen every time.
Pretty cool.
When you're binding events, you
should know that you can
namespace each of
these events.
Here you can see I'm
namespacing click.
So I'm just giving it an extra
.flightSchedule name.
Then when I want to unbind
it, I have to
reference that same name.
Alternatively, I could add that
namespace to all of the
different events.
If I did this and I wanted to
unbind all those events all at
once, I could simply call
unbind(".flightSchedule").
The next piece of functionality
we want to add
is the ability to select an
individual price, to basically
pick out the flight and pick
out if we want to do first
class or coach.
And as we click on a
different one, that
one should get selected.
Here's what the HTML looks like
on our flights table.
You can notice that one of these
has class selected, and
that's what's going
to highlight
that particular flight.
Let's jump into the jQuery
to make this work.
So here we're going to bind
on the click action.
It's going to call the
selectFlight function.
Inside of the selectFlight
function, we're going to
preventDefault.
We're then going to remove the
selected class from the one
that's currently selected, then
we're going to add the
selected class to the one
that we just clicked on.
If we jump into our browser and
try this out, notice that
it doesn't seem to work.
We're clicking on stuff and
nothing's getting highlighted.
That's because we shouldn't be
using the bind function.
What we should be using
is the live function.
Because we're loading in that
flight data dynamically using
AJAX, we need to have it look
for that event no matter
what's on the page.
What bind does is it goes
through, it only hooks onto
that event one time.
What live does is it looks for
that selector, and whenever it
finds that, whether it's now or
in the future, it's going
to properly catch that event and
call the right function.
So if we jump back in our
browser, we can now click on
the different prices and
select our flights.
Using live, like we showed you
there, turns out to be not
such a good practice.
There's a better way
to bind events.
Live, this line up here,
is the same as saying
(document).delegate.
So what that (document).delegate
thing is
saying is on the document, the
highest level document, look
for the click event that matches
this selector, and so
every time the click happens,
it's going to be trying to
match at the top event level.
Which isn't so good.
We can fine tune this command by
giving it the selector that
we want to be checking inside
for the click event on the
flight link.
There are two benefits
to using delegate.
First of all, it can
be method chained,
so you can have a bunch
of methods all up
against each other.
And secondly, as I mentioned
before, it also performs
faster because it only has to
be checking for that event,
for that element, in this part
of the code instead of the
entire document, as
using live does.
That about does it for Level
1 of jQuery Air 2.
I hope you're ready to get your
hands dirty with some of
the code challenges.
Good luck.