[SINGING]
While on jQuery Air, you'll
arrive super quick.
With our in-flight
service you'll
learn code with a click.
Yes, now all this and more
taught by Greg Pollack.
We hope you enjoy your flight.
I'm Greg, and I'll be
your Captain this
evening on jQuery Air.
In Level 3, we're going to be
talking all about effects and
the advanced things you can do
with them, starting with
chaining effect and
adjusting speed.
We'll look at how to create
our custom effects by
manipulating CSS.
We'll then talk about
effect easing--
so that's sort of the rate at
which the effects come in.
Using a queue, how you
might do that.
Then we'll talk about adding
delays to your effects, and
finally, how to stop them
when you need to.
Let's take a look back
at the application
we've built so far.
So here, you can see we click
on a price, and that
brings up the login.
We can log in, and then we
have our trip total.
Cool.
That login box that
I showed you?
Wouldn't it be nice if that
faded out and then faded back
in when I got back from
that AJAX request?
How might we do that using
effect chaining?
So, we're going to chain
the effects.
We're going to fade out, load in
the HTML, and fade back in.
When you run multiple effects
on the single element, it's
going to chain them together.
So it's going to run one, and
then the next, and the next.
It's not going to run
them all once.
It's going to wait until the
first one's done, and then run
the next, and the next.
Definitely check out the
documentation if you want to
read about the different effects
you have available.
So here we are back
in the browser.
We click on a price.
We get the login button.
We click on it, it fades
out, and then back in.
I'm going to show you
that one more time.
Pay close attention.
It's not quite right.
Notice how the HTML changes as
it's fading out, and then it
fades back in, which isn't the
real behavior we want.
We want to make it so that it
fades out, then it changes the
HTML back from the AJAX call,
and then it fades back in.
How might we do that?
We can do that using
a callback.
So that fade out method, it
takes a function as one of its
parameters, and inside that
function we can say, this is
what we want you to call after
the fade out is done.
So in this case, after the fade
out is done, it's going
to load the HTML and
then fade back in.
If we wanted to, we could
adjust speed as well.
So we could say, fade
out fast, and then
fade back in slowly.
In case you're wondering what
fast and slow is, and what the
default speed is for
these effects, it's
something like this.
Fast is 200 milliseconds.
Default is 400 milliseconds.
Slow is 600 milliseconds.
And of course, for all
these, you can send
in your custom time.
For example, here I'm sending
in 1,000, which is 1,000
milliseconds.
So in this case, it's going
to fade out in one second.
So with this new callback, if we
go back into the login, we
can see it properly fades out,
then changes the HTML, and
then fades back in.
Very nice.
So as you can see, when we get
back from that AJAX call, we
also set the background
color on the total
price to that brown.
But what if we wanted to call
that out even more?
One way we could do that is
by specifying the animate
function, and we could tell
it what to animate.
In this case, we change the
height of that row to 30.
We also might want to make the
text flash a little bit.
One way we could do this is by
setting the opacity to 0.5,
and then animate it
back up to 1.
It should also be said that
I can use classes and CSS
animations to do
these effects.
However, not all browsers out
there are going to support CSS
animation, so if I wanted to be
the most compatible, this
might be how I do it.
Here we are back
in our browser.
Let's go ahead and see
what it looks like.
We log in.
Ah, it animates pretty nice.
Let's look at it
one more time.
Very cool.
Next up, we're going to
talk a little bit
about effect easing.
So what easing is talking about
is the rate at which the
effect goes from its starting
point to its ending point, and
to jQuery library by default
comes with two different
easing methods.
We have linear and swing.
And by default, swing is going
to be used in our effects.
Take a look at what
these mean.
So here, you can see each of
these sort of sliding up and
sliding down using different
types of easing.
Linear is sort of all at the
same pace, and swing starts
out fast and then slows down.
The jQuery UI library comes with
a bunch more easing
methods, as you can see
in this window.
You don't need to worry about
these for now, but if you want
more information, at the end of
this course, I'll give you
a link to this page where you
can try out all the different
easing methods.
Let's jump back into
our jQuery and
change some of the easing.
So here, we're going to change
the confirm purchase to a
linear easing.
Also, we're going to go into our
animate function there and
change that also to linear.
And let's see what that looks
like in our browser.
It's going to be really hard
to see the difference.
That's just the way it goes
when you have your effects
going this quickly.
But if I slowed it down, it
would be more obvious.
So we're about halfway
done with Level 3.
Next up, we're going to be
talking about queuing.
So, if you look back here at
this login code-- let's take
one more look at it.
With successful login, it
basically returns, it fades
out, it loads in the new HTML,
and then fades back in.
Now, looking at this code, it
made me wonder, wait a second.
Why are we fading out after
the AJAX comes back?
Shouldn't we be fading out,
making the AJAX call, and then
fading back in when
it comes back?
So let's refactor that.
So let's bring the fade
out up into right
above the AJAX call.
And if we wanted to, we could
put that in the before send in
the AJAX callback, but above
it's probably fine, too.
So let's go ahead and see what
that does in the page.
So we log in.
Uh oh.
We're running into
that issue again.
You see it?
Where it's actually updating
that div, and then fading out
and fading back in.
We can't use the callback like
we did before because it's in
two different places.
One's coming back from the
server, and one's getting
called before we call AJAX.
So this is where we might
want to use a queue.
See up here at the top?
We're going to attach this queue
to the login element,
and inside there is where we're
going to load in the
HTML, and then fade it in.
Using the queue syntax,
you have to be aware
of this next parameter.
So we send the next in, and then
we call next at the end
of that code block so
that it'll call the
next item in the queue.
One more thing we might want to
do here before we see what
happens in our browser, we
might want to make that
confirm box happen afterward.
So first, we're going to
have the login box fade
out, fade back in.
Only once it's complete do we
want to draw the user's
attention to the total box
and the submit button.
So to do that, we're
going to jump back.
We're not going to use
the queue again.
We're going to do that
callback function.
So we're going to take this
code, put it as a
callback to fade in.
So after its done fading
in, call these methods.
Here we are back
in our browser.
So we click login, it fades
out, fades back
in, and shows us--
let's look at that
one more time.
Fades out, fades back in,
and shows us the button.
Next up, remember our tool
tips up there at the top?
They hover and they pop up.
Well, let's make them a little
more user friendly.
This time let's make them sort
of fade in and then fade out,
and maybe add a delay.
So like, when you hover
over it, it doesn't
appear right away?
Like a real tool tip.
So here we are, back in our
showNumberOfFlights
function, and then we also
have our hideNumberofFlights
function.
And all we need to do there to
add fade in, fade out, and
delay is write
delay(300).fadeIn, just like
so, and then down below, we're
going to fade out, and we're
going to only remove
the element once
the fade out is complete.
Otherwise, it would just
make it disappear.
All right.
Back in our browser,
let's check it out.
Hey, that looks nice.
We hover, and it feeds
in and fades out.
Pretty cool, but
there's a bug.
See what happens when
we scroll our mouse
over all of the tabs?
It's not so nice.
So let's try to fix that, so
that when we move the mouse
across the page, we don't have
cascading tool tips.
So here we are, back
in our code.
All we need to fix this is
add the stop variable.
So, stop is going to stop the
effect wherever it is.
And in this case, it's
going to stop, and
then just fade out.
So, let's take a look.
Now we could scroll
over all of them.
Nothing appears until we hover
over it for a little while,
and it's much nicer.
Pretty cool.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Looks like you made it all the
way to level Three 3, so it's
time to get your hands dirty.
Go through those challenges
and practice your effects.