(SINGING) "While on jQuery Air
you'll arrive super quick.
With our in-flight
service you'll
learn code with a click.
Yes, now all this and more
taught by Gregg Pollack.
We hope you enjoy
your flight."
I'm Gregg, and I'll be
your captain this
evening on jQuery Air.
Welcome to jQuery
Air 2, Level 2.
In this level, we're going to
be talking all about AJAX,
AJAX error handling, AJAX
callbacks, AJAX aborts, AJAX
timeouts and also how to send
back and forth JSON, parse it
out, send it, some JSONP.
And then finally, we'll take
a look at a form and
how to submit it.
We're going to keep on
continuing with our example
application--
looks something like this--
where we click on the
different tabs and it brings
up all the flights.
And we skipped over the AJAX
part, so let's jump back to
that and see with AJAX looks
like to fetch flights.
Here you can see we're back in
the showFlights function.
We need to write that
fetchFlights function.
Well, really we're just going to
get rid of the fetchFlights
function and write the
AJAX right in there.
The path we're going to
call in the server
is the flights path.
We're going to send
it some data.
This is just a little snippet
of JSON where I'm sending in
the date and the activeDiv.
The URL it's constructing looks
like this where we have
flights, question mark,
and the date.
That little escaped bit
is just the #.
In this case, we're going to get
back HTML from our server.
And if the AJAX request is
successful, we're going to
take that HTML and simply
print it out into the
activeDiv and show
the flights.
There's one other thing we want
to do before we actually
see this in action.
You'll notice here that we're
showing the activeDiv before
we do the AJAX call.
That's not right.
So we're going to take that
command, move it into the
success function for
that command.
Another way we can write this
AJAX command is by using the
get function, as you see here.
These two functions pretty
much do the same thing.
On using the AJAX command
explicitly, though, gives us
more configuration options.
Whereas you can see here with
the get command, the third
parameter we're sending
in is the success.
If it's successful, it's going
to call this function.
The last option we're going to
add is the cache option to our
AJAX command.
You see, there's some browsers
out there that improperly
cache the HTML that you get back
from your AJAX request.
So it's just a safe thing to
put cache false in there to
ensure that the browser's not
improperly caching anything.
Now we're AJAXified, and if
we look back inside of our
browser we can see that,
hey, it works.
Uh-oh.
Something went wrong there.
We clicked on the tab, and at
that point in the video I went
and looked at the server, and
we hit a server error.
Huh.
Well, we probably should account
for that in our AJAX
code somehow so that if the
server errors out our user
isn't left staring
at a blank page.
So let's see what
that looks like.
Here in our AJAX code
we're going to
add an error callback.
It's going to show the
new error div which
were about to create.
And also we want to make it so
that before we actually send
the AJAX request we hide that
error div, if it was shown.
If it wasn't shown in the first
place, it doesn't matter.
We can still call hide on it.
In our HTML at the div
level, we're going to
add an error div.
And you'll notice here on the
error div we've got that click
here to try again link.
So we're going to write some
JavaScript so that it goes
ahead and tries to call
showFlights again when
somebody clicks on that link.
So here's what it looks like
with error handling.
When you click on
the tabs and--
Oh.
We hit an error.
And it says, whoops, unable
to pull flights.
And we can click on
the link, and it
brings back the flights.
Yay.
But what if we add some
latency here?
What if we have some server lag
when we click on a tab?
Oh.
Our user is still stuck staring
at that blank screen
until it comes back
from the server.
So we probably want to add
some sort of loading div.
Let's go back and do that.
So here we have our error div.
Below that we have a
loading div now.
Back in our AJAX function, we're
going to add another
command to show the loading
div on before send.
And then, when the AJAX returns,
it's going to call
the complete function that
always gets called when the
AJAX function returns.
And we're going to hide the
loading screen there.
Just to review, that successful
callback gets
called if it returns
successfully and error if it
doesn't return successfully.
So if we jump back into our
browser we can see we have
this nice loading screen with
that little spinner there
while we wait for the request
to return from the server.
Nice.
But we also introduced a bug.
Check this out.
If I click two different tabs,
the first one returns and the
second one returns as well.
Ah.
We had two AJAX calls.
They both got called, they both
returned, and they both
loaded into that div.
Ugh.
That's not good.
So we need to figure
out some way to
keep that from happening.
Maybe figure out some way to
abort the first AJAX request
if a second one is called.
The problem, again, is that this
showFlights function is
getting called every time a
tab is clicked, which is
triggering that AJAX call.
So well, we need to fix this.
To fix it, the first thing we're
going to do is add a
fetchingFlights variable that's
outside of our function.
We can set that variable
equal to the AJAX call.
Then when the AJAX function is
complete, we're going to unset
that variable.
Now if this method is called
twice, the second time it's
called it's going to check
to see if we're
fetching flights currently.
Well, if we're still fetching
flights and the AJAX hasn't
returned yet, then abort that
current AJAX request.
Just cancel it.
Cool.
Let's see what that does
in the browser.
So we click on one, click
on the second.
Uh-oh.
It's showing the loading
div and the error div.
Oh, and then it shows the
flights properly.
So it's showing the loading div
again and the error div,
and then it shares
the flights.
Huh.
Well, it turns out when you call
abort on an AJAX request,
as you might expect it calls
the error callback.
So we need to go into the error
callback and make it so
that it doesn't show the error
div if it's been aborted.
So here we are back in
our error callback.
We're going to check to see if
the status text of that error
is not equal to abort, right?
Because if we're aborting
we don't want to
show the error div.
That's all we have to do.
So now if we go back into our
browser and click on two tabs,
we can see that it properly
shows the loading screen and
then pulls up the
proper flights.
Hmm.
But what happens if we have a
slow server, if it just loads
and loads and loads
forever, right?
We need some sort of timeout
to make sure that our user
isn't waiting for like, 30
seconds for it to return.
We need a timeout.
So let's go back to our AJAX
call and add that.
So all we have to do to add a
timeout is simply specify
right here as an option
timeout 8,000.
And that's in milliseconds.
So we're saying after eight
seconds make it error out.
Here's what that might look
like on the server.
So we click on a tab.
It's not eight seconds,
more like two seconds.
But I want to show you
here that it's
properly calling timeout.
And that is triggering the error
callback and giving us
that nice error message.
About halfway done
with Level 2.
Next up we're going
to talk about
receiving and parsing JSON.
And we need to add a little
bit to our example.
We're going to add what
you see down here.
Basically, once somebody clicks
on a price, we're going
to do a callback
to the server.
And the server's going to give
us the base price, the taxes,
and the trip total, which
we're going to
display down there.
Let's jump back into our
selectFlight function,
which we created in
the last level.
We're going to have two
variables, one for the flight,
one for the flight class.
Then we're going to hide
the confirm box.
That's what we're creating
is the confirm box.
It might already be there.
We're going to hide
it if it's there.
Then we're going to create an
AJAX request where the URL
we're calling is going to
reference the flight.
The data is going to reference
the flight class.
We're also going to specify the
data type option as JSON,
because we're expecting back
JSON from the server.
We're explicitly putting this,
but if we didn't have it would
still work.
JQuery would still figure out
that what is getting back from
the server is JSON, and it
would act accordingly.
But we're going to be just a
little more explicit and tell
it right here in the AJAX
call that we're
expecting JSON back.
If it's successful, we're
going to call
this showTotal function.
This AJAX function we just wrote
we could also write a
different way using the getJSON
function like so.
Let's jump into the showTotal
function where we're getting
the JSON back from the
server and putting it
out onto the screen.
Here's what part of the
HTML looks like
that's on our screen.
So as you can see here, we have
a table cell for price,
fees, and total.
To get the price out of the
JSON object, we just call
json.price.
Then we've got json.fees to get
the fees, json.total to
get the total.
And finally, let's slide down
the confirm box and show it on
the screen.
So here we are back
in our browser.
We click on a number, and it
slides down, gives us the
total, the taxes, the base
price, and our login box.
Nice.
Before we flush out the login
box, I want to take a moment
to talk about JSONP.
You see, when you're doing AJAX
back and forth on your
server, that's fine.
That's safe.
As long as you're using the
same domain, you can
call back and forth.
But what if you want to get
AJAX data from a different
domain, from a different
server?
That's where you want
to use JSONP.
It wraps the AJAX call
differently in a script tag.
You don't need to really worry
about that, but here's what it
looks like.
So there's our normal
AJAX call.
All we need to do is specify
JSONP and it's going to work.
Here's another example
of using JSONP
that might be useful.
There's this service at Weather
Underground that
allows you to get the weather
for a certain location, and it
has a JSONP API.
And if we called it just like
so, we'd get back an alert
that looks something
like this.
Next, let's work on AJAXifying
that login form.
So here's the HTML that goes
along with that login form,
pretty typical.
First thing we're going to do
is grab the submit event on
the form, have that call
the login function.
The login function is going
to prevent default.
Obviously we don't want
the form to submit.
Then we're going to slide up the
title of that login box so
that the user knows that
it's submitting.
We'll then fetch the email and
password out of the form and
then do an AJAX call.
Now this isn't the best code.
There's a better
way to do this.
Instead of fetching all the data
out of each of the form
elements, instead of
doing that we can
actually call serialize.
Serialize pulls all the fields
out of our form, and then our
AJAX request we can
just specify form.
Data, form.
In this case, instead of
expecting JSON back, we're
going to specify dataType
script.
So we're going to expect
JavaScript back from the
server, and we're going to
execute that JavaScript.
You also might have noticed
we're using type here to
specify that we're doing a post
instead of a get request.
Because our Ajax request is
expecting back JavaScript, we
need to write some JavaScript
on the server side.
I'm going to show you
what that looks
like in my Rails app.
You don't have to
be using Rails.
It should be readable anyway.
So here we are inside
of our Rails app.
Those little percentage
brackets, that's just Ruby.
Don't worry about it.
It's saying execute this.
It's not jQuery.
So we're saying if logged in,
then go ahead and render it
out a welcome message.
Then go ahead and slide down the
purchase button, which is
currently hidden.
We're going to change the
background color of the total
price just to call it out.
And if they didn't successfully
log in, we're
just going to print out invalid
email and password.
Please try again.
So here's what it looks
like in the browser.
We can go ahead and
click login.
Welcome back, Craig.
And now we can confirm purchase
and select seats.
So now that you know all about
AJAX, it's time for you to do
a little bit of learning by
doing in the code challenges.
Good luck.