[SINGING]
While on jQuery Air you'll
arrive super quick.
With our in-flight
service you'll
learn code with a click.
Yes, now all this and more,
taught by Gregg Pollack.
We hope you enjoy your flight.
[SPEAKING]
I'm Gregg, and I'll be
your captain this
evening on jQuery Air.
Level four's the last level
on our jQuery Air flight.
We're going to be talking about
each and map utility
methods and then how to create
your own utility method.
We'll then talk about plug-ins
and create our own plug-ins,
then encapsulating our code,
keeping it more organized,
followed by talking about
custom events.
And then finally we'll take a
look at something newer in
jQuery, which are jQuery
Templates, allowing you to
write some--
you would call it, view HTML--
that gets started on the client
side and load it up.
It's pretty cool stuff,
so stay with us.
Remember the AJAX we used
to load in the flights?
Well, we're going to change
that around a bit.
Instead of loading HTML, getting
HTML back from the
server, for the sake of our
examples we're going to switch
that to using JSON.
So basically on our server,
we're going to be calling a
different URL.
It's just so happens that
our server wants .json.
And it's going to come back with
this, as you see here.
It's basically a JSON array of
objects with the values for
our flights.
So now we need to
load this in.
In our success callback, we're
now going to remove all the
rows that we currently have.
Then we're going to create
a variable called Rows.
We're going to go through each
flight in that flights array.
For each flight we're
going to add a row
onto the rows variable.
And at the very end of that
callback, we're going to load
that HTML into the body
of the table.
Instead of using each function,
there's one other
way we could have done this
using the map function.
What the map function does is
it takes an array and it
returns an array.
So here you can see we're going
through all the flights.
It's going to return each of
the rows, and it's going to
set that array that it returns
equal to our flight rows
variable, so that when
we'll have array.
The to load the flight rows back
into our table, we simply
at the bottom call
flight_rows.join.
So it's going to join
that array together
into one big string.
There are two different ways you
can extend jQuery and keep
your code DRY.
DRY, in case you're not
familiar, means
don't repeat yourself.
We don't like repeating
ourselves.
There's two ways
you can do it.
The first way is by creating
your own utility functions.
Just like a map and each and
AJAX are utility functions, we
can create our own.
And later on, we're going
to create one
called filter flights.
We can also extend jQuery by
creating our own plugins.
The difference here, of course,
is that plugins can
be called on jQuery objects.
And we're going to be creating
one later for our tool tips.
Here's our hello world utility
function, so you can get used
to the syntax.
So here we have hello,
function, alert.
Utility functions can be
wrapped a little bit
differently than our
normal code.
We can use what they call
in jQuery a closure.
It looks something like this.
So the cool part about this is
that it's taking that dollar
sign, we're adding a function
basically into jQuery.
And then using the closure like
this makes it so that we
can use that function elsewhere
in our code.
So it's going to make sure that
that method we attach,
the dollar sign, can get used
in code that we might have
elsewhere in other libraries
on the same page.
To run this function, we just
call .hello and it gets us
back this alert you see here.
Now, let's take a look back in
our application, see if we can
find some place where
we might want to
use a utility function.
So here you can see I've added
a little box up top that
allows us to filter by
number of stops.
So if we're only looking for a
nonstop flight, we can just
click this filter and only
look at nonstop flights.
So how to implement this, here
is the HTML for this box.
So it's just a bunch
of radio buttons.
And we're going to want to
trigger an event when one of
these radio buttons is
pressed and call the
filter by flights method.
Let's define that method.
So inside filter by flight we're
going to grab the value,
grab the number of stops.
We're going to have an empty
array called filter flights.
Then we're going to go through
each of our current flights.
Now behind the scenes, I've
basically created a global
variable that has the
current flights
that are getting displayed.
So it has the JSON array of the
current flights that are
up on the page.
So here, I'm referencing that.
We're going through
each of them.
If the user selects two or more
flights, that means we
can push on this existing
flight no matter what.
And then I'm not going to show
you the rest of the code, but
it goes through all the other
conditionals to build up that
filtered flights array.
And then it's going to print
out the filtered flights.
So let's take a look
at this in action.
Here you can see we can filter
the different flights.
It displays them
on the screen.
But when we click over to
another tab, you'll notice it
doesn't save our preferences.
It doesn't stay filtered.
So we can filter from here, but
as soon as we click onto
another tab, it would reset.
So how do we figure out how to
make it so that even when we
switch tabs it stays filtered?
Since there are multiple places
we need to filter
results, we're going to create
a utility method for it.
So we're going to call
it filter flights.
We're going to send in current
flights and stops.
Then we're going to go through
each of the current flights
and then just return the
filtered flights.
Pretty simple.
Then in the code where we
display new flights, when we
click a tab, we're going to get
the checked radio button,
get the value of that, and then
call filter flights, send
in the current flights
and stops.
Let's take a look at that
in the browser.
So we change the number of
stops, and now we click and we
get back nonstop,
just nonstop.
We can change it to 0-1,
and everything
remains properly filtered.
Next up, let's create some
jQuery plugins.
So here's a very basic
jQuery plugin.
Let's say I wanted to create a
callout, which is less than a
highlight, just that maybe
opacity from 0.5 to 1.
So there's the CSS.
We're going to animate
it fast.
And that's our plugin.
You'll notice it has that .fn.
This we also want to wrap in one
of these closures, so we
reuse it in many different
places in our code.
Now as I mentioned before,
plugins have to be called on
a jQuery object.
Here we have activeDiv.callOut.
One other programming pattern
that you see with plugins
deals with defaults.
Specifying defaults,
but with the
ability to override defaults.
For instance here, let's say
one of my defaults is the
duration of the callout.
So I have a little default
object here.
I can say extend defaults
options.
So what this says is use the
default setting unless it's
overridden by something that
I send in using options.
So then I've got options
duration with the animate.
And now down below I can call
callOut without any
configuration options, or I
can send in a customized
duration if I want to override
the default.
So where in our application
might we
want to use a plugin?
Well, remember those
tool tips?
Those tool tips were
pretty nice.
We might want to use those
someplace else in our
application.
So let's extract those
into a plugin.
Here's our bind command, which
you should be familiar with.
Here's our show a number
of flights function.
And here's our hide number
So let's extract this
into a plugin.
So our plugin in this
case is going to be
called addToolTip.
It's going to return a
bind on mouseenter.
It's going to grab
the tool tip.
I've changed the data naming
here so that all we have to do
is have data tool tip and
that'll pick it up.
It's a little bit
more generic.
Then we're going to create
a span and append that.
And on mouseleave we're going
to find that tool
tip and remove it.
All we need to do to add this
function is simply to get an
element and call .addToolTip.
Now, if we look back
in our browser, it
shouldn't look any different.
It's pretty much the same.
Except now, we can take that
plugin and use it elsewhere
in our code.
All right.
We're about halfway down
with level four.
Next up, we're going to be
talking about how to
encapsulate and organize
your JavaScript code.
So here you can see what we've
written so far in our
application.
We've got a couple variables and
a bunch of functions and a
bunch of stuff we
load and unload.
And it's a bit messy.
So how might we refactor
this to encapsulate it?
Well, what we're going to do is
we're going to encapsulate
it in two different objects.
Up here at the top, we have
the select flights object.
Inside there we have two
attributes, fetchingFlights
and currentFlights.
Then we're going to have
an init function.
We're writing the functions a
little bit differently now.
We're wrapping them
all like so.
Then we have a more object
called confirm flight at the
bottom, where we're separating
functions that
have different concerns.
To run the functions that we
need to run when the page
loads, we're simply going to
run selectFlights.init.
One other thing we need to
change in here to make it
work, we need to reference
the methods like so.
If we're talking about methods
inside our current object, we
can also use the
this variable.
Next up, we're going to talk
about custom events.
And what we're going to try to
implement on our little flight
selecter is the ability to use
the keys one, two, three,
four, five to select the
five different tabs.
So what might that
code look like?
We're going to write
a function that
gets called on keydown.
And if the key code is between
these two key codes, which is
basically one and five,
we're going to
set the number selected.
I should mention that if they
press the number one, it's
actually going to set
numSelected to zero.
So we're making it from
zero to four, really.
Then we're going to set
tabSelected and get the tab
that was selected using that EQ
function that we saw earlier.
So if it's EQ0, it's going
to select the first tab.
Then we want to select the
proper tab, switch the
classes, call the AJAX.
Now, there's one other place in
our code, though, that does
the same thing, our
old tab code.
So when a tab is clicked, it
does the same exact thing.
And we don't like to
repeat ourselves.
So let's make it dry.
So where we have this repeated
code we're going to move this
up into a custom event.
We're going to call the custom
event selectTab, just
like you see here.
Then it to trigger the
event, we simply
call the trigger method.
So down here we say, trigger
selectTab, and then down in
our click event, we call
trigger selectTab.
So selectTab's our custom
event, and we
call it by using trigger.
Here it is in action.
Here we go.
One, two, three, four,
and then five.
So it works using both keys
and clicking on the tabs.
Remember this code from earlier,
where we're getting
back a JSON array and mapping
that into a new array and
printing out to the screen,
and then having
some HTML in there?
Well, I was kind of hiding the
ugly stuff from you, because
really it looks a little bit
something like this.
We have all this HTML
in the middle of
our beautiful jQuery.
Not so good.
How might we get around this?
Well, one way we might
get around this
is by using a template.
Once we use jQuery Templates,
the code looks a lot cleaner.
Looks something like this,
where we, say, take this
template called flight template,
send in the flights
arrays-- remember that's
a JSON array--
and then append that
to this div.
And that's all there is to it.
Well, we have to specify
the template.
Let me show you what
that looks like.
To basically in our HTML, we
might have something that
looks like this.
So the ID is the name of the
template, the flight template.
And here you can see all of
the different values that
we're pulling out of
our JSON array.
You might notice that there's
no each in here.
That's because jQuery Templates
is smart enough to
know that this is a JSON array
that it's getting.
And it's going to iterate
through this
template for every row.
jQuery Templates isn't baked
into Quora jQuery library, at
least it isn't yet.
It may be in the future,
but it isn't yet.
Which means you're going to need
to go and grab the source
and include that in
your application.
Something like this.
I also really recommend
looking through the
documentation.
There's some really great
examples of how to use it.
And you may have noticed, when
we switched over to using a
jQuery template, we lost that
nice formatting of our routes.
It used to say nonstop,
one stop, two stops.
But it's not doing
that anymore.
Well, how might we implement
that on the client side?
Using jQuery Templates,
we can have some
conditionals in there.
So if routing is equal
to zero, put nonstop.
Otherwise, if it's equal
to one, put one stop.
Otherwise, just print
out whatever stops.
Just like that, we can use
conditionals in our code.
And then when we go back into
our browser, you can see that
we have nicely printed routes.
There's a couple other template
commands that I want
you to know about.
So you saw that we used dollar
sign curly brackets for
printing data.
But we can also say HTML and
then have the field name if we
want to print out markup.
We can use each if our
JSON has an array
embedded inside of it.
We can iterate through each of
the items from that JSON.
We can also use the template
command, which you'll need to
look up some examples to figure
out how to use it, but
basically allows you to include
templates inside of
other templates.
Well, that's the end
of jQuery Air.
Wait.
That's the end of
all the videos.
And that stuff got
pretty hairy over
the past level here.
So I hope you're ready to get
into the challenges and
actually learn by doing.
And hopefully, they'll be a
next course after this.
Hey, if you get this far, you
might keep a look out for the
CoffeeScript course that we
might be doing, where you'll
be doing a lot of the same
stuff, but programming it in
nicer code, in nicer
CoffeeScript code.
So as they say when you leave
the flight after you're done,
bye bye, now.
Bye bye.
Bye bye, now See you.