JavaScript has been around for
a while now, and over the
years, many libraries have been
built to make it easier
to program and protect you from
the not so great parts of
JavaScript.
Allow me to illustrate.
See, JavaScript--
The Definitive Guide
has 900 pages.
JavaScript--
The Good Parts, just
176 pages.
Side by side, it looks something
like this, and
that's got to tell
you something.
Almost makes you wonder if
there's a book out there
somewhere called JavaScript--
The Evil Parts.
Well, there isn't, but this is
where CoffeeScript comes in,
which combines syntax from
languages like Ruby and Python
to create a dynamic, pleasant
language that compiles into
JavaScript.
So if you spend any of your
time writing JavaScript,
you'll probably love A
Sip Of Coffee Script.
In this course, we have six high
quality screen casts each
followed by in-browser code
challenges so you
can learn by doing.
Let's take a quick tour of
the course interface.
To start the course, you'll
watch through the first video.
You can navigate around the
video using the numbers on the
top, and when you're ready to
start the challenges, just hit
the big green button
down below.
In the challenge interface,
you'll see the number of
points a question is worth, the
challenge itself, and then
a window where you can start
typing the solution.
As you type CoffeeScript, you'll
be able to see what
JavaScript is generating
live on the right
panel for instant feedback.
If you get stuck at any point,
you can ask for up to three
hints, but of course, every time
you ask for a hint, you
get less points for
the question.
Over on the right side of the
screen, you'll see your total
points, you'll have the ability
to jump around to
different levels or different
challenges, rewatch the video,
use some interface shortcuts,
and most importantly, download
the slides which you'll
definitely need to help solve
the challenges.
The six levels in A Sip Of
CoffeeScript start with
learning variables, functions,
and the command line, followed
by practice converting jQuery
code into CoffeeScript, We'll
then dive into conditionals,
operators, and comparisons for
level three, followed by arrays,
objects, iteration,
and list comprehension.
In level five, we'll apply these
topics to some advanced
jQuery, and then finally in
level six, finish up with some
object orientation, inheritance,
fat arrow, and
encapsulation.
Each of these levels have a
badge you'll earn as you
finish the level, finally
earning the course completion
badge, which we'll display
in your public profile.
You'll need to have a basic
understanding of JavaScript to
learn CoffeeScript, and
knowledge of some jQuery is
definitely recommended.
Fortunately, if you don't know
either of these, maybe check
out our jQueryAir course
over at jqueryair.com.
It's completely free.
Mmmm.
Got to love the taste
of CoffeeScript.
Definitely makes
that JavaScript
taste so much better.
Want a sip?