[MUSIC PLAYING]
They call it CoffeeScript.
Come by and take a sip.
I know it's quite a trip, but
somehow you can write less
code to get more done.
Yeah!
Come on and take a seat,
don't end up obsolete.
They call it CoffeeScript.
CoffeeScript, yeah.
Welcome to level five of
A Sip of CoffeeScript.
In this level, we're going to,
once again, go through some
jQuery code which was from
jQuery Air Captain's Log, and
practice converting that
into CoffeeScript.
So let's jump into it.
Here, you can see a bind
command, where we're sending
in an object for binding
on click, mouseenter, and
mouseleave.
What would this look like in
CoffeeScript? Well, we might
code it like so.
So as you can see here, we
remove the curly braces and
the parentheses.
We also remove the commas
at the end of each line.
We're using the spaces and the
new lines to designate each
item in the object.
Now let's jump into a more
complex jQuery example, and
we'll convert it into
CoffeeScript line by line.
So here you can see
this function
showFlights, we hide a div.
We're setting fetching flights
equal to the ajax call that
we're doing.
We also have an error
call back with a
conditional inside of it.
So let's jump into it and go
line by line converting this
into CoffeeScript.
So over the top, we are
declaring the function and
hiding the div, pretty
straightforward.
Then for the conditional right
here, this goes to two lines,
if fetchingFlights, then
fetchingFlights abort using
indentation instead
of curly braces.
Next we need to convert that
ajax function call into
CoffeeScript.
But before we do that take a
close look at the parameters
which we're sending into
that ajax call.
What you'll notice is
that we have two
different objects, right?
The first object is inside the
first set of curly braces, and
the second object is inside
that data property.
So inside there, we have another
object were sending in
for the parameters we're sending
to the server.
So let's try getting rid of
all the curly braces.
So here's what it
might look like.
You can see that we're
using indentation
instead of curly braces.
Let's replace that code there.
Next for the error callback,
our CoffeeScript is going to
look a little bit like this,
where we send in a function.
If result status text isn't
abort, then show this div.
The resulting CoffeeScript is
46 less characters than the
JavaScript, including
white spaces.
That's pretty substantial.
We're writing less code
to get more done.
And less code means it's easier
to change, its more
agile, and it probably
has less bugs.
Lastly, we're going to refactor
some JavaScript to
use a list comprehension.
So here's some code.
We have filteredFlights.
We're going through each
of the currentFlights.
currentFlights is
just an array.
For each flight, we're checking
to see if it has a
certain number of stops
and for the routing.
And then if it does have the
right number of stops, push
that onto the array.
So we're trying to generate a
new array of filtered flights.
One way we could implement this
in CoffeeScript is by
creating a new array,
go through
each item, same function.
If the stops is two,
routing is zero,
then push on the flight.
But there's a better way we
can do this using a list
comprehension.
Let's take a look.
So for the list comprehension,
we're going to say flight for
flight in currentFlights.
We saw this before in level
three, I believe.
So we're going through each
currentFlight, setting it
equal to flight, returning the
flight when stops is two,
routing is zero.
That's all wrapped in
parentheses because we want to
set it equal to the
filteredFlights array.
So that's the end of the
video for this level.
Now it's time for you to take
this knowledge and apply it to
the challenges to earn
your next badge.