[MUSIC PLAYING]
They call it CoffeeScript,
come by and take a sip.
I know it's quite trip but
somehow you can write less
code to get more done.
Yeah!
Come on and take a seat,
don't end up obsolete.
They call it CoffeeScript.
CoffeeScript, yeah.
Hey look, you made it all
the way to level six.
In level six, we're going to
be talking about object
orientation, stuff with classes
and how to apply that
and all the cool new mechanisms
that CoffeeScript
gives you to do object
orientation.
So let's dive into it.
Remember this object?
We played around with
this a little bit.
We have our coffee object.
Well, what would happen if we
wanted to, instead of having
it as an object, create
it as a class?
Let's give that a try.
So here we have our
Coffee class.
It has a constructor.
That constructor is called
when it's instantiated.
We can't call it explicitly.
I'll show you how to instantiate
it in a minute.
And then we have these
parameters we sent in, which
we're going to set as properties
on the class.
Some people might think of these
as instance variables
because they're properties of
the instance of that class.
Another way we can write this
constructor is simply by using
this one line you see here.
So the parameters with the
@ symbol basically
does the same thing.
It's just a shortcut.
If we want to have functions
inside of our class, it looks
pretty much the same as they did
when we had them inside of
our object.
Pretty much the same thing.
Now if we wanted to instantiate
this coffee
object, we're going to just call
it French coffee with the
strength of two, we can do
something like this.
Then if we call french.brew,
it's gonna pop up an alert
that looks like this.
But how do we do inheritance
in CoffeeScript?
What if we have a coffee class
like this and we want to have
a category, a type
of coffee that's
under a certain category?
We might, for instance,
have class
MaxgoodHouse extends Coffee.
And if we just instantiated
MaxgoodHouse, it would work
just like the Coffee class.
We can also override the
constructor if we want to.
So in this case, the default
strength is going to be zero.
And we can also add properties
at this point.
So we can have brand =
"Maxgood House"
At this point, we can
instantiate that class, and if
we run boring.brew, we're going
to get back "Brewing
boring." We can also override
functions in our parent class
just by declaring
them, like so.
So in this case, if I
instantiate this object and
call brew, it's going to print
"Brewing Maxgood House
Boring." Another thing that we
can do when we're overriding
functions--
if we want to call the function
from the parent
class, we can use the
keyword super.
So in this case, we're calling
#", but it sucks,"
and then when we call that pour
function, it's going to
print out, "Pouring a single cup
but it sucks." We're going
to want to use this
Coffee class from
inside of our jQuery.
So let's put some jQuery
in here with
the pourClick function.
So we're going to watch
for a click event.
If inventory isn't zero, take
away one, and then alert that
we poured a cup of coffee.
But this isn't going to work.
Why?
Well, it's because of this.
So we have that @
symbol in there.
So it's going to be calling
this dot from inside a
different context.
So basically, it's going to
error out because it's going
to be looking for the property
of the dom element called
@inventory and @name,
which isn't good.
We want this to refer
to our class.
To fix this, we need
to use something
called the fat arrow.
What the fat arrow is going to
do is bind to the current
value of "this," so no matter
what context this code is run,
it's always going to be
referring to the Coffee class.
We're going to go through one
more jQuery Air Captain's Log
example before we're all done.
In jQuery Air Captain's Log,
we used an object to
encapsulate some code and
keep it organized.
Let's take a look at the code.
So here we have selectFlights,
we have a property inside of
there, an init function.
We're going to bind
a click event.
We're going to bind another
click event-- this time
calling it a different way.
Show the flights.
At the bottom, we have
two extra functions.
I'm not going to bother
showing you what those
definitions are.
Let's try converting this into
a CoffeeScript class.
So up at the top, we're
going to have a
SelectFlights class.
That SelectFlights class is
going to have a constructor
for the fetchingFlights
property.
Next, we have bind function.
That's pretty simple.
We just need to get rid
of the parentheses
in the curly brackets.
Now we have another
click event.
We're just calling
it differently.
And here, we're just pretty much
going to get rid of the
curly braces, the parentheses,
and use the @
instead of the this.
Also notice that we're using the
fat arrow here, instead of
the skinny arrow, so we can
bind that @ symbol or the
this to the correct context
inside of our
SelectFlights class.
Lastly, we have our two
functions, showFlights and
changeTab.
Notice that it's only the second
one that we have the
fat arrow on.
Once we've declared the class,
we need to instantiate it so
that it binds to the
proper events.
Well, you made to the end of
the final video in A Sip of
CoffeeScript.
From here, just got to do the
last couple challenges to
unlock a badge, some prizes,
and the final video.