[MUSIC PLAYING]
They call it CoffeeScript.
Come by and take a sip.
I know it's quite a trip, but
somehow you can write less
code to get more done.
Yeah!
Come on and take a seat,
don't end up obsolete.
They call it CoffeeScript.
CoffeeScript, yeah.
Hi.
I'm Greg Pollack, and you're
watching A Sip of
CoffeeScript.
And this is the first level
where we're going to be
talking about variables
and functions.
But before we get into that, I
want to take a moment to think
about what makes words
and text beautiful.
There's something artistic about
text when you put it
together in certain forms,
like you see here.
What makes it beautiful,
though?
Is it the font, using
a specific font?
Is that what makes
it beautiful?
Is it that, in combination with
color and design that
makes it beautiful?
Or is it the content itself?
In math-- here we have
some science.
In science, you have symbols.
Would a mathematician
look at this and
think that it was beautiful?
And lastly, we want to ask,
what makes up a beautiful
programming language?
Well, in my opinion, it has to
do with three principles.
The first is the ability to
write the least amount of code
to get the most accomplished.
It also has to do with
readability and
understandability, so that if I
write a piece of code and I
come back to it a month later,
I can immediately pick up
where I left off and I'm going
to be able to understand it.
Also, other people have
to be able to read it
and understand it.
And of course, lastly, it
has to be maintainable.
Now these three principles
aren't always associated with
JavaScript, the language.
JavaScript obviously has its
good parts, but it also has
its bad parts.
Luckily, this is where
CoffeeScript comes in.
When we write CoffeeScript, it
compiles into JavaScript.
And CoffeeScript, the language,
does follow these
three principles pretty closely,
and I think what
you'll find throughout this
tutorial is that it's a
beautiful programming
language.
As we go through this tutorial,
I highly recommend
you check out the official
CoffeeScript web page.
It has some great documentation
about the
language that will help you
through the challenges.
Also on this page, if you click
try CoffeeScript, you'll
get this interactive console
where you can type in
CoffeeScript on one side of the
page and it will show you
the JavaScript that
it generates.
You see those icons there?
Throughout this whole tutorial,
you're going to see
lots of code.
And next to the code, it's
either going to have a coffee
cup sometimes and a JS
sometimes, to designate
whether what you're looking at
is CoffeeScript or JavaScript.
Later on, you'll see just
CoffeeScript, and in that
case, I'm going to put that
CoffeeScript icon at the top
of the page--
also good to know in case you
look at the slides later.
So let's take a look at our
first CoffeeScript.
Here you can see some code.
If we ran that code, it would
make this alert pop up.
OK.
Well, what's the JavaScript
that this CoffeeScript is
generating?
It looks something like this.
Two things to notice here.
The first is that in
CoffeeScript, we don't have to
do any variable declaration.
It all gets handled for us.
Second thing to notice,
that there's no
semicolons in this code.
We don't have to deal with
those semicolons anymore.
I know, weren't they
a headache?
There are two different ways
we can declare functions in
JavaScript.
You've probably done
it both ways.
The first is by using
named functions.
It looks a little
bit like this.
Here, we're declaring
a coffee function.
We can also declare functions
in JavaScript using function
expressions.
They look like this.
Both of these functions we can
call in the same way by
running just Coffee,
Parens, Semicolon.
In CoffeeScript, it's only
going to create function
expressions for us.
So let's take a look at the
CoffeeScript code that
generates this JavaScript
down below.
Couple things to notice
about this code.
First of all, you'll notice
instead of using curly
brackets, we are
just indenting.
We can either use two spaces
or, if we want, we can just
use a tab, but you need
to be consistent.
The next thing you're going to
want to notice about this code
is that little arrow.
Well, that converts to the
function parens curly braces,
as you can see here
in JavaScript.
And lastly, all of the functions
that get generated
for us from CoffeeScript are
going to have a return value,
no matter what.
Even if you're not using it,
it's always going to have a
return value.
What's convenient about that
is you can assume the last
item in your function is what's
going to get returned.
You never have to use
that return keyword.
Let's take a look at that.
So here we have a CoffeeScript
function.
It's going to create a confirm
box and then it's going to
return, "Your answer is,"
whatever the answer is.
The JavaScript it would
generate is going
to look like this.
Notice the return
that got added.
The return value in
CoffeeScript, we can write in
a better way using an
interpolated string.
So here you can see, we say,
"Your answer is," answer.
It's going to get converted to
the same code in JavaScript
using the Plus.
To add function parameters,
this is how we do it in
CoffeeScript and this is
the JavaScript that
it's going to generate.
Pretty straightforward.
Let's talk a little bit about
how to call functions in
CoffeeScript.
So if I have just a single
function that doesn't have any
parameters, I can call Coffee
just like that.
If I have a function with one
parameter, I can call it with
or without the parentheses.
The parentheses are optional.
If I had two parameters, I could
also call it with or
without the parentheses.
Let's call our coffee function,
and then whatever
returns, let's put that out
into an alert like this.
First, it's going to print
out this Confirm box.
Then it's going to return the
string and alert's going to be
called on that string
to print this out.
If you take another look at
this alert function call,
you'll notice that there are
still some parentheses here
even though parentheses
are optional.
This would still work without
any parentheses, but it's sort
of a best practice to use
parentheses on everything but
the outermost function call.
So in this case, the outermost
function call is alert.
One nice feature about
CoffeeScript is that it gives
you the ability to do
optional parameters.
So what if I wanted to have an
optional parameter of, "Ready
for some coffee?"
as the message?
I'd write code that
looks like this.
Then if I call a function
without any parameters, it'll
ask, "Ready for some coffee?"
And if I send in a parameter,
it'll override the default and
ask, "Want some decaf?" In case
you're wondering, here's
the JavaScript that this
CoffeeScript compiles into.
Lastly, I want to talk briefly
about how to install
CoffeeScript, which is
completely optional for this
tutorial, and give you some
command line tools and talk
about the TextMate bundle.
So to install CoffeeScript,
first you're going to want to
install Node.js, so follow
the instructions there.
You'll then need to install
npm, which stands for node
package manager.
Then you'll use npm to
install CoffeeScript.
You're going to know you did it
right if you can go to the
command line and type coffee -h,
which will give you all of
the commands that you can
use to run CoffeeScript.
If we ran this command from
the command line, it would
take that test.coffee file and
it would convert it into
JavaScript into a
test.js file.
If we were going to make a lot
of changes to that file, if we
were developing with it, we
could add the W command here.
What that would do is it
would watch that file.
And every time it got saved,
it would then recompile the
CoffeeScript into the
JavaScript file.
If we had a bunch of files
in, let's say, the src
directory, we could
run this command.
It would look for .coffee files
inside that directory.
It would compile each of them
into JavaScript files and
output them, -o, into the
js directory.
Lastly, if we were doing a lot
of development with this code,
we could add that -w command,
which would keep an eye on
that src directory every time
a single .coffee file was
changed, it would compile
that into a .js
file into the js directory.
If you think you'll be using
TextMate or Sublime Text 2 to
edit your CoffeeScript, I highly
recommend you install
the plug-in.
Here's what the plug-in does.
So here, you can see
my CoffeeScript.
I can write CoffeeScript, and
then if I hit command B, it's
going to take that CoffeeScript,
compile it into
JavaScript, and show me the
output, which is really
convenient for debugging.
That's all we got
for level one.
At this point, before you jump
into the challenges, you might
want to take a moment to
download the slides.
In the bottom right hand
side of this page,
there should be a link.
You can click that, download the
PDF, because you'll want
to use them as reference to
solve the challenges.
Also, please don't be afraid
to use the hints.
They're there so that
you can use them.
So if you get stuck, let's
say, for longer than 10
minutes on a challenge and can't
figure it out, use a
hint or two or three so you can
get to the next challenge
and keep on progressing and
learning CoffeeScript.