[MUSIC PLAYING]
They call it CoffeeScript.
Come by and take a sip.
I know it's quite a trip, but
somehow you can write less
code to get more done.
Come on and take a seat.
Don't end up obsolete.
They call it CoffeeScript.
Welcome to Level Three of
A Sip of CoffeeScript.
In this level, we're going
to be walking through
conditionals and operators, so
conditionals like if, else.
Let's jump into it.
So an if statement in
JavaScript looks
something like this.
How would we write it
in CoffeeScript?
Well, as you can imagine,
the curly braces
are going to go away.
It's gonna look something
like this.
The parentheses, of course,
are optional.
We could also write this in a
single line if we wanted to,
alert('Under age') if
age < 18.
We can write this another way
in CoffeeScript using then.
We can say, if age < 18
then alert 'Under age'
What about using else?
Well in JavaScript, it looks
something like this.
In CoffeeScript, well, it's
just not going to have the
parentheses.
So something like this.
We can also write it using the
longer syntax, if age < 18
, then alert 'Under age',
else alert 'Of age'
It's worth noting that
CoffeeScript doesn't have any
ternary operators, so you're
not going to be able to use
question mark or
colon anywhere.
You're really encouraged to
be a little more verbose.
Next up, let's take a look at
the different operators and
what the CoffeeScript translates
to in JavaScript.
So if you have Equals Equals or
Is in CoffeeScript, that's
going to translate to Equals
Equals Equals in JavaScript.
It's just a safer way
to do equality.
Not Equals or Isnt is going
to be Not Equals Equals.
Not is just going to be
exclamation point.
And is going to be Ampersand
Ampersand.
Or is going to translate
to pipe.
True, Yes, or On is going to
translate to True, and False,
No, or Off is going to
translate to False.
Let's take a look at some
of these in action.
Here we have if paid() and
coffee() is on then pour()
So here you can see that is
on part is checking the
truthiness.
So let's take a look at
the JavaScript here.
Next up, we might say
addCaffeine if not decaf()
That's one way we
could write it.
Also in CoffeeScript, we could
write this as
addCaffeine() unless decaf()
Another cool feature of
CoffeeScript is the ability to
do chained comparisons.
So whereas you would have
something like this in
JavaScript, you can rewrite that
in CoffeeScript like so,
all chained together.
Next up, switch statements.
Here's how you might implement
a switch statement in
JavaScript.
It's kind of verbose,
isn't it.
Well, here's what it looks
like in CoffeeScript.
So you can see here it's much
nicer, much more readable,
much more maintainable and
dare I say, beautiful.
Lastly we're going to talk about
existential operators,
existential meaning
checking to see if
something exists or not.
So for example, how do we check
to see that cups of
coffee isn't defined and
it isn't equal to null?
Well, in JavaScript, we would
do something that looks like
this, right?
In CoffeeScript, we have a
better way of writing that.
We could write
if cupsOfCoffee?
alert 'it exists!'
Much nicer.
So we're just using that
question mark.
These two lines are pretty
much the same.
Or really, the CoffeeScript
compiles into that JavaScript.
We could also write this on a
single line if we wanted to,
just by writing
alert 'it exists!' if cupsOfCoffee?
What about when you want to set
a variable to a default
value if it hasn't been set yet,
if it's null or it hasn't
been defined yet.
Well, with the knowledge we have
so far, you could do it
like this, or if you wanted
to, you could do it in a
single line.
However, there's an even better
way to do this in
CoffeeScript.
You can simply do,
cups of coffee,
question mark equals zero.
So if it isn't defined or if
it's equal to null, it's going
to set it to zero.
What if we want to call a
function on an object only if
that object exists?
For example, call brew() on
coffeePot only if it exists.
Well with knowledge again that
we have so far, we could write
it like this, but CoffeeScript
has a better way to do it.
We can simply write
coffeePot?.brew()
That's all there is to it.
This existential operator
also works on functions.
So if you want to call a
function only if it exists on
an object, well, you
do it like this.
So here we have
vehicle.start_engine
It's only going to call that
start_engine function if that
function exists on vehicle, then
it's only going to call
the shift_gear function if the
shift_gear function exists on
whatever gets returned
from start_engine.
If you're familiar with the
try function in the Ruby
programming language, this kind
of functions like try.
So it's going to try to run
this function only if this
function exists.
Now you don't want to overuse
that existential operator
here, especially with in regards
to this function here.
It can be considered a bad code
smell, just so you know.
Don't want to overuse it.
But that brings us to the
end of level three.
So now it's time to get your
hands dirty in some of the
challenges.