(SINGING) They call
it CoffeeScript.
Come by and take a sip.
I know it's quite a trip, but
somehow you can write less
code to get more done.
Yeah!
Come on and take a seat.
Don't end up obsolete.
We call it CoffeeScript.
All right, you're halfway
done with the course.
Now, we're onto level four.
We're going to be talking
about arrays,
objects, and iteration.
So in CoffeeScript, we have
these things called ranges.
So we can say range
range = [1..4]
And that's going to translate
into the JavaScript of just
one, two, three, four
in an array.
We can also say range = [1...4]
So that's three dots, which is
going to give us an array with
everything but the last item.
So it's just going to be one,
two, three in JavaScript.
This may not seem
very powerful.
Where it starts to get more
powerful is when you realize
that you can use it with
variables and to get subsets
of existing arrays.
So here we have two variables,
and we have a
start and an end.
So it's going to create
an array with 5, 6,
7, 8, 9, and 10.
Then we can get a subset of that
array by just doing one
dot dot four.
And that's going to return six,
seven, eight, and nine.
We could get a range from
one with three dots to
range.length.
So we would get from
the second item to
the end of the array.
We could also write this with
just range = [1..-1]
So when we do negative 1, it
will wrap around from the
front to the very last item.
To create a basic array in
CoffeeScript, you can either
do the normal sort of array
syntax you see here.
But you can also take out
the commas if you
use the proper spacing.
So here you can see we have
storeLocations, Orlando,
Winter Park, and Sanford,
just like that.
Now, let's talk a little bit
about looping through the
array we just created.
So we can obviously just
do a forEach loop.
That's going to translate
from CoffeeScript into
JavaScript like so.
Pretty basic, nothing
amazing there.
However, it's much more common
in CoffeeScript to not do a
forEach and do something
that looks a little
bit more like this.
We have for location
in storeLocations.
So it's going to go through each
of the items in the store
locations array, set it equal
to location every time it
iterates through the loop, and
then call alert on it.
So we should have three
different alerts.
If we wanted to, we could also
move this for loop to the end
of the line.
So we could say alert location
for location in
storeLocations.
There's another word for this.
It's called a list
comprehension.
Let's take a look at a couple
more list comprehensions.
So what if we wanted to add
", FL" for each of those
cities in our array?
Well, we could write
it like this.
So we have our interpolated
string for location in
storeLocations, and that
would be the array that
it returns for us.
If we wanted to overwrite our
original array, we want to
write it like this.
The parentheses here are
really important.
Keep that in mind.
If we didn't have the
parentheses around the list
comprehension, it would set
storeLocation equal to
Orlando, then Winter
Park, then Sanford.
So the result would be
storeLocations equals Sanford.
But because we have the
parentheses there, it's going
to build the array and then
send that array into the
variable we declared.
Another list comprehension
example, if we wanted to call
the geoLocate function on each
of our storeLocations except
for the Sanford location, we
could say for location in
storeLocations when location
isn't Sanford.
That's called a filter, and
you can put any sort of
expression after a filter.
What if we wanted to create a
new array, a brand new array,
without Sanford?
How would we do that?
Well, one way we could do that
is like this, basically
reiterating through each item,
push that onto our brand new
array, and we would have a new
array without Sanford.
However, let's use a
list comprehension.
So we could also do this by
doing location for location in
storeLocations when location
isn't Sanford.
Now, I know this may look
a little bit confusing.
Feel free to pause the video
and let it absorb.
But all this is saying is
return location for each
location where location
isn't Sanford.
So it's going to return an array
that doesn't include the
Sanford location.
Next up, let's talk about using
splats in CoffeeScript.
It's a fun name, and we use it
for when we want to have a
variable number of parameters
sent into a function, or send
a variable number of parameters
into a function.
Let me explain.
So here we have a function
called searchLocations.
You can see we have the dot
dot dot in the parameters.
Now, we can call that function
using two parameters.
We would get this returned.
We can also call this function
using three parameters or four
parameters or five parameters.
You can see here that it's
basically taking whatever
parameters are after the first
one and combining them into an
array, which we are then joining
inside of that string.
Not only can splats be used in
the definition of a function,
but you can also use them
to call a function.
Let me show you.
You see here, we have a
parameter array, array of the
parameters.
Well, we can send in those
parameters into our
searchLocation function.
And these two lines are
basically equivalent.
Next up, let's talk about
objects which you're probably
already familiar with, the term
JavaScript objects, where
you have a key and
you have a value.
In some languages, we
call these hashes.
So here is an object inside
CoffeeScript, pretty basic.
Optionally, we can remove
the curly braces.
We can do without the
curly braces.
And, if we want to, we can
even get rid of a comma.
So if we write it in a spaced
out way, with two spaces in
this case, we can avoid
the commas.
In jQuery Air Captain's Log, we
covered how to encapsulate
a function inside
of an object.
Here's how we might do
that in CoffeeScript.
You'll notice here that I'm
using the @ symbol here.
So @name, that's going to
reference the value
French, in this case.
We can call this function by
just doing coffee.brew()
And here's the JavaScript that
it's going to generate for us.
Let's add one more function
to our coffee object.
We're going to call it pour.
It's going to have a default
parameter of one for amount.
And that's all there is to it.
Here's the JavaScript that's
going to generate for that
particular function.
It should be said that you need
to be careful with your
indenting when you're
doing CoffeeScript.
Obviously, indenting
matters a lot.
For example, if I didn't get the
indenting right with this
object, here's the JavaScript
that it would render out.
Let's take a look at a more
complex object, maybe an
object that has other objects
inside of it.
So here you can see I have a
bunch of different coffees
inside each of those coffees.
It has the strength of
that coffee and how
many I have in stock.
If I wanted to see how much
Italian I have in stock, I
would use this command
right here.
Here's the JavaScript that the
CoffeeScript is going to
compile into.
Now let's play with
that object.
What if we wanted to iterate
through that object, printing
out certain things?
Could we use a list
comprehension?
Well, we can, although it will
look slightly different.
So we're going to print out the
coffee and then the number
we have in stock.
We're going to iterate through
each of them, storing the key
in coffee and the rest of the
object in attributes.
You'll notice that of
key word there.
When we were doing list
comprehensions with arrays, it
had in instead of of.
When we want to iterate through
an object, we use the
of keyword and specify two
variables that we want to
store the key and the value in
every time it iterates through
things in that object.
Here's what this would
print out.
And another way we could write
this loop is by doing
something like this.
Now, what if we wanted to print
this out nicely, the
string we're creating here, but
we didn't want to include
any of the coffees that don't
have anything in stock?
What might that look like?
We might do something
like this, where we
have a to_print variable.
You'll notice here we're doing
when
attrs.in_stock > 0
So we're using a filter.
And at the very bottom, we're
joining the array together.
So we would get French has
20, Italian has 12.
If you take a look at the
JavaScript that's generated
from this CoffeeScript,
well, it's longer, and
it's not very pretty.
So you can start to see some
of the beautiful code that
CoffeeScript allows
us to write.
You don't have to write any
of this extra stuff to do
something that we can
explain using less
code to get more done.
And that's about it.
We've reached the end
of level four.
It's time to get into the
challenges, maybe do some
arrays, some objects, and some
list comprehensions.