They call it CoffeeScript.
Come by and take a sip.
I know it's quite a trip.
But somehow you can write less
code to get more done.
Yeah.
Come on and take a seat,
don't end up obsolete.
They call it CoffeeScript.
CoffeeScript, yeah.
Welcome to the second level of
"A Sip of CoffeeScript." In
this level, we're not going
to be learning any new
CoffeeScript concepts.
We're simply going to be
applying them and practicing
them using some jQuery.
If you played through the
jQuery Air Captain's Log
course, some of this should
look familiar.
We're going to take some jQuery
from there and convert
it to CoffeeScript.
You'll remember, if you played
jQuery Air Captain's Log, that
we had this flight selector you
see down here with a bunch
of different tabs.
And we could select a tab, and
it would become active.
The code that we wrote looked
something like this.
Here, we have the
jQuery wrapper.
On the click event for one of
these tabs called the Change
Tab Function, here is the Change
Tab Function where we
call Prevent Default.
Then we remove the active class
from the one that's
currently active.
And we add the active class
to the clicked tab.
Let's start converting this line
by line to CoffeeScript.
Often in CoffeeScript code
you'll see people just use
Dollar Sign, Arrow.
And that's fine to do as long as
jQuery is the only library
in your application that's
using that dollar sign.
Let's use that in our code.
Let's move that up.
Next is the function
definition.
We can define Change Tab.
For most of the remaining lines,
all we really have to
do is remove the semicolons
and curly brackets.
Let's do that.
Our code is looking nicer.
We can also optionally remove
the parentheses from some of
those function calls.
Let's go ahead and do that.
There's one last thing we
can do this code to
make it look nice.
You see that "this"
word in there?
Well, in CoffeeScript we have
a shortcut for this.
We can simply use the @ sign.
So, I could write this
line like this.
Now, let's take a look at
the JavaScript and the
CoffeeScript we wrote
side by side.
Feel free to pause the video at
this point if you want to
take a closer look and really
examine the differences.
Let's convert a couple more
snippets of JavaScript to
CoffeeScript.
Here you can see we have
a click handler.
To convert that to CoffeeScript,
it would look
something like this.
Here's some JavaScript
where we use a queue.
Let's convert this
to CoffeeScript.
It would look something
like this.
Before you jump into the
challenges, let's take a look
at one more example.
Here's some JavaScript
from jQuery Air.
Let's convert this
line by line.
So
First line, here is the
function definition.
Next line, we declare the
num_flights variable.
You notice I'm using the @
symbol instead of this.
Next line, we have
(this).append.
Again, I'm using
the @ symbol.
You'll notice here we're using
an interpolated string.
And the last line is
pretty obvious.
It's basically the same thing
without the semicolon.
And that about wraps up
the second level.
I know it was pretty short.
But I want to get you more
familiar with using this new
CoffeeScript syntax.
In the challenges, you're going
to write some jQuery and
convert it from JavaScript
to CoffeeScript.