Congratulations, you made it
all the way to the end of A
Sip Of Coffee Script.
Hope you enjoyed the ride.
In this outro, I'm going to be
talking about other resources
you can use to continue
learning CoffeeScript.
We'll then do some credits, and
then finally, we'll just
thank you profusely for playing
through the course.
So let's get to it.
First of all,
coffeescript.org, great resource.
If you haven't gone through the
main CoffeeScript website
yet, I highly recommend
you go through it.
Lots of really good
information.
And the cool part about this is
if you scroll down, you see
all these different--
this Load button down here, if
you hit Load, it loads it
right into the Try CoffeeScript
window, so you
come play with it, and run it,
and experiment with modifying
your CoffeeScript, just
like you did in
the application interface.
Next up, Jeremy.
This is the guy who created
CoffeeScript.
He's got a GoRoku talk here
where he talks about
CoffeeScript for the
well-rounded Rubyist, but even
though you don't have to be a
Ruby guy to see this guy talk.
Pretty good talk, also, but
introductory for you at this
point, since you already know
some of this stuff.
Also, a little book on
CoffeeScript, another really
good online resource for
continuing your learning, if
you'd like to go and read
through more documentation.
Next up, also Smooth
CoffeeScript.
Both the previous book and
this book are free.
You can view it online
and go through it.
Next up, if you're a fan
of Ryan Bates, he did a
RailsCasts on the topic
back in May, 2011.
Take a look at that
if you want.
All these links, by the way,
are in the sidebar.
Also, if you don't mind paying
a few bucks, Geoffrey
Grosenbach did a CoffeeScript
PeepCode.
If you played through one of the
other Code School courses
where you got a free PeepCode,
you can use that for this if
you want to.
Also, the Pragmatic Programmers
put out a
CoffeeScript book.
It's a paid book, but I've heard
good things about it, so
I want to let you
know about it.
Also, my friend Mark Bates is
putting together a programming
in CoffeeScript book.
It's not complete yet, but you
can view the rough cuts if you
go on Safari and follow
the link.
It might be done by the
time you're watching
this, so check it out.
Also, the CoffeeScript
Cookbook.
Free, online cookbook for
CoffeeScript recipes for the
community, by the community.
So this is really good
reading to sort of
further your knowledge.
So if you want to find out how
to do capitalizing words, you
click that, and there it goes.
It gives you a solution.
Sometimes multiple solutions.
Really good read to figure out
how to do complicated things
in CoffeeScript.
Also, if you go to this URL on
GitHub, you'll see the most
popular open source projects
that are using CoffeeScript,
and it might be a good read.
It's always good to read
through code to get
familiar with it.
One of these on there, which
you might have heard of, is
Hubot, which is get GitHub's
Campfire bot.
That's all in CoffeeScript
as well.
OK, it's time for the credits.
First I've got to thank
Caike Souza, who works
here at Envy Labs.
He helped me a lot with all
the different challenges,
putting together all the code
for the course, and putting
together the course itself.
Eric Allam is one of our lead
code school developers here at
Envy Labs, and he also helped
a lot the course together.
Tim Dikun, one of our lead
graphic designers did most of
the graphic design that you saw
on the course, as well as
Drew Barontini also did
a lot of the graphic
design code up in CSS.
Everett Simpson did the jingle
that's stuck in your head.
CoffeeScript, yeah.
And Oliver Tosh is
our video guy.
Got to thank him for doing
all the good video.
And finally, everyone
else at Envy Labs.
While Envy Labs supports Code
School for now, it's
definitely not profitable yet.
If you dig this course
and you want to see
us create more content--
God, we spend a lot of money
on these courses--
if you want to see more of it,
maybe consider enrolling in
code school.
For just $25 a month, you can
get access to not only courses
as we put them out-- we try to
do about one a month-- you get
access to all of our Code TV
screencasts, which we put out
once a week, and some
other perks as well.
So if you're not a member yet,
consider enrolling if you want
to support us.
And I think that's about it.
Lastly, thank you.
Thank you for getting through
CoffeeScript course and
supporting Code School.
And if you want to Tweet about
it, we'd appreciate it.
Feel free to give us your
feedback, any feedback about
the course, additional courses
you want to see.
If you want to review the
course using that button
below, that would be
great as well.
And that's about it.
So, thanks for playing A Sip
Of CoffeeScript, and
have a great day.