[SINGING]
He's got your data in his pocket
and a gun in his hand.
He's got his finger on the
trigger and a secret plan.
He'll take mutable arrays and
put them in formation using
your view controllers for
his world domination.
He'll take your data into models
before it explodes.
The only secret agent who
encodes and decodes.
He's Mr. Higgie.
Hi.
I'm Jon Friskics, and this
is iOS Operation Models.
In this course, we're going to
be learning how to create
models and use them to represent
data inside of your
application.
Now where we left off in Try
iOS, we were building an app
called InstaPhoto, and
InstaPhoto had a couple views.
It had a
FeedTableViewController.
It had a PhotoViewController
that you could activate by
tapping on one of the cells in
the FeedTableViewController.
It had a favorites table view
controller, and it had a
ProfileViewController
that stored
information about Mr. Higgie.
We're going to be updating
InstaPhoto to use models.
Now if we think about MVC and
what each of those pieces
represent, we've got our views,
which are used to
display data inside
the application.
We've got controllers, which are
used to tell the views how
to display data.
And we really should have all of
our data in models so that
our controllers can read data
from those models and display
it in the views.
And models really just make it
very easy to organize and
store data inside
an application.
So the current approach that
we're using in InstaPhoto is
we have a
FeedTableViewController that
contains a UI table view
with a list of photos.
When one of the cells is tapped
in that UI table view,
a photo view controller is
displayed on screen that gives
a little bit more detail
about each photo.
That's no good!
Mr. Higgie's right.
This is not the best approach
because we have a controller
that's drawing views using data
that comes from inside a
controller rather than
from inside a model.
So if we want to update this
approach to use an MVC
architecture, we're going
to still have a
FeedTableViewController and
PhotoViewController, except
the data inside of our
FeedTableViewController is
going to come from a model.
And the way this works is that
the FeedTableViewController,
when it loads, requests a model
template, and then the
model template is returned to
the FeedTableViewController
with a set of data.
Hooray!
Now, creating a model
is really easy.
All you need to do is go into
Xcode and choose New File,
give that file a name,
and make it
a subclass of NSObject.
NSObject is the base parent
class of almost everything in
Objective C.
So this is the code that Xcode
will create for you whenever
you create a new model that's
a subclass of NSObject.
If we look at the classes that
we've already been using, like
UITabBarController and
UINavigationController, if we
follow the class hierarchy up to
the top, we would see that
UITabBar and
UINavigationController are
subclasses of UIViewController.
UIViewController, in turn, is
a subclass of a class called
UIResponder, and UIResponder
is a subclass of NSObject.
So even when we look
at something like a
UITabBarController, we can see
that ultimately it inherits
from NSObject, just like
our model will.
To help you understand how
models work, we're going to
use an app that Mr. Higgie ends
up using every day called
Planet Hig, and planet Hig has
a similar feature set to
InstaPhoto, so we'll be able
to learn a lot from each.
There's a
PlacesTableViewController that
contains a list of places that
Higgie visits while he's on
his international travels, and
then if you click on one of
those cells, a
PlaceViewController gets
loaded that has more detailed
information about that place.
There's an InterestingPlace
sTableViewController that Mr.
Higgie can mark places as
interesting that he wants to
go visit later, and then there's
a CityViewControler
that contains information
about the city that he's
currently visiting.
Straight to the top
of the app store!
And if we were to analyze the
structure of that app, it
would look something
like this.
We have an AppDelegate that runs
when the app first loads,
and that AppDelegate loads the
individual controllers,
PlacesTableViewController,
InterestingPlace
sTableViewController, and
CityViewController.
This is the code that Xcode will
create for you whenever
you create a new model that's
a subclass of NSObject.
First we import the foundation
library, as most header
classes do.
Then you can see that the
@inaterface declares the model
name and the subclass of
that model, and then
the header file ends.
And then the implementation
file imports place.h to
connect the two and declares
that there's going to be an
implementation of the place
object, and then the
implementation ends.
Even though Planet Hig contains
multiple places,
you'll notice that we're
naming our model class
singular not plural.
This is a common convention
when naming models.
Inside of our place.h file,
we're going to need to declare
some properties, and these will
hold the data that gets
stored inside the model.
In Planet Hig, the place model
has two NSString properties,
one for the name of the
place and one for a
description of the place.
In place.m, we're going to need
to create a method called
init that's responsible for
instantiating and returning a
copy of a place object.
Init returns type ID, and inside
of init, we have to set
self equal to super init.
Now, self refers to the class
that we're currently in, which
in this case is place, and super
refers to the parent
class of self, which in
this case is NSObject.
So really, what we're doing when
we write super init is
we're saying go up to the super
of place, NSObject, and
run the init method
in NSObject.
That's going to return an
instantiated copy of our
model, which we then set to
self, and then we'll return
self, which is a copy of the
object we just created.
Now that we've seen how a
place model object is
initialized, we can initialize
one in a view controller to
see how the properties work.
First we'll send the place model
an alloc init message,
which creates a local copy of
the object stored here in
aPlace variable, and then
we'll set the name and
description properties
of that place.
And then if we NSLog that name
and description, we can see
that it logs out to the console
and our model was
created correctly.
So notice that there's two ways
that we can retrieve the
data that's inside
of our object.
The first way is by passing a
message, and the second way is
just by accessing the property
through dot-notation.
Dot-notation is a recent
addition to Objective C, so
both approaches are
still valid.
So now it's time for you to
start coding up your first
models in the challenges.