Often we need to create multiple
model objects based
on one model class.
To do that, we just alloc init
multiple model objects and set
the properties individually
of each.
That's a lot of repetition.
If there's one thing Mr. Higgy
hates, it's wasting time with
repetition.
So to fix this, we can use
what's called a convenience
initializer to combine object
instantiation and data setting
into one step.
So here we've created a method
called init with name
description that we can
use instead of the
standard init method.
Notice that this initializer
takes two arguments, one for
the name property of the place
model and one for the
description property
of the place model.
Unfortunately, we don't
get these kinds
of methods for free.
We have to define them in our
model if we want to use them.
So we'll start by going to the
place.h class and declaring
the init with name description
method, like we see here.
And then to implement the init
with name description method,
it's very similar to how our
default initializer works.
We first have to write self
equals super init.
And then we're going to want
to check if that object was
created correctly first.
So we write if self.
If self was not created
correctly, we don't want to be
trying to set properties
on it.
But if it is, we want to set the
self.name property equal
to aName and the
self.description property
equal to aDescription,
aName and aDescription being
the local arguments for the
strings that the user sent in.
Then we return a copy of that
self object and we have a
place object containing the name
and description that were
passed into the convenience
initializer.
And now we can run this
initializer with the init with
name description method we
declared in the place model.
We've got a great convenience
initializer but what happens
when we call init in
our application?
Now let's create two places, one
with our new convenience
initializer and one with the
standard init message.
When we log out the name
property of each of these new
model objects, we can expect
to get two names
logged to the console.
But instead, place one correctly
logs out the name
property and place
two logs out nil.
What country is nil in?
What Higgy's pointing out is
that we don't ever want one of
our model properties to
have a nil value.
To prevent these kinds of nil
values, we can add some code
to our init method that calls
our convenience initializer
init with name description and
returns an instance of an
object that has some
default values
inside of it, like this.
Now if we create two place
models, one with the init with
name description initializer
and one with the standard
initializer, the standard
initializer will actually be
calling init with name
description.
Then, if we log out the name
property of each of our place
objects, we will have
no nil values.
There are several conventions
that you'll want to follow
when you're creating
new models.
The first relates to
memory management.
You want to always declare your
properties as strong nonatomic.
Next, any arguments that you
pass into a convenience
initializer should start with
either a, an, or the.
So instead of arguments like
city and address, these should
be written as aCity
or anAddress.
And finally, if you have a long
method name which you
usually will when you're
creating convenience
initializer, you should line up
the different parts of the
method name by vertically
aligning the colons that
separate the argument data types
and the argument names.
You've reached the end of the
video so now it's time to try
some more challenges.