[SINGING]
He's got your data in his pocket
and a gun in his hand.
He's got his finger on the
trigger and a secret plan.
He'll take mutable arrays and
put them in formation using
your view controllers for
his world domination.
He'll take your data into models.
before it explodes, the
only secret agent
who encodes and decodes.
He's Mr. Higgie.
Welcome to Level 2 of iOS
Operation Models.
In this level, we're going to
look at how we can efficiently
get data into our
model objects.
As I mentioned in the last
level, Planet Hig has a
controller called
CityViewController.
CityViewController contains a
view that has three subviews,
one for the name of the city,
one for the state that the
city is in, and one for the
population of that city, and
those are all stored
in UI labels.
So let's see where that
city data comes from.
There's a JSON file called
cityData.json that contains
one NSDictionary, and that
NSDictionary has keys for two
NSStrings and one NSNumber.
Now the old way that we would
get this data inside of a view
controller is we would declare
a property of type
NSDictionary, and then we would
make an AFJSONRequest
Operation to get that JSON file,
and then store that JSON
response inside of
self.cityData.
Once we had the JSON response
stored, we'd call a method
like dataRetrieved so that we
could then draw our UI labels
and other subviews
on to the canvas.
Here in dataRetrieved, all we're
doing is logging out the
JSON response to make sure
that the AFJSONRequest
operation worked properly.
This seems like a good
place for a model.
That's right Mr. Higgie.
We can take all this
data and store it
inside of a city model.
To create that city model,
just like we did with the
place model, we need a city.h
and a city.m file.
Just like with the place model,
our city model needs to
be a subclass of NSObject.
And in the city.h file, we
want to declare our three
properties as part
of the model--
name, state, and population--
and in the city.m file, want
to create our initializer.
Back in CityViewController,
we'll want to import City.h so
that we can access the
city model inside of
CityViewController, and we'll
want to change that
NSDictionary property
to a city property.
Then in CityViewController.m,
instead of storing the JSON
response in an NSDictionary,
we'll want to set each one of
the city model properties equal
to the values in the
JSON object.
Down in dataRetrieved, we can
then log out the model
properties instead of
the dictionary keys.
The problem here is that
the controller is still
responsible for fetching the
data, not the model.
We have a CityViewController
that's requesting a city model
template, and then it's
returning that template into
the view controller and setting
all the data from
inside the controller before
it displays on the view.
What we really want to
happen is we want the
CityViewController to still
request a model object, but we
want that model object to
initialize itself with data
and return a fully data-filled
copy back to the controller.
I love convenient solutions.
To implement an initWithJSON
convenience initializer, we
first need to declare that
initializer in the city.h
file, and then we need to
implement it in city.m.
the implementation of
initWithJSON is going to be a
pretty standard initializer,
except after we create a copy
of the self object and check if
it exists, we're going to
want to move all of our
AFJSONRequestOperation code
from CityViewController into the
initWithJSON initializer
in the city model.
Then, inside of the
AFJSONRequestOperation, we're
going to be setting the model
properties equal to the values
that are returned by the JSON.
Since we're inside of the city
class itself, we can reference
those model properties with
self.name, self.state, and
self.population instead of
first trying to create an
intermediary object to
access them through.
All we should have to do is
create a new city object using
the initWithJSON initializer,
and then we should be able to
NSLog the properties inside
of the object.
But when we try to do that
here, we get nil.
What the nil is going on?
To understand why these values
are coming up as nil, let's
look at what's happening
whenever we call the
initWithJSON method.
First, CityViewController
requests a copy of the city
object using the initWithJSON
method, which then fires
initWithJSON method
inside the model.
At the same time,
CityViewController doesn't stop.
It continues executing.
At some point in the future,
the model object returns an
instantiated copy of the city
object, and the view in
CityViewController tries
to display data.
The problem is that there's
no guarantee that the
initWithJSON method returns a
filled model before the views
in CityViewController
try to be displayed.
Some people refer to the way
this code is working as
non-blocking because the
CityViewController doesn't
stop and wait for the
model to come back.
It just keeps running.
The way that we can solve this
problem is using a tool called
Notifications, and the way this
is going to work is that
the controller is still going to
ask for a model, the model
is still going to call the
initWithJSON method, and then
when the initWithJSON method is
finished and data is fully
loaded, it's going to
post a notification.
Back in CityViewController,
there's going to be some code
that is listening for
notification to occur, and
when that notification occurs,
the views are going to be
filled with data.
NS NotificationCenter is a
messaging center that can be
used by different parts of the
application to listen for
different events, or
notifications, happening.
In addition to listening, the
NSNotificationCenter can be
used to broadcast events,
which is called posting
notifications.
To post a notification,
you can send the
postNotificationName object
method to the
NSNotificationCenter
defaultCenter object, and to
listen for a notification, you
can send the addObserver
selector name object method to
the NSNotificationCenter
defaultCenter object.
The value for post-notification
name can be
any string that you want, but I
suggest naming it something
that makes sense.
So I've named this string
initWithJSONFinishedLoading,
because this is going to be a
message that we post whenever
initWithJSON finishes loading
all if its data.
Listening for a notification
has a few more arguments.
The first argument, observer,
is going to be whatever
instance will be listening
for the notification.
In our case, that's going
to be self, the
CityViewController.
The selector is going to be
a method that gets called
whenever the notification
is heard.
In this case, we're going to
call our dataRetrieved
selector, which then fills all
of our views with data.
The name argument is the name
of the notification, which
from our posting, was called
initWithJSONFinishedLoading,
and the object argument is an
optional argument that lets
you listen for notifications
that only come
from a specific object.
In this case, we want to listen
for that notification
coming from anywhere, so we'll
set that value to nil.
So back in initWithJSON, we're
going to want to post the
notification that initWithJSON
method has finished loading
after all of the data is set
inside each of the model
properties.
Then, in viewDidLoad in
CityViewController, we're
going to want to listen for
a notification with the
addObserver selector
name object method.
Once the notification is heard,
we're going to call the
dataRetrieved method that logs
out the state and population
values from the city object.
And we can see that those values
log properly now.
While we're optimizing things,
why not go ahead and make
initWithJSON the designated
initializer in the city model?
To do that, in city.m, we'll
just make sure to set self
equal to self initWithJSON
inside of the standard init
method, and then
CityViewController's
viewDidLoad, will call self.city
equals City alloc
init, instead initWithJSON, and
the initWithJSON method
will still run.
Notification name, OHYEAAAAAA!
Oh yeah is right, Mr. Higgie.
And now it's time for you to
try some more challenges.