[SINGING]
He's got your data in his pocket
and a gun in his hand.
He's got his finger on the
trigger and a secret plan.
He'll take mutable arrays and
put them in formation using
your view controllers for
his world dominiation.
He'll take your
data into models
before it explodes, the
only secret agent
who encodes and decodes.
He's Mr. Higgie.
Hi and welcome back to Level
3 of iOS Operation Models.
In this level, now that we have
models with data inside
of them, we're going to look at
how to populate views with
data from models.
So if we look at the structure
of Planet Hig so far, we've
already looked at the
CityViewController, so let's
spend some time looking at the
PlaceTableViewController and
see how that table view
gets its data.
It gets its data from a file
called placedata.json, and the
structure of placedata.json is
an NSArray that contains three
NSDictionary objects, and each
one of those NSDictionary
objects contains
two NSStrings.
So we have array of dictionaries
instead of just a
single dictionary, like
we had with city.
If we followed our standard way
AFJSONRequest operation,
we would make a request for
placedata.json, and when that
request was received, we
would have an NSArray--
I'm calling this one places--
that we store the JSON
response in.
And this works, but
it's not creating
any place model objects.
It's just creating dictionaries
in an array.
So let's refactor to store an
array of place models instead
of dictionaries.
First, in
PlaceTableViewController.h,
we'll need to import place.h h
so we can access the place
model from inside
this controller.
And we don't actually need to
change the NSArray property
because we're still going
to end up with
an NSArray of objects.
Then, inside of
PlaceTableViewController.m, we
can create several different
place objects and use the
convenience initializer,
initWithName description, and
the values that come from
the JSON response.
And then store all of those
in the self.places array.
And this works too, but it's
not very efficient.
For example, what if there are
20 objects that we need to
create, or 100 objects that
we need to create?
That's going to be a lot
of code repetition
that we don't need.
The solution we're looking for
is part of the Objective C
language, and it's called
fast enumeration.
Fast enumeration is basically
just an easy way to create a
for loop and loop through
individual pieces inside of
some array all at once.
Imagine that we have an NSArray
called catNames, and
that array has four names
inside of it--
Fluffy, Pepper, Whiskers,
and HiggieCat.
If we want to enumerate through
each one of those
items in the array one at a
time, we can use the for in
enumerator.
And the way this works is that
we write "for," and then
inside the parentheses, we
declare an object that will be
local to that loop and the data
type for that object.
So here I've declared NSString
catName, and then I say in
catNames array.
Now inside of that loop, we can
do anything that we want.
Here I'll just NSLog out
the value so we can
see that it's working.
And I can NSLog, cat name is,
the catName variable that's
local to this enumerator.
If we run this code, we see the
console output is cat name
is Fluffy, cat name is Pepper,
cat name is Whiskers, and cat
name is HiggieCat.
Now this is gonna
speed things up.
You bet it is, Mr. Higgie.
So now let's go back to our
original problem, figuring out
a way to quickly create
place model objects.
Our goal is to have an NSArray
called places that has place
object 1, place object 2, place
object 3, all the way up
to as many place objects as we
need stored in a single array.
To accomplish this, we're going
to want to create a for
in loop where we pass in
a single NSDictionary--
I'm calling ours
oneDictionary--
that exists inside
the JSON object.
And then inside the loop, I'll
create a temporary place
object using the initWithName
description convenience
initializer and the values that
exist in that dictionary,
and then I'll take the
self.places array and
add the new place
object onto it.
But this is not going to work.
The reason is we can't actually
modify an NSArray
after it's been created.
So Objective C has two types of
some classes called mutable
and immutable.
NSArray is an immutable class,
which means that once it's
been instantiated, you
can't change the
objects inside of it.
So Objective C provides a set of
mutable class versions for
every one of the immutable
classes that it has.
And you can see a list
of these here.
NSString has an equivalent
called and NSMutableString.
NSArray has an equivalent
called
NSMutableArray, and so on.
Now you're probably asking,
why can't I use mutable
classes all the time?
Why do immutable classes
even exist?
Well, there's some complicated
reasons, like memory
management and threading, that
can be affected when you use
mutable versus immutable.
But using mutable classes can
also be a problem if you're
trying to keep track of your
data and make sure that it's
not getting accidentally
rewritten.
To solve our problem, we're
going to use an
NSMutableArray, but we're only
going to use it really quick
and in a temporary fashion, and
we're going to reassign
the output of that mutable array
to an immutable version.
So here you can see we're
creating a temporary
NSMutableArray outside
of the enumerator.
And then inside of the
enumerateor, we're still
creating a new place object
for each one of the
dictionaries inside of our JSON
response, and then we're
adding the new object to
the temporary array.
When the enumerator finishes
running, we should have
tempArray filled with
place model objects.
Then we take the place model
objects in the tempArray, and
we recast it as an NSArray
so we can store it in
self.places.
So now it's your turn to try a
few challenges related to fast
enumeration.