We've got an NS array
called, self.places.
And now we need to put that data
to use in the
PlaceTableViewController.
Like all UITableView
Controllers we need to
implement these three methods
tableView numberOfRowsInSection,
tableView cellForRowIndexPath,
and
tableView didSelectRowIndexPath.
And when we're done our output
should look like the
screen on the right.
We're not doing anything
new and tricky.
This is the standard approach
to creating UI table views.
So in tableView
numberOfRowsInSection,
we're going to want to use the
count of our places array, and
return that so we have the
correct number of rows.
In tableView
cellForRowIndexPath,
we'll use our standard code for
creating a cell, checking
if it hasn't been created yet.
And then we need to set the
textLabel.text property of the
cell, equal to data that's
inside the self.places array.
Now you're probably going to
want to write self.places,
indexPath.row.name, and think
you can access the name
property of the place model
that's in that array position.
But that's actually
incorrect syntax.
The reason is, is that Objective
C is going to
interpret this as trying to
take the name property of
indexPath.row, instead of
the place object that
indexPath.row returns.
So instead we can use the
messaging notation and get the
correct property out
of the object.
And here self.places
at indexpath.row will
first return a place object.
And then the name message will
pull the name property out of
that place object.
And finally in table view,
didSelectRowAtIndexPath, we're
going to deselect the row that
was currently tapped.
We're going to create
a new place view
controller called placeVC.
And then we're going to set
the place property of the
PlaceViewController equal to
the current place model that
was tapped.
That we can access from
self.places@indexPath.row.
And then finally we're going
to want to push that place
view controller on to the
navigation stack using
self.navigationController,
pushViewController:placeVC,
and will animate
the transition.
So here you can see what our
place table view controller
looks like, after we set up
all the UI table view
controller code correctly.
Next, since we're pushing to
PlaceViewController from
PlaceTableViewController,
we're going to want to set
PlaceViewController up so
that it can manage a place
object that we're
sending into it.
So in PlaceViewController.h,
I'll import the place.h
header, so I can access
the place model class.
And then I'll declare a
property called Place.
In PlaceViewControllers
implementation, I'll set up
all of my labels in
viewDidLoad.
And then I'll set the data
inside of those labels in
viewWillAppear.
And of course the data that I'm
pulling from is going to
be coming from the
self.place object.
Once PlaceViewController is
set up, we're now able to tap
a cell in PlaceTableViewController,
and be pushed over
to a PlaceViewController class
that lists all of the
information in that
place object.
As long as we're filling all our
different controllers with
data, let's go ahead and fill
the CityViewController up
with data from the city model.
First let's imports city.h
into the city
view controller class.
And then create a property
for the city model.
Just like we did with place.
That's right.
And CityViewController.m
looks similar to
PlaceViewController.m.
In viewDidLoad we create
copies of all of our labels.
And in viewWillAppear, we
set the text properties of
those labels using data that's
inside of the city model.
Once we have data in all three
of those controllers, you can
see that Planet Hig is really
starting to come together.
And here's what the structure
of our classes
looks like so far.
And that's all we
need to display
model data in to views.
And now it's your turn to
try a few challenges.