[SINGING]
He's got your data in his pocket
and a gun in his hand.
He's got his finger on the
trigger and a secret plan.
He'll take mutable arrays and
put them in formation using
your controllers for his--
World domination.
[SINGING]
He'll take your dollar and the
models before it explodes, the
only secret agent who
encodes and decodes.
He's Mr. Higgie.
Hi, and welcome back to
iOS: Operation Models.
In level four, we're going to
talk about editing data inside
of Models after it's
been instantiated.
Planet Hig's data is in a
pretty good place, but Higgie
wants to be able to add notes
about a city that he's
visiting from the City
View Controller.
It really is a useful feature.
Ultimately, we're going to want
to get to a point where
we can tap an Edit button at
the top right of the View
Controller and open up an Edit
View Controller where we can
edit note information
about that city.
Then when we tap on Save Note,
we'll be sent back over to the
City View Controller and we'll
see our updated note data.
So to start, we're going to need
to add a Notes property
to the City Model.
And you can see that in City.h,
we're adding an
NSString property
called Notes.
And in the init with JSON
implementation, we're going to
want to set self.notes equal to
some default value because
the JSON file doesn't have
any of that note
data inside of it.
Next, we'll need a UI Label and
a UI Text Field inside of
the City View Controller.
In CityViewController.h, we've
already got our City Model
Property, and we're also going
to need a UI Label and a UI
Text Field to store the notes
and the editable version of
those notes.
And then in
CityViewController.m, we'll
need to allocate and initialize
a City Model Object
and then allocate and initialize
a Notes Label
Object and a Notes
Field Object.
Also notice that we're setting
the text value of the Notes
Label using the data that's
in self.city.notes.
If we want to set the text
inside of a UI Text Field, we
just access the Notes Fields
Text Property and set that
equal to some string.
On the flip side, if we want
to access the text that's
already inside of Notes Field,
we can just reference the text
property directly in something
like an NS log.
Now the keyboard that pops up
is customizable also, and
Objective C provides a number
of constants to help you
decide which keyboard
should display.
The default keyboard type is UI
Keyboard Type Default, but
there are some other constants
like UI Keyboard Type Decimal
Pad, which brings up a numeric
keypad, and UI Keyboard Type
Email Address, which brings up
the default keyboard with an
at symbol and a period symbol
in it to make writing email
addresses easier, and a whole
list of other keyboards, too.
You decide which keyboard should
display by changing the
Keyboard Type Property
of a UI Text Field.
Another useful property of
UI Text Field is the
Border Style Property.
There's four borders styles
that you can choose from,
UITextBorderStyleNone,
UITextBorderStyleLine,
UITextBorderStyleBezel, and
UITextBorderStyleRoundedRect.
For the Notes Field, we're
going to use a
UITextBorderStyleRoundedRect so
we can see the field easily
and distinguish it from
the other UI labels.
Now it's time for you to try
some UI Text Field challenges.