You probably noticed that while
the keyboard pops up when you
tap inside of the UI text field,
it doesn't go away when
you tap out of it.
In order to make the keyboard go
away, you're going to need
a special class called UI
Text Field Delegate.
The UI text field delegate class
has a bunch of methods
that are useful for dealing with
all the different states
that a keyboard could be in.
So we've got things like, text
field should begin editing,
text field should end editing,
text field did end editing.
But the specific method that
we're going to want to access
right now is, text field
should return.
And this is going to run
whenever the Return key is
tapped on the on screen
keyboard.
So we have a problem, we have
a method called text field
should return that's in the UI
text field delegate class, but
we're not in the UI text field
delegate class right now.
We're in the City View
Controller Class.
So we need a way to get the
methods from UI text field
delegate into the city
view controller.
And the way that Apple let's us
do this is with a procedure
called Protocols.
Protocols are just a way to take
methods from one class
and get them inserted
into another class.
So the way that we declare
a protocol is in the
cityviewcontroller.h file, in
Angular brackets after the
subclass, which in this case
is UI View Controller.
We put the protocol that we
want to implement,
UITextFieldDelegate
Then in CityViewController.m,
we also need to access a
property called delegate
of the text field.
We need to set
self.notesfield.delegate = self.
So remember that self
here is the
CityViewController object.
So what we're saying is that
we want the CityView
Controller object to respond on
behalf of the notes field.
We want to delegate that
response to the
CityViewController.
And since the CityViewController
adopted UITextFieldDelegate
protocol, it's
going to understand what to do
when some message is received on
behalf of the text field.
If the message that gets sent
to the notes field is
TextFieldShouldReturn, then the
CityViewController is going
to look for tha
TextFieldShouldReturn method.
So we better implement it.
This text field should return
method is really going to do
two things.
First it's going to update the
city model object with the
text that has been entered
so far in notes field.
And it should make the keyboard
go away after that.
So to update the city model
all we need to do is set,
self.city.notes equal to the
text in self.notesfield.
And then to make the key word
go away, we need to pass in
that instance of the text
field a message called
resignFirstResponder.
The first responder means that
an object is going to be the
first one to respond to any
interactions with the view.
To become a first responder, the
element just needs to be
interacted with.
The keyboard appears on screen
whenever a UI text field
becomes the first responder.
And whenever it loses its first
responder status, the
keyboard disappears.
So when we resign first
responder status of the UI
text field that's what's making
the keyword go away.
It's time again to try your
hand at some challenges.