Our UITextField is working
pretty well now,
but we have a problem.
It's in CityViewController
right now, but we really
should modify it to where it's
in a separate view controller.
We'll call that
EditNoteViewController.
And this is the structure that
we want to end up with.
We want to have
CityViewController that has a
view holding a UI label that
will hold the notes data.
And we want a way
to transition to
EditNoteViewController, which
has its own view, that has
nothing but the UI text field
notesField inside of it.
The simplest way to do this
is to create a UIButton in
CityViewController and have the
action of that UIButton
call a method called
editPressed.
And inside of the editPressed
method, we will create a new
EditNoteViewController, set
the City property of the
EditNoteViewController to the
City object that's currently
in CityViewController, and
do a standard navigation
controller push where we push
EditNoteViewController onto the stack.
In EditNoteViewController, we're
going to need to import
City.h so that we can access
the City model.
We're also going to need to
create a City property.
And finally, we're thinking
ahead a little bit, and we're
going to need a UIButton
that takes us out of
EditNoteViewController and back
into CityViewController.
So it's probably a good idea
to declare a savePressed
method now also.
You know the drill by now.
That's right, we've done this
a couple times now.
Inside of
EditNoteViewController's
viewDidLoad method, we're going
to want to instantiate a
copy of a City object.
Then we're going to want to
instantiate a notesField and
set the frame of the notesField
appear on the
screen and set the Delegate
property of that notesField so
that it can use those UITextField
delegate methods.
And then in viewWillAppear,
we're going to want to set the
text property of the notesField
equal to whatever
is currently in self.city.notes.
And that's so Higgie can
have a copy of what's already
in the Notes property available
in the UITextField
before he begins editing.
In the CityViewController, we
had an Edit button to take us
from CityView to EditNoteView.
And in EditNoteViewController,
we're going to need to Save
button to take us from
EditNoteView back into
CityView with our newly
saved data.
So we create a button, and we
set the action to a method
called savePressed.
In savePressed, we'll
do two things.
First, we'll set the
self.city.notes property equal
to whatever text is currently
in the notesField.
And then we'll call the
popViewControllerAnimated
method to pop us off the stack
back into CityViewController.
Let's see what that looks like
in action, and then you're off
to more challenges.