[SINGING]
He's got your data in his pocket
and a gun in his hand.
He's got his finger on the
trigger and a secret plan.
He'll take mutable arrays and
put them in formation using
your view controllers for
his world domination.
He'll take your data
into models
before it explodes.
The only secret agent who
encodes and decodes.
He's Mr. Higgie.
All right.
Welcome to Level Five of
iOS Operation Models.
In this level, we're going to
be talking about how to
archive data in models
to a file.
Planet Hig is working
pretty well.
Higgie can get a list of places
that are near him, he
can view specific information
about each one of those
places, he can view information
about the city
that he's visiting, and he can
even leave himself little
travel notes along the way.
But it all kind of falls apart
if Higgie closes the app and
tries to reopen it.
An app that loses all of its
data every time it's closed,
is not going to be a
very powerful app.
Aw, come on.
It took me forever to
make that edit!
So let's look at what we can
do in order to save data in
between app sessions.
We'll need a couple pieces
to make this work.
And the first one is
called NSCoding.
Now a model object can contain a
wide variety of data, things
like NSStrings, NSArrays,
NSDictionaries, and NSNumbers.
And the NSCoding protocol is
like a package that takes all
those different pieces of data
and puts them into one format.
Once we have it all in that one
format, we can then save
it to a file on a disk and
read back from that file
whenever we want to expand
our data again.
Really the way that NSCoding
works is kind of like sending
a package through the mail.
Let's say you have a present
to deliver to someone.
You can't just take
that present and
put it in the mailbox.
You have to put it inside of a
box first and you have to wrap
it all up and tape
the box down.
Once we have that box with
our city model in it,
NSKeyedArchiver and
NSKeyedUnarchiver are going to
act as the delivery person that
takes our data from the
city model and moves it from
point A to point B.
In this case, the place where
we want our city model to go
is to be archived in a file.
And when we need to get the data
out of the file system,
we call our delivery person
again by using
NSKeyedUnarchiver to get a new
fresh copy of the object.
We need to adopt the NSCoding
protocol in the city model so
we can do that in
the city.h file.
And then in the city.m file,
we need to implement
initWithCoder and
encodeWithCoder.
Now notice that
encodeWithCoder does not
return any specific object.
But initWithCoder should always
return a model object
instance of the model class
that you're in,
in this case, city.
Implementing encodeWithCoder
is pretty simple.
You can see that the
encodeWithCoder method pulls
in one argument of
type NSCoder.
And in our previous analogy,
NSCoder is the box that
contains all of our data.
In encodeWithCoder, we're going
to want to take all of
our data and put
it in that box.
So we pass the
encodeObjectForKey message for
each one of the properties
that are in our model.
The first property
is self.name.
So we passed the self.name
object into the
encodeObject method.
And the key that we choose could
be any string but we
probably want to take a string
that relates to the name of
the model property so we don't
get confused later on.
Well then repeat this for each
one of the model properties in
the city model.
InitWithCoder does the opposite
of encodeWithCoder.
It takes in that box full of
data and it unwraps the box so
all the data inside
can get out.
It looks very similar to
a standard initializer.
It starts off with self equal
super init, it then checks if
the self object was created, and
then we need to go through
each one of the properties
in our model and decode
objectForKey for each one of the
keys that we just set in
encodeWithCoder.
InitWithCoder and
encodeWithCoder don't ever get
called directly, but instead,
they have that set of helper
classes that are the delivery
person, NSKeyedArchiver and
NSKeyedUnarchiver.
So to create a model from an
archive, we pass the unarchive
object with file message to the
NSKeyedUnarchiver class.
And that's going to return
to us a model.
To archive a model with the
encodeWithCoder method, we're
first going to need
to have a model.
Here I've created a city model
based on the initwithJSON
initializer.
And then we pass the archive
route object to file message
to the NSKeyedArchiver class.
The object we want to archive,
of course, is city and the
file, again, is going
to be a path to our
model archive file.
Now both of these need a path
to the archive file which is
that warehouse that's going
to store all of our data.
So let's look at how we
can get that path.
Every iOS app actually consists
of a couple of
subfolders.
The first one is a folder called
App.bundle and this is
going to be all of the
compiled code that
makes your app run.
This folder is read only so
you can't write any custom
data to it.
Next, there's a set of folders
called Documents, Library, and
Temp, and then Library also
has two subfolders called
Caches and Preferences that
get used to store some
temporary cache and
preference data.
The best bet for us to save
our model data is in the
Documents folder because that's
a writable folder and a
good place to store data.
So we need a way to
programmatically access that
Documents folder if we're going
to save model data in it
and pull model data out of it.
So first we need to grab a
listing of all documents
directories that could be in
our application and that's
what this first line does.
It creates an NSArray called
paths that contains all the
possible document directories.
Now because by default our app
is only going to have one
documents directory, we need to
pull that directory out of
the path's array by referencing
it at position zero.
Finally, to create our full
archive path, we need to take
the path to the documents
directory and we need to
append onto that the name
of our archive file.
Now we can name our archive file
anything that we want but
it's usually a good idea to name
it something related to
the data being saved.
So here we're saving a city
model data so I'm going to
call this city.model.
Now that we have that archive
path stored in an NSString
called archive path, we can use
that archive path variable
inside of the NSKeyedArchiver
archive root object to file
method and the NSKeyedUnarchiver
unarchive
object with file method.
But we can probably do even
better than that.
That's a lot of code to write
over and over and over again.
So let's declare a class method
which is just a static
method that we don't have to
instantiate an object in order
to be able to call called
get path to archive.
Whenever we want to call the get
path to archive method, we
want it to return a path
to this city model.
Notice that little plus sign
in front of the get path to
archive method.
That means that this is a
class method and not an
instance method.
That means that whatever we need
to call it, we don't need
to create an instance of the
city model first, we can just
pass the getPathToArchive
message to city.
Since this method returns
a path to the city model
archive, in the NSKeyedArchiver
and
NSKeyedUnarchiver methods, we
can just call city getPathToArchive
and get that path.
It's time again to try your
hand at some challenges.