[SINGING]
He's got your data in his pocket
and a gun in his hand.
He's got his finger on the
trigger and a secret plan.
He'll take mutable arrays and
put them in formation using
your View Controllers
for his--
World domination.
[SINGING]
He'll take your data into
models before it explodes, the
only secret agent who
encodes and decodes.
He's Mr. Higgie.
You're watching level six of
iOS Operation: Models.
And in this level, we're going
to add some features to Planet
Hig to make it more useful and
have a better user experience.
One of the first features we're
going to add is the
ability to view a list of
interesting places, and Higgie
is going to be able to mark
places as interesting and then
view them on a single
list later on.
To accomplish this, the
structure of Planet Hig is
going to be modified
a little bit.
We've still got our
InterestingPlaces
TableViewController, but we're
going to need to create
a connection between
PlaceViewController and
InterestingPlacesViewController.
Looking at the structure of
Planet Hig, you see that we've
got almost everything
implemented except for
InterestingPlaces
TableViewController, so let's
look at how we're going to
implement that and where that
data is going to come from.
In the City Model, we're going
to add an NSArray called
interestingPlaces, and that
interestingPlaces array is
simply going to store a list
of Place model objects that
have been marked as interesting
by Higgie.
Just like we did when we added
a Notes property to the City
model, we're going to want to
set a default value for that
interestingPlaces array in
initWithJSON method.
In this case, we're going to
set it to nil because by
default, there are no places
that have been marked as
interesting.
So the place where Higgie is
going to mark a place as
interesting is in
PlaceViewController.
So in PlaceViewController, we'll
import City.h and create
a City property, and we're also
going to define a method
called makeThisPlaceInteresting,
which is going to be triggered
whenever Higgie taps a UI
button in the interface.
In the viewWillAppear method in
PlaceViewController, we're
creating our standard
UI button and
adding it as a sub view.
And the target action for that
button is a selector called
makeThisPlaceInteresting.
So whenever the user
taps on the button,
makeThisPlaceInteresting
will be called.
And we're going to do a couple
of things inside of
makeThisPlaceInteresting.
First we're going to get a
current copy of the city model
from the archive.
Next, we're going to create an
NSMutableArray temporary
array and initialize it
with the contents of
self.city.interestingPlaces.
This is going to give us a
temporary mutable array that
we can add an object to when
Higgie marks it as
interesting.
Next, we add the current
place object into
the temporary array.
Then we set
self.city.interestingPlaces,
which is the NS array inside the
model, equal to this new
temporary array that has an
additional item added.
And finally, since we modified
the state of the City Model,
we'll want to archive
it to disk.
So if we look at what that code
looks like, we now have a
UI button in the middle of
PlaceViewController, and we
tap on that UI button,
internally the City Model
nterestingPlaces property is
being updated to contain that
current place.
So next, we'll want to update
the interestingPlaces
TableViewController to show a
list of all of the content of
that interestingPlaces array.
We've got our standard UI
TableViewController methods
that we need to work with here,
which are TableView
numberOfRowsInSection,
TableView cellForRow
AtIndexPath, and TableView
didSelectRowAtIndexPath.
In numberOfRowsInSection, we
can return self.city.
interestingPlaces.count to make sure
that we have the right number
of rows that appear
in the table.
In cellForRowAtIndexPath, we
create a new cell and then we
set the cell's textLabel.text
property equal to the Name
property of the place model at
that position in the array.
And then in TableView
didSelectRowAtIndexPath, we're
going to go ahead and create a
new PlaceViewController, set
the Place property of the
PlaceViewController equal to
the Place model at this position
in the array, and
then push out to the
PlaceViewController.
Now if we start at the
PlaceViewController, mark a
place as interesting, and
then switch over to the
InterestingPlaces
TableViewController tab, we
can see that that place
appears in the list.
Now it's time for you to set up
some similar functionality
in InstaPhoto in
the challenges.