There's several enhancements
that we can make to the way
that makeThisPlace
Interesting works.
The first one is that the button
still stays on screen
even after we've tapped it,
which could lead to adding the
same place into the
interestingPlaces array
multiple times.
So the first thing we should
do is we should remove the
button after it's been tapped.
And doing this is really easy.
All we need to do is pass the
removeFromSuperView method to
the Sender Object.
Remember that Sender in any
method that's called by a UI
button contains that
UI button.
So then by calling Sender
removeFromSuperView, we're
really saying remove the button
from the super view.
Next, just making the button
disappear might not be enough
to clue Higgie in that he's
added a place to the
interestingPlaces array, so why
not pop up an Alert View
on the screen?
We can do this by creating a
UIAlertView object and then
passing it the initializer,
initWithTitle, message,
delegate, cancelButtonTitle,
otherButtonTitles.
And then we pass the Show
message to that alert object
and the Alert view will
pop up on the screen.
And you can see what the
different arguments in the
Convenience Initializer do.
The initWithTitle passes in
the title of the UIAlertView,
the message is the detail
text in the Alert View,
the cancelButtonTitle
is the single button
that appears on screen.
I renamed mine to OK.
And I'm not setting any of the
values for the delegate or the
otherButtonTitles because
they're not
needed in this example.
Now the button disappears when
it's tapped, and we get a
UIAlertView pop up to confirm
that the place has been added
to the interestingPlaces array,
but look what happens
when we visit PlaceView
Controller again.
The button still shows up.
That's not what we want.
To fix this, in PlaceView
Controller, we're going to
need to write a conditional that
checks if the place is
currently in the
interestingPlaces array.
If it is, we don't want
to show the button.
If it's not, it means we want
to add it, therefore the
button should appear.
You might think we can write
code that looks like this,
where you can pass the
containsObject message to the
interestingPlaces array and see
if it contains self.place,
but unfortunately, this
is not going to work.
That's a bummer, man.
Yeah, Mr. Higgie, that
is a bummer.
The reason why this won't work
is that every object in
Objective C under the hood is
given a unique identifier.
When we run the containsObject
method, we're actually
comparing the unique identifiers
between two
objects and not the contents
of the objects themselves.
So even if data from self.place
exists in a place
object in
self.city.interestingPlaces,
the two objects will not be
equivalent according to the
containsObject method.
Instead, we can come up with
a workaround that uses
enumeration to compare
individual properties of two
objects as opposed to the
objects themselves.
Let's start by declaring a
Boolean variable called
placeAlreadyInteresting, and
let's set its default value
equal to No.
Then we'll enumerate through
all of the places inside of
self.city.interestingPlaces, and
we'll check if the name of
the place in our interesting
Places array is equal to the
name of the place that's in
our PlaceViewController.
If they're equal, we'll set
placeAlreadyInteresting to
Yes, and if not, we'll do
nothing, leave it at No.
Then we check if the place is
not already interesting, and
if it's not interesting, we
want to show the button so
Higgie has a chance to
make it interesting.
If it is already interesting,
we don't
want to show any buttons.
Wouldn't it be great if we had
a way to see how many items
were in the InterestingPlace
sTableViewController without
having to tap and load the
controller itself?
One way we can do that is by
accessing the Badge property
of the tabBarController.
Remember that every
tabBarController contains a
tab bar with multiple
tab bar items.
We can access different
items in the tab bar
just like an array.
So if we want to access
the second tab in the
tabBarController, we can access
it by referencing
self.TabBarController.
TabBar.items at position one.
If you were to look up the
UITabBarItem documentation,
you'd see that there's a
property called badgeValue,
and that's the property that
we're going to want to set.
So we'll pass the setBadgeValue
message to the
UITabBarItem at position one,
and the argument that we'll
give it is an NSString version
of the integer in
interestingPlaces.count
So let's look now at where
we want to actually
set the badge value.
The first place that we want
to set it is in
makeThisPlaceInteresting.
Whenever a new place is made
interesting, we'll update the
badge value.
And next, we're going to also
want to set the badge value in
AppDelegate because we want to
make sure that whenever the
app loads, it gets a fresh
number in that badge.
We don't have a city model
currently in the AppDelegate,
though, so in AppDelegate.h,
we'll first want to import
city.h, and then in the
applicationDidFinish
LaunchingWithOptions method,
we'll set city equal
to City getCity to pull that
model out of the archive.
But wait.
What if this is the first time
we've ever loaded the app?
If it is, we won't have a
city model archive yet.
So what we'll need to do is
we'll need to say, if city,
then update the badge value,
because if a city exists after
we call the City getCity
method, then we
know we had an archive.
If it doesn't, we don't want to
update the badge value with
any bad data.
So here's our finished Planet
Hig in all its glory.
We can get a list of places, get
information about a city,
edit the information about
notes in that city.
We can add a place to an array
called interestingPlaces, and
then we can get a new
InterestingPlacesTableView
that contains information
about all of this.
This thing just keeps
getting better.
Just you wait until the next
course, Mr. Higgie.
Now there's just a few more
challenges and we'll see you
at the wrap up.