You watching Ruby Bits Level
One, where we're going to be
going over expressions.
Now the purpose of this course
is to give you a feel for some
of the more advanced
features in Ruby.
But you might already know
some of this stuff.
The first couple levels are
a little bit basic.
So if it feels too basic, feel
free to skip ahead to the
challenges and see if you
can get through them.
In this course, we're
going to be reading
a lot of code together.
So we put together some symbols
so you'll know the
good code from the bad code.
So we have the bad code
symbol followed by
the worse code symbol.
Then we have the good
code symbol.
And finally, the awesome code
symbol with the free life.
So here's our first code sample,
where we have
if !tweets.empty?
puts timeline.
And then we print
out the tweets.
Ruby has a more expressive
way of doing the if not.
Instead, we can use unless.
So we can say,
unless tweets.empty?
And it reads a little
bit better.
However, if our example has
an else statement--
so we have unless and else--
things start to get a little
bit confusing.
So here is where we might want
to switch the order around and
say if tweets.empty?, do this,
Otherwise, do that.
Here we have some more code
where we're checking to see if
the file path is not
equal to nil.
So we're going to see if
there is a file path.
And if there is, then go ahead
and post the attachment.
However, in Ruby, nil is treated
as false when it comes
to conditionals.
So instead we can write,
if attachment.file_path
attachment.post without
the comparison.
You gotta be careful when
you're doing conditional
statements because not
everything that you assume is
false evaluates to false.
Here you can see an empty string
is treated as true.
0 is also going to
evaluate as true.
And an empty array is also going
to be treated as true.
So here's a surprising
example.
You can see we have here
unless name length.
So we're checking to see if
length is equal to 0.
If it is equal to 0, then we're
printing out a warning.
However, what we just learned
is 0 is true.
So no matter what gets returned
from name length--
well, the code inside
this conditional is
never gonna get run.
Here we have a few more
conditionals.
Each of them executes
one line of code.
This might be a good chance to
use the inline if and unless.
So we'd write instead like so.
And this code is a little
more readable.
Next up, let's talk about
the short circuit and.
So here we have some code where
we're checking to see if
the user is nil.
And if it's not nil, we have
another conditional checking
to see if the user
is signed in.
However, because of the way and
works, we can simply put
if user and user signed in, if
user is nil it's going to fail
and not check to see if
the user is signed in.
Now let's look over a couple
examples using the short
circuit assignment.
So here we have result
equals nil or 1.
Obviously nil's going
to be falsey.
And it's going to return 1.
Then we have 1 or nil.
Obviously this is going
to return 1.
And then 1 or 2.
Again, going to return 1.
As you can see, if the first
part returns true that's going
to get return and the second
part of this is never going to
get touched.
Let's take a look at a couple
more examples using this.
Here we're getting some tweets
from a timeline.
And if nothing got returned from
those tweets, let's go
ahead and set tweets
to an empty array.
We could write this
in a better way
using the short circuit.
So here we can say tweets equals
timeline.tweets or the
empty array.
So if timeline.tweets is
nil, it's going to set it
equal to the empty array.
From within a method, you can
use a shortcut like this.
So we can check to see if
there's a current session.
And if there's not a current
session and that returns nil
or false, it's then going
to call sign user in.
These both are methods.
And one thing to keep in mind
with this, is that you can
either use it this way
or you could use it
with an if and else.
You can obviously write
it that way
if it's more readable.
Another way we can use those
or symbols is with an equal
sign to do some conditional
assignment.
So here you can see we're
setting an i_was_set variable.
We're then using the
conditional assignment operator.
This is going to check to
see if that variable
has been set yet.
And if it has been set, well,
it's not going to set it equal
to anything.
It's going to keep
the same value.
And then if we put it out
to the screen, we're
going to get 1.
In our second example, here
we have a variable we
haven't used yet.
So it's currently
equal to nil.
So in this case it's going
to get set to 2.
This is a good way to set
defaults with your variables
if they need them.
Here we have some code, and see
if you can figure out how
we're going to refactor it.
Obviously we have an options
hash, and on each line we're
checking to see if the options
hash value is equal to nil.
And if it is nil, then
go ahead and
set the default value.
As we learned just a minute ago,
we can instead use the
conditional assignment operator
to set some defaults
on these options
if they're nil.
Next up, let's figure
out how to use
conditional return values.
Here we have a conditional where
we're checking to see if
list name is nil.
And if it's not nil, we
set the options path.
Otherwise we set it
to something else.
This is a good opportunity
to use a
conditional return value.
In Ruby, conditionals always
return a value.
So in this case, we can move the
options path in front of
the conditional.
And the values that get returned
from the conditional
will get set to it.
Now let's put that conditional
inside a method and figure out
how we can refactor it.
Now as you know, every method
in Ruby returns a value.
So we can refactor
this to become a
little bit more readable.
As you can see here, we can get
rid of the URL variable
altogether.
Because the if statement
itself is
going to return a value.
And that value is going to get
returned by the method.
Just like our if else
conditional returns a value,
even things like case statements
return a value.
So here you can see we're
evaluating the client name.
And whatever gets returned we're
setting equal to the
client URL.
Two other useful ways we can use
case statements are first
by using it with a range,
as you see here.
We can also use it with a
regular expression, as you see
here, to figure out if our tweet
is a mention, direct
message, or if it's public.
And there's another
way we could
write this case statement.
If we wanted to, we could write
it with whens and thens.
Obviously, this is just a little
bit more readable.
And that pretty much wraps up
Level One with expressions.
It's time to get your hands
dirty with the challenges, and
we'll see you in Level Two.