You're watching Ruby Bits, and
this is Level Two, where we're
going to be going over
methods and classes.
[MUSIC]
So here we have a tweet method,
which you can see
expects three arguments.
But only sometimes are we going
to have a latitude and
longitude to pass
into the method.
And even if we don't, we still
have to call it with all three
arguments, as you can see here,
specifying nil and nil.
One way to get around this is
by using a default for both
latitude and longitude.
So here we can declare def tweet
message lat equals nil
long equals nil.
And then we can call
this method
without those two arguments.
So let's say that our parameter
list for this method
keeps on growing and now
we have a reply ID.
Now when we call this method,
we've got to specify even more
parameters, getting to the point
where it's hard to read
and maybe hard to remember
what position
each argument is in.
On top of that, if we have a
reply ID but no latitude and
longitude, we have to type
placeholders for those arguments.
Not so good, right?
One way to solve this problem
is by using an option hash,
which will replace all
of those parameters.
Here you can see we read out
all the values out of that
option hash.
The cool part about this is
when we go to call this
function, well, we specify
all those different keys.
It shows meaning.
And now we know all the
parameters that are
getting passed in.
Let's go over a couple different
ways to write this.
First, we could use the Ruby 1.9
hash syntax, which would
look like this.
A little bit more readable,
which looks a little bit more
like JSON.
We also don't have to
worry about the
order of the keys anymore.
We can reposition
them as we like.
We don't need to send in
all the parameters.
We can specify just the ones
that we care about.
And if we want, we can omit the
option hash completely and
the method still works.
Extra life.
Combo times 5.
Let's take a look at some code
and see if you can figure out
how we can improve it.
So here we have a
get_tweets method.
We're checking to see if we're
authorized for this list.
And if we're not, then
we're going to
return an empty array.
Then when we go to call this
method, we call it,
check to see if tweets are empty,
and if we are, we'll alert
that we're probably not
authorized to access
this list.
However, what sucks about this
is we can't be totally sure
that this is an error.
Well, what if there's no
tweets in that list?
That could be bad and we
wouldn't want to throw an
error in that case.
So this might be a good chance
to use an actual exception.
So here you can see up in the
get_tweets method, if we're
not authorized this time
we're going to raise an
authorization exception.
Then when we go to call the
method, we're going to use
begin and rescue to
rescue from the
authorization exception.
And at that point we're
going to know
that there's a problem.
We're going to know that
we've run into an
authorization error.
And we can warn them with
a proper message.
Another other useful features
methods in Ruby
is the splat argument.
That's a little star up there.
And what that signifies
is that we're
sending in an array.
And that array is made up of all
the parameters we send in.
It could be 0 parameters, it
could be many parameters.
As you can see here,
we're sending in a
couple different names.
And those they're getting
assigned to that array.
The arguments get put
into that array.
And in this case, they get
joined together with spaces
and then printed out.
So we're done with methods.
Now let's jump into classes.
But let's all make sure we
understand why we need to
classes through this example.
So here you see we have
an array of names.
You might notice the last
item in this array
doesn't have a last name.
So when we go through each of
them and we print them out,
well, we can see that the last
line has a comma Madonna.
That's not so good.
So we need some way to signify
a different behavior when our
name only has, well, one
part of its name.
This might be good opportunity
to create a class because now
we have data that's associated
with a specific behavior.
So let's create a name class.
We're going to have an
initialize method that has
first and last name.
And the last name here
is optional.
We're going to set those
instance variables to
what got passed in.
Then we have a format method
which takes the last name and
the first name, compacts
them together.
Compact, in case you're not
familiar, takes out any nil
values from an array.
And then we're going to
join the resulting
array with a comma.
And of course, only if the array
has more than one item
is there going to be a comma
in between them with the
resulting string.
So as you can see here, our
class has state on the data
and some sort of behavior
on that data.
So let's go ahead and
use our class.
So as you can see here, we're
creating a bunch of new names.
Then when we go through
each of them, we
call the format method.
And our output is properly
formatted.
Here comes some more code.
And see if you can figure out
what's wrong with it.
So we have two attribute
accessors,
status and created at.
And our initialized method
pretty much just sets them.
In case you're not familiar
with attribute accessor,
remember that just creates a
getter and a setter method for
us on our instance variables.
Now let's go ahead and
use our class.
And, hey, look at that.
We're actually able to set our
created at instance variable.
Which isn't too good.
We wouldn't want to reset that
created at date sometime in
the future.
So how might we make it so that
that's not able to get
set later in the future?
Well, one way we could solve
this is by using just an
attribute reader instead of
an attribute accessor.
The reader is just going to
create a reader function and
no setter function.
So if we try to set it, well,
we're going to get undefined
method created at.
Here's our tree class.
And if we called tweet.to_s we're
going to get back this
string, which, well, it's
just not very readable.
How might we, well, overwrite
that string to give it a
different behavior?
Well, what we're going to
do here is we're going
to reopen the class.
As you probably know, Ruby
allows us to reopen any class
to give it additional
behavior.
So here, let's reopen
the Tweet class.
We'll redefine 2 string to
print out the status and
created at.
Then when we create a tweet
and call to_s, it prints out
something that is much
more readable.
So in Ruby we have this
awesome power.
We can reopen any class and add
additional functionality.
Which of course, is a
double-edged sword.
It's cool, but you have
to be careful.
You don't know what other
classes are depending on.
The class that you just maybe
overwrote a few methods on.
So a good best practice is just
to do this with classes
that you yourself own.
That belong to your project.
Let me introduce you to
the UserList class.
Inside the UserList class, we
have an attribute accessor,
which is name.
And inside the initialized
method, of course,
we want to set it.
Can we set it like
this, though?
Would it work?
Well, let's run it.
So here we create
a new UserList.
And list name is equal to nil.
And it didn't work.
It didn't get set.
So inside the initialize method,
it's just setting the
name equal to name.
It's actually creating a local
variable called name.
And it's not calling the name
equal method that the
attribute accessor gave us.
So instead, if we want to call
it like this, we have to
specify self.name.
That's going to call that
name equals function
on the current object.
And now we run the code again,
we're going to see that it
properly prints out
celebrities.
Sweet.
We got to the end
of Level Two.
It's time for you
to get coding.
And Caike Souza
will see
you in Level Three.