You're watching Ruby Bits and
this is Level 4, where we're
going to be going over Active
Support and some of the
additional helpers
that gives you on
top of the Ruby language.
To install Active Support,
you're going to want to
install it as a gem.
You might also want to install
the internationalization gem,
because there's a lot of
libraries inside Active
Support that depend on it.
To load it inside of your
classes, you're going to want
to just run require
active_support/all, if you
want to include all
the classes.
But you might not want
all of them.
In which case, it's very easy
to just include a specific
library that you might
want to use.
As I mentioned, Active Support
adds a bunch of helper methods
to existing Ruby classes,
such as array.
If we have a plain old array
with some numbers in it, we
can call array.from(4).
The from helper method allows us
to get a new array starting
from the item in the fourth
position in the array.
The to method is going to give
us a new array that starts
from the beginning until the
index, which we passed in as
an argument.
The in_groups_of method will
split up the array into groups
of three, padding with nil,
if there's extra spaces.
And the split method will
split the array into two
different arrays at the index,
which was passed in.
Also notice that it removes the
element that it split on.
Some of the most useful methods
from Active Support
are added to the date class.
So here, let's get a DateTime
that we can call
at_beginning_of_day, or
at_beginning_of_month, or
at_beginning_of_year--
all helper methods that
Active Support adds.
We could also call advance if we
want to advance four years,
three months, two
weeks, one day.
And, of course, you could pass
in just one of these hash
options if you wanted to.
You can also advance using
tomorrow, or go back a day
using yesterday.
Next, let's take a look
at a couple of Active
Support hash methods.
So here we have two
different hashes.
And if we wanted to know the
difference between the two, we
could call diff.
As you can see, this returns
the difference
between the two hashes.
Also, there's the stringify_keys
helper method
which is going to turn all
of our key into strings.
Remember back in Level 2 when
we used an options hash as a
parameter into a method?
Well, when you look through
other people's code, sometimes
you're going to see them using
this Active Support method
called reverse merge, which
will allow them to specify
defaults into that
option hash.
So here you see the options,
which we're passing into the
method, and the defaults that
we're setting once we get into
the method.
So in this case, we might
run options.reverse_
merge(defaults).
What this is going to do is
construct a new array,
starting with the
options hash.
And if any of those defaults
aren't included inside that
new hash, it's going
to add them.
A couple more extensions
on hash.
You have the except method,
which is going
to remove that key.
And, lastly, there's the
assert_valid_keys method,
which is going to throw an
exception if the hash contain
any keys besides the ones that
are listed inside of it.
If you've built web apps before,
you might have run
into the situation where you
have tabular data and you want
the data to alternate color
between different rows to make
it more readable.
One way to implement this is by
creating a background class
helper, which if the index that
we're on is odd, returns
white, and if it's even,
returns grey.
So odd and even are the Active
Support helper methods.
Then we can iterate through each
of the tweets, calling
the background_class method.
This will then alternate
between grey and
white as the div class.
Another useful Active Support
feature is inflection.
So as you can see here, we're
calling 1.ordanilize, which is
giving us 1st place, then 2nd
place, and then 23rd place.
So as you can see here,
it knows when to
use st, nd, and rd.
The Inflector also allows you
to pluralize strings, to
singularize strings, and it even
knows how to deal with
some irregular rules.
And if you need to customize it,
because it's not going to
get everything right, it's
pretty easy to add your own
rules for pluralization
and singularization.
There's also the titleize
string helper.
You've also got humanize, which
is going to add spaces
and capitalize the first word.
And there's a bunch of other
little string helper methods,
which you can learn more about
either in the documentation or
by going to read the Rails
Guide on Active Support.
It's very useful.
And now we're done
with Level 4.
So it's time for you to practice
your Active Support,
and we'll see you in Level 5.