My name is Caike Souza, and
you're watching Ruby Bits.
This is Level Five, and
we're going to be
talking about modules.
[MUSIC]
When you're working in a Ruby
script, you might be working
with functions that would make
sense to be grouped together.
And the easiest way to do this
in Ruby is to simply place
those functions into a file.
And you can name the
file accordingly.
In this example, we've created
a file call image_utils.rb.
And in order to use those
functions, all you have to do
is require the file.
Then you can simply call
the functions.
One problem with this is that
the functions are thrown out
there in the global name space,
which means that they
could potentially conflict
with other functions
with the same name.
So one way to solve this problem
is to wrap those
functions into a module.
When we do that, the way that we
call those functions is by
prefixing them with the
name of the module.
A common pattern in Ruby is
to include the module
inside of the class.
This will expose the module's
methods as instance methods in
the object, which means that
those methods will have access
to the object's internal
properties.
You may have noticed that we're
no longer passing Image
as an argument to both preview
and transfer, because they're
now part of the Image class.
So when we run this code, we can
simply call preview on the
Image class.
So when we include a module in
a class, what's happening is
that module is being included in
the class's ancestor chain,
which looks something
like this.
So when we call the ancestors
method on the Image class,
we're going to get a list of
all the classes and modules
that the Image class
has descended from.
If we only want to list the
modules, we can call the
included_modules method.
So we've just looked at
including a module into a
class, also known as mixin.
So when would you really use
mixin versus classical class
inheritance when we have a child
class inheriting from a
parent class?
Well, let's take a look
at this example.
So we can see here we have three
different classes that
all have the same method.
This is code duplication,
and it's not cool.
So one way to solve this problem
would be to create a
sharable class and move
all the common methods
into that one class.
That way we can have the Post,
Image, and Tweet classes
inherit from the shareable
class.
The problem with this is that in
Ruby, a class can only have
one superclass.
So by inheriting from sharable,
we're basically
limiting these classes from
inheriting from any other
class in the future.
Also, inheritance suggests
specialization.
And in this case, it doesn't
really make sense to say that
a Post is a kind
of Shareable--
or an Image or a Tweet.
And some behaviors are just
not fit for classes.
So in this case, it makes more
sense to use a mixin.
So instead of a class, we're
going to use a module and
include the module
in those classes.
This allows for these classes
to include any other module
that they want to inherit
behavior from.
In this case, we have
Favoritable.
Given a module, we could also
expose the module's methods as
class methods to a class.
So let's look at the searchable
module in see how
we can expose the find all from
method as a class method
to the Tweet class.
In order to do that, we use the
extend method, which, when
called from a class, will expose
the module's methods as
class methods.
So as you can see here, we can
call the find all from method
from the Tweet class.
Now as a recap, use extend if
you want to expose module
methods as class methods.
And use include if you
want to expose
them as instance methods.
Now let's look at some
more advanced stuff
we can do with mixins.
Here we have an ImageUtils
module and an Image class.
Given that we have an object
from the Image class, we can
include the methods from the
module by using extend.
Extend will expose the methods
from the module to that
specific object.
And the module will not be
available in other objects
from that class.
And you're probably thinking
this looks a little weird,
because we've just talked
about how extend exposes
methods as class methods.
But note here that we're using
extend from an object as
opposed to a class.
So remember, if you call extend
from an object you're
going to be including the
methods from that module as
instance methods
on the object.
Now let's take a look at how we
can include both instance
and class methods from a
module into a class.
One way to do that is to include
the ImageUtils module
and then extend the class
methods inner module.
We can then use both instance
methods and class methods from
the module.
But there's a better way to
do it using method hooks.
Method hooks are methods that
are automatically called by
Ruby given an event.
In this case, we're going to use
the self.included method
hook, which will be run
when a module is
included into a class.
The self.included method also
takes the host class as the
argument, which allows us to
call extend and include the
inner module class methods.
Notice how in the Image class
we're not extending the module
anymore, and this code still
works as intended.
It's worth noting that the name
of the inner module here
is pretty much a convention.
You can call ClassMethods
any other name.
Now let's switch up
the ImageUtils module
a little bit, by adding
an extra class method which
will then call on the host
class when this module
is included in it.
If you remember the active
support gem from a couple of
levels ago, I'm going to show
you how to use that to make
this go a little bit cleaner.
Now here's the same
module extending
active_support/concern.
First thing it does is it looks
for a ClassMethods
inner module and extends your
host class with that.
Then it gives us an included
method, which we can pass in a
block that will be run
within the context of
the included class.
So one last thing I want to show
you is how Active Support
Concern deals with modules'
dependencies.
Let's take a look
at some code.
Here we have an Image class that
includes both ImageUtils
and ImageProcessing modules.
The ImageUtils module defines
a class method on the host
class called clean_up, which
will then be called by the
ImageProcessing module
once that module is
included in a class.
This means that ImageProcessing
depends on ImageUtils
also being included
in order for it to work.
So you might think it would be
better to include ImageUtils
module from ImageProcessing.
However, this doesn't
work at all.
The reason is that when the
self.included method from the
ImageUtils module is run, base,
which is the argument, is not
the class Image, but rather the
ImageProcessing module.
So when the time comes that
ImageProcessing is included,
the clean_up method will not
exist and we'll run into a
runtime error.
So one way to solve this is to
simply extend Active Support
Concern from your
ImageProcessing module, which will
handle all the dependencies for
you and make sure that the
self.included method from
the ImageUtils
module is run properly.
We can clean this up even
further by extending Active
Support Concern from the
ImageUtils module.
This will automatically extend
class method modules and also
gives us the included block to
work, as you can see below
So this is the end
of Level Five.
It's now time to play around
with some modules.
And good luck.