My name is Caike Souza,
and you're watching
Ruby Bits.
[MUSIC]
In this level, we're going to
take another look at classes.
As you may know, classes are
all about encapsulation, so
let's take a look at this
send_tweet method that takes
two arguments.
The second argument is the
owner_id, which is used by the
method to retrieve the user.
However, the send_tweet method
shouldn't really know how to
retrieve a user.
It knows too much.
A couple things to keep in mind
is that passing around
data as strings and numbers kind
of breaks encapsulation.
Places using that data need to
know exactly what to do with
it, and individual changes to
that behavior may influence
other areas of your code that
might be using that.
So one way to make this better
is to simply wrap all of that
in a class.
So you can see here, we've
created a tweet class with a
couple of attribute
accessors, and we
created the owner method.
So now, instead of passing data
to the send_tweet method,
we pass a tweet object, and the
tweet object knows how to
retrieve its owner.
Classes are not always
the solution.
When all you're dealing with is
data, then passing around
an options hash should suffice,
so let's take a look
at the user class that
has two methods.
In Ruby, if you don't say
otherwise, all the methods in
your class are going
to be public.
However, in this case, we only
want the up_vote to be
accessible from outside
of the class.
The bump_karma should not be
part of the public API.
One way to hide this method from
outside the class is to
declare it private.
Inside the up_vote method, the
first call to bump_karma works
as expected.
The second call,
friend.bump_karma, will error
out, and this is because private
methods in Ruby cannot
be called with an explicit
receiver.
The correct solution here is to
use protected, which will
prevent the method from being
called from outside the class,
but at the same time, it allows
the method from being
called with an explicit
receiver, which needs to be an
object from the same class that
the method belongs to.
Now, let's take a look
at these two classes
for image and video.
As you may notice, they both
have the same attribute
accessor for title,
size, and url.
This is called duplication, and
it's definitely not cool.
So let's get our duplicate code
and move into a Parent
class, which we'll call
attachment, and both image and
video will inherit from that.
We say that image and video
are both kind of an
attachment, so in the future, if
we have any custom behavior
for any of these subclasses, we
can simply write the code
on the specific subclass.
Let's take a look at
some more code.
Here, we have a user class,
whose constructor initializes
the name property, and a
Follower class, which is a
kind of user, and its
constructor initializes the
following property.
If we instantiate an object from
the Follower class and
call the relationship method,
we'll notice that the name
property was not set.
This is because the constructor
for the Parent
class is not being called.
If we want to do so, then
we use the super method.
If we want to set the name
property in this case, we can
just call super, which will look
for a method by the same
name on one of the Parent
classes, in this case user.
So you might be wondering how
is super able to find the
correct method in the Parent
class, so let's look at a more
complex example.
Here, we have a Grandparent
class that declares my_method,
then we have a Parent class
that inherits from
Grandparent, doesn't
declare any method.
Then we have a Child class that
is a subclass of Parent,
and it's got its own my_method
declaration.
When we call my_method
on a Child object, it
first invokes super.
What super does is look at the
Parent classes to find methods
with the same name.
First, it's going to look
in the Parent class.
It doesn't find it, then it
looks at the Parent class's
superclass, which
is Grandparent.
Grandparent happens to have a
my_method declaration, so it's
going invoke that, then it's
going to print the string
my_method call in
the Child class.
So what if both my_methods
took arguments?
You can see here, my_method on
the Grandparent takes an
argument, and my_method on the
Child takes an argument.
However, we're calling super
with no arguments.
It so happens that in Ruby, if
you called super with no
arguments or params, it will
automatically pass in the
arguments that were passed
to the method calling it.
Now, let's look at the
attachment class with a
preview method and a case
statement in it.
The case statement is checking
for the type of attachment.
If it's an image, then
it's going to call
the thumbnail method.
Otherwise, if it's an MP3, then
it's going to call the
player method.
In this case, being an image,
it's kind of the typical case,
so what we can do is make this
the default behavior for the
attachment class and override
this method in any class that
happens to behave differently.
If speed is important to you,
this is actually faster
because every time we call the
preview method, we don't have
to go through the case
statement and the
comparisons in it.
Now, let's take a look at the
user class with two methods
that both have access to
the first and last
name instance variables.
There's some duplication going
on here, and coupling with
these two instance variables.
One way to make this better is
to create another method,
let's call it display_name,
which will return the value
used to display the
name of the user.
That way, if we ever need to
change the way we display the
name of the user, we only have
to worry about changing code
in one place.
Here, you can see we decided
to add the title to the
display name, and all we had to
do was change the code in
the display_name method.
You have now reached the
end of level three.
Start playing with the
challenges, and I'll
see you in a bit.
No pun intended.