You're watching Ruby Bits.
I'm Gregg Pollack, and this is
Level Six, where we're going
to be going over blocks.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So let's start out
with an array.
We have a words array up here,
and one way we can iterate
through it is by doing
a for loop, like so.
However, there's a more
expressive way to do this in
Ruby using the each method,
which takes a block.
And in this case, it's going to
go through each item in our
array, and print each one
out to the screen.
Now, there's two different
conventions with blocks which
I'm going to dispense
to you now.
And it's up to you which
religion you want
to subscribe to.
The first religion says that
when you have a single line
block, you would use
the curly braces.
And if you have a multi-line
block, you use do and end.
So that's the first
convention.
The other convention is that
if your block simply does
something as a side effect, and
you don't care about the
return value, then you
might put do and end.
Whereas, if you do care about
the return value, you would
use curly braces.
Now blocks always return
something, so the do, end, or
curly braces doesn't
really matter.
This is just personal
programming preference if you
want to use the convention
or not.
Now let's break down how blocks
work, piece by piece.
So here, you can see
that we've got the
call_this_block_twice method
that yields two times inside.
If we call that method, we're
going to be sending in a bit
of code into that method.
It's almost like for passing a
piece of code to get executed
instead of arguments.
So we pass that piece of code
in there, it gets executed
twice, and we get twitter,
twitter, and tweet, tweet.
Blocks can also take
arguments.
And in this case we're
passing in tweet.
So we call it and we send
in this method.
We accept the argument and
then we print out tweet.
The second piece of code is
going to call upcase on tweet,
and then print it out.
As we mentioned earlier, all
blocks in Ruby return a value.
In this case, our block is
simply the tweet string.
That gets evaluated and then
printed out to the screen when
we call puts.
Now let's combine all these
techniques, and really try to
visualize what's
going on here.
We invoke the method
call_this_block, we're sending
in a block which reverses
a string.
Right.
Foo is sent as an argument.
It's going to get reversed and
returned from the block, which
is sent to the block result.
Then we simply print out
the block result.
Let's take a look at some code
which could be refactored
using a block.
So here you can see we have the
list_tweets method and the
store_tweets method.
Both of them get all of the
user's friends, iterates
through each of them, and
then find all the
tweets for those friends.
And notice where they differ is
inside of that each block.
So that's probably where we're
going to put our yield.
See you can see in there,
we have yield tweet.
We can then call to each method
sending in a block with
each of these different
behaviors.
One will simply print
the tweet.
And one is going to cache it.
As a bonus, because we've
defined the each method, if we
include the Enumerable module,
we're going to get
access to a whole other set of
helper methods we can use on
this the array.
Methods like sort_by, to sort
the tweets, map, which will
return a collection of
the tweet statuses.
Now, let's take a look at one
more example of some code that
we can refactor using a block.
Here we have update_status and
get_list, let's see if you can
figure out what's the same and
what is the different between
these two methods.
We'll bring the parts that are
the same into a method called
while_signed_in_as.
Then we can call that method,
passing as a block the
behavior that is different
between each of the methods.
The code here on the left, we
can actually refactor a little
bit to make it a little
shorter and sweeter.
Because we're inside of a
method, we can get rid of the
begin and the end inside this
method, so it'll look
something like this.
It's time for you to start
coding up some blocks in the
challenges.
This is Level Six, which
means it's the end of
Ruby Bits part one.
But after you get through the
challenges, we'll have an
outro video which will help you
learn more bits of Ruby.