(SINGING) Your online
application's starting to
fail, it's crawling on
the network just
as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming,
starting from the top.
Better write some code, so
the world doesn't stop.
With the non-blocking model
we will be just fine.
Built on Google Chrome's
v8 runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
use the Real Time
Web with Node.
(SPEAKING) In the Real Time Web
with Node.JS, Eric Allam
and Gregg Pollack will take you
through seven high quality
screen tasks and 45 in- browser
code challenges, so
you can learn how to use
JavaScript on the server side.
Let's take a look at the
interface for this course.
The first video lesson
will be your
introduction to level one.
You can skip around chapters
using the numbers at the top.
And when you're ready to start
the challenges, just hit the
big button below the video.
In the challenge interface,
you'll see your total points,
the number of points this
challenge is worth, and the
challenge instructions.
Just below, a JavaScript code
editor will allow you to type
in your answer to
the challenge.
If you don't get it right, an
error message will give you
some feedback.
You can look at the
video slides.
And there's no shame in asking
for a hint, so you don't get
stuck for too long.
On the left side of the screen,
you will see a list of
the challenges for this level.
You can re-watch the video if
you need to, learn how to use
the interface shortcuts, and
download the slides, in case
you need some reference
material for later.
In this course, we'll cover the
non-blocking concept and
the event loop.
We'll learn how to listen,
trigger and create events.
Then we'll look at streams at
the core of the Real Time
infrastructure.
Modules will allow us to share
and use third party code, like
the Express web framework and
Socket.io, so we can use the
websockets API.
Finally, we'll discover how to
use Redis to store our data.
For each level you complete,
you'll receive a badge,
finally earning the course
completion badge which will be
displayed in your
public profile.
Finishing this course will
unlock a final video and
resources to continue learning
Node.JS and server side
JavaScript.
You'll also receive a discount
on your subscription or your
next Code School course.
To be able to play Real Time web
with Node.JS, you'll need
to have some basic knowledge of
JavaScript and server side
programming.
If you don't, you should take a
look at our previous courses
on Jquery and Backbone.JS, the
first one of which is free.