Your online application's
starting to fail.
It's crawling on the network
just as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming
starting from the top.
Better write some code so
the world doesn't stop.
With a non-blocking model,
we will be just fine.
Build some Google Chrome's
V8 runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
use the Real Time
Web with Node.
You're watching Real Time
Web with Node.js.
In this level, we're going to be
covering Socket.IO to build
a chat application.
So because we're building a chat
application, we're going
to have a bunch of different
clients that need to receive
messages right away.
Let's say someone sends
a message to the chat.
We want to push that message
from the server to all the
clients at the same time.
But in traditional HTTP, this
isn't really how it works, as
you can see here.
What we want to be able to do
is send and receive messages
from the client to the server
and from the server to the
client at the same time.
And this is exactly what
websockets do.
Unfortunately, websockets is a
pretty new technology on the
client side, so we need
something to abstract
websockets and give us a good
API to use on newer browsers
and older browsers.
And that's where Socket.IO
comes in.
So let's start using Socket.IO
to build this chat
application.
All we have to do is first
install it using NPM.
Inside our app, we can
require socket.io,
and then after we create our
express server, we can pass in
the application created
by express to the
socket listen function.
This will return an object that
we can use to listen for
connections coming from
the client side.
Here, all we're doing is when
a new client connects to our
server, we're just going to
log out client connected.
We need a client, which in this
case is just our browser.
On the client side, we
also need to load
the Socket.IO library.
Then we can connect to the
server from the client passing
in our server's URL.
Now on our server, we're
actually really easily able to
send messages to the client.
Now this isn't possible with
just regular HTTP.
When our client connects, we can
start emitting events on
that client, such as submitting
a messages event
and passing in this data.
To receive this event on the
client side, all we have to do
is listen on the messages event
and pass in a callback.
And that callback will
have the data
emitted from the server.
Here, all we're doing
is alerting
that data to the browser.
So let's see this in action.
Let's fire up our Node app and
go over to the browser and
load up our site.
So you see when the client
connects to the server, it's
going to alert the data that
came back from the server.
And we're also going
to see in the log
that our client connected.
Just like we sent a message from
the server to the client,
we can also do the same thing
from the client to the server.
First, on our server, let's
set up a listener on the
messages event to log data
whenever the client sends the
messages event.
Over on our client, we're going
to use jQuery to hook
into our chat form.
And whenever that's submitted,
we're going to take the value
out of the chat input, which
is our text box, and we're
going to emit that messages
event on the server.
Let's see that in action.
Again, let's fire up
our Node app and
go over to the browser.
Connect to localhost:8080.
As you can see, the client
connected successfully.
And when we type a message and
submit the form, it will emit
the messages event
on the server.
As you can see here,
the data is being
printed out to the console.
Pretty cool.
The really powerful thing about
Socket.IO, as opposed to
just regular websockets, is that
makes it really easy to
do something else other than
one-to-one communication.
Let's say you have a client
sends a message to the server,
and you want to broadcast
that message out to
all the other clients.
Well, Socket.IO gives us the
broadcast flag for that.
Let's use the broadcast
functionality in our chat app
to, instead of just logging
the message to the server,
let's broadcast that message out
to all the other clients.
The only thing that we need to
do on our client now is listen
for messages events.
And when we get one of those
events, we insert the message
into our chat app.
Once again, we're over in the
terminal and we're going to
fire up our Node app.
And now we're going to connect
with two different clients so
we can see this broadcast
functionality at work.
So we connect with our first
client, and we see that it has
connected successfully.
Then we open up another browser
and connect with that
client, and we can
see that now we
have two clients connected.
So when one of those clients
types in a message and hits
enter, it's going to broadcast
out that message
to the other client.
Pretty fantastic.
As we saw in that last screen
cast, now that we're
broadcasting messages around
between clients, we may
actually want to attach a name
to that message so we know
who's sending it.
So how do we do that
in Socket.IO?
Let's go back to our server.
And we're going to listen on
a custom event called join.
Now when our client emits that
event, it's going to pass in
the name of the user.
So we have our name
in the callback.
All we need to do is call set
on the client to define that
client's nickname.
We'll see how to use
that later when
broadcasting messages.
But for now, let's check
out the client.
We're going to add code to
listen for the connect event.
And when that happens, we're
going to prompt the user for
their nickname.
After they enter their nickname,
we're going to then
emit the join event on the
server, passing it in.
Back on our server, now before
we send out a new message to
all the other clients, we
have to use client.get.
We pass in the property
that we want to get.
And we give it a callback, which
will include the name
that we previously set
on the client.
So now when we broadcast out
that message to all the other
clients, we can pass the name
and the message to identify
the client.
Let's see it in action.
Just like before, we fire
up our Node server.
We connect with our
first client.
And now we're actually going
to ask the user for their
nickname when they first
connect, as you can see here.
So Dog is the first user.
Our second client
is named Spider.
So now, when Spider sends a
message to the dog, the dog
sees that Spider is the one
sending the message, as you
can see here.
So we're done with Level Six,
but we're going to continue on
in Level Seven on building
this chat application.
But for now, go into
the challenges and
practice using Socket.IO.