[SINGING]
Your online application's
starting to fail.
It's crawling on the network
just as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming
starting from the top.
Better write some code so
the world doesn't stop.
With the non-blocking model
we will be just fine.
Built on Google Chrome's
V8 runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
use the Real Time
Web with Node.
Welcome back to Node.js.
My name is Eric Allam.
I'm going to be leading
us through the
rest of this course.
In Level four we're going to
be going over modules.
In the first three levels, we've
been using require to do
stuff like HTTP, and the file
system, but what exactly is
going on here?
So how does require work?
How does require find these
libraries, and what does
require return?
How do we define what
require returns?
Well, let's look at what
that would look like.
In node.js when we want to share
code, we create these
things called modules.
So let's create a function
and we want to share
that with our app.
So we're going to create
a custom hello js file.
In that file we define
a hello function.
All it does is log out
to the console.
To define what we want to return
when we require this
file we use the exports
object.
So here we're saying export
the hello function.
Now down below, in our
application, when we require
that file we have access
to the hello function,
and we can call it.
Another way we can do that, as
you see here in
custom_goodbye.js, we can
actually export a function
into the exports object.
So when we require it, an object
is returned, and then
we can call that function
on the object.
So here we're requiring
custom_goodbye.
Then gb is the exports object.
We don't have to assign
what is returned by
require into a variable.
We can actually just call
require, and then right away
call the function that it
returns, like we see here.
You might notice here that we're
using .slash in front of
our module name.
And we're going to go over
why we're using that
a little bit later.
It has to do with how require
searches for our module.
In our previous examples we've
only exported one function,
either by assigning the function
to exports directly,
or assigning that function
on the exports object.
Well, let's say we want to
export multiple functions.
How do we do that?
We can do that by assigning
multiple functions in our
my_module.js file
to the exports
object like we see here.
Now our module exports two
functions, foo and bar, and it
keeps the baz function private,
which means that our
app js won't be able
to use it.
But if you tried to call
baz it wouldn't work.
Let's walk through a real world
example of creating our
own module.
And for this we're going to
introduce a little bit of new
functionality with
the HTTP module.
Instead of creating a server
and responding to requests,
we're actually going
to make a request.
So we're actually building
a HTTP client.
First, we're going to require
our HTTP module.
We're going to have a message
that we want to send in the
request body.
So we define that.
Next, we'll define an options
object that'll eventually be
turned into a URL
for the request.
Then we'll call the request
function on our HTTP module.
That function accepts
two parameters.
Our first one is the options for
the URL that we're going
to make the request to.
And the second parameter is a
call back that passes in a
response, which is a readable
stream, so we can read data
back from the response.
And just print it out
to the console.
Finally, we write our message
to the request body.
And when we call end it'll
finish the request.
So our first step here is
let's encapsulate this
functionality using
a function.
We'll call it makeRequest.
And now when makeRequest
is defined we
can use it like this.
And all we have to do is pass
in the message body that we
want to write to the request.
So now we have our makeRequest
function.
But we want to use this across
multiple different pieces of
our application, maybe multiple
different files, or
maybe we want to share it with
someone else on our team.
So we would want to
create a module.
As you can see we've moved our
makeRequest function into a
new file called make_request.js.
And now all we have to do is
assign the makeRequest
function to the exports
object.
Then to use this module we
go back to our app.js.
And we require make_request.
And then we can use it just
as we were before.
You might be wondering where on
our file system is require
looking for our make_request
module?
When we require with .slash
make_request we're telling
require to look in the
same directory.
We could tell require to look
one directory up using dot dot
slash my module.
And these are relative paths.
We could also just pass in an
absolute path to our module.
But what happens when you just
pass in the name of the
module, like make_request
without dot slash or dot dot
slash in front of it?
By default, what it's going to
do is search in the node
modules directory.
So as you can see here we're
in Home/eric/my_app/app.js.
So when we require make_request
it's first going to search in
Home/eric/my_app/node_modules.
If it doesn't find it there
it'll keep going up one
directory and searching in the
node modules directory.
So now we know how to create our
own node modules, it would
be nice if there was a way to
easily install third party
modules from the community.
And luckily, node comes with
something called NPM, stands
for Node Package Manager.
NPM is a lot like RubyGems
for Ruby, or CPAN
for Perl.
It has a central repository
where people can publish their
modules, and you can
install from.
NPM comes with node, so it's
really easy to install.
If you have node, you already
have and NPM.
It hosts a module repository
on a server.
It also has tools for dependency
management.
It makes it really easy to
publish your own modules.
And it follows a local only
install mode that we'll go
into a little bit later into
why that's important.
First, we're going to look at
how easy it is to install
third party modules with NPM.
Here you can see I'm using the
NPM command line tool.
And I'm saying, NPM
install request.
And that's going to
install the third
party request library.
As you can see here it's going
to install it into the local
node models directory.
So remember before when we saw
that require searched in the
node models directory, well as
you can see here, when NPM
installs that module into node
modules, we can automatically
require it in our app,
and it'll work.
When we did NPM install request,
you saw we installed
that module in the apps local
node modules folder.
Well, let's say we
want to install
something like CoffeeScript.
It comes with an executable,
called coffee, that we might
want to use to compile
CoffeeScript files to JavaScript.
So we can't use the
local install.
We actually have to pass this
flag, -g, that'll
install the coffee
script globally.
And then we can call the
coffee executable.
So the rule of thumb here
is if the module has an
executable you need to
use the global flag
when installing it.
One thing to note though is
that you can't actually
require global modules.
You have to install the
module locally.
And then requiring the
module will work.
There are a lot of places you go
to find NPM modules to use
in your applications.
NPM has its own registry
where you can go
and search for modules.
You can actually search from the
command line, as you can
see here, using NPM search.
You can always go to github
and use their search.
And there's this really great
website called node toolbox,
where they list the
best modules
based on their category.
After a while when you're
building your application,
you're going to start
installing more
and more NPM modules.
So it would be nice to have a
place where you can define
which modules your
app depends on.
NPM makes that really easy.
All you have do is define a
package.json file in the root
of your application.
This file contains
a json literal.
All you have to do is define the
name of your application,
which version it currently is,
and then you can pass in a
dependencies object.
In the dependencies object we
simply list the modules that
we depend on next to their
version numbers.
After we have this package.json
file defined, we
can actually just run NPM
install from our app.
And it'll go out and install of
our dependencies for us in
the node_modules directory.
As you can see here, when
we install the connect
dependency.
You might depend on modules
that have their own sub
dependencies, like our
connect module here.
And when you run NPM install
it's smart enough to go out
and also install those
sub dependencies.
But it's not going to install
them all at the root node
modules folder.
It will actually install
in the connects
node modules directory.
As you can see here, under
connect node modules we have
the three dependencies, qs,
mime, and formidable.
The great thing about this is it
actually prevents a lot of
problems that have to do with
conflicting modules.
So imagine instead if it
installed all the module
dependencies in that
one folder.
One thing I think we should
cover before finishing this
level is semantic versioning.
Now semantic versioning is a way
to give meaning to version
numbers on dependencies.
So as you can see here, we
defined our version number on
connect as 1.8.7.
The one indicates the
major version.
The eight is the
minor version.
And seven is the patch level.
What that means it that you
don't have to specify the
exact version number in your
package.json dependencies.
By using semantic versioning we
don't actually have to put
the exact version number
in our dependencies.
We can use what's
known as ranges.
As you see here, we can
use the tilde to
define a certain range.
When we do tilde one, that
means when we do an NPM
install, as long as the version
is greater than 1.0.0
and less than 2.0.0.
This is considered dangerous
because any changes to the
minor version could
break your app.
We can make it a little safer
by doing tilde 1.8.
And this would mean NPM would
install anything greater than,
or equal to, 1.8 and
less than 2.0.
This is still a little bit
dangerous because the API of
connect could change
from 1.8 to 1.9.
The safest way to define a
range, and still have the
dependency considered safe, is
to use tilde 1.8.7, or tilde
major, minor, patch.
What this means is that NPM will
install anything greater
than or equal to 1.8.7,
but less than 1.9.0.
Which means that when running
NPM install you'll only get
patch updates for connect, which
means it shouldn't break
your application.
We have reached the
end of level four.
Have fun in the challenges.
We'll see you back here
for level five.