[SINGING]
Your online application's
starting to fail.
It's crawling on the network
just as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming
starting from the top,
better write some code so the
world doesn't stop.
With the non-blocking model,
we will be just fine.
Built on Google Chrome's
V8 Runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
use the Real Time
Web with Node.
[END SINGING]
Hello, I'm Greg Pollack.
And you're watching Real
Time Web with Node.js.
In this level, we're going to
give you a quick introduction
to Node, talk about what it is,
what it isn't, blocking,
non-blocking, what evented
programming is, and then,
finally, what that event
loop is that you've
heard about with Node.
So let's jump into it.
Node.js allows you to build
scalable network applications
using JavaScript
on server-side.
Underneath the covers of Node,
you're going to find the V8
JavaScript Runtime.
This is the same runtime that is
used in your Chrome browser
on your client-side.
What Node does is provides a
wrapper around this engine
providing additional
functionality for building
network applications.
It's really fast.
Why is it fast?
Well, if you looked under the
covers of Node and this
runtime, you'd find it's all
written in C, which,
obviously, is very fast.
So what can you build
with Node?
Well, here's a couple
examples.
You could build a Websocket
Server.
So a good example of this is
maybe a chat server where you
have your browsers,
lots of browsers,
connecting to the server.
And there's chat going on.
You're sending messages back and
forth between the client
and the server.
And the socket stays open.
You could also do a File
Upload Client.
So when you think about
uploading big, large files,
you want to be able to do it in
a way that's not blocking.
So you can do more than one file
at a time and maybe even
start processing the file
as you get the first
few pieces of it.
Also you could create
an Ad Server.
When you think about ads that
get served on web pages all
over the net, they need
to be really fast.
These are maybe images that
are appearing on other
people's websites.
And they need to be able
to be rapid and
quick across the network.
Also any Real-Time Data Apps,
so not just from the
internet, not just from your
browser to your server, but
any sort of network servers,
maybe even local network
servers would be a good
fit for Node.js.
Node.js is not a
web framework.
It's not going to
replace Rails.
replace Django.
It's very low level network
communication we're talking
about here.
There are libraries that people
have written that sit
on top of Node to be
a web framework.
But Node at its most basic
level is not that.
Node is also not
for beginners.
Because we are talking about
network communication.
Node is also not a
multi-threaded application.
When we write our applications
with Node, we write them as if
we're dealing with a
single-threaded server.
Before we get into some actual
Node code, we need to make
sure everybody knows the
difference between blocking
code and non-blocking code.
So here's some pseudo code to
print some file content.
First, we want to read the file
from the file system, set
it equal to the contents
variable, print the contents
variable, and then do
something else.
So when we think about how this
code executes, first, we
read from the file system.
We can't actually print out the
contents until we've read
out all the contents
from the file.
So it's kind of blocking here.
And then, obviously, we
can do something else.
What would a non-blocking
version of
this code look like?
Well, we might read the file
from the file system, whenever
we're complete with that, print
out the contents from
the file, and then, finally,
do something else.
That technique there saying,
when you're complete, do this,
we call a callback.
We're going to call back
that function once the
file is done reading.
Executing the pseudo code might
go like this where we
read the file from
the file system.
We might do something else.
So it's simply going
to continue on.
And then at any point and time
in the future, when it's done
reading the file, it's going
to print the contents.
So here's some actual
Node code.
First of all, the blocking
version of reading out the
file might look like this where
we're getting all the
contents of the file.
We're then logging that out and
then doing something else.
So obviously, when this
gets executed, it just
runs one at a time.
The non-blocking version
of this in Node is
going to call readFile.
And look at this.
We're actually sending in
a function as the second
parameter to readFile.
That's our call back.
And when we get the contents,
log the contents.
And then we can say doing
something else.
So when we execute this, as we
mentioned, it's going to start
reading the file.
It's then going to continue
execution.
And when it's done reading the
file, it's going to print out
the contents at some point
in the future.
Hopefully, this JavaScript
syntax looks familiar.
And there's another way we could
write this which would
be just fine.
We could declare the
function and set
that equal to a variable.
And then, when we call readFile,
we could send that
function into readFile.
Either syntax would
work just fine.
They do the same thing.
Let's take a closer
look at this code.
And let's see what happens when
we're reading two files
at the same time.
First of all, if we had to do
this in a blocking way and we
look at the time line, if this
was blocking, it would read
one file and then
the next file.
However, since our code is
non-blocking, if we read two
files at the same time, they're
going to read in
parallel and happen
much quicker.
Now it's time for our Node.js
hello world or, in our case,
let's do a hello dog.
So our first line in this
file we need to
require the HTTP module.
So we're including
another library.
This is how we include libraries
typically in Node.
We're going to call the
createServer function.
That function takes as its
single parameter a call back
with request and response.
We're then going to write a 200
status code in the header
for the response.
We're going to write out
the response body.
And then, finally, we're going
to end the response
connection.
We want our server to listen
on port 8080.
And then to ensure our server is
running, we're simply going
to log out listening
on port 8080.
We run the server on
our command line.
We're going to see that
it prints out
listening on port 8080.
And then, if we use the curl
command line tool to hit the
server, it's going to return
to us "Hello, this is dog."
We could also just call up our
browser and go to that port.
And we would get the
same result.
Now let's talk a little
bit about how Node
executes this code.
The first time we go through
this code and execute it, Node
is going to register events.
In this case, we're registering
the request event
for whenever a request
comes in.
Once it gets done executing
the script, Node goes into
something called
an event loop.
It's checking for events
continuously.
Did a request come in?
As soon as a request comes
in, it's going to
trigger that event.
And it's going to run the call
back that we wrote and print
our "Hello, this is dog."
Now you might be wondering, why
are we writing JavaScript?
Well, the creator of Node, Ryan
Dahl, wrote this really
good quote, which kind
of explains why.
I'll let you read it.
So JavaScript makes it really
easy for us to program in an
evented way, to do evented
programming using that event
loop and write code that is
potentially non-blocking.
When we run a Node application,
like we said, it
registers a bunch of events,
like request,
connection, or close.
And those events sometimes even
trigger even more events.
And then we have this event
loop, which is constantly
looking for events.
And once our application gets
into that event loop, it can
start triggering and emitting
events into what we might call
our event queue.
So if a request event comes in
at the same time as a close
event, well, events are going to
be processed one at a time
on our event loop.
Let's make our hello world code
a little bit more complex
and simulate a long-running
process.
So here we're creating
our server.
We write the status code
back to the response.
We write dog is running.
Now we're going to
do a timeout.
We're going to pause for about
five seconds to simulate a
long-running process.
Once that timeout is done, we're
going to write out dog
is done to the response
and end the response.
We're going to pause for 500
milliseconds, which is
basically five seconds, and
listen on port 8080.
You might notice here there
are two different
events in our code.
We have the request event, which
we should be familiar
with from earlier.
And we also have a
timeout event.
So every time a request comes
in, it's going to create a new
event, a timeout event, which
will then be called back in
five seconds.
We're going to send in two
requests to our hello world
server with the timeout
and see what happens.
So our first request
comes in, triggers
that request event.
The request callback executes.
That setTimeout code
registers.
And it's going to wait
five seconds.
Meanwhile, another request
comes in, triggers that
request event again.
The call back executes.
The setTimeout registers.
And now this has to
wait five seconds.
And when our first timeout is
done, it's going to trigger
that setTimeout event, which
will trigger the
setTimeout call back.
And it returns that response.
Then our second request is going
to trigger the event and
do the call back and
so on and so forth.
So as you can see, two requests
can happen at the
same time and nothing
is blocking.
What would this look like,
though, if that
setTimeout was blocking?
Well, let's try it.
So a request comes in.
The request callback executes.
And the setTimeout
locks the world.
It stops the world.
And nothing else can execute on
this process while we are
on a timeout.
It is officially blocked.
So if a request tries to come
in, well, it just has to wait
for the server to
get unlocked.
Once it is unblocked, it'll
trigger the setTimeout event
and so on and so forth.
And the second request gets
to lock the server again.
Now, obviously, blocking
is bad.
And you might be wondering,
why would anybody write a
programming language or a
framework that blocks and
stops the world?
Well, you find this in a lot
of programming languages.
Often, when you do a call out to
web services, it'll block.
When you're doing a read
or a write to the
database, it'll block.
Or when you're calling out to
C extension, it will block.
And this is one of the reasons
why people love Node.js.
Because from the very start with
Node, its purpose was to
be completely non-blocking.
And all of the libraries that
you'll find for Node are all
non-blocking.
That's pretty cool.
Well, we've reached the
end of level one.
It's time to get your hands
dirty in the challenges.
So we'll see you at level two.