(SINGING) Your online
application's starting to fail.
It's crawling on the network
just as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming
starting from the top that'll
write some code so the
world doesn't stop.
With the non-blocking model,
we will be just fine.
Built some Google Chrome's
V8 runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
use the Real Time
Web with Node.
(SPEAKING) You're watching Real
Time Web with Node.js,
and this is Level Three where
we're going to be talking
about streams.
So in Node, we're building a lot
of network applications.
And we're sending data
back and forth.
Some of that data might be big,
and we want to be able to
start processing that data
the moment that it
arrives, piece by piece.
And we do that using streams.
Streams can be readable,
writeable, or both.
And you may not have known it,
but you've already been
working with streams.
If you look back at our example
we've been going
through, that request is a
readable stream, and the
response is a writeable
stream.
Now let's get the rest of
this code back in here.
And if you looked under the
covers, if you looked on our
client's side as to what it's
receiving when it receives
this data, you would see that
it receives first "Dog is
running," and then five seconds
later, it gets another
packet, which contains
"Dog is done."
Up until now, we've
only been sending
data back to the response.
But how do we read from the
request if we send some data
into the server?
Well, that request is a
readable stream, which
inherits from event emitter.
It emits a couple different
events, two of which are the
data event and the end event
when it's done transmitting
data to the server.
Let's write some code together,
where we print what
we receive from the request.
So here we create the server.
We write the status code,
and then we listen
for the data event.
Whenever a chunk of data
comes in, we'll
log it to the console.
We have to call toString,
because chunk is a buffer.
We could be dealing with
binary data here.
Then when there's no more data
to read on the request, it's
going to emit the end event.
And we can use that to
end the response.
With this code, we're printing
out whatever data we get from
the request.
But how might we create an echo
server and echo back to
the response what we're getting
from the request?
Well, all we have to do is add
one line of code here and
simply say response,
write, chunk.
When all we need to do is read
data from a readable stream
and write it to a writeable
stream, there's a shortcut in
Node that makes this easier.
We can simply call
request.pipe(response).
So basically, read stream
pipe, write stream.
So if we replace our code with
pipe and run our server, we
can then issue a request with
some data and that's going to
get echoed back out to us.
Now if you're familiar with
the Unix command line, you
might have heard of pipe.
For example, maybe you cat a
file and pipe that to the grep
command to find a
specific word.
This is the same sort of
technique, where you're piping
a read stream to
a write stream.
Let's go over another example
of streaming.
This time let's read a file from
our hard drive and write
a file back.
So in this case, we require
the file system module.
We call the create read stream
function, passing in the file
we want to read.
That returns us a read
stream obviously.
And then we're going to create
a new write stream for the
file we want to write
to, which returns a
write stream obviously.
All we have to do to read from
one and write to the other is
simply do file.pipe(newfile).
That's all there is to it.
Now let's combine both of these
examples, where we're
going to connect to the server,
we're going to send
the server a file, and we want
to write that to disk.
What would that look like?
Let's include the HTTP module.
We're going to create
our server.
We already have our new file.
We're simply going take
the request and pipe
that to the new file.
We also need to listen for the
end event on the request, so
we know when to end
the response.
And when we end the response,
we can also send in a string
that we want to send it
back to the client.
Now if we run the server and we
use curl to initiate a file
upload, it'll upload the file
and print out "uploaded!" from
the client side.
Now let's take a moment to
reflect upon what's really
going on here, because it
is kind of amazing.
We're sending or we're streaming
pieces of the file
from the client to the server.
And then the server
is streaming
that to the hard drive.
At no point in time does
the server ever
have the whole file.
It's all streaming.
And what that means, because
we're using Node, is that it's
also non-blocking.
So if we take a look back at the
time line, if we send in
two files at the same time into
the server, they're going
to be uploading and streaming
in parallel.
However, because we're streaming
like this, piece by
piece, it could introduce
another problem, which looks
something like this, where we're
reading files from the
client faster than we can write
them to disk and pieces
of a file might get built up
in memory and fill up our
memory, which is bad.
Pipe takes care of this
for us actually.
It will properly pause the
read stream, so the write
stream can catch up.
However, it's important that you
know what's going on under
the covers.
In order to do that, I've
got a metaphor for you.
This is our milk jug.
We poked a whole in the bottom
of our milk jug, and we're
going to start pouring
milk into it.
We start pouring milk into it.
As you can see, it drains out
the bottom, and it starts
filling up, and filling
up, and filling
up, and filling up.
So here, the milk that
we're pouring in
that's our read stream.
And the milk that's
getting poured out
is our write stream.
And we're reading more
than we were writing.
So we need a way here to sort of
pause that milk stream when
our jug is too full.
And then, once the milk jug is
drained, we need a way to then
resume the milk stream.
Now let's figure out
how we can do this
with some Node code.
How might we pause when the
write stream is full.
Well, if we're reading the data
chunk by chunk, when we
call write on the writeStream,
write is going to
return false if our kernel
buffer is full.
We can then check that, and if
the buffer is not good, let's
go ahead and pause
the read stream.
Then we need to know when we can
resume, when we're ready
to write again.
We do that by listening
for the drain event.
And the drain event means we're
ready to write again, so
we can resume the read stream.
And as we mentioned, all of
this sort of logic is
encapsulated in that
pipe command.
So if you're using pipe,
you don't have to
worry about back pressure.
One of the reasons Ryan Dahl
created Node was to deal with
file uploads.
If you're familiar with file
uploads and web applications,
you know all of the drama that
goes along with doing it well.
Sometimes, file uploads
can lock your server.
They can lock the world.
And it's hard to get file
progress as you upload.
But Node actually makes
it easy to do.
So let's go ahead and try to
implement our own file
uploader with some progress.
Once we complete the file upload
code, we're going to
want to be able to issue a
request and send in a file
either from curl or from the
browser and get back some
progress as it gets uploaded.
We're going to need two
different modules to write
this, the HTTP server module
and the file system module.
We might want to go ahead and
jump into the documentation
and take a look at these
two modules.
One thing, you might notice when
you're going through the
Node documentation, because
Node hasn't hit 1.0 yet,
different pieces of the code,
different modules have
different stability levels, so
you can see how often they
might change.
You might want to keep
an eye on that when
you're coding Node.
To create this, we're going to
start from our file upload
code, which we already
created.
First, we're going to
add some variables.
We need to store the content
length, the size of the file
inside fileBytes.
We're also going to declare a
variable to keep track of how
many bytes we've uploaded
so far.
Then we're going to listen to
that data event, which gets
called every time we receive a
new chunk from the request.
We're going to increase the
number of uploaded bytes.
We're going to get the length
of the chunk and add that to
the uploaded bytes.
We're going to calculate the
total progress by dividing
uploaded bytes divided by total
file bytes times 100.
And we're simply going
to write the
progress back to the response.
That's all there is to it.
So let's jump into our terminal
and run the code.
So here we're running
the Node server.
Then if we go to upload the
file, we can see that it gives
us back progress.
And we're complete.
Very cool.
Well, that about sums it up for
this level on streaming.
It's time for you to get
into the challenges.
And Eric Allam will see
you in level four.