Your online application's
starting to fail.
It's crawling on the network
just as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming
starting from the top.
Better write some code so
the world doesn't stop.
With a non-blocking model,
we will be just fine.
Build on Google Chrome's
V8 runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
use the Real Time
Web with Node.
You're watching Real Time
Web with Node.js.
In Level Seven, we're going to
be continuing to build our
chat application, and we're
going to introduce some
persistence.
One of the limitations of the
chat application that we wrote
in Level Six was that when a
client connected, we didn't
show them the recent messages
that were sent
in that chat room.
As you can see here, when Spider
connects, he doesn't
see any of the messages that
Dog has sent previously.
So let's walk through how we
would add that functionality
to our app.
So currently on the server,
our code looks like this.
But we need to add some code
that will emit the recent
messages when our new
client connects.
So our first iteration of
this, let's just use an
in-memory array to store
recent messages.
So first, let's just create
an empty array.
We're defining a storeMessage
function that takes the name
and the data of the message, and
we're going to push that
onto the messages array.
If that messages array is longer
than 10 elements, we're
going to remove the oldest
element by calling shift.
Down in the messages event
handler, we're going to call
this storeMessage function
to insert our
message into the array.
Now when our client joins the
chat, we're going to use the
forEach function to iterate over
the messages array and
emit a new message for each
item in that array.
Let's go back and see
what that does.
Now when Dog is connected and
he sends out a couple of
messages, when Spider connects
later on and enters his name,
he'll receive those previously
sent messages by Dog.
There's a little bit of
a problem with this.
What happens if we restart our
node application and then a
new client connects?
Are they going to see those
previously sent messages?
Well, they're not, because we
were storing those messages in
a in-memory array, whenever we
restarted the application,
those messages were lost.
To solve this problem, we need
a way to persist these
messages outside of
our node process.
Let's say, like a file system
or a data store.
And luckily, Node works really
great with a bunch of data
stores, like MongoDB, CouchDB,
PostgreSQL, Memcached, Riak,
and Redis, which is
a key-value store.
You can use all of these
persisting data stores in
Node.js in a non-blocking way.
What's great about that is, say
you can send a query and
you can tell it to call back
when the results come in,
instead of having to block and
wait for those results.
So for our chat application,
we're actually going to choose
to use the Redis library to
do persisting messages.
Redis is a key-value store,
but more importantly, it
doesn't just store
strings as value.
It can store things like
lists, hashes,
sets, sorted sets.
And you interact with all of
these data structures in Redis
using these commands.
Redis has a really great
documentation website, where
you can go and search for
commands by the data structure.
And, let's say we want
to learn how
to use the Get command.
So all we do is Get, and then
we pass in a certain key.
But what's really great about
this website is that you can
actually run these Redis
commands right on the website,
just like Code School.
So I can do SET newkey
equal to "Dog,"
and then when I run GET newkey,
I get the value "Dog" back.
Let's say I want to learn
about how to use lists.
I can go to the LPUSH command,
which means just push a new
value onto a list.
I'm going to go in here and
experiment with this command.
I can run LPUSH newlist
I can push "dog" onto that list.
And I can push "cat."
And I can see that my list
is getting bigger.
And then I can use the
LRANGE command to get
those values back.
Pretty cool.
There is a really great
third-party library called
Node Redis for working with
the Redis library.
And it's completely
non-blocking, like I said before.
Let's see how we would
use the Redis module.
First, we just run npm
install redis.
Then in our application, we can
require the Redis module.
And then create a new client
using createClient.
Finally, we use the set command
to set "hello, yes
this is dog" to the
key message one.
And we're doing the same
thing, pretty much, for
setting the key for
message two.
Then when we want to get back
out that information, we run
client.get,
we pass in the name of the key
and a callback that will be
called when the result
is ready.
For our chat application, we're
probably going to want
to use something like lists.
We had an array before, so now
we're going to want to
translate that into
using Redis lists.
But first let's look, how would
you use lists in Redis?
Here I'm pushing a new message
onto the messages list.
And the callback that gets
called will reply with the
length of that list,
if I want that.
I can go ahead and
do that again.
And now I have two
items in my list.
And a really common pattern in
Redis is to combine the use of
LPUSH where we add a
new item to a list.
And when the callback is called,
we call LTRIM, which
in this case will remove
all but the first two
items in the list.
This allows you to cap the
length of your list.
When we want to retrieve all the
items from that list, we
use the LRANGE command.
We pass in the key,
the starting
index, and the end index.
In this example, we're using
minus 1, which just means give
me all of the messages
in the list.
Now that we've explored the
Redis API a little bit, let's
go ahead and convert our
chat application
to using Node Redis.
And let's start with the store
message function from before.
We're going to update this
function to use Redis lists.
So as you saw before, we
were just pushing new
messages onto the array.
But now we're going to need to
use the Redis client, so let's
first create that client.
In our store message function,
we have to use JSON to
stringify our message
object so we can
store that in the list.
Then we'll use the LPUSH command
again and push that
message onto the
messages list.
And when we get a response from
that, we're going to use
the LTRIM command to make sure
that we only have the newest
10 items in the list.
Now all we have to do is update
the code that outputs
these messages.
We're going to want to reverse
those messages so they come
out in the right order.
Then we can loop through each
message like before.
But this time, before we emit
the message, we have to use
JSON parse to get back
out the JSON object.
Let's see how that fixes our
chat app, now that we're using
persisting stores.
So our dog connects and sends
a couple messages.
And now when our spider
connects,
he gets those messages.
He can send a couple himself.
We're going to go back and
restart our Node application.
And now when we connect with a
third client, we can see that
our messages show up just
like they should.
Now let's add a new bit of
functionality and implement
that chatter list that we
saw on the left side.
This is just going to show
who is currently
connected to the chat room.
And for this, instead of lists,
we're actually going to
use a different data structure,
Redis sets.
And a set is pretty similar to
a list, but instead of just
having everything in there, it
can only be unique data.
So for a list of names, this
will work, because the names
need to be unique.
We can add to the set by
using the sadd command.
And here we're adding three
members to the Names set.
We can remove values from the
set using the srem command.
When we want to retrieve all the
members of a set, we use
the smembers command.
And that will call the callback
with an array of
names of everyone in the set.
So let's jump right
into using sets to
implement this feature.
When a client joins, we're going
to do two new things.
First, we want to notify all the
other clients that a new
chatter has just joined
the chat.
We also want to use the Redis
client library to add the
person's name to the
chatter set.
Then we'll go back to our
client, and we're going to add
a new listener on that add
chatter event that we added in
the server.
And when that event gets
emitted, we're going to call
the insertChatter function,
defined here.
The insertChatter function just
creates a new list item
with the name.
And it appends it
to the chatters
unordered list in the DOM.
Actually, we want to do one
more thing when the client
joins the server.
We can use the smembers command
to get back all the
names that are currently
in the chat room.
And then we can loop through
those names and emit those
names on the add
chatter event.
Conversely, when a chatter
leaves the room, we want to
remove them from that list.
So in our application, we're
going to listen to a new event
on our client called
disconnect.
And when that client
disconnects, we're going to
first grab their name off the
socket, broadcast out all the
other clients that this
chatter has left, and then
remove them from the
chatter set.
On our client, we're going to
listen to the remove chatter
event, and when that's fired,
we're going to find the li in
the list and remove
it from the DOM.
Let's see that in action.
So our first client's
connected, Dog.
We can see he is already
in the room.
So he's going to
send a message.
And now when Spider connects,
he's going to see that Dog is
already connected.
And he's going to see that
message from before.
We go back to the Dog client,
we can see that now he knows
that Spider is in the room.
When a third client connects,
he'll also see everyone who's
currently in the room.
And the other two clients will
also see that he has joined.
So Dog has to go for a walk,
and now when he leaves the
room, the other two clients
are going to
see that he's left.
Well, now we've reached
the end of the course.
Actually, it's the end for me.
You still have a little bit
more work to do in the
challenges.
And when you finish up the
challenges, you'll earn our
last badge.
And we'll see you all
in the wrapup video.