Your online application's
starting to fail.
It's crawling on the network
just as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming
starting from the top.
Better write some code so
the world doesn't stop.
With a non-blocking model, we
will be just fine, built on
Google Chrome's V8 runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
use the Real-Time
Web with Node.
You're watching Real-Time Web
with Node.js, and this is
level two, where we're going
to be going over events in
more detail.
When we talk about events, you
might think about the Document
Object Model in your browser
because the DOM triggers
events, and you can listen
for those events.
Events like click,
submit, or hover.
If you want to run some code
when those events get
triggered, you might run some
jQuery for instance listening
for a click event, and when
click event is triggered, you
want to run some sort
of function.
This code effectively attaches
that function to the DOM
listening for that
click event.
Just like in the DOM,
many objects in
Node also emit events.
And odds are, if they emit
events, they inherit from the
EventEmitter constructor.
The net.Server class inherits
from EventEmitter, and it
emits the request event,
as we saw in level one.
If we're reading a file and we
call fs.readStream, it returns
a stream which inherits from
EventEmitter, which will emit
the data event as we're reading
data out of the file.
Let's take a closer look at the
EventEmitter constructor
by creating our own custom
EventEmitter.
So we're going to require
that class.
For our customer EventEmitter,
we're
going to create a logger.
So we want our logger to
sometimes emit error events,
warn events, and info events.
And we want to be able to write
listeners so we can
listen for when those
events occur.
If we wanted to listen for the
error event, we could write
some code like this.
So here we're saying,
on the error
event, run this callback.
To trigger, or emit, the event,
we call logger.emit, we
specify the name of the event
we want to trigger, and any
additional parameters
here will get
passed to the listeners.
And here's just another example
where we log another
error message.
And we can call this emitter
is many times as we want to
emit the error event.
So back in level one, you'll
remember we had a function
with a request and a response,
and we wanted that callback to
be called every time our server
emitted a request event.
Here's the code that we wrote,
but you might be wondering
what is going on here.
How is that event getting
attached?
Well, we're going to go
ahead and look at
that a little deeper.
We're going to dive into the
documentation now and see
what's going on under
the hood.
So if we look up the
createServer function, we can
see that it returns a new
web server object.
We pass as a parameter a
requestListener which listens
on the request event.
If we look up the server
documentation, we're going to
see that it's an EventEmitter.
It emits several events, one of
which is the request event.
And you can see here the request
event passes two
parameters to the callback,
which is what we're using as
our only parameter to
createServer function.
If we wanted to, we could
write this code
in a different way.
Instead of sending the callback
into createServer, we
could instead just create the
server with no parameters, and
then tell the server
that on the request
event, call this function.
This syntax is typically
how you add event
listeners in Node.
You can listen to multiple
events on an object, or you
can have multiple functions that
listen to the same event.
Doesn't matter.
For instance, if we want to
listen to the close event on
our server and call a function,
we could simply
write server on close, and
then send in a function.
Well that's it for this level.
Admittedly, this is one of the
shorter levels in this course.
Don't worry.
But it's really important at
this point that you understand
how to work with
events in Node.
So, time to get to it.