[SINGING]
Your online application's
starting to fail.
It's crawling on the network
just as fast as a snail.
We need evented programming
starting from the top,
better write some code so the
world doesn't stop.
With the non-blocking model
we will be just fine.
Built on Google Chrome's
V8 runtime.
And all you need to do is write
some JavaScript code and
then use the Real Time
Web with Node.
Welcome back to Real Time
Web with Node.js.
We're starting Level 5, and
we're going to be talking
about the Express
web framework.
First let's talk a little
bit about Express.
Now, Express is a
Sinatra-inspired web
application framework
for Node.js.
Express gives you routes,
middleware, environment-based
configuration, redirection
helpers, file
uploads and a lot more.
So let's jump in and create a
hello world style app for
Express to see how it works.
We can require Express after
we install it with npm.
Then we call a createServer on
Express which will return an
application, and using the
application, we can set up a
root route that responds
to the get request.
And whenever we get a request
to that route, it's going to
call this callback where we're
going to use response.sendfile
to respond with index.html from
our current directory.
And finally, we just listen
on port 8080.
Now, when we issue a request for
the server, we get back a
200 response.
Let's build a little bit
more complex example.
Let's say we want to make a
request to the Twitter API and
respond with the JSON.
We're going to use the request
and URL module, so let's
require those.
Then we're going to set up our
route here to respond to a get
request for the URL slash
tweet slash username.
Inside of our callback, we can
get access to the username and
the URL by calling
req.params.username.
Then we're going to set up an
options object to build our
URL for the request.
We're going to use URL format
to turn that options object
into a URL string.
Then we can pass our URL
string into the request
function and pipe back
the response.
That's all there is to it.
So let's jump into the
screencast here.
You can see we're going to start
up our application using
node app.js.
Then we're going to hop over
to another terminal window
where we're going to use curl
to issue a request to
localhost 8080, and then we're going
to pass in a username--
that's my username there--
and we're going to get
back a bunch of JSON.
It's kind of hard to read, so
we're actually going to
quickly install this pretty
JSON module globally.
We can pipe the JSON into that
executable, and it will print
it out in a much nicer format,
as you can see here.
But instead of just printing
out the JSON, how do we
get onto a web page?
Well, Express has really good
support for using template
libraries and layouts
to build web pages.
Now we're back here in our
route, and instead of piping
the results right to the
response, we're actually going
to pass in a callback.
Inside that callback, we can
parse the body of the response
using JSON, and then we're going
to call response.render,
which is provided to
us from Express.
We pass in the name of the
template file as the first
argument, and then
we pass in an
object as a second argument.
As you can see here, in our
template tweets.ejs, we have
access to that object.
This allows us to print out
the name, and we can loop
through each tweet and print out
an li tag with the tweet's
text inside of it.
Going back to our example, we're
going to fire up our app
again, and now instead of going
to the command line,
we're going to open up a
browser, go to local host 8080
slash tweet slash codeschool.
Oops!
It looks like when we issued
that request, there was an
error saying that we couldn't
find the layout.
So when Express tried to
render our tweets.ejs
template, it actually looked
for a layout to insert that
template into.
So how do these layouts work?
To fix this, all we need to do
is define a layout.ejs file.
And in our layout, we're going
to have things like the head
of the HTML document with a
DOCTYPE, and where we want our
template to go, we just
put this body tag.
Now, when we go back to our
example, fire up the node app,
when we go back to the browser
and refresh, we should have
our HTML page with the tweets.
There's a lot more to the
Express web framework, so
you're probably going to want
to go to their website and
check out their documentation.
That's it for Level 5.
Get your hands dirty in the
challenges, and we'll see you
back here for Level 6.