[SINGING]
Your style sheets are bloated
and making a mess.
Your HTML is ashamed
of your CSS.
It's not organized and
it's not classy.
It's time to make your
style sheets sassy.
Using CSS extensions are the
preference, we'll use mixins
nesting, and inheritance
Functions extend and partials
we'll amass.
In no time you'll be
assembling Sass.
Welcome to Level
Three, Utility.
Now that we have a handle on
Compass, we're going to start
diving into a lot of the
utilities and image functions
that Compass grants us.
But first a bit of a warning.
Before we get into it, while
there are a ton of helpers and
utilities in Compass, we're
going to be going over a few
of our favorites.
But not everything is actually
going to be useful to you.
Always make sure you're checking
the output and
determining whether or not you
should be using that mixin or
utility that Compass
grants us.
As an example, let's take a
look at the clearfix mixin
that's provided to
us by Compass.
So when we use this mixin, it
outputs a bit of code for us,
the overflow hidden, and the
zoom has layout older IE hack.
This helps us clear any children
that are floating in
the parent container.
And while it's useful, it's
not the current accepted
version of a clearfix,
which looks
something more like this.
So while it's available to
us, it's not the best way
currently to go about
a clearfix.
So we definitely recommend not
using that mixin over
using this version
of the clearfix.
With that warning in mind, let's
go into some helpers
provided to us by Compass.
The first set of helpers we'll
look at are the image-url and
font-url functions.
Instead of being forced to write
a URL and then provide
the relative or absolute path to
that asset, we can instead
use these functions to only be
forced to write the name of
the asset and have the path
output for us like so.
This should look pretty familiar
if you're used to the
Rails asset path.
Back in Level One, we introduced
scale_color, which
helps us relatively
scale aspects of a
certain input color.
Now Compass actually gives us
a helper to do the lightness
version of this without having
to pass any keyword arguments.
So we're able to replace our
original scale_color with
scale-lightness and just include
the percentage as a
second argument and achieve
the same relative color
lightness scaling.
If we need to, we can include a
negative value as the second
argument to darken our
color instead.
Similarly, scale-saturation does
the same thing but for
the saturation of the color.
So if we wanted to up the
saturation of the color
relatively, we can use
scale-saturation in place of
scale_color.
And if we wanted to decrease
the saturation, we could
change that second argument
to a negative value.
Like Sass, there are quite a few
color functions available
to us in Compass.
Things like shade and tint can
also be used to add black and
white to a color.
So if you're trying to do more
complex color alterations,
definitely take a
look at those.
The next helper we'll look
at is opposite position.
So opposite position is a
function which returns the
opposite side or pair of
sides that we pass in.
If we pass top into
opposite position,
it will return bottom.
If we pass right bottom,
it returns left top.
To start playing with opposite
position, let's build a
triangle using CSS.
This is a bit of a hack.
We're kind of building a
triangle based on how browsers
draw borders.
So using this set of properties,
draws a border on
our element that has
no height and width
to look like a triangle.
Don't worry too much if you
don't understand the CSS right
now, just know that this
builds a triangle.
If we want to make this reusable
and be able to define
which direction the triangle
points in, we can rewrite this
as a mixin.
So we're going to start a caret
mixin in just past where
we want the point of
the triangle to be.
For now, everything
else is the same.
And then once we've defined the
mixin, we can use it by
just using plus caret within
our caret class down here.
We'll go ahead and pass our top
point in, but we're not
going to use it quite yet.
First up, we need to find the
opposite side of our point
because that needs a special
value for our border.
So we're going to set an
opposite variable equal to the
opposite side of the
point we passed in.
Once we have that opposite side,
we can interpolate the
point and the opposite point
into the border properties for
those two special cases.
So here, the first border is
what the value needs to be to
create a triangle using
the opposite value.
And the second border of 0 is
what the point value needs to
be to create our triangle.
Once we set this up, now we can
pass different points in
and to have our triangle facing
different ways, like
using this left value.
If you wind up needing to deal
with more complicated math in
Saas, Compass does add a number
of math functions like
pi, sin, logarithms,
square root.
These aren't incredibly useful
in the day to day, but
inevitably you're going to
need one of these for
something more complicated down
the road, and it's useful
to know that they exist.
With helpers out of the way,
let's dive into a few more
utilities that Compass
gives us.
First up is contrast color.
So with contrast color, we're
going to pass in a color, and
it will return a light color or
a dark color based on how
light or dark that original
input color is.
We're going to create a set of
buttons that have different
backgrounds, and we'd like to
automatically know which text
colors those buttons should be
based on the lightness or
darkness of those background
colors.
So we're going to pass the
background colors into a new
function we create called
button text.
And that should ultimately
return the color that those
button's text should be.
The return value of that
function is going to use our
contrast color function.
It's going to pass in, as the
first value, that background
color of each button.
The first return value
is a dark color.
The second return value
is a light color.
And the third is that threshold
which determines at
what point it breaks between
the light and dark value.
In this case, dead
center at 50
So with the first background
of our button being dark,
it'll return the light value for
us, ultimately ending up
with a button that
looks like this.
The second button, with a
lighter background, returns
the dark value using
contrast color.
So we end up with a button
that looks like this.
Next up is stretch.
So when dealing with larger,
full-screen applications that
might make use of complicated
panes, sometimes we need to
position bits of content and
have them stretched to fit
their parent container.
In this example, we have an
aside inside of our content
with a class of sidebar, and
we want our sidebar to
automatically stretch to
fit the exact size
of our content container.
It's a common pattern to go
ahead and give this container
a position of absolute
and then set a value
for all four sides.
When you do it this way, it's
going to stretch it to fit to
the zero position of all four
sides of its parent container.
So that works.
But with Compass, we can
simplify this process.
Using the stretch mixin, it will
automatically output all
five of those values for us.
If we need a bit more
complicated use, we're able to
pass values into stretch like
so, using the normal order of
top, right, bottom, and left
to alter how far away from
those sides it sticks.
Here we're going to pass five
pixels into all four values,
so our container stretches to
fit the container five pixels
off from each edge.
If needed, we can set auto to
be one of the values so that
it doesn't stretch that edge.
And then, alternatively, define
a height or a width
like here, where we no longer
have it stretching to the
right edge but are manually
setting a width.
Let's finish up with a
few image functions.
For this example, we're going
to be looking at this png,
s.png, which is 236
by 236 pixels.
If we want to use this as a
background image of our logo
class, we can include it as
such, and then we can manually
find the height and width
if we'd like.
However, if we have to change
the image, if the height and
width change, we have to
manually update this
and it's not ideal.
So we're able to automatically
find the height using the
image height function
and passing in
the name of the image.
And we're able to do the same
with the width using the image
width function.
Now, no matter what the
dimensions of that image are,
if we end up changing it later,
it'll automatically be
updated in our style sheet.
As you might remember from CSS
Cross-Country, we're able to
embed images directly into our
CSS using Base64 encoding, and
Compass can do this for
us automatically.
So using the inline-image
function, followed by the name
of the image, it'll go ahead and
create the Base64 encoded
version of the image and include
it in our style sheet.
And the image height and the
image width will still work
for that image should
we choose to use it.
Embedding the image directly
into the CSS
helps us out a bit.
We no longer have to worry
about loading flashes for
states like hover and focus
if we're changing
the background image.
Ultimately, though, while it
reduces the HTTP requests, it
adds about 10more file size
than including it separately.
So you have to weigh
those benefits.
It's only available on IE8+,
which only supports up to 32
kilobytes of image.
But it has good mobile support,
where HTTP request
reduction is very useful.
That wraps up Level Three, so
it's time for the next set of
Challenges.
We'll see you back here
for Level Four.