[SINGING]
Your style sheets are bloated
and making a mess.
Your HTML is ashamed
of your CSS.
It's not organized and
it's not classy.
It's time to make your
style sheets sassy.
Using CSS extensions
are the preference.
We'll use mixins, nesting
and inheritance.
Functions extend and partials
we'll amass.
In no time you'll be
assembling Sass.
You're watching level
four, rhythm.
In this level, we're going to be
going through the Vertical
Rhythm module of Sass and the
various ins and outs of how to
use its mixins.
In dealing with grids on the
web, most of us are familiar
with horizontal grids like the
one that Susy provides.
Will go into Susy in the
wrap-up, but it's a compass
and Sass extension for dealing
with layouts like this.
In this level, though, we're
talking about vertical grids,
or baseline grids.
Ultimately, we're going to be
working towards something like
this, a very simple set
of text styling.
And when we overlay a baseline
grid, we can see that
everything in this text
styling aligns
to that grid properly.
We're going to start with
this bit of HTML, one h1,
a couple paragraphs,
and a block quote.
Without some sort of baseline
grid, we might style this
using a set of magic numbers and
eyeballing different sorts
of margins.
If we look back at our content
with this style applied, it
might look something
like this.
This isn't bad, but it doesn't
really conform
to any sort of rhythm.
If we overlay a baseline grid,
we can see that the elements
don't fall into any sort
of organization.
We're going to use Compass to
add a baseline grid for us and
allow it to manage all of the
alignment and margins and
padding for us.
And so initially we're going to
start with just a reset of
our content, which looks
something like this.
Then, to start using the
Vertical Rhythm module, we
have to set a few global
variables.
First up, we'll establish our
base font size and our base
line height, and then use the
establish-baseline mixin
which outputs some CSS like
this, ultimately changing our
output to look like this.
Now we have a base font size set
and our baseline grid is
in place with all the line
heights matching.
With our baseline grid started,
let's start adjusting
font sizes and leading.
Because of the relative line
heights to keep our vertical
rhythm going, if we try to
change the font size in a
normal way, it's going to throw
off our vertical rhythm.
So in order to change font size
while using it, we can
use the adjust font size
to mixin like so.
Here we're going to change
the font size of
our h1 to 50 pixels.
And the output will go ahead
and figure out the relative
unit to match up for us.
Now we can see our h1 has been
increased to the relative unit
for 50 pixels, and it still
conforms to our baseline grid.
Let's talk a bit about
typography for a moment.
Leading is the
distance between our baseline
grid units.
Back when type was handset, they
would take strips of lead
to help separate out
the lines of text.
So we continue this function in
our vertical rhythm grid.
To determine the number of units
a single line of text
should use up, we can
adjust our leading.
So we're going to adjust the
leading of our block
quote to two units.
And with the leading adjusted
on our block quote, it now
takes up two units of vertical
space with the text vertically
centered within.
It's important to note that when
we're dealing with our
vertical rhythm mixins, if we
adjust the base font size for
that unit, we usually need to
tell that mixin that the font
size has changed.
Otherwise, it tries to calculate
any relative units
based on our base font
size variable.
Here, if we adjust the font size
of our block quote to 20
pixels and take a look at the
output again, we can see that
it's been thrown slightly off.
We have to go back to our adjust
leading to mixin and
include a second argument of
that adjusted font size.
And our output is now fixed and
calculated correctly to
compensate.
As you might have noticed,
there's a bit of extra CSS
that's being output.
Since we're adjusting the font
size, it's outputting an
adjusted line height for us.
And then when we change the
leading, it outputs another
line height change on
our block quote.
Because of the way the Vertical
Rhythm module works,
there's no way to stop these
overriding properties from
being output so you need to
make sure that any use of
these mixins is deliberate to
keep your CSS from being
bloated with overuse of these
sorts of properties.
Finally, let's wrap up by
showing how we can change
margin, padding and borders
without affecting
our baseline grid.
To add margins to the top or
bottom of elements, we can use
the leader and trailer mixins,
like the one unit of leader
and trailer we're adding
to our paragraph.
Now our output shows a one unit
margin above and below
every paragraph.
Just like our just leading to
mixin, if we change the base
font size on an element, we need
to notify our leaders or
trailers of that change.
If we add a two unit trailer
to our h1, we need to make
sure we pass as a second
argument that 50 pixel
adjusted font size so that our
output keeps the baseline grid
going correctly.
Here's what this looks like now
with a two unit trailer.
There are other mixins given to
us by Compass for dealing
with vertical rhythm, including
padding leader and
padding trailer.
Both of these work the same way
as leader and trailer but
output a padding
value instead.
If we have to use a combination
of leaders,
trailers, and padding leaders
and trailers, we can combine
everything using the
rhythm mixin.
The rhythm mixin takes arguments
including the
leader, padding leader, padding
trailer, trailer, and
the adjusted font size, if
necessary, to combine and
output all those properties.
Be careful in your
use of rhythm.
If you don't need all these
values and you include zeros,
it's going to output properties
in your CSS with a
zero that you might not need.
The final property that throws
off our baseline grid and
styles is border.
So if we add a standard bottom
border to our h1 element and
look at the output,
our baseline grid
has been thrown off.
To add a border that doesn't
mess with our grid, we can
either use the leading border
or trailing border mixins.
Here we'll add trailing
border.
The first argument is the
width we'd like of
the border, 10 pixels.
The second argument is the
padding we'd like between the
border and the element,
one unit.
And the adjusted font size,
if necessary, which
it is in this case.
So if we look back at our
output, our h1 now has a
border on the bottom and
our grid is maintained.
If we'd like to add a border to
all sides of an element, as
well as the white space around
all sides of that element as
well, we can use
rhythm borders.
So the rhythm borders mixin
takes the width of the border
as the first argument as well,
then the amount of white space
in units, one here, and
then the adjusted
font size, if necessary.
So now our block quote has a
two pixel relative border
around it and equal
white space of
one unit on all sides.
As a recap, here's all
the code we've
written in this level.
As you can see, we've styled our
text without writing any
normal CSS.
Everything is mixins that are
handled through our Vertical
Rhythm module.
Baseline grids are difficult
to maintain on the web,
especially when it comes to
adding images and especially
design elements.
Just because these things might
throw off your grid,
something is better
than nothing.
And if you're interested in
tools to help you maintain
your vertical rhythm despite
images, we'll go into a few of
those things in the wrap-up.
That does it for level four.
So you're on the next
set of challenges.
We'll see you back here for
the final level, five.