[SINGING]
Your style sheets are bloated
and making a mess.
Your HTML is ashamed
of your CSS.
It's not organized, and
it's not classy.
It's time to make your
style sheets Sassy.
Using CSS extensions are the
preference, well it makes
stems nest in an inheritance.
Functions extend and partials
we'll amass.
In no time you'll be
assembling Sass.
Welcome to the final level,
Level Five, Sprites.
In this level, we're going to
talk a bit about spriting and
how Compass can make it much,
much easier on us.
Back in CSS Cross-Country, we
talked a bit about how we can
set up sprites and why
they're useful.
It combines a lot of images
into one, large image.
And then we use background
position to position that
image within an element
correctly so that we're only
seeing the part that we need.
This reduces the number
of HTTP requests.
And it's a very good
practice, but it's
not universally loved.
It's usually seen as a really
tedious process, and we
usually resort to third-party
tools to help us manage our
sprites for us.
There are a lot of really large
sites that make use of
sprites, like YouTube's
sheet right here.
In dealing with background
images in your CSS, always
make sure you're using
the correct solution.
Sprites, icon fonts, embedded
images all have their
advantages and disadvantages,
so choose appropriately for
your project.
Throughout the level,
we're going to be
using these three images.
They'll all be inside a
subdirectory of our Images
folder, Icons.
And they're all at different
sizes, making spriting a bit
more difficult when
done manually.
To automatically sprite these
using Compass, we're going to
use @import in a new way.
We can import the items in the
Icons folder using the
asterisk to pull all pngs, and
this is going to create the
sprite for us, which looks
something like this.
The file will be added to the
Images folder, then it's going
to include a long string
after a hyphen.
You won't need to worry about
that because we're always
going to let Compass figure
out what the images and
include it into our style
sheet for us.
Once we've used this @import to
create our sprite, we can
automatically set up all
these sprites using the
all-icons-sprites mixin.
Now icons in this case refers to
the folder in which all of
our icons are found.
If all of your icons were in a
separate folder, you'd need to
change this name.
So when this runs, it outputs
all of this CSS for us,
automatically setting up classes
based on the file
names of our icons, and creating
separate classes to
set the background position
of each of those icons.
So this might be what you need
for your projects, but there's
a few problems.
Up first is creating a chain
of classes for all of the
icons that we have.
So the larger our style sheet
becomes, the larger that chain
of selectors becomes.
Also, while it outputs the
background position for us, it
doesn't set a height and
a width for that class.
So we have to go ahead and
manually figure that out and
set it later if we want to use
the sprite correctly and only
show that bit of the image.
To combat that, we're going to
set up sprites manually.
To start a manual set up,
we're going to use the
sprite-map function and
set it equal to a
variable called icons.
We use this same argument in
sprite-map that we used in
import to go ahead and
set up that sprite.
However, unlike import, it's
not going to go ahead and
create that image for us yet.
With that ready, we're going
to do something similar to
Twitter Bootstrap, and we're
going to use the i element as
the main HTML element for
all of our icons.
That allows us to set the
background of i to be our
sprite and not be required
to create a long chain of
selectors, like the automatic
version that might get too large
if we have a large amount
of sprites.
Once we set the background of
our i element to be the icons
variable that stores our
sprite-map, then the image is
created in the Images directory,
just like our old
@import in the automatic
method.
And it's automatically
added as the
background of the i element.
With that set, we need to start
building out our sprites.
So we're going to manually
create an icon cancel class,
and we need to set the
background position to use the
correct positioning
from our sprite.
Now Compass gives us the
sprite-position function helper.
We have to pass in the
sprite-map of the icons
variable and the name of our
icon, which in this case is
cancel, then it automatically
outputs that background
position for us.
Like we talked about in the
automatic method, though, this
is still missing some sort
of height and width.
We could use the Image Width and
Image Height helpers that
we saw back in Level Three.
But there's a sprite dimensions
mixin that's
included in Compass for us that
we just need to pass the
sprite-map again and the name of
the sprite, and it outputs
the height and the width
for us automatically.
Now if we want to use the cancel
icon in our sprite, we
simply need to use the i
element, give it that class,
and it just uses the portion of
the sprite at the correct
height and width for
that icon to show.
With that pattern set, now all
we need to do is build out the
other two icons.
So we create a class of icon
next and a class of icon
warning and set the appropriate
background
positions and sprite
dimensions.
So this works and we could
use this, but we
see a pattern forming.
The same code is used in each
example, only the name of the
file changes.
So there's still some ways to
optimize this using Sass.
First up, we can create a list
that just contains the names
of our icon files--
cancel, next, and warning--
store it in the Icon
Names list.
And we can loop through those,
kind of like we did with
authors earlier in the course,
and output the same bit of
code since that name is just
used in three locations.
Ultimately, our CSS compiles
to the exact same thing.
This is better, and all we would
need to do to update our
sprites now is add a new file
to the Icons folder and that
name to our Icon Names list.
But we're still manually
updating the Icon Names list.
We can really optimize
that a bit more.
Fortunately, Compass gives us
a sprite names function.
So we can pass our sprite-map
of icons into sprite names,
and it returns the list of the
no extension file names for
each icon automatically, which
is exactly what we need.
So any time we add an image
to our Icons folder, it
automatically is part of the
output of this and creates a
new class for us.
So the output is ultimately the
same, and we can see our
full bit of code here.
The only thing we need to do
to update our sprites is to
add a new icon to our
Icons folder.
There are other configuration
options in dealing with
sprites in Compass, like adding
white space around
every icon on a generated sprite
or having the generated
sprite be a different
orientation than vertical.
That's it for the video, so
you're on to the last set of
challenges.
Good luck, and we'll see you
again in the wrap-up.