[SINGING]
You're style sheets are bloated
and making a mess.
Your HTML is ashamed
of your CSS.
It's not organized, and
it's not classy.
It's time to make your
style sheets sassy.
Using CSS extensions
are the preference.
We'll use mixins, nesting
and inheritance.
Functions extend, and partials
we'll amass, in no time,
you'll be assembling Sass.
You're watching Assembling
Sass part two.
I'm Nick Walsh.
And this is level
one, More Sass.
Our agenda in this course
is two-fold.
First up, we're going to be
talking about a few more
useful bits of Sass we didn't
get to in part one.
And then we're going
to go into this the
Sass extension Compass.
So one level 1, we're going to
talk a bit about the indented
syntax and then go into some
useful bits of lists,
utilities, and place
holders that help
extend our Sass knowledge.
First up, let's talk about
the other Sass syntax.
In the first part of the course,
we talked about Sassy
CSS, the defaults Sass syntax.
But there's also a second
syntax called
the indented syntax.
So files using the indented
syntax end in .sass.
And the primary difference
between Sassy CSS and the
indented syntax is, removing
semicolons and curly braces.
So this bit of code, rewritten
in the indented syntax, has no
curly braces and
no semi colons.
It's white-space active,
so it's a bit simpler.
The second main difference
between using the indented
syntax and Sassy CSS is how
we define and use mixins.
So in Sassy CSS we have
to go ahead and say @mixin,
followed by the mixin name.
And then to call it,
we use @include.
The rewritten version of this
in the indented syntax just
uses equals to define our mixin,
and then uses plus to
go ahead and use that
mixin in our code.
Throughout the course, all of
our examples are going to use
the indented syntax to
keep things simple.
And then, in the challenges,
you'll be able to use either
syntax as you please.
We definitely recommend giving
the indented syntax a shot.
It's going to be really
strange at first.
You probably have semicolons and
curly braces sort of built
into your muscle memory
now if you've been
doing CSS for a while.
But it definitely grew on us,
and it might grow on you, too.
Back in part one of the course,
we talked about the
list data types.
So groups of values, either
space separated or comma
separated, like these
two lists.
And then we went on to use the
lists to loop through and
create sets of classes, like
setting the authors variable,
here looping through each, and
making sets of classes and
background URLs based on the
names of the authors.
In Sass, we also have access
to functions to modify our
lists or to pull values
out of lists.
First up is length, which lets
us find the number of values
in our list.
We also have append, which can
add value to the end of the
list, and append doesn't
actually alter
our original list.
If we want to use that value,
it returns a value.
And we can set it to
a new variable.
We also have the ability to
join two lists together.
And we can find the index of a
value that we pass in via the
index function.
So if we pass in dan, we
can find the index
of dan in our list.
Or if we pass in a value that
isn't found in the list, we'll
get false as a return value.
It's important to note, unlike
arrays, like you might be used
to in other languages, our lists
functions in Sass
don't start with an of 0.
They start with an index of 1.
The alternate of
indexes is Nth.
And so we can pass
in an index, and
instead return a value.
So passing in an index of 3 here
returns the value of dan.
And so our final list function
is zip, which is a bit strange
at first but is pretty easy once
you get the hang of it.
We'll have two lists here,
authors and co-authors.
And then, if we use zip, we're
going to create a paired
version of these two lists.
It'll take the first value of
both lists and join them into
a list of their own, the second
value of both lists and
join them into a list of their
own, and make both of those
list one large list.
So we end with two lists inside
of one larger list,
each paired up indexes from
the original list that we
started with.
So that seems a bit
strange, right?
How could we make use of that
in our actual style sheets?
Here we're going to start with
two separate lists, an authors
lists and a colors list.
And we're using these throughout
our style sheets in
other places.
But also, you find out we want
to combine the two of them to
use the colors as backgrounds
for each of our authors.
So we're going to use the zip
function, and the zip function
returns something like this--
one large list that contains
four separate lists of paired
index is between our
two original lists.
Now we can do a loop similar to
our original authors loop.
We do an each loop over our
new, combined zip list.
And the first iteration of this
loop will have the list
of Nick and Green as the
instance variable.
So in order to pull Nick out to
add to our author class, we
can use nth and pull the index
one value out for the author.
And then, to find the correct
background color, we can use
nth, the second index,
to get green out.
So when this loops through and
outputs our CSS for us, we
have a bunch of authors based
on the other names, and each
background is set to the
paired-up color.
Another way we can make use of
our list functions is in
determining widths based
on length lists.
So here, we have a
list of authors.
And if we want to set them side
by side, we might create
a separate class, like author
here, have it floating, and
have the width be set so that
they can be set side by side
based on their length,
25 120720n this case.
If we were to add another item
to our authors list, that
width would longer be correct.
We'd need to manually
alter it to be 20
So instead, we can use
Sass to go ahead and
handle this for us.
We can start with the width of
100 0x1.b5aa00001d79p-753nd then divide that by
the length of our
authors list.
So it'll output the same CSS
that we originally started
with, and if our list changes
length, then it'll
automatically update
that for us.
Now that we've finished up with
lists, let's go over a
few more utilities available
in Sass for us.
First up is scale color.
So in part one, we talked about
the lighten and darken
functions, amongst other
color-altering functions,
which allow us to sort of
predictably change colors.
And they're extremely useful,
but they have one main flaw,
in that they're linear.
If we start with a pretty light
color, like our hex
value here of all e's, and
lighten it by just 7 120720t
already outputs white.
So anything above 7will be
white, and that really reduces
the usefulness of our
lighten function.
Instead, we can make
use of the scale
color function in Sass.
So scale color allows us to
relatively scale colors, and
we can do either the red,
green, blue saturation,
lightness, or alpha values
using scale color.
It combines all of those.
We can do more than
one or just one.
And since it can take all of
these arguments, we need to
use keyword arguments.
So we can go back to our
original example here, we can
change it to scale color, still
pass in the same color,
and then pass a keyword argument
of lightness 7
So when we look at our output
now, instead of scaling it
directly to white, linearly,
it's going to relatively scale
it 7between the original start
value and white, so we
have this as our output value.
Also in part 1 of this course,
we introduce control
directives, like the if
and else conditionals.
And we had an example like this,
in which we are setting
a theme variable, and the
dependent on the value of that
theme variable, outputting a
certain background color.
In Sass, though, we also
have the ability to do
a single line if.
And if you come from something
like JavaScript or Ruby, you
might be familiar with
this as it's sort of
like a ternary operator.
So with this single line if, we
pass in a condition as the
first argument, then
the true value, and
then the false value.
So we're able to rewrite our
example like so, setting the
background equal to the return
value of this single line if,
passing our same condition,
passing the true value next,
and then passing the false
value, ultimately ending up
with the same thing.
Finally, let's revisit
placeholder selectors.
So in part one, we talked about
placeholder selectors as
selectors we can extend but
not use in our normal CSS,
things that don't
create their own
selectors when they compile.
And we use this in the button
examples to have a bit of
shared code between buttons that
went ahead and fixed sort
of the extend problems if
we scoped those changes
accidentally later.
But what if we wanted to use
these shared styles on their
own, without affecting our
extend structure that we've
already created.
We obviously can't go ahead
and use this placeholder
selector in our HTML, since it
doesn't really compiled down
to anything.
So just because we're using a
placeholder selector doesn't
mean we can't create selector
chains like
normal in our Sass.
We can still add a class of
button with that placeholder
selector so that those styles
compile down, and we can use
that button class as normal
without affecting any of our
extends that are
already set up.
Similarly, we can still use our
placeholder selector like
normal Sass as well.
If we have a bit of HTML that
need some nested style, and we
want to include that nested
styles in our placeholder
selector to be extended
into our other
buttons, we can do so.
Now it's important to note
that while this now works
based on the number of times
that this placeholder
selector's extended is also a
number of times that that
nested style will
appear in this
selector chain like shown.
So for longer extends, you 're
going to need to watch out how
you use this, so you're
not creating
overblown, bloated CSS.
You've made it to the end of
level 1, so now it's time to
go ahead and do some challenges
on your own.
Make sure you use the hints
if you need to.
We don't want you to get stuck
in any one place for too long.
And we'll see you back
here for level 2.