[SINGING]
Your style sheets are bloated
and making a mess.
Your HTML is ashamed
of your CSS.
It's not organized and
it's not classy.
It's time to make your
style sheets Sassy.
Using CSS extensions
are the preference.
We'll use mixins
nesting and inheritance
Functions extend and partials
we'll amass,
In no time you'll be
assembling Sass.
You're watching Level
Two of Assembling
Sass, Part Two, Compass.
In this level, we're going to
introduce the Sass extension
Compass and show a few early
ways on how we can go ahead
and start using it.
So what is Compass?
Compass bills itself
as an open-source
CSS authoring framework.
So it adds a lot of tools on
top of Sass for us like
repeated patterns and modules
that we can use in our
everyday styles.
There are a lot of things in
Compass, but we're going to go
ahead and focus on the high
points in this course for you.
We'll start off with
a bit of history.
So Compass was started by Chris
Eppstein, who's one of
the core maintainers on
Sass as charityware.
Other core maintainers on the
Compass project includes Scott
Davis, Eric Meyer, Brandon
Mathis, and Anthony Short, and
the source for Compass is
available here on GitHub.
Now that we know what Compass
is, let's talk a bit about how
to start using it.
So Compass is comprised
of five main modules--
the utilities module,
typography,
CSS3, layout, and reset.
The first four don't actually
include any CSS until we start
using things inside of them.
Only the fifth, reset, actually
outputs any CSS on
its own, and we'll talk
about that again soon.
So once Compass is installed,
which we're not going to worry
about until the wrap up of the
course, we can go ahead and
start using it in our style
sheets by importing it.
By importing Compass, it's
going to include the
utilities, typography,
and CSS3 modules.
And then if we need to use the
layout module, we can do so by
saying @ import compass/layout.
Since none of these modules
actually output any CSS until
we use the tools within, we
definitely recommend just go
ahead and importing them at
the top of your main Sass
style sheet so that the tools
are useful throughout.
If you do need to restrict which
modules or submodules
are available, you can include
them separately, but normally
this won't be the case.
Now we did talk about
that reset module.
If you do include the fifth
module, reset, you need to do
so kind of like we did with
the layout module.
And what that's going to do is
output a bunch of CSS based on
Eric Meyer's CSS reset
style sheet.
So this seems very useful, as
we usually reset our CSS in
some way, but it's not
ideal in production.
Because it's outputting the CSS
automatically for us, we
can't modify it to just
fit our site's needs.
And if you're one of the
Normalize.css folks and prefer
that sort of reset, you
definitely won't want to use
this module.
With Compass available now,
let's talk a bit about how we
can use it.
Back in Part One, we talked
about how mixins could be used
to remove our need to write a
bunch of prefix CSS3 classes,
kind of like box-sizing here.
So instead of writing the
Mozilla WebKit prefixes, we
have a mixin which handles
that for us.
But when we look at our output,
we have the WebKit and
Mozilla prefixes.
We're missing Opera
and Microsoft,
or are those needed?
I'm not really sure.
We're going to need to maintain
this box-sizing mixin.
It becomes a difficult sort
of back and forth game.
With Compass, once we include
it, there's already these
mixins for CSS3 prefix
properties, like box-sizing,
already handled for
us in Compass.
So once we import Compass, our
box-sizing mixin call still
works and outputs the CSS, which
ultimately shows us that
we didn't need that Opera and
Microsoft prefix after all.
Other useful CSS3 mixins
included in Compass include
background for gradients,
border-radius, box-shadow,
transitions, columns,
transforms.
Always make sure that you're
checking what you need to
support in the browsers that
you intend to support with
your project to see whether or
not you need to use the prefix
properties.
Things like border-radius and
box-shadow are getting to the
point now that you don't
necessarily need those prefixes.
So it might vary from
project to project.
In dealing with CSS3 prefix
properties, though, gradients
still take the cake.
Just to do a simple one, we
still have to output code that
looks something like this,
especially a mess when it
comes to the original WebKit
gradient syntax.
But we're mostly going to
focus in on the bits of
non-prefix code here at the
bottom and see how we can use
that using Compass.
So this original gradient
outputs something
that looks like this.
And using the Compass background
mixin, we can go
ahead and remove the need to
write all of that extra syntax
and just include
that non-prefix
version in the mixin.
Once it compiles, all of those
extra prefix properties will
be output by just writing
this line of code.
In the same way, we can handle
our radial gradients using the
radial gradient syntax in
our background mixin.
And that ultimately will
compile down to look
something like this.
And we're still able to use the
more complicated versions
of gradients, like extra color
stops at specified positions
like this one, ultimately
outputting this gradient.
So now you've been introduced
to Compass, and it's time to
move on to the second
set of challenges.
We'll see you back here
for Level Three.