[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Journey into
Mobile and this is Level
Three, Adaptive Adventures.
In this level, we're going
to talk about what
adaptive web design is.
We're also going to talk about
break points and why they
matter, and then finally
we're going to
introduce media queries.
So what is adaptive design?
Well, essentially, adaptive
design is designing for
controlled adaptation.
And basically what this means
is you know the device or
design context that you need
to design for, and then you
design accordingly.
So let's use a real world
example to better illustrate
this concept, and we're
going to use
the design site Dribbble.
Now, Dribbble was originally
created as a desktop web app,
and what they found is that
more and more users were
accessing the site through
their mobile devices.
Now if you have a smartphone, an
iPhone, or an Android, you
know desktop optimized sites
work on a mobile device but
usually you have to zoom in a
lot and swipe a lot, and it's
not exactly an optimal
experience for mobile.
So the guys at Dribbble realized
this and started to
think about, OK, what could they
do in order to optimize
the site for a mobile context.
Well, they could have done
one of two things.
They could have created an
entirely separate mobile site
using separate markup, separate
styles, separate
content, which is a totally
legitimate option if you need
to do that.
They could have created an
adaptive design where they
adapt the styles from the
desktop site to a mobile
environment, or they could
create a responsive site,
which we'll actually cover
in a little bit.
What they did is they chose an
adaptive approach to their
design and they adapted the
styles of their CSS from the
desktop environment to a mobile
environment, creating
an optimal environment if you're
on your laptop or a
desktop computer but also
creating an optimal
environment if you're
accessing the
site on a mobile device.
Adaptive design doesn't mean
that you're covering all the
needs for the universal web.
Usually what it means you are
designing for a specific
context, and that context might
be the device, it might
be screen size, it might
be resolution.
But the bottom line is you know
what it is and you're
specifically targeting
that context.
Now with any design, important
to consider four basic
principles.
You need to know who your user
is, you need to know how
they're going to use the site,
you need to know the context
in which they're going to use
it, so that could be what
device they're using or in what
environment they're using
it, and then finally, you need
to know what your content is
and how that content is going to
adapt based on the context.
So to better illustrate this,
we're going to use another
demo site, and what we've done
is created a fictitious
restaurant called the Nautilus
Bar and Restaurant.
If we apply our four design keys
to the restaurant site,
what we come up with is that
our user probably wants to
either find the restaurant
or learn more about it.
The context is they're probably
going to be accessing
the site either on their laptop
or maybe on a mobile
device, and therefore their
content needs to include
location info, needs to include
a menu, and needs to
include information about
the restaurant.
It probably doesn't need to
include those irrelevant
iStock photos of random people
eating, for instance.
So in our case we're going to be
adapting the design from a
desktop environment to a mobile
environment just like
the Dribbble example.
So here's what we want our site
to look like in a mobile
context, and here's what we want
our site to look like in
a desktop environment.
Alright, so when we cover
adaptive web design, we really
want to look at three
main things.
The first is our markup, the
second is our break points,
and the third is going to be
our media queries that
actually make this work.
So real quickly, let's go ahead
and take a look at how
the site is structured.
We have our main header section
up here at the top,
then we have our menu content
here in the middle, and
finally we wrap up at the bottom
of our page with our
about section.
Next, let's cover
break points.
What are break points?
Well, essentially break
points are where your
design breaks down.
Now, in an adaptive approach
typically your break points
are going to be the height and
the width of the device or the
context that you're targeting.
Now when we talk about a mobile
context, this could
mean a number of different
things.
We have iPhones, we have
Android phones, we have
Kindles, we have iPads, so when
we're talking about a
mobile context, we need to
know what specific mobile
context we want to target.
In our case, we're going to keep
it simple and we're going
to use the size for our
standard iPhone.
In this case, it's going to be
a height of 480 pixels and
it's going to be a width
of 320 pixels.
One of the things you might be
asking is, well, what about
the iPhone 4 or the iPhone 4S?
Well, those have double the
pixel density, but they still
have the same size when it comes
to browser size, so we
actually don't need to double
the size of our break points.
We can keep the height and the
width exactly the same, but
when we talk about things like
images we're going to have to
deal with pixel density.
We'll actually cover that
in a future level.
Alright, so how do we
make this all work?
Well, to make it work we have
to use media queries.
Now you might be familiar with
media queries or at least the
foundations for them if you've
ever written, say, a print
style sheet.
And you might have seen
something like this, where you
put these in the head of
your HTML document.
And basically what this is
saying is we're telling the
browser, hey, for this
particular device or for this
particular thing, use this
CSS style sheet.
And the W3C actually came out
with a new query a few years
back where they actually
targeted mobile devices.
The problem with this is there's
a number of different
mobile devices, so if we use one
style sheet it might look
great on an iPhone but it might
look terrible on, say,
your mom's old Nokia.
So this wasn't a good solution
when we're talking about the
universal web.
So as part of the CSS3 spec, the
media query was introduced
and this is what
it looks like.
We have two main items here.
First, we have the media type--
in this case, we're
looking at screens--
and then we have the actual
query itself,
max-width of 320 pixels.
And then beneath that, we put
all of the styles that we want
to be contained inside
that media query.
So what is this actually telling
the browser to do?
Well, essentially it's saying
for any of viewport that is
less than or equal to 320 pixels
in width, use these
styles over our original
styles.
And if we use max-width, it
stands to reason that we can
also use min-width.
So in this case, what we're
saying is for a viewport size
that is greater than
or equal to 1024
pixels, use these styles.
Now there are a number of other
options that we could
put into our media queries and
we'll actually cover those in
a future level, but for the time
being we're just going to
stick to these simple min-width
and max-width examples.
Alright, so where do you
put your media queries?
You could make a separate style
sheet for each, but that
would be pretty cumbersome and
it would also increase the
load time for your site.
It's a better practice to put
your media queries in a group
at the bottom of your style
sheet like you see here.
It's easier to maintain, it's
easier to find, and it doesn't
increase the load time
as much as including
separate style sheets.
So for our demo site, the
Nautilus Bar and Restaurant,
we can actually have two media
queries, one at 320 pixels,
which is the iPhone in portrait
mode, and one at 480
pixels, which is the iPhone
in landscape mode.
But if you recall back to level
two when we talked about
fluid layouts, we've actually
built the site on a fluid
foundation.
So what that means is the site
can actually scale based on
the viewport size.
And this is great, because it
means that we don't have to do
extra work.
We can actually set the value
of the media query to be the
higher version-- in this
case, 480 pixels--
and we know that when we turn
the iPhone into portrait mode,
the design is going to
scale appropriately
because it's fluid.
Alright, let's look at our
styles for our desktop site,
and then we'll actually adapt
to those to our mobile site.
So first, we're looking
at our header area
for our desktop site.
As you can see, we have our main
logo image and then we
also have a bottom border
of 15 pixels.
Those are going to be the main
things that we change as we
adapt this portion to a
mobile environment.
And as you can see, we've
included a separate logo file
here, which is smaller,
and we've also
removed that bottom border.
And here's what it looks like
in a mobile environment.
Next, what we want to do is we
want to actually move the
location and contact information
beneath the logo.
In the desktop environment
it was floated to the
right of the logo.
So as you can see, these are
our original desktop styles
where we have a lot of floats
and we also have a set width.
As we adapt to a mobile
environment, we're going to
clear all of those floats.
We're actually going to add a
background color, and we're
also going to stretch the width
to be the full width of
the viewport.
And as you can see, now we have
all of that information,
it looks great beneath
the logo.
Now for our menu section in our
desktop environment, we
have our two menu blocks floated
to the left and the
right of each other, but this
isn't going to work on a
mobile environment because those
boxes would get really
small and you wouldn't be able
to even read the menu.
So what we want to do is
actually stack these on top of
one another.
So as you can see in our desktop
styles, we've defined
a width and a percentage and
we have those floats.
As we adapt that to a mobile
environment, we're going to
actually allow the width to
inherit the full width of the
viewport size, and then we're
going to clear those floats.
So instead of having them
floated next to each other,
we're actually going to have
them stacked on top of each
other, which is a much more
readable design for a mobile
environment.
So let me show you what that
looks like in the browser.
So first let's take a look
at our desktop site.
As you can see, we have our logo
up here at the top with
our location information
floated to the right.
We have our menu section here,
the two blocks, and then we
have our about section
beneath that.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at how we've adapted these
styles to a mobile
environment.
And as we pull up our iPhone
here, you can see that we have
our logo centered-- it's a
little smaller-- and we have
all of our location information
stacked beneath that.
Our menu section is stacked on
top of each other, and we've
actually stretched the width
of the image in our about
information to the full
width of the viewport.
So this is an optimal design
for mobile, and this is an
optimal design for
desktop, as well.
Alright, now it's time for you
to work on some challenges.
Good luck on those and we'll
see you in the next level.