[MUSIC PLAYING]
Welcome to Journey
into Mobile.
This is level one, Foundations
for Mobile.
And in this level,
we're going to be
covering three main things.
First, we're going to be talking
about what is the
mobile web.
Then second, we're going to
cover a brief overview of the
course, and then finally,
we're going to look at
relative font sizing.
So let's first talk about
the mobile web.
So what is the mobile web?
Well, there's actually no mobile
web, in as much as
there isn't necessarily
say a desktop web.
You see, this isn't the web.
This is the web.
And what I mean by that is that
the web isn't limited to
one particular device or one
particular environment.
Tim Berners-Lee has a great
thought here where he says
that the primary design
principle underlying the web's
usefulness and growth
is universality.
And that's really what we're
talking about here.
We're talking about
the universal web.
See, the web must work with
any form of information.
And it must be accessible
from any device.
And that's really our
responsibility as web
designers and web developers,
is to make sure that our
designs, that are sites, work
on the universal web.
That they don't just work in a
desktop environment, or just
work in a mobile environment.
So our goal is to make sure that
we are working towards
this universal web.
Because, at the end of the day,
this will be the web.
We're going to see many more
devices come out, many more
environments that we're going to
have to make sure that our
sites and that our applications
actually work in.
So when we talk about mobile
design, or adaptive design, or
even responsive design, really
all we're talking about is
just web design.
So in this course, we're going
to look at three main areas.
First, we're going to cover
fluid layouts and why those
are important.
Second, we're going to talk
about adaptive design.
And then finally, we're going
to wrap up talking about
responsive design.
But before we get into any of
that, we're going to cover a
little bit about fluid
typesetting.
And here's what I
mean with that.
Here's the image that we're
going to be working with.
Let's first take a look at the
mark-up for this image.
It's pretty simple.
All we have is an h1
with a link inside.
Let's take a look at how our
styles render for this
particular mark-up.
Once again, pretty simple.
Our h1, we have it set at 30
pixels for our font size.
And this would be fine, except
that we want our fonts to be
proportional, or relative in
size, so that when we talk
about scaling sites we
can actually have our
font scale with us.
So instead of having our font
size be 30 pixels, we actually
want to convert our pixel
values into ems.
So I'm going to show
you how to do that.
The standard font size for most
browsers is 16 pixels.
But, as you know, browsers
can be kind of finicky.
So we want to make sure that for
all of the browsers that
we're working with we have a
standard font size set on our
HTML element.
So that's why we've gone ahead
and set our standard font size
to be 16 pixels.
But you'll notice down below
that I've also got another
declaration for font size
in our body element.
I've got this size set
at 62 and 1/2%.
Now, what is this for?
Well, since our standard font
size is 16 pixels, that means
that one em is equal
to 16 pixels.
But 16 is kind of a rough
number to divide by.
And you'll see why that
matters in a minute.
So what we've done here is we've
actually taken 62 and
1/2% of 16, which is 10.
So we've converted our font size
to be from 16 pixels to
10 pixels, which is going
to be a much easier
value to divide by.
Now why does that matter?
Well, we're going to be using
this formula in order to
convert our pixel
values into ems.
This formula is target divided
by context equals our result.
And, in this case, our target is
our target font size, which
we want to divide by
the font size of
our containing element.
And that's going to give
us the value that we
need for our ems.
So, in this case, we take our
30 pixels, which was the
value of our h1.
We're going to divide that by
our standard default font
size, which is 10 pixels.
And then we get our
value of 3 ems.
So we plug that back
into our CSS.
In place of 30 pixels,
now we have 3 ems.
And, voila, we've
got our relative
proportional font size.
So that's great.
As you can see from our
image here, it looks
relatively the same.
But we still have to work on
that link because our link
inside of our h1 is
now inheriting the
properties for our h1.
So let's go ahead and do that.
For our link we have it set at
14 pixels, and we need to
convert our pixel
values into ems.
So we're going to use
our formula again.
Now, would we do the same
thing that we do before?
In this case, 14
divided by 10.
Well, let's see how
that looks.
Unfortunately, that doesn't
work, and that's because we
have the wrong context.
You see, in this case, our
context is not the default
browser font size, but actually
the size of our h1,
because our link is inside
of our h1 element.
So in this case, we actually
need to change our context
value from 10 pixels to 30
pixels because, remember, 30
pixels was the original
as of our h1 element.
So if we do this, we get this
value, and we can plug that
into our CSS.
And now it renders properly.
One quick note here.
You might have noticed with our
last conversion that it's
a pretty ugly number.
But that's OK.
We really should let
the browser do the
heavy lifting here.
We don't need to round up or
round down because this is
actually the exact value of
our original pixel size.
So, in this case, we're
not going to round.
We're just going to keep that
value like so, plug it in to
our CSS, and it's going
work just fine.
So why do we spend the time
covering relative font sizing?
We're supposed to be talking
about mobile design, right?
Well, yes.
But see, it's important for you
to understand the formula
for actually converting pixels
to ems because when we start
talking about fluid layouts and
layouts that scale, we're
actually going to be using
the same formula.
So it's important for you to
grasp the concept, and this is
a pretty easy way for
you to do that.
So this level is fairly
simplistic, and the challenges
might not be all that
difficult for
you, but that's OK.
We're going to get to
more advanced stuff
later on in the course.