[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Journey into
Mobile, and this is Level 2,
Fluid Foundations.
In this level, we're going to
be covering the foundations
for fluid layouts and
then also talk
about the fluid grid.
Now, why are we talking about
fluid layouts in a mobile
design course?
Well, when we talk about fluid
layouts, really what we're
talking about are layouts
that scale based on the
size of the view port.
That could be the browser,
that could be the device,
whatever it is that
you're using.
So what makes up a fluid site?
Well, there's really two
main things that
make up a fluid site.
The first is fluid sites are
usually based on a fluid grid.
And, basically, what this means
is the grid is a series
of same size columns spaced
apart evenly across the page.
Now, this helps from a design
standpoint to make the design
more legible to the user, and
just better organized from a
design standpoint.
Additionally, fluid layouts
also have relative values.
Most of the time they're
in percentages.
So, for instance, instead of
setting an element, say at 500
pixels like you see here, we
could convert that into a
percentage of 50%.
So now, if you were to resize
that element, it would be
proportional, or relative, to
its containing element.
So in order to illustrate
this concept we're going
to use a demo site.
Now this demo site is actually
built on a fixed layout, and
we're going to convert
that fixed layout
into a fluid layout.
How are we going to do this?
Well, we're going to actually
use the same formula that we
used to convert our pixel values
to ems back in Level 1.
Let's first go over the mark up
of the site just to get you
familiar with how the
site is structured.
We have a main container div
called site that basically
contains all of the elements
of the site.
Additionally, we have a sidebar
element over here to
the left, and then we have our
main content area which
includes all of our content.
So when we're talking about our
site container, currently
we have it set at a width
of 940 pixels.
Now this is a fixed width site,
and there's nothing
wrong with fixed widths, but
the problem is they don't
necessarily scale with
the view port size.
They're going to be static.
They're going to be fixed.
So we want to actually create
this in a way that the site
scales with the view
port size.
So instead of 940 pixels,
we need to set this as a
percentage.
Now, when we're talking about
our main site container,
there's really not a magic
formula that we can use to
determine the proper
percentage.
It's really a matter of trial
and error because you want to
make sure that the design looks
good in the browser.
So in our case I've played
around with a little bit and
have determined that 90% percent
width is a good value
for our site.
So if we take a look at what
this looks like, you can see
that at a smaller view port size
it really doesn't look
any different, which
is a good thing.
But as we scale the view port
you can see how things change.
The site no longer is centered
in the browser, and you can
see everything is flush left.
Now, the main site container,
div class site, is actually
scaling at 90%.
But the problem is that
the rest of our
elements are still fixed.
So we need to convert those.
The first thing we're going to
look at is going to be our
sidebar element.
So here's our markup for that.
It's pretty straightforward.
We have a section with a class
of sidebar, we have a header,
then we have our nav elements,
and then beneath that we have
our footer.
Let's take a look at
the styles for
this particular section.
In this case, we have our width
set at 305 pixels, which
is obviously fixed, we
need to convert that.
So we're going to bring out
our formula once again.
In this case, our sidebar
width is going to be our
target, and the width of our
main site container is going
to be our context.
So, in this case, we're going
to divide 305 pixels by 940
pixels, and then you're going
to get this lovely number
which you see here.
Now, since we're dealing with
percentages, we actually need
to move the decimal point
over two places.
So we get a value
of 32.4460809%.
Once again, it's one of those
really long numbers, but we
can let the browser do the heavy
lifting and just put
that into our CSS and move on.
So as you can see, we've
replaced our fixed width of
305 pixels with a relative
percentage, and that's going
to allow this section to
scale appropriately.
Let's take a look at what that
looks like in the browser.
So this looks good from a
sidebar element, but it's
creeping into our content
area which,
obviously, isn't very good.
So we need to go ahead and
fix that section next.
All right, so as you can see
from our mark up here, we have
a section with a class of
content, we have an aside
which gives us that pull quote
up at the top, we have our
paragraph content, and then
we have our footer content
beneath that, which includes our
image and our little bio
section down there
at the bottom.
So let's move on to our CSS.
For our content element, you
can see that we have three
main fixed values here.
We have our width at 590 pixels,
and then we have our
left margin and our padding.
So we're first going to tackle
converting the width.
We're going to do the same
thing that we did before.
Our target is the width of
the element in question.
In this case, it's our content
width of 590 pixels.
Our context is going to be the
width of the site container.
If you remember, that
was 940 pixels.
So if we do that equation we
get this value, and we move
the decimal over two places
to get our percentage.
So if we pop that over into
our CSS, now our width is
proportional as opposed
to fixed.
So if we take a look at how this
renders in the browser we
can see that our content area
is actually scaling
appropriately.
Now, obviously, we still need to
fix our left margin and our
padding because those
still aren't right.
As you can see, that
our sidebar is
still creeping over.
But one thing to note here
as well is our paragraph.
Now a paragraph is a block
element, which means it's
going to inherit the width
of its parent element.
In this case, it's going to be
the width of our content area.
So the paragraph is actually
going to scale with the width
of our content area, which
is a good thing.
So it's one thing to keep in
mind as you're creating your
styles, to make sure that
you're not setting fixed
widths on elements that
don't need it.
All right, so now let's
tackle our left
margin and our padding.
Now, we're going to use this
same formula but there's a
couple of different things that
you need to keep in mind
when dealing with margins
and padding.
Let's first talk
about margins.
Now, Ethan Marcotte talks about
flexible margins, and he
says that when setting flexible
margins on an element
you're context is the width
of the elements container.
So we're actually going to do
the same exact thing that
we've been doing and keep
our context the same.
Our margin width is going to be
our target of 325 pixels.
The width of our div class site
container is going to be
our context.
And if we plug those
values into the
equation we get this value.
Once again, we move our decimal
point two places over,
and now we've set our left
margin to be this value, as
opposed to a fixed value.
But when we talk about padding
we have to do things a little
differently.
When setting flexible padding on
element, your context is
the width of the
element itself.
And this makes sense if we go
back to the box model because
when we're talking about padding
we're talking about
the space within an element.
Whereas margin you're talking
about the space
outside of the element.
So as you can see from our
graphic here, we have our box
and the padding is inside.
So our box width is actually
going to be the context, as
opposed to our main site
container which was the
context for our margin.
So if we take a look at our
equation once again, our
target is the width of our
padding, which in this case,
was 20 pixels.
But our context is going to be
the width of the content area,
since that's the box
in question.
So instead of 940 pixels that
we use for our main site
container, it's actually going
to be 590 pixels, which is the
width of our content area.
And then we get this value.
And now we have both flexible
margins and flexible padding,
in addition to, flexible
width.
And, as you can see, from this
screenshot, once again, our
site looks great, and now we've
created a site on a
fluid layout, as opposed to
having it be a fixed width.
So as you can see, the site
scales based on the size of
the view port.
Now it's not perfect, but when
we talk about designing for
the universal web, we're talking
about not knowing the
size of every users view port.
So by creating a site with a
fluid layout we can create a
site that flexes and is very
fluid, as opposed to just
being very fixed and
very static.
So now it's time for you to
actually jump into the code
and try some of the
challenges.
Good luck on these, and we'll
see you in the next level.