[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Journey into
Mobile, and this is Level 4,
Responsive Adventures.
In this level, we're going to be
talking a little bit about
the Mobile First design
approach, then we're going to
talk about how to apply
responsive design, and
finally, we're going to
wrap up with some
advanced media queries.
So when we talk about the Mobile
First approach, Luke
Wroblewski, who sort of
pioneered the concept, has
three important items
to consider.
He talks about Mobile First
as preparing you for the
explosive growth and
new opportunities
on the mobile internet.
Secondly, the Mobile First
approach forces you to focus.
And finally, it enables you to
innovate in ways that you
previously couldn't.
The Mobile First approach forces
you to focus on the
most important things
in your design.
It forces you to simplify
the content.
It forces you to prioritize the
layout, and it forces you
to optimize the user
experience.
Because, if you think about it,
in a mobile design, you
don't have near the screen real
estate as you do in a
desktop environment.
So your space is much more
valuable in a mobile design,
which means you can't just have
filler material, random
photos, or random pieces
of information.
You really have to prioritize.
And this is a great design
concept because as we talk
about the universal web, we need
to make sure that both
our design and our content
is optimized for this.
The Mobile First approach
provides great foundation for
responsive design.
Now, one of the things you
might be asking is, is
adaptive design the same thing
as responsive design?
Well, all responsive designs
could be classified as
adaptive designs, but not
all adaptive designs are
responsive.
You see, responsive designs are
essentially fluid sites
with a series of break points,
whereas adaptive designs are
selectively optimized for the
context that you're targeting.
Ethan Marcotte talks about
responsive designs as
providing continuity
between context.
And that responsive designs
are also portable and
accessible.
And when we're talking about
designing for the universal
web, these concepts are more
important than ever.
So let's kind of recap where
we've come thus far.
We talked about fluid layouts,
which are great except they do
have limitations when it comes
to view port size.
As you saw, as we started to get
smaller and smaller, the
site basically became
unreadable.
So that's not a great
universal solution.
We also talked about adaptive
designs, which are great for
targeted context, but it doesn't
necessarily cover all
of the universal web.
Now we're talking about
responsive design, which is
both flexible and universal.
Because, again, we're providing
continuity between a
variety of different contexts.
Which means we can ensure that
there's an optimal design
experience, whether you're
looking at the site in a
desktop environment, a mobile
environment, or, really,
anywhere in between.
When we talk about responsive
design, our content defines
our break points.
Remember, in adaptive design,
the height and width of the
device determined
our break point.
But in this case, our break
points are determined by the
content of our site and where
that breaks down.
Because, remember, in responsive
design, our goal is
to create a seamless design
experience across a variety of
different contexts.
So where our site design breaks
down, that's where we
want to make sure
we optimize it.
So back to our demo site, The
Nautilus Bar and Restaurant.
As we look at our site we can
see that at around 870 pixels
our site gets a little
crammed up at the top
in our header section.
So this is going to be our first
break point where we
realize a need to optimize
the design for
this view port size.
So here's how we're going
to go about that.
We're going to use the same
formatting for our media query
as we discussed before, and
we're going to set our max
width at 870 pixels.
I'm just going to give you a
couple of examples in our CSS
about what we want
to change here.
I'm not necessarily going to
go over all of the changes,
but what you need to remember
is that for any media query
that you're inputting into your
site, everything that you
want changed needs to be within
that media query.
So, for instance, if you want
to clear a float you need to
make sure that you actually
define that in your media
query, otherwise it's just going
to inherit the property
that was in your original
styles.
So what we've done in this case
is we're actually going
to use a new logo image, and
we're going to move all of our
location information beneath
that logo image.
So you can see the styles
that we've used to
achieve that here.
And here's what it looks
like in the browser.
So, as you can see, we've moved
everything underneath
our logo, we've flushed or
information left and right,
and this is a great optimal
design for that break point,
which we talked about earlier.
Now we also see another issue
at about 768 pixels.
At this point our menu items
start to get a little too
skinny, and the text becomes
hard to read.
So this would be another good
place to set a break point.
Now, we've let our content
define where our break points
are, but it's also a good point
to notice here that's
768 pixels is a standard width
for tablet devices.
So, yes, you want to have your
content drive the break points
for your site, but it's also a
good idea to keep in mind some
of the devices that you have.
In order to optimize
for those as well.
So as you can see from our
styles here, what we're
changing is we're actually going
to stack our menu items
on top of each other similar to
what we did in our mobile
environment.
We're going to clear some
floats, and we're going to
stretch the width across
the view port.
So, as you can see, instead of
those being skinny and floated
to the left and right of each
other, we've got them stacked,
the width stretches across the
view port, and this is much
easier to read now.
Finally, we see another issue
happening at about 510 pixels
where the contact information
starts to break below the
location information.
So we could set another break
point here, but if you
remember back to our adaptive
level, we actually have
already set our mobile
styles with a media
query at 480 pixels.
And, once again, since this
site is built on a fluid
foundation, our site can
scale appropriately.
So instead of declaring a whole
other media query, and
having more and more styles
put in there, why not just
move our media query up from
480 pixels to 510 pixels.
So, in this case, at 510 pixels
our site is going to
break into those mobile styles,
it's going to clear up
that issue that we saw, and it's
also going to optimize
for those device sizes.
All right, so we're going
to start at our
desktop view port size.
And what I'm going to do is
scale the browser down.
And as you can see, at those
break points that we defined,
the site design changes.
So instead of our site breaking,
we actually have our
site being optimized for these
break point sizes.
And we can get all the way down
to a mobile environment.
So from a mobile environment
all the way up to a desktop
environment, our site design
it's optimized for the user.
Now, nobody's going to sit here
and scale their browser
up and down, except if you're
a designer or a developer.
So our goal here is not
necessarily to create a design
that works when you scale your
browser size up and down, the
point is that at each of those
sizes the site design works.
So if a user is accessing a
site on a mobile device, on
a tablet device, on a small
laptop, on a large laptop, on
a large monitor, the site design
is going to look great
and it's going to be optimized
for the user experience.
Finally, we're going to take
a quick look at some of the
other options that we can
include in our media queries.
So here are a few charts from
Ethan Marcotte's book on
responsive web design, and
it shows you a number of
different options that you can
incorporate into your media
queries besides just min
width and max width.
So let's look at one of
these as an example.
So if we go back to our demo
site, here are some
screenshots of the site both
in portrait mode and in
landscape mode.
Now, we've already optimized
the design with our media
queries, but what if we actually
wanted to call
specific device orientation.
So what if we wanted to have
specific styles, if the site
was in portrait mode, or the
site was in landscape mode?
Well, we can actually do that by
incorporating those values
into our media queries like
you can see here.
So instead of min width or max
width, what it becomes is
orientation portrait or
orientation landscape,
depending on what you
want to target.
The bottom line is, by using
media queries it gives us a
ton of flexibility in how we
design our sites, and how our
sites are optimized for a number
of different contexts,
and a number of different
devices.
Now it's time for you to work
on some challenges.
Good luck with those.
And we'll jump into
the next level.