[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Journey into
Mobile, and this is Level
Five, Responsive Media.
In this level, we're going to
look at responsive images and
retina images.
Let's first get started with
responsive images.
Now up until this point, the
images in our layouts have
been fixed width.
And this is an OK solution, but
it's not great if we want
to create responsive,
scalable sites.
What we want to do is actually
have our images be able to
scale with the viewport size,
just like all of the rest of
our content.
So how do we do that?
Well, there's really a two
step process here.
The first is we want to actually
save out an image
that is larger than
we actually need.
For instance in our Nautilus
Restaurant site, we have this
image, which is actually 640
pixels by 490 pixels.
Now, chances are we won't ever
actually need that image at
that size in our site, but what
we can do is if we save
it out larger, we can scale
it down as necessary.
And the way that we do that is
we're actually going to add a
max-width property to our image
element in our CSS.
And basically what this says is
if we have a set width for
our image, it tells the browser
to fill that set width
with 100% of the image.
So even if the image container
is smaller than the total size
of the image, we still get
the full resolution
image in that container.
I've already added the max-width
property up at the
top of my CSS styles to my image
element, but now what I
want to do is I want to call
the specific image in the
about section.
As you can see, this specific
image has a width of 29.6875%.
So that means that the
containing element is going to
scale, and as a result the image
is going to scale because
of the max-width property.
So let me go into the browser
and actually show
you how this works.
Alright, so if we look at our
Nautilus Restaurant site, I
want you to pay attention to the
image in the lower left.
Now notice as I expand and
contract the browser window,
the image also scales.
This is because we've
incorporated our max-width
property into our CSS and saved
out a larger image than
we actually need.
So as we get smaller and to a
mobile environment, we can
optimize the image for that
context, but then also we can
optimize the image as
we get into larger
environments, as well.
So not only can you do this with
images, you can actually
do this with any types of media,
and that can include
video, for instance.
So if you have a video embed in
your HTML, you can actually
cause that to be responsive so
that as your site scales, the
video element can
scale as well.
Now just like practically
everything else, there really
is no IE6 support for this.
So if you absolutely have to
support IE6 in your designs,
check out this link and it gives
you a good idea of how
to achieve that.
Now prior to Windows 7, there
was poor support for the
max-width property, so if you
need to support browsers-- in
particular, Firefox 2 and IE7 on
devices that are lower than
Windows 7--
take a look at this link where
it teaches you how to use
AlphaImageLoader, which is
another solution to be able to
achieve this max-width property
on these devices and
in these browsers.
So that's how you scale images
and other types of media
responsively.
But if you're looking for more
robust options to do that,
here are a few alternatives
to look at.
Now, these are JavaScript
libraries that you can
incorporate into your sites
which give you more options as
it comes to making things
responsive.
Alright, so let's talk
about retina images.
Now with the new iPad that
recently came out and with
iPhone 4 and iPhone 4S, retina
images have become more of an
issue, because as you know,
retina screens have 1.5 to two
times the pixel density, which
means that if you save out a
normal image on a retina screen
it might look kind of
blurry or even pixelated.
And that's not good if you're
trying to optimize your
designs for a variety of devices
on the universal web.
So what do we do?
Do we double the image size?
Well, we could but that's not
a great solution, because
obviously you're talking about
larger images, larger
downloads, slower site speed.
We can actually use media
queries to target those
specific devices and optimizer
images for retina displays,
and here's how we
would do that.
In this media query, we're
targeting devices that have a
pixel density of at least 1.5.
Now the iPhone 4S, the 4, and
the new iPad had have pixel
densities of two, but some
Android devices have 1.5.
So what this is doing is saying
at least 1.5 and up, so
we can cover all of our bases.
And what we do is we would put
our styles within that media
query, including our retina
images, and here's how we
would do that.
Let's hypothetically say we have
a logo file, logo.png,
that has a size of 200 pixels.
So the idea here is that we
would want to actually double
this image size, so we would
save out a new logo file at
400 pixels.
And you can call it whatever you
want but a good practice
is to follow the iOS convention
for retina images
and that is the same name of
the file with an @2x before
the file extension.
So let's go back to our demo
site, the Nautilus Bar and
Restaurant, and let's look at
an example of how we can
actually apply this.
So as you can see in our
Map It button, we
have this map icon.
The original size of it is 12
pixels by 16 pixels, so what
we want to do is save out a new
image that is 24 pixels by
32 pixels-- it's double
the size--
and then we would actually put
that into our media query.
First, let's recall our
original CSS for this
particular file.
As you can see, we have a
logo.png, and we have it set
as a background image.
So if we plug this into our
media query, here's what it
would look like.
As you can see, we have our own
new file, the logo@2x.png,
but we've also included CSS3
background size property.
Now, why have we done this?
Well, if we don't do this, then
the browser is going to
serve up this new image
at its original size.
Basically, what we wanted
to do is keep the same
constraints as the original
image, the same size, just
double the pixel density
so that it looks
better on retina screens.
So by using the background size
property, we can tell the
browser what the original size
of the image was, but just
fill it with the better
optimized image.
And then as you can see in this
screen shot, our image
looks much better.
It's much clearer and crisper
than our original image was.
So this point, we've seen two
examples of how to make images
responsive.
We've talked about content
images and how to actually
scale those, and we've talked
about background images,
things like logos or like the
map icon that you saw.
But for both of those examples,
we still have to
worry about file size because
we can save out a bunch of
these very high resolution
photos that would look great
on, say, a retina screen, but
if you didn't have a retina
screen you'd have to download
these huge files and it would
look good, but it would just
work really slowly and
wouldn't be optimal.
So what do we do?
Well, Scott Jehl has created a
pretty novel concept called
PictureFill that really solves
this problem that we have.
And in this case, what we do is
we create a picture element
that's similar to the video
element in HTML5.
And what it does is it specifies
different image
sizes to be served by different
devices, depending
on if they're a retina device
or a nonretina device.
Let me show you how
this works.
So in this case, as you can see,
we have our picture tag,
and within that we have first
our regular image,
content-image.jpeg, that's going
to be used for generic
devices, nonretina devices.
Then we're also including a
larger image, one that can be
served up on retina devices that
has more pixel density.
But in this case, we're only
going to be serving that up
for devices that have a minimum
width of 800 pixels.
So once again, we're using that
media query concept where
we're only going to be serving
up that image if that device
has a min width of 800 pixels.
Now, the picture element
doesn't actually exist.
It's not part of
the HTML5 spec.
So what we have to do is include
picturefill.js in the
head of our HTML document.
And who knows, maybe someday
they'll actually adopt this to
be a part of the HTML5 spec
and we can use it
as much as we want.
Now what happens to those
users that don't have
JavaScript enabled?
Well, we can create a fallback
for those users.
We can include the same code
that we talked about before in
our picture element, but at the
bottom we can include our
regular image in
no script tags.
And basically what that means is
if the user has JavaScript
disabled, then we're just going
to serve up the regular
image to that device.
Congratulations, you've made
it through all the videos.
You still have some challenges
to complete, and after that be
sure to stay tuned for a wrap-up
video where I'll give
you some further resources to
help you learn more about
designing for the mobile web.
Thanks for taking the time.
I really appreciate it, and
we'll talk to you later.