[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Rails Testing
for Zombies, and this is level
two, where we're going to be
talking about model testing.
So we're going to take what you
know about unit testing
and figure out how to test our
Active Record models inside of
our Rails app.
When we run rails generate
scaffold inside of a Rails
app, it generates a bunch of
files for us, some of which
may be tests.
You can see here it generated
a test/unit/zombie_test.rb.
It also generated for us a
fixture, which we'll see later
on in this level.
If we open up the
zombie_test.rb, inside there
at the top, we'll see that
it requires test helper.
This is a configuration file.
Inside here, we can require
other testing libraries, we
can write custom methods that
all of our tests get access
to, and of course, we can write
configuration in here.
You can see it defined a zombie
test class, and did it
write any tests for us.
No.
Sorry, Rails doesn't write
your tests for you.
That would be amazing,
but it doesn't.
We need to write our
own model tests.
But before we get into that,
we're writing model tests.
Model tests run against
Active Record.
Active Record interfaces
with our database.
So we need to take a step back
and talk a little bit about
configuring a database
to do testing with.
If we look inside of our
database.yml file, we'll see
that there are three different
environments by default--
one of which is the
test environment.
This is only for testing.
So we need to make sure this
test database is d populated
with the right database
structure so we can test
against it.
How do we do that.
Well, there's a couple different
rake tasks we need
to be familiar with, starting
with rake db:test:prepare.
That's going to check to see if
there's any migrations we
need to run.
If there aren't any we need to
run, then it's going to simply
load the schema.rb file
into our test database.
A few other commands you
should know about.
The rake test command--
or just rake by default-- is
going to run db:test:prepare,
and then it's going to try
to run all of your tests.
To run an individual test file,
we would simply write
this in the command line.
You'll notice that we're using
the dash capital I again, to
specify our load path.
This is because at the top of
that test file, remember, it
requires test helper,
and that test helper
is in the test directory.
So we need to specify dash
capital I, test.
Just like so.
To run a single test case, we
simply run that same command
and then dash n and then
the name of the test.
So let's go ahead and create our
first model test already.
I'm pretty sure we're going to
want to put a validation on
the name field inside of our
Zombie class, so let's write
the test first before we write
the implementation.
So here we have a function
called
test_invalid_without_a_name.
Inside there, we create
a new zombie.
And then we're going to assert
that the zombie is not valid,
and specify a custom failure
message, "Name is not being
validated."
Now before we run the test, the
one thing you might have
noticed about ZombieTest
is that it inherits from
ActiveSupport::TestCase.
This is a class from Rails that
gives you access to a
bunch of helper methods.
One of the helper methods allows
you to write your test
definitions in a nicer form.
We can rewrite the test
definition to say test
"invalid without a name"
do, and include
the test in the block.
A little more readable.
Now let's run our test by
using the rake command.
And--
uh-oh.
Looks like we forgot
to run a migration.
So let's go back and
run that migration.
So rake db migrate.
Our database is migrated.
Now we can go ahead and run
rake again, and it fails.
Yay, it fails.
It was supposed to fail.
Don't worry.
Remember, the first step is to
write a test and make it fail.
So let's jump back now and
write our validation.
Here we are in our zombie.rb
file, and all we have to write
is validates :name,
presence :true.
If we run our tests
again, they pass.
Now that we've written a test to
ensure that our validation
fails if we don't have a name,
let's write a test to make
sure that if we have all the
properties on zombie that it
does pass-- that it is valid.
So we're going to test
"valid with all
attributes." We have a zombie.
We set the name.
We set the graveyard.
We're going to assert
that it's valid.
And if it errors out, we're
going to say "zombie was not
valid."
Now you may see a pattern
emerging.
Very often in our model test,
the first line is going to
start out by creating a new
zombie and setting fields over
and over and over again.
So how do we stop this
duplication.
Well this is where
fixtures come in.
Remember at the beginning of
the level when we ran the
Rails generate scaffold, it
created for us this fixture
file here--
Zombies.yml.
Inside there, by default, it
looks something like this.
We obviously want to customize
this a little bit more.
So we're going to do that and
specify a zombie named Ash and
a zombie named Tim.
Now instead of creating a new
zombie every time, we can just
do z equals zombies(:ash).
What this command is doing, is
it's actually pulling zombie
Ash out of the database into
an Active Record object and
setting that equal to
the z variable.
So how do fixtures
work exactly?
Well when you run your tests,
the first thing that happens
is that your Rails application
goes, grabs all the fixtures,
puts them all into the
test database.
Does that at the very
beginning when
you run your test.
Then when you run a test, if
anything gets changed there in
the database, at the end of
that individual test, any
changes get rolled back.
It's transactional
for each test.
Now we can take that command,
move it back into our test.
Let's go ahead and create
another test too, called
"invalid name games error
message." So here, we're going
to set name equal to nil, so
we're sort of resetting our
fixture, checking to see if it's
valid, and we're going to
assert that the /can't be blank/
validation message gets
put into the errors
hash properly.
And if not, it's going to give
the failure message "Presence
error not found on zombie."
Enough with validations.
Let's create a new method on
our zombie class using test
first development.
So we're going to say "can
generate avatar_url." We're
going to use our fixture
to get zombie(:ash).
Then we're going to assert that
this string gets returned
when we call z.avatar_url.
All right.
We have a test.
We would run the test.
Hopefully it would fail.
Then we're going to go back
into our model and let's
define that method.
So inside the zombie class,
we're going to have avatar_url
returns this string.
If we run it again, all of
our tests should pass.
What about testing model
relationships.
Because remember, we're building
Twitter for Zombies,
so our zombie has many tweets.
So one way we could test that,
is saying test "should respond
to tweets." We're going to have
an assert_respond_to.
So here, we're going to make
sure that our zombie Ash has a
method called tweets.
We can also test this by saying
that our zombie should
contain tweets.
So we get the zombie and then we
assert that z.tweets equals
two tweets.
Uh-oh.
We need tweets now.
We need tweets out
of the database.
So this might be a good chance
to go back and add some tweets
fixtures, which we can
use for this test.
Here inside the tweets fixture,
we're going to
declare two tweets.
We have Ash's first tweet
and Ash's second tweet.
You'll notice that each of
them has a zombie ID 1.
But if you remember back to our
zombie fixture, we never
declared any IDs.
So we're going to have to reopen
that zombie fixture,
and specify that Ash has an
ID of 1, and maybe Tim
has an ID of 2.
And that will get properly
set in our database.
Now if we call
zombies(:ash).tweets, it will
return all of Ash's tweets.
And that's basically the same
thing as creating an array
where we return both
of these fixtures.
So we go back to
our assertion.
We might say assert that this
array is equal to what gets
returned when we call
zombies(:ash).tweets.
However, this is kind
of a brittle test.
It's not so good.
Down the line, we might have
more tweets for Ash.
Things might get changed.
So how might we write this
test in a better way?
Instead, we could test that
zombie tweets should only
contain tweets that
belong to zombie.
We could do this by going
through all of Ash's tweets
and ensuring that they belong
to him by using that .all?
command.
So that's going to go through
each of them and make sure
that that conditional
is always true.
I know that was a
lot of content.
No shame if you want
to go back and
watch the video again.
But get ready.
Coming at you.
Rails model challenges.
Get to it.