[MUSIC PLAYING]
(SINGING) Yes the zombies
are back now, and
they're ready to test.
They'll take that development
curve and tear
it from your chest.
Refactor your mind, take a test
from red to green,
all with an undead theme.
You're watching Rails
Testing for Zombies.
And this is level three, where
we're going to be cleaning up
some of the code we wrote
in level two.
So let's get started.
Here's the code to where we
tested the tweets association,
and here's the code where we
tested the avatar_url method.
You may notice that
there's some
duplication going on here.
And if there's anything we like
doing as Ruby developers,
it's keeping it DRY.
We don't like repeating
ourselves.
So how might we refactor this so
we don't have to write z =
zombies(:ash) every time?
So let's move this line of code
up into a setup method.
This setup method, by default,
is going to get run
before every test.
In order to have this variable
accessible, we need to make it
an instance variable.
So we're going to add that @
symbol up at the top, and then
add that @ symbol in front
of the variable
wherever we use it.
Let's take a look at two more
tests that we might figure out
some way refactor.
Here we're testing that we have
an error message when
name is blank.
We also need another test for
the graveyard validation to
ensure that the graveyard
field can't be blank.
Again, there's a lot of
duplication going on here.
Each of these is testing if it's
valid and then testing to
see if the right error
message exists.
So let's refactor.
Let's take those two lines.
We're going to bring them up
into another method we're
going to call assert_presence.
It's going to have
two parameters--
model and field.
We're going to check to see
if the model is valid.
We're then going to get
all of the errors on
that specific field.
That will return an array.
We'll join that array together
to single string, which we'll
match against that regular
expression.
Then, we'll create a custom
failure message which says
Presence error for # not
found on #.
Then in our test, all we have
to do is call that method.
assert_presence for z and then
the name column, and then
assert_presence z and then
the graveyard column.
Sweet, we've refactored
this code.
But you may have noticed
something.
The way that we refactored this,
it would be nice to be
able to use this in other models
that also validate
presence and need to
test against that.
So instead of having it in the
zombie test, let's move it up
into the test_helper.
With this method in our
test_helper, we'll have access
to it from any of
our test files.
Now I want to introduce you to
our first external test gem
called Shoulda.
Shoulda makes tests easy on
the fingers and the eyes.
It will allow us to write less
code and get more done.
So in order to install it in
our Rails application, we
simply need to add a line
to our Gemfile.
We only want this gem to be
available in the test
environment.
That's why we have
group :test do.
To test one of our presence
validations with Shoulda,
instead of doing what we did a
minute ago, we can just write
a single line, should
validate_presence_of.
And then, we send in a symbol
which is the column names.
So inside of our zombie test,
we just write should
validate_presence_of(:name).
We might have should
validate_presence_of(:graveyard),
should ensure_length_of
(:name).is_at_most(15).
And these are all Shoulda
helper methods.
You can look up in the
documentation to get a list of
all of them.
But they all test exactly
what they say they test.
It should have_many(:tweets).
A couple other ones that
are really helpful--
should validate_uniqueness_of,
should ensure_length_of.
And you can chain on extra
methods like-- is_at_least(5);
is_at_most(20); should
validate_numercality_of, for a
column that has to be numeric;
should_not allow_value("blah")
for email; should allow_value,
for an email address; should
ensure_inclusion_of;
should_not
allow_mass_assignment_of,
because obviously, you don't
want to allow mass assignment
of the password field.
That would be bad; should
belong_to_zombie for the
relationship; and lastly, should
validate_acceptance_of,
in terms of service, in this
case for a Boolean field.
To get more information on
Shoulda and to look up the
documentation so you can
reference all of these
matchers I showed you a second
ago, be sure to check out the
link down below this video.
And that pretty much wraps
up a level three.
It was a short one because I
want you guys to get better at
writing tests, refactoring your
tests, and using Shoulda.
Good luck.