[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Rails
Testing for Zombies.
In this first level,
we're going to be
going over unit testing.
But before we do that, we need
to talk a little bit about
testing philosophy.
You could say there's four
different philosophies.
First is, of course,
no testing at all.
Not really a philosophy.
You just don't write
any tests.
But that's where everybody
starts, right.
The next phase is verification
testing.
This is where you're going to
write code and then write
tests that wrap around
your code.
The next step is test first.
This is what we're going to be
going through in this course,
where we write a test.
It's a failing test.
We then write enough code to
make the test pass, and then
we reflect and see if we need
to refactor that code.
Lastly--
what we're not going over
in this course--
is strict test driven design.
This is where you eventually
want to be.
And it's where your tests you
use to define the behavior are
almost the design of your
application, and that defines
how your application gets
developed and crafted.
So you might be wondering, what
exactly is unit testing.
Well when we say unit testing,
we're talking about testing
pieces of our application--
pieces of source--
in isolation from the rest
of the applications.
So you're going to end up with
lots of individual unit tests.
So when any one piece breaks,
you're going to know exactly
how to fix it, hopefully, which
makes your application a
lot easier to debug.
Also a lot of people think that
good unit tests lead to
good documentation.
If you're looking at somebody
else's code base and you need
to know how it works, well,
looking at the test might give
you a good hint.
Test::Unit was created in the
very early days of Ruby by
Nathaniel Talbot.
Now you might be wondering, why
are we doing Test::Unit
and not something like RSpec.
You may have heard of RSpec.
Well Test::Unit is a more
basic testing library.
It's also the testing library
that Rails uses by default.
So if you ever want to read
through the Rails source or
contribute back to Rails, you're
going to have to know
Test::Unit.
Test::Unit is also similar to
many other testing libraries
from many other languages, so
it'll be easier to learn if
you're coming from
another language.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at the basic structure of a
Test::Unit file.
The name of the file is probably
going to be the
subject you want to
test _test.rb.
Inside that file, you're
going to require
the test/unit library.
The test/unit library gets
included with Ruby by default.
It's not a gem you have to
install, so all we have to do
is require it.
Inside the test file, we declare
a class that has the
subject capitalized and then the
word "Test." This inherits
from Test::Unit::TestCase.
We then can write a bunch
of methods, which
are each of our tests.
So here we have test, and then
we specify what we are testing
with underscores.
Inside the test, the basic
building block is going to be
a assertion.
So this is what we are asserting
to be true or
asserting to match.
You see that test tube beaker
icon over there?
Throughout our entire
course, you're going
to see that a lot.
And that's to signify where the
assertion is inside each
of our tests.
Each test typically
has one assertion.
That's sort of a
best practice.
You'll see people sometimes
doing a lot of assertions per
test, but it's kind
of a bad practice.
Let's go ahead and write
really basic test.
We're going to call it
boolean_test.rb.
Inside the file, we're going
to require test/unit.
We call this BooleanTest.
Our first test is called
test_true_is_true.
We're going to send a single
parameter into the assert
method, and if that parameter
is true, then that test is
going to pass.
If the parameter is false,
obviously not going to pass.
So let's go ahead and run this
on the command line, ruby
boolean_test.
And here we see, the
test passed.
That little dot right there,
that's telling us that we had
one test, and the test passed.
If we have a bunch of tests,
we're going to
see a lot of dots.
If we change the parameter in
our assert method to "false"
here, and then we run it from
the command line, you're going
to see here that
our test fails.
We get that "f."
You might notice here that the
failure message isn't really
that helpful.
It's not very descriptive.
So sometimes in tests, we need
a way to specify a more
descriptive error message.
We can do that by simply sending
in a second parameter
to the assert method.
In this case, we're saying,
"true should be truthy." Then
if we run the test again, if it
fails, it's going to give
us that nice, descriptive
error message.
Let's jump into a
better example.
This time, we're going to extend
the string class to
give it some methods.
So we're going to start
test first--
writing the test.
So here, we're inside string
extension test.
There's our class.
Our first test is going
to be test_is_number.
So we're going to test
to see if that
string contains a number.
Normally with test first, we'd
only write one test at a time,
but for the sake of this
example, I'm going to write a
second one.
We're going to test to see if
the string is not a number.
So we wrote the tests.
Let's go ahead and run them.
And yes, they fail.
They error out, as
they should.
That's the first step
in test first.
We want to write
a failing test.
Now that we have failing tests,
we can go ahead and try
to implement the method.
To implement our code, we're
going to create a new file
called string_extension.
You can see these asserts
down here at the bottom.
I put them there so that you
can keep in mind what we're
trying to implement.
The first thing we're
going to do is open
up the String class.
Inside there, we're going to
define a is_number method.
We're going to check to
see if the current
string has all the numbers.
That's just a little
regular expression.
If it does, we're going to
return "true," otherwise we'll
return "false."
Before we run the test, we need
to go back into our test
file and include that string
extension, like so.
Once we do that, we
can run the test.
Now you'll notice here I'm
specifying dash capital I dot.
When we run the test manually
like this and we're acquiring
other files, we need to
specify the load path.
We need to specify where our
Ruby application can find the
other files that this
test requires.
So we do that here.
We then run the test.
You can see here, two tests were
run, and we made it pass.
Sweet.
So that's the second step when
we do test first development.
Our last step is going to
refactor our code if we can,
now that we have
passing tests.
And sure enough, you might have
already noticed, I can
simplify this to simply have
this single conditional
because it returns
true or false.
So we refactor it, then we can
go back and run our tests.
So here we are.
We ran our tests, and
they all still pass.
Now sometimes when we talk about
test first development,
we say "red, green, refactor."
Red, meaning
write a test that fails.
Green, meaning write enough code
to make those tests pass.
And then refactor, of course,
reflect back on our code and
see if we can improve it.
Let's walk through one more
example before you get to the
challenges.
We're going to create
a humanize method.
The humanize method eventually
is going to lowercase and
capitalize a string.
So inside of our string
extension test, we're going to
write a really basic test.
We're going to make sure that
the string class responds to
the humanize method.
We can use assert_respond_to.
So as you can see here, we're
sending in an object, and then
it's going to test to
make sure that it
has a humanize method.
Rather than defining the entire
function, we're just
going to write enough code
to make the test pass--
which in this case, is simply
defining the function.
We run the test,
and it passes.
Now we can write another test.
We're going to write
test_humanize_returns_something.
So here we're going to
say assert_not_nil.
We're asserting that
this method returns
something that isn't nil.
We're also going to give it an
optional error message so that
if it errors out, we
have a better idea
of what went wrong.
Then again, in our string
extension class, we write just
enough code to make it pass.
Let's go ahead and write
another test.
We're going to use assert_equal
this time.
Assert_equal takes
two parameters.
The first parameter is what we
expect to receive back from
the second parameter.
So as you can see here, we're
saying we expect to have this
string get returned.
And then the second parameter,
we actually call the humanize
method on a string.
And we want these two
to match, otherwise
the test will fail.
Now inside of our humanize
method, all we have to do is
call .downcase.capitalize.
Run our tests, and
now they pass.
Another test we could write
is test just for brains.
We're going to use the
assert_match assertion.
Here, it takes a regex as the
first parameter, and it tries
to match that regex against
the second parameter.
And if it matches,
it will pass--
which it does.
Our method is called humanize,
and we want to make sure
there's no zombies inside
of our humanize method.
So we're going to make sure that
a runtime error is raised
when we call humanize on a
string that contains the word
"zombie." If we run this test
right now, of course it's
going to fail.
That's good.
We want to make sure
that it fails.
Then of course, the second step,
we're going to add the
implementation.
So here, we're going to say, if
the string contains zombie,
raise a runtime error.
And if we run the tests at this
point, they all pass.
Test::Unit comes with a bunch
of different assertions.
Here's a couple of them.
We have assert--
which looks for conditional--
assert_equal, assert_not_equal,
assert_respond_to, assert_nil,
assert_not_nil, assert_match,
assert_no_match, assert_raise,
and assert_kind_of, if you
want to make sure an object
is a certain class.
If you need the error message
for each of these to be more
specific, they can all take an
additional parameter, which is
a string, and you can type in
exactly what you want the
error message to be.
You've reached the end of
Level One talking about
Test::Unit.
It's time to get your hands
dirty in the challenges.
Good luck.