[PLAYING MUSIC]
You're watching Rails Testing
for Zombies, and this is Level
Six, Using Factories.
Now, all throughout this course
we've been focused
mostly on fixtures when
we're trying to
load data for testing.
This level is all about
another alternative to
fixtures, which is
called factories.
So what is it that's so terrible
about fixtures?
Well, I mean, if you've been
around the Rails community
long enough, you probably heard
that fixtures are bad,
so let's look at maybe some of
the things that aren't so good
about them, although to this
point we do see that they do
their job well.
So one of the problems is that
associations are hard.
Greg showed this to you in some
of the earlier levels
where to create a zombie that
had tweets, we had to
reference that zombie as its
zombie ID from the tweet
fixture back to the zombie.
You could see that that could
get to be really difficult
when you start to get
a lot of fixtures or
a lot of test cases.
You'll quickly learn that your
fixtures file exponentially
grow with edge cases, because
you might want a zombie with a
name or a zombie with a certain
name or a zombie with
a certain graveyard, and
so it multiplies out.
And finally, you'll find that
they really do repeat a lot--
it's a lot of this is my zombie,
this is his name, this
is his graveyard, this is my
zombie, this is his name, this
is his graveyard, and factories
really try to kind
of appease all of
these issues.
So in this level, we're going
to talk about Factory Girl,
which is another external gem.
This one's written by thoughtbot
that you can use to
implement the factory pattern.
So what Factory Girl does is it
allows you to define valid
model attributes, it allows you
to easily modify them at
run time or at test time, and
it allows you to inherit and
modify attributes and
configurations
between your factories.
So how do we install it?
Well, just like everything else
we go to the Gemfile.
In this case, you're going to
notice that I'm actually
grouping the Factory Girl gem
into development and test
groups, not just test alone.
And you'll also notice that
instead of using the Factory
Girl gem, which is kind of the
generic, I'm using
factory_girl_rails.
So what this does is it allows
Rails to add hooks to
automatically generate our
factory files for us when we
do things like run the Rails
generator for a model.
So let's see what running
that model
generator might look like.
So here, we'll say rails
generate model zombie.
On the command line, we'll go
ahead and say that a zombie
has a name and a graveyard,
both of which are strings.
And if you look closely in the
generator, you'll see that it
actually invokes Factory Girl,
and it will create a new file
for you at
test/factories/zombies.
It's the pluralized form
of the model name
that you gave it.
What does that zombies factory
file look like?
By default, it's going to look
something like this.
It's going to say
FactoryGirl.define--
so Factory Girl, name
of the gem--
and that block that it takes is
basically saying inside of
here, I want to define
some factories.
And inside of this, we actually
have a DSL written by
thoughtbot that is purely
about these factories.
So here it's going to say I have
a factory called zombie,
it's going to default to the
model name that we used
earlier, and it's going to say,
oh, since we defined some
attributes of the command line,
it's going to go ahead
and put those in for
us just like it did
with fixtures earlier.
So you're going to see name,
MyString, graveyard,
MyString again, because
we defined
them as strings earlier.
And let's just quickly look back
at how this might relate
to the earlier fixture file
that was automatically
generated by Rails before.
I should also note here that
because we're using the hooks
for Factory Girl, it's actually
not going to generate
the fixtures for us anymore
but rather generate the
factories instead.
So let's look at
the two files.
So on the left hand side,
you see we've got
test/fixtures/zombies.yml,
that's the .yml file.
In this case we've Ash, name,
Ash, graveyard, Oak Park, and
to the right of that you see our
factory definition file,
which is located in
test/factories/zombies.
So it's in factories rather
than fixtures, it's a Ruby
file rather a .yml file, and
it's pluralized just like the
fixture was before.
So here you've got
FactoryGirl.define do, factory
zombie, so we're creating a
factory called zombie, and
here I've dictated that the name
is Ash and the graveyard
is Oak Park.
And then how do we actually
use this in our tests?
So whereas before we would say
zombies in all lowercase and
pluralized and pass it an
attribute that matched the
name that we defined earlier, in
this case Ash, when we use
a factory we can just
say, Factory(:zombie)
We want to say basically
factory, give us
a new zombie, right?
So it looks like that.
Let's look a little bit
at this factory method
that we used here.
So it's a little bit weird
because it's a method that is
capitalized as if it were a
class name or a module but
it's taking a parameter, which
is the factory that we want to
instantiate.
That actually equates to
FactoryGirl.create with the
same factory name.
So it's just kind of a shortcut
to make writing our
tests a little bit easier if
what we want to do is create.
And I say if what we want to do
is create, because Factory
Girl actually gives us a few
different options of what we
might want to do with
our factories.
So the first one we've
discussed is
FactoryGirl.create and what
that's going to do is going to
create and instantiate a new
zombie, give it the attributes
that we've defined, save it to
the database, and then give us
back that saved zombie.
So what that boils down to is
Factory Girl, take this action
and perform it on
this factory.
The other actions that we can
take are FactoryGirl.build,
where it will create a new
zombie, load it with
attributes but not save it, and
also not validate it, or
you could do
FactoryGirl.attributes_for
this particular factory.
And rather than returning a
zombie instance, it's simply
going to return you a hash of
attributes that make up a
valid zombie.
Let's look back at fixtures
real quick just to compare
again some of the differences as
these things start to grow.
So over here you see a fixture
file with zombies in it.
In this case, I've got
three zombies--
I've got Ash in Oak
Park, Bill in Oak
Park, and Mike in Sunnyvale.
How could we do this
as a factory?
Well, in our factory file we
would do FactoryGirl.define,
factory zombie, so it's a
generic zombie factory.
I'm going to say that my generic
zombie is always
called Ash and I'm going to say
that my generic some is
always in Oak Park.
I could then define
an inherited
factory underneath that--
in this case, I'll call it
zombie_bill just so has a
different name, and I'm
going to override
the name to be Bill.
So what it's going to do is it's
going to take the parent
one, which is zombie, it's
going to load those
attributes, and it's going to
override with anything that
I've specifically defined.
So in this case, name will get
overridden as Bill, but I'm
going to take in graveyard
Oak Park from the parent.
And in the case of Mike where
both values are different, I
can still define it as a child
of the original zombie
factory, but I'm just going
to override both
values in this case.
So let's look a little bit
at how to actually
interact with a factory.
Let's say, for example, that we
have a zombie class where
we do some validation,
which Gregg actually
talked about earlier.
So we're validating the presence
of name and we're
validating the presence of
graveyard, in this case.
So let's say we're writing a
test, and in that test we're
going to say we want a couple
of zombies, for example.
Maybe we want to test to make
sure one zombie doesn't equal
another zombie.
So we might say zombie_1
equals factory zombie.
So that's going to use the
default zombie factory, it's
going to create us a zombie
named Ash in Oak Park, and
it's going to store that
onto zombie_1.
Maybe in that same test we say
we need our second zombie, so
I'm going to say zombie_2
equals factory, give me
another zombie.
Well, the factory is
going to say, OK.
Well, name is Ash, graveyard
is Oak Park.
If you look closely up to the
validations at the top you see
we also have a uniqueness
constraint.
So in this case when we call
the factory, it's going to
instantiate a zombie with a name
Ash and a graveyard of
Oak Park, but this time when
it goes to save it to the
database before returning it to
us, it's going to throw an
exception and explode.
In this case, we get an
ActiveRecord::RecordInvalid,
because we've got the uniqueness
constraint on name.
We already created a zombie
with the name of Ash,
validations fail.
So how do we make this work?
Let's say you have a test
that you do need
both of those to load.
How do you get around
the validations?
Well, if you remember earlier
we actually defined two or
three factories where we
had different names.
That would get around
the validation.
So one option here is to rewrite
zombie_ 2 equals
factory zombie as zombie_2
equals factory zombie_bill.
What that's going to do is use
the other factory with a
different name that's basically
to sidestep the
validation and everything
will work.
The downside there is that we're
now no longer better
than fixtures, because if we
have to define a new factory
every time we need a variation
it's basically fixtures again.
So how else could we have
solved this problem?
Well, Factory Girl actually
allows you to override
attributes at run time as I
mentioned at the beginning.
So we could say zombie_2 equals
factory zombie
name: 'Ash1'.
We happen to know the first one
was named Ash, so in our
test we can just say, I need a
new one after that one and I'm
going to call it Ash1.
That'll do it, and that's great,
but there's actually an
even better way to go,
which Factory Girl
gives us, called sequences.
Sequences allow us to generate
unique information based on
the number of times that
information was called.
So over here in this definition,
you can see
FactoryGirl.define do, factory zombie
do, and now I have a
sequence name, so I'm calling
the sequence method and the
attribute that I want the
sequence to run on and be
applied to, and I'm passing
it a block.
The block takes one argument,
which is a numeric, and that
block represents the number
of times that
sequence has been called.
So if I call the zombie factory
one time, that'll be a
number one.
If I call it five times,
it'll be a number
five, ten times, ten.
So in this case, I'm just
taking that numeric and
applying it directly to the
string, so I'm guaranteed a
unique name--
Ash1, Ash2, Ash3.
So getting back to the example
that started this, we might
have a test that says zombie_1
equals factory zombie.
Great, we get our
zombie Ash back.
And now we could say, zombie_2
equals factory zombie.
You'll notice that the two names
are different and both
of them are saved and no
exceptions were thrown.
That means that we could
do something like this.
We could say, in this test we
need 1,000 zombies, so we'll
say 1,000 times give me a
zombie, which will create a
new saved zombie each
one of those times.
So you're going to see zombie_1,
Ash1, zombie_2,
Ash2, zombie_3, Ash3, four,
five, six, up to 1,000.
And that means we now have
a zombie factory.
So now that we've seen how to
make a zombie with a factory,
let's look at a case where we
need to make an association.
So in this case, we're going
to introduce a weapon model
and say a weapon must always
belong to a zombie.
So we have a belongs_to
zombie and
validates presence of zombie.
So in theory, a weapon can't
exist without a zombie.
How would you define
that factory?
Well, you might do something
like this.
So in our
test/factories/weapon.rb, we
would define a new
weapon factory.
Let's say this weapon
is a broadsword.
We're going to say association
zombie, and what that's going
to do is that Factory Girl is
actually going to look at our
weapon class.
It's going to see that we have
an association named zombie,
so it's going to say
OK, I know where to
apply this zombie to.
Factory Girl is also going to
look into itself and say there
is a zombie already defined as
a factory that I can use.
So in your weapon factory, you
say association zombie, it
knows what the local method is
on the weapon, and it knows
what the factory is to
create that zombie.
So now whenever we just say
weapon equals factory weapon,
we not only get a weapon but we
also get a zombie that it
belongs to.
The idea behind factories as
that they're always valid when
you call them.
So now let's look at another
case, still with associations
but this time let's look at it
from the zombie's perspective.
So you can see we've got class
zombie has one weapon.
So we've restricted zombies to
only having one weapon, but we
haven't required them to have
a weapon, so a zombie may or
may not have one.
They're valid without one and
that's perfectly fine.
So how might you dictate a
factory where, let's say, we
need for a particular test
a zombie with a weapon?
So what we might do is open our
definition and we might
make a high level factory called
armed zombie, in this
case, because in theory I might
have already defined a
zombie factory.
So here we've got our armed
zombie, sequence name, we get
the unique name, association
weapon, which we just learned
about before.
So whenever we create a zombie,
it will automatically
have a weapon.
It's got a graveyard
of Oak Park.
That's great, except that if you
actually try to use this
it's going to explode, and it's
going to explode because
Factory Girl doesn't
know anything
about an armed zombie.
Because this factory is defined
at the top level,
there is no parent
to this factory.
It's just going to take
the name and try to
turn it into a constant.
So it's going to say OK,
you want a factory
called armed_zombie?
I'm going to assume you have
an ArmedZombie class.
That's not going to work in this
case, so how do we get
around that?
Well, factories actually
take parameters.
They're optional.
In this case we could
say, class zombie.
And so what that's going to say
is, Factory Girl's going
to say, you need an armed
zombie, I know how to make an
armed zombie and I know what
class represents and armed
zombie and everything
will be great.
Or better yet, since we had
already defined a zombie
factory, we could just define
an armed zombie as a
subfactory to the original one
and it will just inherit the
inferred name from the parent.
And even better, we might say
well, for this particular
factory, we don't just want the
generic weapon, which if
you remember back was
a broadsword.
Maybe for this particular
factory all of these zombies
have hatchets, and so we can
say association, weapon,
factory, hatchet.
So how do factories actually
look in tests?
We've seen how they operate,
we've seen how to define them,
let's see how to actually
use them.
So here's a test that we might
have written earlier at the
unit level.
So in this case we are loading a
zombie from the fixtures, we
are decapitating the zombie, and
we are asserting that his
status is now dead again.
It's fine, it's a perfectly
good test.
There's a couple of issues here,
though, in that one,
we're still using fixtures, but
two, we don't know what
the status was necessarily
before we called decapitate.
So this test could be passing,
because maybe the fixture
actually defined his status as
dead again-- decapitate didn't
actually do anything, and here
we are, a passing test that
didn't actually test anything.
So maybe to get around that you
had a particular fixture
called not dead again zombie.
Maybe the status was dead
in the fixture.
So in this case, you're kind
of saying I know that it
wasn't dead again
to start with.
I'm asserting that after
decapitate it's dead again.
That's a better test,
but you can see we
now have new fixtures.
So using factories, we might
actually just say zombie
equals FactoryGirl.build
zombie.
In this case, I used build
instead of create because I
don't actually care if it's
saved, but we're running into
the original issue of we don't
explicitly know what the
status was before decapitate
was called.
So we might get around that by
just doing a run time setting
and saying status is dead when
I create you, I'm going to
decapitate you, I'm
going to make sure
you're dead again after.
So now that we've seen what it
looks like at unit level,
let's take a look at an
integration test.
So here's something that we kind
of saw a little bit of
earlier, so we're going to
test that navigation is
available to the zombie page.
We are going to load a zombie
from the fixtures, we're going
to load a tweet for that zombie
from the fixtures,
we're going to visit the root
URL-- again, we're using
Capybara here--
and we're going to say within a
particular area of the page
we want to make sure there is a
link to the zombie and that
when I click on that link, I end
up on the zombie's page.
So using factories, we
could say zombie
equals factory zombie.
We could say tweet equals
factory tweet.
In this case, you can see I
actually passed the zombie
into the tweet, and that's
because the tweet factory, in
all likelihood, has an
association to a zombie
already and if I just said
factory tweet, it's actually
going to create a new tweet with
a new zombie that isn't
the same one that
I just created.
So in this case, I pass in the
zombie that I've already
created so it overrides that
autocreation, and now I have a
zombie, a tweet, and everything
else stays the same.
Even better than that, I could
actually just say tweet equals
factory tweet knowing that it
would create a tweet and a
zombie for that tweet, and then
I could just say zombie
equals tweet.zombie.
I only called a factory once, I
happen to know that it will
automatically create the
association for me.
Everything else stays
the same.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Congratulations, you've made
to the end of all of the
videos for this course, and
you now know how to make a
zombie factory, and we're
actually going to test you on
that right now.
But please stay tuned because at
the end of your challenges,
we're going to have a wrap up
video to tell you where you
can go to learn more.