[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Rails Testing
for Zombies, and this is level
four where we're going to be
talking about mocks and stubs.
So you remember back with Rails
for Zombies 2, we talked
about a zombie having one weapon
or has_one weapon.
We're going to create a method
in there called "decapitate,"
which calls into that weapon
call slice, sends in the
zombie to get its head sliced
off, and then sets the status
of the zombie to "dead again."
The test for this might look
something like this, where we
have "decapitate should set
status to dead again." We're
calling the decapitate method
and then asserting equal "dead
again" to zombie status.
Pretty straightforward.
However, this test
is not very good.
Why is that?
Because that slice method
on weapon--
well, that could be
pretty complex.
We don't know what's
going on in there.
It might have 10 steps in there
that might fail, and
then our test here fails, when
all it's trying to test is
that the status is
getting set.
So we almost need a way here so
that we can test just that
that status is getting set
without having to change our
source code.
So take a look here.
We have these two
objects, right.
So we have the decapitate method
inside zombie that
calls the slice method
inside weapon.
But we almost need a way to
make it so that that slice
method doesn't get run--
or that it's sort of faked
out in some way.
We need to fake that call.
In order to do that, we need
to introduce a new external
library called mocha.
Mocha is a library for
mocking and stubbing.
To include it in our
application, we need to once
again modify the gem file.
Of course, don't forget once you
modify the gem file, you
need to run bundle.
Then we can start writing
stubs and mocks.
But what are stubs and mocks.
Well a stub is for replacing a
method with code that returns
a specified result--
so sort of faking
out a method.
And mocks are basically a stub
with an assertion hidden
inside of it to make sure the
method actually gets called.
These two concepts are really
hard to understand, especially
if you're hearing about them
for the first time.
So I'm going to try to repeat
myself a couple times.
If you have to watch the video a
few times, don't be ashamed.
Just do it.
These are hard concepts
to understand.
So back over in our example, we
need a way so that when our
decapitate method gets called
and it calls out to slice, we
need a way to sort of fake out
that method and have it just
return nothing, have
it return nil.
To do that, all we need to do
is call weapon.stub(:slice).
So we're stubbing out the
slice method inside this
instance of weapon.
So let's move this back
into our test.
So here's our test method again,
"decapitate should set
status to dead again."
We stub out the slice
method for this test.
We call the decapitate method,
and we assert that the zombie
status is "dead again." So now
our test is much better.
We're faking out that
slice method call.
It's just returning nil.
The status is getting set,
and we're testing for it.
That's great.
But we almost need another test
here for this method.
Not only do we need to test that
the status gets changed,
but we also should test
that that slice
method itself gets called.
OK, so how would we do that.
Well here we are,
back over here.
We need to stub out the slice
method, but we also need to
make sure it gets called.
That's where mock comes in.
So here, we're going to say
zombie.weapon.expects(:slice).
That's going to mock out the
slice method, and it's also
going to assert that the method
itself gets called.
We move this back into
our test, we call
weapon.expects(:slice),
and then we call
the decapitate method.
Notice here we don't have an
assert method, but we do have
that little beaker there to show
you that there's kind of
an assert going on
under the covers.
It's checking to see that that
slice method gets called.
And if it doesn't get called,
it's going to fail our test.
Now let's take a look at another
example where we might
need a mock and a stub.
So inside of our zombie class,
we have a geolocate method.
There, we call an external
service.
We'll call it "Zoogle." It
has a graveyard locator.
We send in the graveyard
and we get back a
latitude and longitude.
So how might we test this.
We might test that geolocate
calls the
Zoogle graveyard locator.
All we want to do is test
that the graveyard
locator gets called.
So we say Zoogle.expects(:
graveyard_locator).
Then we invoke the method.
We also might want to test the
proper parameter gets sent
into this method, so we can say
with(@zombie.graveyard).
This is going to stub the method
and add an assertion to
make sure that the graveyard
locator method gets called
with the correct parameters.
Now let's mix it up a bit and
make that geolocate method a
little bit harder to test.
This time, that external service
is going to return a
hash, which we're going to
combine into a string.
So if you take a look back at
our test code down here,
you're going to notice that our
mock is going to need to
return a value, otherwise
it's going to error out.
Otherwise, that method
won't work.
To do that, we simply need to
chain another method and call
returns, and specify what hash
we want it to return.
With this, our tests now pass.
However, with the new complexity
in our geolocate
method, we now have two things
we need to test.
We need to test that the
external service gets called,
but we also need to test that
the proper latitude and
longitude string gets
put together.
So how would we write
that test.
Well we were using
a mock before.
Now we need a stub.
We need to stub out that
external method call and test
that the proper string
gets created.
Let's try that.
So here we have our stub and
then we'll say assert_equal
"2, 3" when we call geolocate.
Before we go to the challenges,
we're going to
make it even more difficult
to test.
So let's revise geolocate
one more time.
This time, we're going to
get back an object--
a location object--
and we're going to use
that location object
to create that string.
And you see we're calling
loc.latitude and
loc.longitude.
So how might we test that.
We're not just talking about
a single hash anymore.
It's almost like what we need
to do is create an object--
an object that has a latitude
method and a longitude method
that just return numbers.
To test this, we can use
the stub command.
With the stub command,
we send in a hash.
Each of those keys inside those
hash are turned into
methods, which return
the key value.
So it's a lot like what
you see above.
We'll then make the graveyard
locator method return that
stub object.
And then we just need to assert
that the proper string
is created.
All right.
That was a lot of information,
mocks and stubs.
It's not simple things,
even for a zombie.
So now it's time for you to get
into the challenges and
get your hands dirty with
some mocks and stubs.
Good luck.