[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching Rails
Testing for Zombies.
I'm Nathaniel Bibler,
and this is Level
Five, Integration Testing.
Greg just walked you through the
first few levels talking
about unit testing and isolation
testing, and the
problem there is that when
you're testing little pieces
it's hard to tell if the
whole thing works.
That's where integration
testing comes in.
So let's get started.
Integration testing tests your
full application stack.
Now in a Rails context, that
generally means from the rack
level down into Rails
and then back out.
It could be said that it tests
from the outside in.
It could also be called
black box testing.
It's basically testing what the
end user's going to see
and how your application
is going to respond.
Now it should be noted here that
integration tests don't
actually spin up your entire
server stack, so if you need
to test something like Nginx
or a caching layer or
something else, this isn't quite
the place to do that.
So if you've ever done any Rails
development in the past
or ever used the scaffold in
the past, you might have
noticed that Rails will actually
generate controller
and view tests for you
automatically just like they
do with the model tests.
Why are we talking about
the controller
and view tests here?
Why did we jump straight
from unit tests
into integration tests?
And the reasoning there is that
views and controllers
really shouldn't have logic to
them, and in the case that
maybe they do, those should be
isolated tests which aren't
considered integration tests.
Integration tests should
ultimately completely have you
covered because they test your
full stack, they're going to
touch the view, the controller,
your business
objects, and back out.
There are some people out there
that do test their full
application at every level,
isolating the view,
controller, model and
then having a
full integration stack.
At Envy Labs, we've found that
we can pretty much get by with
testing our models in isolation
and then having a
full integration suite
on top of it.
Now let's talk about some of
the things that Rails gives
you to help you with your
integration tests.
First of all, it gives you web
browserish-like queries to be
able to actually call into your
application, acting like
the end users' web browser.
You'll see that these are really
low level calls, such
as get, post, put, and delete.
These aren't clicking on links,
these aren't filling
out a form, right.
These are very, very low level,
and what they do is
they send a request and they
get back a response, and at
that point, your tests
are against
those particular responses.
So because these are very low
level requests, it's not going
to do things like follow
redirects for you.
So, Rails also gives you
some other helpers like
follow_redirect, where it will
look to see if the last
response was a redirect
response, follow that
redirect, make a get request to
whatever the location is,
and let you continue
with your testing.
I should also note here that if
you call follow_redirect or
any of the other redirect
helpers that Rails provides
and the last response wasn't a
redirect, it's going to throw
an exception.
So now that we've seen how to
act like a web browser and
kind of make those external
calls into your application,
we need to come back again
to assertions.
You know, we saw that Ruby
gives you some level of
assertions.
We saw that Rails adds some
extra assertions to that at
the modeling unit level, but
at the integration level,
Rails gives you even more
custom assertions, such
assert_response.
And again, this is going to
look at your last response
coming in and assert_response
is going to check the status
code of that response.
So in this case, we're checking
that the last
response was a success,
which equates to 200.
So you could either use the
success symbol or you could
use the numeric 200 and
get the same result.
Rails also provides you a few
other helpers for the
assert_response such as
redirect, missing, or error
where it will check for a three
anything response, a 404
in the case of missing, or a
five anything response for a
server error.
Rails also gives you access
to all of the rack defined
symbols that represent status
code, such as move permanently
with HTTP 301, or accepted
with 202.
So along with assert_response,
Rails also gives us
assert_redirected_to.
What that's going to do is check
that the last response
is a redirect and it's going
to test that the location
header in that response
is what we expected--
in theory, that the end users'
web browser is going to go
where we think it's
going to go.
It also gives you assert_tag,
where you can test against the
contents of the DOM returned.
So what it's going to do is
look at the last response,
look at the body, make sure that
it's an HTML document,
and then you can basically
define what elements you're
looking for.
So in this case, maybe we're
looking for an anchor tag that
has an href to the root URL.
We could also conversely say it
does not have a tag, so we
could say it doesn't have a
div with an ID of zombie.
Rails also gives us the
assert_select, where unlike
the tag assertions where we talk
about DOM elements like a
and div, we can use
a CSS selector.
And it actually takes an
optional parameter after that
where we can even specify the
content that we're looking for
in that particular element.
So how do we actually create
an integration test?
Well, Rails actually has an
integration test generator
that can be used like this.
You can say Rails generate
integration_test and
then give it a name.
That name can be anything you
want, it doesn't have to match
a model that exists, it doesn't
have to match anything.
In this case, we're saying
zombies so that's going to
create an integration test
called zombies_test, and
inside it it's going to make
a new class, zombies_test.
When it gets run, you're going
to see it creates a test
integration zombies_test file.
At the top, you're going to see
the require test_helper,
which is what we saw in the
models, and then you're going
to see class ZombiesTest.
But in this case, you're going
to see that it's inheriting
from ActionDispatch
IntegrationTest, whereas
before it was coming from Active
Support Test Case.
And then you're also going to
see fixtures all, which is a
call to tell Rails to load
all of the fixtures.
But again, Rails isn't actually
going to generate any
tests for us, there's just going
to put in a stub to tell
us where they want us to put the
test and it's up to us to
define them.
So let's write our first
integration test.
To do so, we're probably going
to have to know a little bit
about the response coming back
because we want to know what
we're going to say
is happening.
So over here, you can see what
the response might look like
for the Zombie Show page.
And in this case, what's
important is that we're
showing a page for Ash, and
we're dictating that by saying
in the header the zombie's
name-- in this case, Ash--
is present.
So how do we test or something
like that?
Back in our zombies_test
integration test file, we're
going to add a new test that
says anyone can view zombie
information.
And what we're going to do here
is load a zombie from the
fixture, we're going to get
the zombie URL for that
particular zombie, and then
we're going to assert that
response was successful.
This will give us an early
indication if we have a typo
on the view page, a typo in the
controller, or some other
blatant issue here where we
would see a 500 response.
Next, we're going to
call assert_select.
We're going to look for the h1
element, and we're going to
test that the contents of it are
Ash, in this case, which
is what we're looking for.
I should note here that unlike
earlier when Greg taught us
that you should generally have
one assertion per test, you're
seeing that we're doing two.
The reason for that is because
now that we're at
integration test, it takes a
little bit longer to run down
the entire stack and make the
fake request and check the
response, so it's a little bit
of a tradeoff between time to
run the test versus what
we're testing.
I should also note that because
we have two assertions
in one test, if the first
assertion fails, we're not
going to have any clue as to
whether or not the second
assertion passes or fails.
That's the benefit
of splitting it
into separate tests.
Now that we've seen what Rails
gives us to aid with
integration testing, you've
probably noticed that there
could be some issues with it.
You know, how do you navigate
multiple pages?
Do you make 30 get requests?
How do you exercise
forms and buttons?
We haven't even talked
about that yet.
And at the end of the day,
wouldn't it be better if it
acted more like a web browser
where it followed redirects
automatically and kind
of handled some of
those things for us?
So I want to introduce you to
Capybara, which is going to be
another external gem.
It was written by Jonas
Nicholas, and it simulates
user activity and the
user's browser.
And with it, you could do things
like visit login_path,
so this is different
from the get, put,
post that we saw earlier.
You can say within a particular
element on the page
we would like to fill in the
login field with a value, we'd
like to fill in the password
with another value, maybe we'd
like to check a remember me
button, and we'd like to click
on a login button.
And unlike the original Rails
integration tests, it acts
like the browser, so redirects
are automatically followed.
So how do we install Capybara?
Well, just like with the other
gems, we're going to open our
Gemfile inside of
the test group.
We're going to say gem Capybara,
we're going to
rebundle to make sure it gets
installed, and then we're
going to open our test helper.
In our test helper, at the
top we're going to add a
requirement that says require
capybara/rails.
That's going to tell Capybara
to place whatever hooks are
necessary to tie into the
integration test suite that
Rails that already provides
that knows
where things are at.
We're also going to open
up the ActionDispatch
IntegrationTest class that we
saw earlier being inherited in
our test, and we're now
going to include the
Capybara DSL module.
We're also going to define a
teardown at this level that
instructs Capybara to reset its
sessions because, again,
it acts like a web browser, so
it actually has a session, it
has cookies, it has a history.
And then we're also going to
tell Capybara to use the
default driver.
We're not going to touch much
on drivers, but what they
allow you to do is things like
exercise end user JavaScript,
access third party websites,
et cetera.
There's multiple drivers out
there, but for the purposes of
this course, the default is
perfectly acceptable.
So we touched a little bit on
some of the methods that
Capybara provides to allow us
to act like an end user and
their web browser.
Let's look into a little
bit more detail at
what they might be.
You can see here we
get click_link,
click_button, or click_on.
So click_link looks for an
anchor tag with an href,
click_button looks for a button
element, or click_on
looks for either of the two.
In all cases, you can provide
a parameter to the methods
that have either text, which is
the text the end user would
see on the page, or
the element's ID.
Next, Capybara gives us a bunch
of form interaction
methods, such as fill_in element
with value, choose a
radio button, check a check
box, uncheck a check box,
attach a file, or select a
particular element from an
option group.
These fields can be looked up
from their form label, from
their element name, or
from the element ID.
And finally, Capybara gives us a
couple of helper methods, if
you will, called current_path
and current_url.
Because Capybara acts like
a web browser, it's
automatically following
redirects so sometimes it's
nice to know exactly where we
are because it might not be
the last place that
we requested.
Let's look at the integration
test that we wrote earlier and
see how we might write
it using Capybara.
So in this case we've got
anyone can view zombie
information, we're
still loading our
zombie from the fixtures.
In this case, we are now going
to visit instead of get the
zombie URL.
We're going to assert on that
we're on the page that we
expect to be on, and we can use
another Capybara method
called within to say within h1,
which will isolate where
it looks on the page to say that
within that h1, we want
to make sure the zombie's name
is present using the
has_content method.
So what is this has_content
method?
Well, just like everything else,
has_content is a method
provided by Capybara to help
us with our testing.
In this case, has_content takes
a parameter which is
text that we're trying
to check to
make sure is on the page.
It's going to return true or
false, and it's going to make
sure that it's visible text
on the page, as well.
Along with has_content, there's
has_no_content.
And since this is such a widely
scoped thing to say,
like Ash should be somewhere
on the page, a lot of times
it's nice to be able to
constrain that using the
within call.
Along with has_content, Capybara
provides us with
has_selector.
In this case, rather than giving
it text we can give it
a CSS selector and it can
find an element on the
page by that selector.
So here we have the ID of
zombie_1 with an h1.
It also has_no_selector.
And you can use has_selector
with optional parameters like
text to say it should have a
zombie_1 element that has an
h1 and that h1 should
have the text Ash.
Or, you could say this page
has zombie class elements.
There should be five of them
on the page and all five
should be visible.
Along with has_content and
has_selector, we get something
like has_link, has_field, where
we check for a hyperlink
and we check for a form field.
We also have even lower
level things
like has_css or has_xpath.
If that's what you need, it's
also there for you.
So getting back to our tests
with Capybara, we should talk
about how Capybara tries to
enforce testing behavior.
Because we're acting like the
end user, we want to test as
if we were the end
user, right?
So getting back to our earlier
test, we might load a zombie
from the fixture file, load a
tweet for that zombie from the
texture file, and browse
to the home
page using visit root_url.
We could say, well, within a
element with the ID of tweet
one, for example, we want to
make sure that there's a link
with the zombie's name on it.
And when we click on that link,
we want to make sure
that we end up on the
zombie's page.
So rather than looking for
elements and text on the page
that says I should have an href
that does this, we're now
saying this is what we did
and this is where we are.
Finally, let's write a more
interesting test and maybe
test something like
a sign up form.
So here, we'll make a
test called should
create a new zombie.
We're going to visit the
root_url, we're going to click
on the link to sign up.
On that page, maybe
there's a form.
We're going to say, fill in Name
with Brains, we're going
to say fill in Graveyard with
Brains, we're going to click
the sign up button, and we're
going to now assert that we
are on the zombie's page.
So the idea is if it created the
zombie and redirected us
to the page, it must've
been successful.
Now for integration tests,
you'll find that signing up or
signing in are something that
probably happens a lot.
Just like in the first group of
unit test levels where we
talk about refactoring your
code and refactoring your
tests, since this is something
that's going to be used a lot,
we might want to extract some of
that activity into a helper
method such as sign_up_as.
And what that will do is allow
us to rewrite our test once
again to just say, visit the
root URL, sign_up_as Brains,
assert that I have content,
welcome, Brains, in this case.
So that's it.
I know it was a lot
of content.
Capybara and integration tests
are a little bit of a change
of thinking against what we've
been doing up to this point.
Up ahead are some challenges for
you to see how much you've
learned writing your tests,
testing your assertions, and
seeing how well you do.
Again, if you need to look back
at the video, go ahead
and do that.
Good luck.