You're watching 3 For 5.
I'm Jason VanLue.
And this is Level Three.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
In this level, we're going to
look at header and navigation
elements, some of the
most important
elements on your website.
First, I'd like to introduce
you to our case study site
that we're going to be using
throughout the rest of the
course, to sort of
practically apply
what we've been learning.
So this is Border & Radius, a
local brew house with great
food and even better beer.
Sounds like my kind of place.
Now, we're going to be using
this site and breaking down
individual elements of the site,
to apply some of the
HTML5 and CSS3 expertise
that you now have.
As we move through each level,
we're going to be focusing on
three primary points, design,
markup, and style.
But before we go any further,
let's chat for brief moment
about what makes up a successful
navigation and a
successful header.
So we have five points that we
want to consider, when it
comes to designing and
developing effective header
and navigation sections
of our site.
The first is know your user.
Now you want to know your user,
no matter what site
you're developing.
A one-size-fits-all approach
to web design
just doesn't work.
So you want to make sure that
you're keeping your user in
mind, when you're building
these elements.
The second is keep it clean.
Now, we want to make sure that
our header and navigation
elements are free from
distraction.
So that means that we want our
branding to be prominent.
And maybe a couple of key
call-to-action points are also
appropriate for that section
that section.
Third, we have three
to four elements.
Now, we all should know what
the top priorities of the
sites that we're building are.
We should ask ourselves the
question, what do we want the
user to do, when they
access our site.
Now, all of those priorities
don't necessarily have to be
totally flushed out in your
header or your navigation.
But maybe you have a couple of
key call-to-action points or
key links that you want to call
your user's attention to.
The header is a perfect
place to put that.
We also want to simplify
our navigation.
So we don't have 28 different
links to all of our pages of
our site in our main
navigation.
I think it's a good practice to
keep our main navigation at
around six to eight
primary links.
And then, you can decide how
you want to drill down the
rest of your navigation
from there.
Finally, we want to
be a tour guide.
Now, it's our job as designers
and developers to guide our
users to where we want them
to go on the site.
So it's important for us to
think like a user, as we're
building these websites.
All right.
So let's quickly go through
some design practices and
strategy that we use to build
the Border & Radius site.
So in talking with the client,
over a few pints, of course,
we went through the five points
we discussed earlier.
Let's apply those points
to our design.
First, know your user.
Border & Radius knows that their
customers are drawn by
the history of the brew house,
as well as their changing
organic menu.
We wanted these to be featured
prominently, since each is a
valuable component
of the brand.
Second, keep it clean.
This section is certainly
very clean.
It matches up with the
restaurant's existing branding
and keeps unnecessary
distractions to a minimum.
Third, three to four elements,
we have two key elements,
history and menu, in this
section, in addition to the
branding elements.
So this works.
Fourth, simplify navigation.
We have seven links, which
is towards the
upper end of our limit.
But since we've chosen to use a
fairly wide page layout and
have kept our overall styling
simple, it works.
Finally, be tour guides.
We've constructed the layout and
overall design of the site
with the user in mind, helping
to guide them to the most
important elements on
this page and in
the rest of the site.
All right.
So now let's move on
to the markup.
So here's is our header
and our navigation.
So previously, in HTML4, we
might have marked this up to
look something like this.
We have our div id="header."
And then, we have
three anchor points.
We have our two images,
"better-beer" and
"menu-promo." And then,
we also have our logo.
Now, if we add our navigation,
it would look
something like this.
We have a div id="navigation,"
with an unordered list, with our
navigation elements there.
So how might we use our new
HTML5 skills to refactor this
into HTML5.
Well, we could move our header
element into a header tag and
we could also move
our navigation
elements into a nav tag.
So all of this is still
valid HTML.
But we've just organized our
markup a little bit better.
So in this case, I've chosen to
give the primary navigation
and the header an ID.
Now, if you remember, in HTML5,
we can use HTML5 tags
in multiple areas on our page.
This is something that you
shouldn't do with IDs.
So if you have a div
id="header," for instance, you
really should only
use that once.
Well, with the HTML5 header
tag, we can use that in
multiple sections of the page.
I know, in our site, we're
going to be using it in
multiple sections.
So I've chosen, in this case,
to give it an ID, to give me
more options and variety
in styling.
Otherwise, our markup
looks exactly the
same as it did before.
So that's our markup for
these two sections.
Now, let's go ahead and
move into style.
So let's review our
elements again.
And we'll start with
the header.
So we have a header with
the ID of main.
And we have two images, Better
Beer and Menu Promo, in
addition to our logo.
So let's start with styling
the two images.
We'll start with Better Beer.
So here are the basic styles
for the Better Beer image.
Now, what we want to do is we
want to create a rollover
state for this image.
So in this case, what we're
going to do is we're going to
use our opacity property
in CSS3.
And we're going to say that our
static image is going to
have an opacity value of 0.65.
Then, when we add our hover
state, we're actually going to
set our opacity value to one.
So what this does is, when we
roll over the image, we're
actually seeing the
full image.
When it's in its static state,
it's actually a little opaque.
And you can kind of see how
this renders, here.
Now, this is a neat little
way of doing it.
Because before, we would
have had to save out
two different images.
In this case, we can save out
just one image and adjust the
opacity, using CSS.
Now, let's look at our second
image, menu-promo.
This is going to follow the
same concept as our Better
Beer image.
So here are the basic styles
for menu-promo.
We're going to go ahead and add
an opacity value to the
static state of 0.65.
And we're also going to add an
opacity value of one to our
hover state.
So just like our Better Beer
image, we have a static state
that is a little opaque and when
you roll over it, you're
going to see the full image.
It's a great way of creating
rollovers states with CSS,
with really not a lot
of time involved.
OK, so let's talk
about our logo.
Now, for our logo, we could have
done the same thing as we
did for our previous two images
and just adjust the
opacity values on hover.
But instead, let's get a little
crazy and actually add
a CSS transition to
the hover state.
First, let's look at our basic
styles for our logo.
Now, we're going to add
CSS transitions
to our style sheet.
So here's what the code
would look like.
Now notice we have our vendor
prefixes first, for WebKit,
Mozilla, and Opera, and then,
the basic property following.
Now, let's spend a little bit
of time talking about CSS
transitions.
CSS transitions create smooth
animations using CSS, as
opposed to maybe JavaScript,
which is what we would have
used before.
Now, CSS transitions have three
properties that we want
to consider.
The first is the transition
property.
Now, the transition property
tells us what piece of the
object is being affected.
So in this case, it's going
to be the opacity.
Now, we could have chosen the
background, or the color, or
another property.
But we'll stick with the
opacity, for this transition.
The second property is the
transition duration.
Now, this tells us how long
the transition lasts.
You can play around with
different values, to get your
desired effect.
But in this case, we're going
to go with 0.2 seconds.
Finally, our third transition
property is the
transition-timing function.
And this basically tells
us how we want the
transition to work.
So in this case, we want to use
the ease-in-out property,
which is going to give it a
nice intro-outro effect.
Now, there are five
properties for the
transition-timing function.
We have ease, ease-in,
ease-in-out, linear, and
bezier curve.
Now, for the most part, you
probably want to stick with
ease and linear, as those are
the most commonly used.
So now that we have our CSS
transition in place for this
element, we're going to go ahead
and add a hover state,
in which we set the opacity
value to 0.70.
So let's sort of summarize
what we've done in this
transition here.
First, we've created a
transition in which we're
going to affect the opacity.
We're going to do that
for 0.2 seconds.
And we're going to use the
ease-in-out function to give
kind of an intro-outro effect.
And what that's going to do
is, when we hover over the
logo, it's going to drop
the opacity to 0.7.
So let's go to the live site.
And I'll show you what
we've built thus far.
So for our Better Beer image and
our Menu Promo image, you
can see the opacity rollovers
that we have in place.
Pretty neat that we can use just
one image and adjust the
opacity directly with CSS.
And if we take look at the logo,
you can see how it fades
in and out smoothly, courtesy of
the CSS transition that we
just built.
Now let's move on to
the navigation.
So in this navigation,
we have a few things
that need to be styled.
We have a background that
we want to style
with the box shadow.
We have our text, which we
want to style with a text
shadow and actually add an
@font-face declaration.
And then, we're going to
add a transition on
the rollover effect.
So let's start with the
@font-face declaration.
So the first thing we're going
to do is add our @font-face
declaration to the top
of our style sheet.
Now, if you remember, we can
hit up the website Font
Squirrel, which will generate
the CSS that we need to set
this @font-face property.
And in doing that, we'll
get code that looks
something like this.
Now, notice we're using
DroidSansBold for our
navigation.
Once we have that, we'll go
into our CSS and continue
styling out the main
navigation section.
So if you remember in our
markup, we had a nav with an
ID of primary.
So here we have the hatch
primary elements.
Now, you'll notice that I've
already put the DroidSansBold
font in my font stack.
Remember, we've declared that
already, in an @font-face
property at the top of
our style sheet.
So now we're calling that
font, in our font stack.
Now we're going to add a box
shadow to the background of
our navigation element.
So here's what the code might
look like for that.
Now, notice we have our vendor
prefixes first, WebKit
box-shadow and Mozilla
box-shadow, in addition to our
regular box-shadow property.
And remember, our values are
x-offset, y-offset, and then
blur, in addition to
our color value.
And then, we put that above
our font stack, which
remember, includes our
DroidSansBold font that we
declared with an @font-face.
Now that's done, let's
go ahead and start
styling out our text.
So here are the basic
styles for that.
Now notice, we've added
a text-shadow.
And just like box-shadow, we
have our values, x-offset,
y-offset, blur, and color.
So in this case, we have a dark
text color on a light
background.
So remember, we're going to do
a text-shadow that is offset
bottom-right, with
a light color.
Because we want to give it that
letter-pressed effect,
like it's being stamped
into the background.
We also want to define
a border-radius
for our hover state.
Because who wants just boring
rectangles in the background?
Why not round those corners?
So in this case, we've added our
vendor prefixes first, for
our border-radius property.
And we've defined our radius
to be five pixels.
Here's how that might render.
Finally, we're going to add a
CSS transition to this, to
really tie everything
together.
So in this case, we're
going to do our
vendor prefixes first.
Remember to include Opera.
And then, we have our
basic transition
property at the bottom.
Now remember, in our case
previous transition example,
we just used the property
opacity, when we're talking
about what portion of the
object we want to be
transitioned.
In this case, we want everything
to be included in
the transition.
So we're going to use the
transition property all.
We're going to set the
time function at 0.3.
And then, we're also going to
use our ease-in-out function,
just like we did in our last
transition property.
So let's go ahead and take
a look at the live site.
And I'll show you what
the navigation looks
like in real time.
So we have our navigation
section with a box-shadow on
our background.
And you can see how
our DroidSansBold
text renders properly.
Let's check out the rollovers.
As you can see, we changed
the color of the text.
Now you can see the
text-shadow.
And we also have our
smooth transition.
To me, it's much better than
just a simple hover state.
It's a small detail.
But I really think it adds
a lot to this section.
Now that we've gone over how to
craft effective header and
navigation elements.
It's time for you to
apply what you've
learned in this level.
Let's start coding.