In this level we're going
to be talking
about footers and forms.
Now we have some great new form
elements is HTML5, so
we're going to start with those
first, and then we'll
close out the course
with our footer.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So just like with the other
levels, we're going to be
using our case study site,
Border and Radius, to sort of
take us through some practical
application
of what we're learning.
But first, let's go through a
couple of key points, both for
forms and for footers.
All right, so with
forms first, we
have intuitive usability.
Now what do I mean by that?
Well, many times your form
elements are some of the most
important elements
on your page.
They could be contact forms, or
newsletter sign ups, or a
lot of different things, so it's
important to keep them
intuitive and usable
for your user.
Second, we have no
ugly ducklings.
Now, forms can usually be quite
technical in nature, but
that doesn't mean that they
don't need design.
A lot of times we can just put
our forms together and not
really style them.
Since they are key elements on
our page, and a lot of times
have key call to action points,
it's important that we spend
just as much time styling them
as some of the other elements
on our page.
With our footer, first, we want
to utilize the space.
Now, most of our users are going
to read our websites
from the top down, which means
most of the time they're going
to end up at the bottom
where our footer is.
And our footer is a great area
to place navigation items, or
key call to action elements.
A lot of things can be put in
your footer if you want to
draw attention to them.
So make sure that you're
utilizing the space
appropriately.
Second, we don't want
to forget the style.
Just like with our forms, where
we can leave out a lot
of the styling, with our footer,
most of the time it's
the last thing that we design
because we usually design from
the top down, starting
with our header.
So we want to make sure that
we're putting, once again,
just as much emphasis and time
into our footer design as the
rest of our site.
All right, so let's look at
the three main points that
we're covering throughout
the course,
design, markup and style.
Let's head back to our Border
and Radius site and take a
look at the design strategy
behind our form
and our footer elements.
Let's take a look at our form
element first, which is the
third block element
that includes a
newsletter sign up box.
Now, we could leave the styling
of the form totally up
to the browsers, but why give up
control when you can style
forms effectively and easily.
In this case, the design is
fairly simple since it's not
really a complex form, but
we've used some CSS3
properties, such as rounded
corners, gradients, and text
effects, to help the form
be more cohesive with
the rest of the site.
Moving on to the footer, with
a site like this we really
don't need to include
a ton of elements.
In this case we've chosen to
tie-in the history of Border
and Radius since this is an
important branding element.
And we carried the design
through with the monotone
image like you see in the
header, and have also included
standard navigation and
copyright elements.
But as with the form, we decided
to kick things up a
notch with CSS3 properties.
We'll go through these
specifically in
just a little bit.
Now that we've covered design,
let's go ahead and move on to
the markup.
Now in HTML5, as I mentioned,
we have some
great new form elements.
These includes some new input
types, native placeholder
text, auto-focus, and
form validation.
So before we hit the actual
markup, let's go through a
couple of these in
more detail.
With our email and URL input
types we can actually define
in the markup what type
of field that we have.
Now, this is great for devices
such as the iPhone or the
iPad, which have different
keyboards depending on what
sort of form field that
you're using.
So, in this case, we have an
email form field, and that's
going to generate the keyboard
that's specific for emails.
So this is a great usability
factor because it allows the
user to go directly into what
they want to do, in this case,
typing in their email address,
as opposed to trying to find
all of the characters.
Now our number, date and color
input types currently aren't
supported in contemporary
browsers all that well, but as
they become more supported
you're going to see them in
use a lot more.
And this is because it's going
to give, once again, some
great new usability features
to our forms.
In this case, like you can see
in the demo, we can actually
bring up different very shades
of color wheels or color
selectors to actually define
what we're looking for.
And we can also do the same
thing for date pickers and
number sliders, for example.
Finally, we have the search
input type, and this thing is
pretty slick.
In web browsers like Safari
and Chrome, the browser
actually renders rounded
corners automatically.
And it also adds a little x
button, just like you would
see in a native, say,
Mac application.
And this is great because if
you're entering a search and
all of a sudden you realize
that's not what you want to
search for, you can click
on that button and it
automatically erases
your entire search.
So, once again, this is a much
more usable feature and it's
going to allow us to do a lot
more with our form fields.
Now, I mentioned that webkit
browsers automatically add
rounded corners.
If this is something that you
don't necessarily want to
have, maybe you want to have a
custom design search field,
all you need to do is enter this
code in your CSS and then
you'll be able to style
however you want.
All right, so let's go ahead
and jump into the markup.
And first, let's take a look at
what we're actually going
to be marking up.
In this case it's our email
newsletter box.
So previously we might have
constructed our markup
to look like this.
We have our div id newsletter,
and then we have our various
form fields beneath that.
So in HTML5 how might
we mark this up?
Well, we're going to do
a couple of things.
First, like you would expect,
we're going to replace our top
level div with a section
because, once again, it's a
grouping of related content.
We're going to add our header
tag with a new h1 for email
newsletter, and then we're going
to do a couple of things
with our individual
form fields.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at those in more detail.
The first thing that we're going
to do, as you can see,
is we're going to add our input
type email, which is one
of those new input types
that we talked about
a little bit earlier.
We're also going to add
placeholder text.
Now this is pretty cool because
previously you'd only
be able to have placeholder text
that disappeared when you
clicked inside the form field
through JavaScript or
something like that.
Now we can do it natively
through HTML5.
So, in this case, we're just
going to add this value
placeholder, and then whatever
we would like to exist inside
of our form field.
In this case, it's
an email address.
Finally, if we want to make our
form fields required, all
we have to do is enter required
at the end of our
string like you see here.
And, natively in HTML5,
our form fields
are required fields.
All right, now that we've
completed our email newsletter
markup, let's go ahead and
move on to our footer.
Now, we're not going to be doing
anything game changing
in our footer markup, but we
are going to be adding a
couple of new HTML5 elements.
So let's take a look at how we
might have previously marked
up our footer.
First, we have our containing
element, which in this case is
div id primary foot.
And then we have our div ID
history section which includes
a little bit of information
about Border and Radius and
has that monotone image
like you saw before.
So in HTML5 we're only going to
make a couple of changes.
As you might expect, we're going
to change our containing
element, div, into
a footer tag.
And we're also going to change
our history section into an
actual HTML5 section because,
once again, it's a grouping of
related content.
We're going to add our header,
our history in this case, and
that wraps up the HTML5 for
that particular markup.
Next we have our footer
navigation and a little bit of
copyright information
below that.
So here's how we might have
marked that up previously.
So in HTML5, just a couple of
quick little changes here.
Instead of having a div ID
info, we're just going to
change that to section.
And instead of having div ID
footer nav, we can go ahead
and change that to our nav tag
because it is navigation.
All right, so now we've got our
markup complete, let's go
ahead and work on the style for
our email newsletter box
and our footer elements.
All right, first, let's take a
look at our markup once again
just to give us a reminder of
what we're working with.
So if you remember, we have our
section id newsletter, and
then our actual form fields.
So let's get our basic styles
out of the way first,
like you see here.
Next, we're going to be focusing
on styling the
specific fields within the
email newsletter sign up.
So as you can see here we're
just going to add our standard
border radius property with our
vendor prefixes ahead of
our standard property, and we're
going to add a radius
value of five pixels.
As you can see by these
images, we have
a before and after.
So before we have our just
standard rectangles, and then
after we have our
rounded corners.
Next we're going to work
on our submit button.
Now our submit button is pretty
cool because prior to
CSS3 we would only be able to
create this using an image.
For our submit button we're
going to render
everything in CSS3.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at how we might do that.
First, we're going to get our
basic styles out of the way
like you see here.
The next thing that we're going
to do, is we're going to
add text shadow, and we're also
going around the corners.
So, in this case, you can see
our text shadow is once again
our letterpress effect.
And we're going to add a border
radius of eight pixels.
Next we're going to add a CSS
gradient to our button.
Now if you can remember when we
covered CSS gradients back
in Level 2, they can be
a little bit tricky.
So for this button I've once
again used John Allsopp's CSS
gradient creator, and it's
given me the code
like you see here.
So, in this case, we're going to
create a gradient from kind
of a darker gray to a little
bit of a lighter gray.
And let's go ahead and take a
look at that button rendered
completely in CSS3
in our browser.
All right, so the last thing
that we're going to do for our
button is add a hover state.
Now in CSS, and in particular
CSS3, we have a number of
different options that we can
use for hover states.
You've seen a couple of those
in this course already.
In this case we're going to keep
it pretty simple and just
add a standard box shadow so
that when you hover over the
button it just lifts it off
the page a little bit.
So our code would look
something like this.
An x value of one pixel, a y
value of one pixel, and then
we're going to give a
three pixel blur.
Now the only thing to mention
here is that we've added in
opacity value of 0.4.
So we've kept the color as
standard black, and then
dropped the opacity to 0.4 as
opposed to trying to find a
gray color that works.
This is a quick and easy fix to
adding some drop shadow to
your elements.
All right, so now that we have
that done the last thing we
need to do is go ahead
and style our footer.
Now our footer includes some
pretty basic style so I've
included them in the reference
slides for this course, but
I'm not going to go through
those in depth right now
because they're pretty much
just standard CSS styles.
What I want to do is go ahead
and jump ahead to the actual
CSS3 properties that we're going
to add for a couple of
elements in our footer.
So let's go ahead and take a
look at the copyright section
of the footer.
All right, so the specific
element that we're going to
target with CSS3 properties is
going to be the bottle image
next to our copyright
information.
So what we want to do here
is we want to add a CSS
transition on hover.
So the way that we're going to
do this is we're going to set
our basic styles first,
like you see here.
And then we're going to add our
CSS transition property.
Vendor prefixes first,
of course.
And in this case we're going to
transition the opacity of
the image with an ease-in-out
function like
we typically use.
And then on the hover state
we're going to add an opacity
value of 0.5.
Now, if you notice, on our
static state, we have an
opacity value of 0.15.
So in this case we're going to
be going from a more opaque
image in a static state,
to a less opaque image
in the hover state.
So ready to take a look
at how this fits
together in the browser?
All right, let's head on over
to Border and Radius
and check it out.
Let's first take a look at our
newsletter sign up form.
Here's a look at what this would
look like if we didn't
use some of our new
CSS3 properties.
Once again, it's usable, but
it's a bit boring and bland.
By adding CSS3 properties we
get a form that looks like
this, rounded corners, native
placeholder text, and a button
with gradients and rounded
corners all in CSS3.
And if we move on to our footer,
most of our content is
pretty straightforward.
You can see that we have a text
shadow with our history
copy, which is a nice element.
And you can see how we rendered
our footer background
to be opaque so the texture
bleeds through the color.
And here you can see the
transition that we added to
our bottle image.
So congratulations, we've built
the Border and Radius
homepage in semantic HTML5
markup, and with some kicking
CSS3 properties.
Hopefully this has been helpful,
functional example of
how to use these great
new features.
But wait there's more.
Since you've made it this far,
we wanted to throw in a little
something special.
So we'd like to invite you
to have a drink on us.
Now what do we mean by that?
Well let's go back to our Border
and Radius site and
I'll show you.
So let's check out our bottle
image again, I think you'll
find a few things
have changed.
Yep, that's a spinning bottle.
And if you look real close you
can actually see the liquid
inside of the bottle
being drained.
So I assume you're taking us
up on our offer a drink.
Pretty cool, huh?
The power of CSS3, it really is
amazing some of the stuff
that we can do.
Now if you're interested in
taking a look at the code that
we used to create this, we've
included at the end of the
slides for this level.
Enjoy and cheers.
All right, so that concludes the
last level of the course.
Congratulations for making
it this far, but you're
not quite done yet.
Let's go ahead and apply what
we've learned in this level
and jump into the code.