You're watching 3 For 5.
I'm Jason VanLue.
And this Level 2.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So it doesn't matter if you're
a designer or a developer.
At the end of the day, our jobs
are basically the same.
We want to craft rich, usable
websites and web applications
with an awesome user
experience.
So we're going to look at
some styles in CSS3.
Now, just like HTML5, this
isn't an exhaustive list.
But it's rather a list of some
the more commonly used
properties.
So we're going to start
with border-radius.
Now, border-radius rounds the
cornders of an element with a
defined radius value.
Now, this is an awesome
property.
Because if you remember before,
in order to get
rounded corners on an image or
a button, you would have had
to do a variety of hacks or
save out transparent PNGs.
Now, we can let CSS do
the work for us.
So if we had a rectangular
button, now we can add rounded
corners, simply by using the
border-radius property.
So in this case, we have a
border-radius of 10 pixels.
The higher the value, the
more rounded corners
are going to be.
The lower the value, the less
rounded the corners
are going to be.
Now, a quick note here, some of
these CSS properties don't
show up the same in every
browser, surprise, surprise.
So in this case, for the
border-radius property, we
need to add vendor prefixes
for WebKit and Mozilla.
So we want to put our vendor
prefixes before
the main CSS property.
So in this case, we have WebKit
border-radius and
Mozilla border-radius,
before our standard
border-radius property.
Next, let's look
at text-shadow.
Text-shadow adds a vertical
and horizontal
offset shadow to text.
And we have the ability to
control direction, blur, and
the color of the shadow.
Now, just like border radius,
before, in order to get this
effect, we would have
to save out images.
Now, we can create shadows on
text, by using this property.
So if we look at an example
here, we have an image from
designswap.com.
And if you notice that the name,
Phil Coffman, that's
actually text with
a text shadow.
So the way that we render
this property is
with a couple of values.
First, we have the
x-offset value.
Then, we have the
y-offset value.
Then, we have the blur value.
So by setting these values,
we can create a variety of
different shadows
for our text.
And then, finally, we can
also set the color.
So one quick design
note here--
we all probably know how to
create a drop shadow.
But what if we wanted to create
a letter-press effect?
That is the text being stamped
into the page.
Well, if we wanted to do that,
something to remember is-- if
you have a light background
and dark text, you want to
create a shadow that's
offset bottom-right,
with a light color.
Or as in this case, with this
image, we have a darker
background and light text.
So we want our shadow to be
offset to the top-left and in
a darker color.
By playing around with a variety
of different values
with the text-shadow property,
you can create some pretty
awesome effects in CSS.
Let's move on now
to box-shadow.
Box-shadow adds a shadow
to a non-text element.
And it basically follows the
same syntax as text-shadow.
So as we see in our example
here, we have an image with a
shadow that we can create in
CSS, as opposed to just saving
out an image.
So in this case, we have our
x-offset value, our y-offset
value, and our blur.
Now, one neat thing about
box-shadow is we can also add
an inset property.
If we wanted the shadow to be
inside of the image, as
opposed to outside the image,
we can use inset, with the
same syntax.
So next, let's look at RGBa.
Now, RGBa isn't a
new CS property.
But rather, it's a new model
for defining color in our
style sheet.
Now, previously, we would use
hex-colors to define our
colors in our style sheet.
But hex-colors didn't
give us the
option of defining opacity.
Now, with RGBa, we can add an
opacity value to our colors,
to allow them to be
more transparent.
So as we see here, with this
property, we have our RGBa
values, Red, Green, and Blue.
And then, the last value here,
0.5, is our Opacity Value.
So in this case, we can allow
colors or background imagery
to actually bleed through
our text, to create
a pretty neat effect.
Let's also look at HSLa, which
is an alternative model for
defining colors in
our style sheet.
Now, HSLa is preferred
by some.
Because it's a little bit
easier to change out the
values of the colors, if you
don't have RGB Values.
And if you're wanting to make
changes to your colors on the
fly, then this might be a good
property for you to use.
So it follows a similar
syntax to RGBa.
Let's look and see
how that works.
We have our HSLa values, which
translate to Hue, Saturation,
and Light, respectively.
And then, just like a
opacity, we have an
Alpha-Transparency Value.
So we can set that to be as
opaque as we want it.
Now, some of you may not
know how to find
the HSLa color values.
Well, we can actually
use Photoshop.
In Photoshop, we can pull
the HSB Values.
But sometimes, these aren't
always reliable.
I actually like to use Matt
Patenaude's Colors app, which
you can pull the HSL values
directly and import them into
your style sheet.
Or Chris Coyier has a pretty
slick interface called the
HSLa Explorer, which
allows you to
pull HSLa values directly.
Next, let's move on to
the Opacity property.
The Opacity property defines
how opaque an image or an
object could be.
So we've talked about RGBa
and HSLa for text.
Now, let's talk about
opacity for images.
So in this case, we can set the
opacity of an image, by
using this property.
This is nice because now, we
don't have to save out
transparent images.
Instead, we could save out full
images and then adjust
the opacity, using CSS.
This gives us a lot more variety
and makes it easier
for us to change values.
Next, let's look at the CSS
Transform property.
The CSS transform property
allows elements rendered by
CSS to be transformed in
two-dimensional space.
So this is commonly used maybe
on a hover state for an image,
if we wanted that image to
break out of its space,
without affecting the
surrounding elements.
Dan Cederholm does this on the
Popular site, Dribbble.
And we can see here, with
his color tags.
So the blue on the hover state
actually pops out of the
surrounding elements
but doesn't
negatively affect them.
So here's what the code
might look like.
We have an Unordered List.
And then, on hover, we set our
CSS transform property.
Now notice, we have
vendor prefixes in
this property as well.
We've also added a vendor
prefix for Opera.
Now, we don't always have to add
a vendor prefix for Opera.
But in this case, we do.
So we've chosen to use
the scale property
for this CSS transform.
And basically, what that means
is we're going to be scaling
the image by 50%.
We could also use one of the
other three properties
available, rotate, skew, or
translate, which moves the
image along the x and y-axes.
Next, let's look at
CSS transitions.
CSS transitions allow property
changes in CSS values to occur
smoothly over a specified
duration.
Basically, what this means is we
can create some pretty cool
transition or roll-over
effects, without using
JavaScript.
So if we had a button that we
wanted to add a transformation
to and not just a hover state,
we could do that.
Now, we're going to get into the
CSS transition property a
little bit more in depth,
later on in the course.
So bear with me there.
Next, let's look at
CSS gradients.
CSS gradients create a
transition from one color to
another, without the
use of images.
So we all should be familiar
with how to create a gradient
for a button, say
in Photoshop.
But this makes it super easy
to create gradients in CSS,
once again, gives you a ton of
variety, and allows you to
change elements on the fly.
So we have our sample image
here, "THAT'S NO MOON." Now,
the syntax for this property
is a little unintuitive.
And it actually renders
differently in each browser.
So I've found that the easiest
way to generate CSS gradients
is to use a pretty cool little
tool from John Allsopp.
He's created an editor
in which you can
just input your colors.
And it automatically spits out
the CSS code that you need to
put in your style sheet.
So in this case, for our "THAT'S
NO MOON" button,
here's how we would
generate the CSS.
We have our background
image property.
And instead of including an
image URL, we've actually set
a gradient.
So you'll notice we have a
WebKit vendor prefix here, as
well as a Mozilla
vendor prefix.
And you can see how
they're different.
But basically, we've created a
gradient with a button, with
rounded corners, simply using
CSS, pretty cool.
The multiple backgrounds
property allows us to add
multiple background images to
our page or within our page.
In this example, from Naz
Hamid's Lost World's Fairs
site, he's actually added a
couple of background images.
So that as you're scrolling down
the page, the different
images move at a
different rate.
So it almost gives a
parallax effect.
So here's what the code might
look like from Naz's site.
He's actually got two
images in this
case, bg.jpg and tile.jpg.
Now, what you want to remember
is the image closest to the
user on the screen needs
to be listed first
in your image stack.
So in this case that would
be background.jpg.
My friend Dan Higby has recently
done this in one of
his blog posts.
He's added multiple
background images.
So as you scroll down the page
and read more of his posts,
the background image changes.
And it also moves because he's
got a variety of background
images, within each section.
You really can create
a lot of neat
effects, using this property.
Now, we're going to look at
a real fonts on the web.
Now, if you remember the old
days, we were limited to just
a few safe fonts.
Arial, Helvetica, Georgia,
or Times New Roman.
Well, now, the age of rich
internet typography is here.
And we have a ton of options,
when it comes to embedding
fonts on our website.
Now, there are several different
varieties of fonts
that we can use on
our websites.
Andy Clark has created a pretty
helpful table in his
Hardboiled Web Design book.
Some of the more common fonts
are OpenType or TrueType.
We also have the Web Open Font
format, which is kind of like
a compressed file of OpenType
and TrueType fonts.
So with the compressed file
size, as well as additional
security features, I think we'll
start seeing this become
more of the norm in browser
supported fonts.
Now, CSS3 gives us a property
for using real fonts in our
style sheets.
It's called @font-face.
In font-face, we have three
values that we need to declare
in our style sheet.
The first is a font file.
The second is an @font-face
declaration, where we'll list
the font family, the source, and
the format of that font.
And then finally, we
can include that
font in our font stack.
Now, an easy way of doing this
is go to a website called Font
Squirrel, which has a variety
of free-to-use fonts.
And they also generate the
@font-face properties for you.
So all you need to do is copy
and paste, put those at the
top of your style sheet,
and you're good to go.
Now the @font-face property is
still the most reliable way,
in my opinion, of embedding
fonts into your website.
But in the past year, we've seen
a number of new startups
really advancing the technology
and web typography.
We have Typekit.
We have webfonts.fonts.com.
And then, we also have Google
getting into the mix with
Google Fonts.
So now, you have a variety of
options, when it comes to rich
web typography.
The bottom line is we're no
longer limited to the old,
safe fonts.
We have a number of different
options, when it comes to
embedding real fonts
into our website.
It takes a little bit of extra
work and preparation.
But the results and the overall
user experience is
much more positive.
Now, as designers and
developers, we know that our
sites might not look the
same in every browser.
But that's OK.
Now, notice I didn't it was OK
for our sites to look broken.
But we understand that there
might be small variances, from
browser to browser.
And as long as we're creating
adequate fall backs in our
style sheets and in our markup,
we can use some of
these new features
to create rich
experiences for our users.
Now, when it comes to browser
compatibility, Dan Cederholm
has put together a helpful
table in his
CSS3 for Web Designers.
He lists out the main CSS3
properties and how they're
supported in today's
contemporary browsers.
Now, you'll notice that Internet
Explorer 9 is the
only version of IE that
currently supports a lot of
these CSS3 properties, with the
exception of text-shadow.
So you want to make sure, in
particular, if you're looking
to support IE 8 or below, that
you're providing fallback
properties in your
CSS style sheets.
But let me also say this, as
great as CSS3 and HTML5 are,
we haven't arrived.
And it's our job, as designers
and developers, to make sure
that we're putting the user
first and creating experiences
that are going to be positive
for our users.
So just because we have elements
that we can use
doesn't mean that we should.
Remember, the most valuable tool
in your creative arsenal
is your mind.
So think through how you want to
design and how you want to
develop sites and use some of
these properties where you
think they're necessary.
As craftsmen of the web, our job
is to use the tools at our
disposal to create the
best experience
possible for our users.
Now, users probably won't know
that you've used some of these
specific elements in CSS3.
But that's OK.
As long as they're functioning
properly, they're going to
have a great experience.
But if they have a negative
experience, they're not going
to care if you use text-shadow
or RGBa values.
All they're going to care about
is the experience that
they have, when visiting
your website.
So make sure that you design
responsibly, that you're
taking everything into
consideration and always
putting your user first.
So now it's time to apply what
you've learned in this level.
Let's get to coding.