You're watching 3 For 5.
I'm Jason VanLue.
And this is Level One.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
In this level, we're going
to talk about HTML5.
Now, as you probably know, HTML5
is the newest version of
HTML and XHTML.
Now, as we were developing this
course, a large debate
came up about whether or not
to call it HTML5 or just
plain, old HTML.
In fact the WHAT Working Group,
the original creators
of the HTML5 spec, came out and
said that we should call
it just HTML.
Well, a lot of people still like
to refer to it as HTML5,
to differentiate between
previous versions of HTML.
So what are we supposed to do?
We're creating this
course on HTML5.
And they go and change
the name on us.
So you say HTML5.
I say HTML.
In the words of Louis Armstrong,
should we just call
the whole thing off?
Well, no, I don't think so.
You see, eventually, we'll
probably call this HTML.
But for the purposes of this
course, we'll go ahead and
refer to it as HTML5.
So that we don't
confuse folks.
And because, well, we're
just cool like that.
So what's the big deal
about HTML5?
Well, we have some awesome new
elements, like new semantic
tags, canvas, rich
media, and more.
For the purposes of this course,
we're just going to
focus on the semantic tags.
We'll also hit canvas and
some of the rich media pieces,
later on in the course.
So in HTML5, we have some
new tags on the block.
In 2005, Google conducted a
survey of over 3 billion
websites, in which they studied
the most common ID and
class attributes that web
designers and developers use
to name their HTML elements.
And their findings became the
basis for the new HTML5 spec.
So as we look at some of the
new tags for HTML5, this
obviously isn't an
exhaustive list.
But it's some of the more
widely used tags.
And it's what we're going to be
focusing on in this course.
First, we're going to
start with doc type
and the head elements.
Now, if you're like me, I've
copied and pasted the doc type
hundreds of times in websites.
I mean, who remembers this?
Well, it's nice in HTML5 for
lazy designers like myself
because it gives us a very
simple and easy option.
I can remember this.
I can even type it with my
own hands, if I want to.
Moving on to the HTML root
element, this also get much
more simplified in HTML5.
So instead of writing something
like this, we can
write something like this.
Also, in the head elements, our
character encoding gets a
lot easier.
So instead of writing something
like this, all we
need to define is this.
And it's the same exact thing.
And then also, when we look at
our links, we no longer have
to include the type attribute.
So instead of needing to type
text CSS or text JavaScript,
we can go ahead and
leave that out.
So our link elements look like
this, relative to style sheet
and then the actual link URL.
So let's first take a look
at our header element.
Now, the header tag in HTML5
is defined as "a group of
introductory or navigational
aids." Now, we all know
what a header is.
We've been using in
all of our sites.
It's usually the top portion
of your site.
And it includes the standard
branding elements, logo, tag
line, and maybe some
key call-to-action
elements, as well.
So previously, we might have
mocked up the header something
like this, div id="header," with
an each an h1 "OMG, Look
at the Zombies." Now, this
is still valid HTML5.
And it works perfectly.
But in HTML5, we now have the
option to organize this a
little bit better and
more intuitively.
It might look something like
this, where we add our header
tags, keep the h1.
Now, the nice thing about the
HTML5 header tag is we're not
limited to its use just
once in a page.
We can use this multiple
times.
So previously, with our div id
header, we would only be able
to use that once.
Now, with the new header tag in
HTML5, as long as we have a
container element in the page,
we can have a header section
for that, if we want it.
So let's say we have a section
id, zombie-family.
And we'd like to have
a header in that.
It's perfectly fine.
We can just add our header
tags, add an h1, "We Are
Family." And that's
semantic markup.
Let's also say we wanted
to add a tag line.
So in addition to the "We Are
Family" heading, we wanted to
say, "All your brains are belong
to us." We can do this
and even organize this
more effectively by
including an hgroup.
And basically, what this is,
is just a nice grouping of
related information, within
a header tag.
So let's move on
now to the nav tag.
The nav tag in HTML5 is defined
as "a section of the
page that links to other pages
on the site or to other
sections of that particular
page." Duh, we all know what a
navigation item is.
So the nav tag is basically
just a navigation area.
In this particular example, with
Frank Chimero's site, we
all know that the top-right
portion is the
main navigation area.
But let's say we have a section
of the site, maybe in
a side bar, that also has
a grouping of links.
How can we tell if this is a
navigation section or just a
grouping of links?
HTML5 makes this a lot easier.
Because now, we can define
the nav tag.
So previously, we might have
marked up something like this,
div id="navigation," with our
unordered list and our
navigation items, within
that list.
Now with HTML5, we can replace
our divs with a nav tag.
And now we know that section
is a navigation section.
So next, let's look at
the section tag.
The section tag in HTML5 is
defined as "a grouping of
content based around a theme."
Now, sometimes, your section
elements can replace your div
elements, maybe more of your
high-level organizational
divs.
But it doesn't necessarily mean
that you have to replace
all of your divs
with sections.
A section also must be
able to stand alone.
So let's look at an example.
Let's say we have a section
of our site called
ACC Basketball News.
Previously, we might
have marked up this
section, like so.
div id="acc-news." And we have
a title, "ACC Basketball
News," a subtitle "UNC Beats
Duke In Championship Game,"
and then, our paragraph
content.
So how might we mark this
up in HTML5, using
this section tag?
Well, we could add the section
tag in place of our div tags.
And now, we can also add
our header tag as well.
Because remember what we talked
about before, with our
ability to use the header
tag in multiple
sections of the site.
So in this case, "ACC Basketball
News" is the title
of this section.
So we can include that
in our header tags.
We can also change the h3 to
an h2, "UNC Beats Duke In
Championship Game." And our
paragraph copy stays the same,
same content, marked
up semantically and
effectively in HTML5.
So now, let's look at
the article tag.
The article tag in HTML5 is
defined as "an independent,
self-contained composition."
These could be news posts,
magazine articles,
user comments.
It's pretty straightforward.
The article is essentially an
article, a news posting,
something like that.
Now, what's the difference
between an
article and a section?
It's a question I hear a lot.
And a section can contain
multiple articles.
Remember, a section is a
grouping of related content,
whereas, an article
is independent.
So let's look at our example
again, our div id="acc news,"
with our title and
paragraph copy.
And if you remember, when we
changed it HTML5, we added our
section tags and our
header tags.
In this case, we've also added
article tags as well.
So now, we can group our
content, "UNC Beats Duke In
Championship Game,"
and our paragraph
content, within that article.
Now notice also, we've also
included more header tags.
In this case, the header for
this particular article is UNC
Beats Duke.
So now, we have two sections
of header tags within this
entire section element.
And that's perfectly OK,
perfectly semantic.
Andy Clark, in his book,
Hardboiled Web Design, has a
pretty good quote to help us to
define what an article is.
He says, "one way to check
if article is the most
appropriate element is to see if
an article's content makes
sense on its own.
For example, would it makes
sense on its own, when viewed
in an RSS reader, like a
Reeder for the iPad?"
So as you're thinking through
your content and working on
your markup, this is a good
quote to keep in mind.
If you're wanting to define
something as an article, does
it work in say a standalone
RSS reader on your iPad.
It's a good question
to ask yourself.
So the next tag is
the aside tag.
The aside tag is defined as
"content related to an article
but not critical to its
understanding." So this might
be those golden nuggets of
useless information that you
bring up at dinner parties
such as, "the airspeed
velocity of an unladen swallow."
It could also be
pull quotes, call outs,
those kind of things.
So let's go back
to our example.
Remember our article here,
"UNC Beats Duke In
Championship Game," our
paragraph copy, "The Blue
Devils are routed by the Tar
Heels." Now, we can include an
aside within this article that
says "Former Duke Players Cry
at Game's End."
Now, this isn't essential to
your understanding of the
actual article.
But it's just information that
helps spruce up that article.
This is a good example of
an aside might be used.
Finally, the last tag that we're
going to look at is the
footer tag.
Now, the footer tag is defined
as a section that "includes
information that closes out a
particular section of the
page." Now just like the
header, we all know
what a footer is.
Footer though, in HTML5, doesn't
have to be only at the
bottom of the page.
Just like the header tag, you
can use the footer tag in
multiple areas of the site.
You can add this tag to any
containing element, to close
out that section.
Let's look at our
example again.
So in this example, this is how
we might have previously
marked up a footer section.
div id="footer," with our h3,
"Talk to Me Goose," and then
our paragraph, copyright
information
Maverick & Goose Ventures.
So how might we change this
into HTML5 markup?
Well, we would add our footer
tags in place of our div tag.
And we would keep the
content the same.
Now, additionally, remember that
I mentioned that we can
use the footer tag in multiple
areas of the site.
So it doesn't necessarily
just have to be at the
bottom of our page.
So let's say that we have a
section with a header "Top
Gun" And we have
our paragraph--
"He's too close.
I'm switching to guns." We can
add a footer to this section,
"Highway to the Danger Zone."
Perfectly semantic markup, and
it allows us to better
organize our
information on our page.
So that's just a brief overview
of some of the more
widely used HTML5 tags.
Now again, as I mentioned, this
isn't an exhaustive list.
We're actually going to be
covering a couple of more
tags, as we go through
the course.
So we have all of these great
new features in HTML5.
But the question remains, how
usable are these features.
When should we start
to use them?
Well, the answer to that
question is, right now.
Now, when it comes to HTML5,
really, all it is-- it's an
extension of previous
versions of HTML.
It just builds on what
already is there and
what already is working.
So you're HTML4 code is
still valid in HTML5.
That's a big deal because it
means that all of your old
elements still are going
to work in HTML5.
Essentially, HTML5 is
just building on
what's already there.
How do we know which browsers
support HTML5?
Well, the big three already
do, Firefox, Chrome, and
Safari, also, the latest
versions of Opera.
And believe it or not, Internet
Explorer 9 supports HTML5.
But alas, our old foe, Internet
Explorer 8 and below
currently don't support HTML5.
So what do you do?
Well, depending on who your
target market is and who
you're building the site for,
you might be able to get away
with not supporting
IE8 and below.
But chances are, you're probably
going to have to
support some of those earlier
versions of the browser.
So what do you do?
Well, Remy Sharp created this
pretty awesome little script
that enables HTML5 elements in
browser versions earlier than
Internet Explorer 9.
So all you would do is you would
enter this script in
your head element.
And basically, what this says
is-- if a user is in a browser
earlier than Internet Explorer
9, cue this script.
And your HTML5 tags will work.
All of the other browsers,
Firefox, Safari, et cetera,
they're just going to
ignore this code.
And we're good to go.
So that's an overview
of HTML5.
Now, it's time for you to apply
what you've learned and
get coding.