[MUSIC PLAYING]
You're watching 3 for 5.
I'm Jason VanLue, and
this is Level Four.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
In this level, we're going to
be focusing on content.
Now content can mean a lot of
different things, but in this
case we're going to be referring
to content as the
inside of your site.
So we're not going to be
talking just about text
content, but we're going to be
looking more high level-- so,
how your information is laid
out, and what sort of
information you're including on
each of your pages in order
to optimize usability and
ultimately optimize user
experience for your site.
So in this level we're going
to continue to use our case
study website Border
and Radius site.
But before we do that, let's
go over a couple of points
related to content.
So first, you want to
have a strategy.
It's essential to
have a content
strategy for your site.
You don't just want to put
content on there without
thinking about how that affects
your users and how
that affects your overall
user experience.
Second, you want to get an ID.
Now, what this means is
information design is critical.
How you lay out your information
is just as
important as what sort of
information you're including
on each page.
Third, easy does it.
Now, just because you can use
something doesn't necessarily
mean that you should.
So for example, just because
you can use some of these
great new CSS3 elements doesn't
mean you always should
use those on your page.
You want to make sure that
you're keeping your user in
mind and making sure that
everything that you do goes
down to the bottom line, and
that's affecting and
optimizing your user
experience.
So just like we've been doing
throughout this course, we're
going to focus on three primary
elements in this level--
design, markup, and style.
So let's go ahead and jump on
over the Border and Radius
site and talk about some of the
design strategy that we
used to design the site.
So we have a few content
sections on this page.
First, we have our main
promotional area which
includes an image and some
promotional copy highlighting
the brewhouse's plethora
of beer selections.
Additionally, we have links
to the two menus below.
Now, the strategy here is to
create quick hit elements that
give the user a sense
of what Border and
Radius is all about.
By including a large image,
large typographic elements,
and large links to the menus,
the user can quickly identify
what this place is all about.
We also have three content
blocks beneath which contain
more important elements that the
client wanted to feature.
Border and Radius is in the news
a lot, so this section
gives users a chance to see how
it has been received in
the community.
They also have a pretty sweet
lunch special running, so that
needs some prominence, and
Border and Radius does a lot
of e-marketing, so the client
wanted to make sure that a
email sign up was prominent
and easy to use.
Throughout a pretty simple,
grid layout, we're able to
accommodate the major features
of the site with a
little bit of flair--
namely in the beer selection
highlighting
and top promo section.
So let's move on to the markup
for this section.
So for a markup, we're going
to start with this section
that you see here.
We have a large image and then
we have a section to the
right, which contain some
important information about
their beer selections, and then
we have two key buttons
that link to the food menu
and the beer menu.
So previously before HTML5, we
might have marked up this
section like this.
We have our div id promotional
with our large image there,
and then we have an unordered
list contained within a div id
selections that showcases
the beer selection.
Now I want to call your
attention to a couple of those
elements that are within italic
and span classes.
Now, we'll get to those
later when we
actually style this section.
Finally, our two menu buttons
below are going to be included
within two anchors.
So how might we change
this to HTML5?
Well, it's actually a pretty
simple change in this case.
Since this is a grouping of
related content, we can go
ahead and replace our
div with a section.
So in this case we're going to
add our HTML section tag in
place of our div id promotional,
and there we go.
Let's take a look at our
markup in the browser.
So it's nice and clean and
semantic in HTML5.
So let's move onto our block
elements underneath our
promotional section.
So as you can see we
have three boxes--
our latest news, current
specials, and
email newsletter box.
So let's go ahead and take a
look at how we might markup
latest news.
Well, first, we have
a containing
element div id blocks.
Now, I won't be referring to
that as we move forward, but
just wanted that that's in there
as a containing element.
So previously we might have
marked up our newsbox like so
with a div id news and h2 for
the title of that box, and
then each news item we might
have marked up with a class--
so in this case, div class
news-item, with the title of
the news item, and then the
actual content beneath it.
So in HTML5, we're going to make
a couple of changes that
will help to organize our markup
a little bit better.
First, we can go ahead and
replace our div id news with
sections, because this is,
once again, a grouping of
related content.
Next, we're going to add our
header tag in place of our h2.
So in this case, we're going to
add our header tag within
an h1, with the title
Latest News.
Now, each news item is an
independent composition.
So if you remember before when
were talking about HTML5 tags,
we talked about the
article tag.
This is a great place to go
ahead and use that tag.
So we're going to replace our
div class news-item with an
article tag.
Now the next thing that we're
going to do is since we have a
title within each news item or
within each article, we can go
ahead and add another header
element with an h1.
So if you remember, I mentioned
before that you can
use HTML5 elements like the
header tag in multiple areas
of your page.
And you can see as we've marked
up this site, we've
actually used the header
tag quite a bit.
Now, that does mean that
we have a lot of header
tags in h1s.
Now, that may or may not
be a good thing.
It's still semantic HTML5, but
if you're more comfortable
using some of the older
practices in HTML, like h2s
and h3s, that's totally
fine too.
It's still going
to be semantic.
I just wanted to show you where
you could apply some of
these new tag elements, just so
you can see how you might
be able to do it
in the future.
So the final thing that we're
going to do to this section in
HTML5 is we can actually
introduce a new tag element.
In this case, it's going
to be the time tag.
Now, this is a pretty cool
little tag because before, we
might have marked up, in this
case, the published date and
where it was published for the
actual article in a paragraph
or a span tag.
Now we can use the HTML5 time
tag to actually give a little
bit more information
to the browser
about what we're rendering.
The HTML5 tag element is
made of two versions.
One is human readable, so in
this case it would be our
Monday, January 26, 2011, and
then the other is machine
readable, and this is done in
ISO format, so we're going to
have our year, month, and
day in that order.
And you can also add hours,
minutes, seconds if you wanted
to, but we're not going
to do that here.
So you can see in our code that
we've added time, date
time, in the ISO format,
2011-01-26, and then we've
also added pubdate to the
end of that string.
Now what does that do?
Well, in this case, since it's
an article pubdate tells the
browser that this is the actual
published date of the
article, as opposed to just
a generic time or date.
So this is great if you're doing
news posts or actual
articles, because you can go
ahead and tell the browser in
your markup that this is an
actual published date.
Now that we've marked up our
latest news, let's go ahead
and mark up our current
specials box.
Now this is a pretty
straightforward piece of
markup here, so I won't spend
too much time on it.
But previously before HTML5, we
might have marked it up to
look something like this.
We have our div id specials,
just like before we had our
latest news, we have our h2 with
the title, and then we
have our image with paragraph
copy underneath.
So how might we change
this to HTML5?
Well, we're going to
do two things.
First, we're going to replace
our div with a section once
again, because it's a grouping
of related content.
And then next, we're going to
add our header tag in place of
h2 for current specials.
So the final piece of
markup would be our
email newsletter box.
But in this case, we're going to
go ahead and leave that to
the next level where we can
spend a little bit more time
talking about the new elements
in HTML5 forms.
So now that we've marked up our
first two boxes, let's go
ahead and move into style.
So let's review just a little
bit about what we're going to
be styling.
First, we're going to style
our promotional area
like you see here.
So if you can remember, we have
our large image, we have
our beer selections copy,
and then we have
our two menu items.
So let's go ahead and get our
basic styles out of the way
first like you see here.
Now what we're going to do it
our image is we're actually
going to add a box shadow to
sort of set it out of the page
a little bit more and help to
match the rest of the styling
on the site.
So in this case, we're going
to use our vendor prefixes
first and add a box shadow
like you see here.
Let's take a look at how that
might render in the browser.
Now we could leave our image
just like that, but let's go
ahead and add a hover state.
We're going to use our new CSS3
transform property and
we're going to use the code
like you see here.
So in this case, we're going to
scale the image by 10%, 1.1
and we're actually going
to rotate it
negative two degrees.
So in this case, we're going
to rotate it to the left.
Remember with the CSS3 transform
property, you're
actually not going to affect the
other elements surrounding
the image, so we're actually
getting get a hover state that
looks like this.
It's a way to interact with the
image a little bit more
without negatively affecting the
rest of your site, which
is pretty cool.
Now let's move on to our copy,
highlighting the beer
selections at Border
and Radius.
Now before, I might have used
images to render what you see
here, but thanks to CSS3, we
can now to render this
natively in the browser.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at how we might do that.
First, let's recall
our markup.
So in this case, we have
an unordered list
with three list items.
And once again, remember, I
mentioned let's take note on
italic and span classed that
we have in each of those,
because we're going to be
styling those individually to
create some cool effects.
So here are basic styles.
Now if you notice, we're going
to use LeagueGothic again,
which we @font-face'd earlier, and
we're also going to add a
text shadow.
In this case, we're going to add
a letter press effect like
we talked about before to sort
of have the text sit
inside of the page.
Alright, so let's take a look
at how that renders.
Now the first image is our
styles before we added any of
our CSS3 properties, and the
second image is what it looks
like after we've added our font
face and our text shadow.
So this looks good, but I'd
like to be able to do
something a little bit
more to the text.
And if you remember, our on is
actually sitting within a
italic element, so let's
go ahead and style that
a little bit more.
So in this case, we're going
to use a different font,
MarketingScriptRegular, Script
which we @font-face'd earlier.
So now if we take a look at
how that renders in the
browser, you can see we have a
nice, subtle little effect on
the on portions of our copy,
which helps to set
it apart even more.
Finally, we're going
to style the actual
numbers of this section.
So here you can see how our
styles might be coded out.
Once again, we're going to use
LeagueGothic, but in this case
we're going to increase the
font size to 75 pixels.
Now, additionally, we've added
another class to the middle
list item just to make sure
that it aligns properly.
So let's go ahead and take a
look at how that renders in
the browser.
So the first image you see is
our styles without our CSS3
properties added in, and the
second image is after we've
added our CSS3 properties.
So this is pretty cool, because
previously we would
have only been able to
do this with images.
Now we can do this natively in
CSS3 and create some pretty
cool effects and an optimal
user experience.
Alright, finally, we're going
to style our two menu item
buttons, so let's go ahead
recall our markup to make sure
we understand what we're
working with here.
So if you remember, we have our
two anchor elements that
are virtually the same,
so that's nice.
Let's go ahead and take care
of our basic styles first.
So here they are, and one thing
to take note of-- as you
can notice in our background,
we've set our RGBA color but
we've also set an opacity
value of 0.5.
Now later on, we're going to
set a hover state because
these are links, and we're
actually going to make this
image a little bit
less opaque.
So we'll get to that
in a minute.
So let's take a look at how our
buttons render with just
these basic styles added.
Alright, so let's get a little
crazy with CSS3.
So in this case, we're going to
add rounded corners again
but we're going to do things
a little bit differently.
We're only going to round the
top left and bottom right
corners of these buttons.
So we're going to add code
that looks like this.
We have our vendor prefixes
first and then our standard
properties, but you can see that
instead of just saying
border radius, we've actually
declared which
corner we want to round--
so in this case, top left and
bottom right, and we've given
a value of 10 pixels for each.
Additionally, we're going to add
a text shadow to our text
to give it that letter press
effect once again.
So let's go ahead and take a
look at how that renders.
And as you can see, we no
longer have just basic
rectangles.
We're able to round certain
corners of the image, which is
kind of neat.
It's a little bit different than
going ahead and rounding
all of the corners.
Alright, so we're
not quite done.
Finally, we're going to add a
transition to our menu buttons.
So in this case, we're going
to set our vendor prefixes
first with our standard property
after, and we're
going to transition all of the
elements, so the button and
the text included
in the button.
We're going to do that for 0.3
seconds and we're going to use
our default ease in
out function.
We're also going to add our
hover state with the styles
that you see here.
Now, remember I mentioned before
that our static state
had an opacity value of 0.5.
Now we're going to add an
opacity value of 0.9.
So the static state of the
button is actually more opaque
and when you roll over it,
it's going to become less
opaque, which is going to be
kind of a neat little rollover
effect that you can do with
just a few easy CSS3
properties.
Let's go ahead and add a few
more styles to our text.
So in this case, we have a span
element in our text on
the button and we're going to
add MarketingScript as the
font for that element.
And then lastly, we're going
to add a pseudoclass to the
right button just to make sure
that it aligns properly with
the rest of our elements.
So let's go ahead and take a
live look in the browser at
how all of this renders.
So we have our large promo
image, and you can see the
rollover effect we added with
our transform property.
Additionally, we have our beer
selections copy, styled with
@font-face and text shadow, and
our menu buttons provide
clear call to action points with
great CSS3 properties,
including the smooth transition
that we created for
the hover state.
OK, so now that we're done
styling our promotional
section, let's go ahead and move
onto our block elements
underneath.
So first, let's look at the
basics styles that we're going
to use to style some of the
shared elements that each of
these boxes have.
Alright, so here are
our basic styles.
So we have our blocks containing
element, we have
our section, we have a
pseudoclass for the last box
in this section, and then we
also have our shared titles
across all three boxes, which
in this case, we're going to
go with MarketingScriptRegular.
So let's go ahead and focus now
on the latest newsbox and
look how we might style that.
So let's go ahead and recall
our markup for
this particular box.
We have our section id news,
we have our header for the
title Latest News, and then
we have our various
news items or articles.
Alright, so first we're going to
get our basic styles out of
the way that pretty much just
styles out the text in each
one of our articles.
So you can see how we might
style those here.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at how that might render in
the browser.
So the first image that you
see is before we've added
these properties and the second
image is after we've
added some of these new
properties to our elements.
Alright, now we could stop
there, but we're actually
going to create a pretty cool
little hover state for each of
our articles.
So let's look at the
basic style that
we're going to need.
Now, one thing I want to call
your attention to in this case
is the width property.
Currently, it's at 285 pixels.
Now, for our rollover state,
we're actually going to create
a rollover effect in which the
background extends out of the
containing box.
So I just want you to keep that
width in mind-- we'll
come back to it in a minute.
So the first thing that we're
going to do is we're going to
add rounded corners.
But just like our menu buttons
in our promotional section,
we're not going to round
every corner.
In this case, we're only going
to round the corners on the
right side-- so, the top right
and the bottom right--
and we would do this by
providing the code like this.
We have our vendor prefixes
and then our standard
properties, and in this case,
we have top right and bottom
right with a radius
of five pixels.
So next, we're going to
add a transition.
Now we could just use a basic
hover state so when you roll
over that particular item it
would just have a standard
rollover effect, but with CSS3
we can create pretty cool
transitions for our hover
states, so that's what we're
going to do here, and we're
actually going to create two
transitions.
So the first that we're going to
do is transition the width.
We're actually going to have the
background break outside
of the containing box, and then
the second thing we're
going to do is have the
background transition as well.
So here's the code that
we're going to use
to make that happen.
Our first transition involves
the width and we're going to
say linear, because we want it
to happen on a linear model.
And the second transition that
we're going to use is we're
actually going to transition
the background--
in this case, we're going
to have it ease.
Finally, we're going to add our
hover state, and in this
case, we're going to add an
opacity value of 0.5.
If you remember, our background
previously didn't
have any color.
It was just the standard
background of
the containing element.
In this case, we want to add a
color so that when you hover
over it, the background can
transition into a color, but
we'd like to keep it semi-opaque
so that it brings
out some of the texture from
the underlying elements.
So let's go ahead and take a
live look at how that renders
to give you a good idea
of what we can
accomplish with CSS3.
First, let's take a quick look
at our news section without all
the CSS3 properties
that we added in.
Now you can see, it's fairly
basic and kind of
boring, to be honest.
Now let's see how much better
this section looks by adding a
few simple CSS3 properties, and
check out the nifty hover
effect that we added through
CSS transitions.
We're able to break the confines
of the box, we've got
rounded corners, and we've got
our opacity value that really
helps to spruce up
this section.
Alright, so our last task
is to style the
current specials section.
Now let's go ahead and recall
our markup, and if you can
remember, it's pretty
straightforward.
We have our section, our header,
our image, and then we
have our paragraph
copy underneath.
So let's go ahead and get our
basic styles out of the way,
and as I mentioned, these are
pretty straightforward
But one thing we want to
focus on is the image.
Now, we could leave the images
static, but let's go ahead and
add a pretty cool
hover effect.
So in this case, we're going to
do a similar thing like we
did with our promotional image
above and we're going to add a
CSS transform property.
We're going to rotate it
negative five degrees.
So in this case, when we hover
over it, it's going to rotate
a little bit to the left and
just give a nice subtle user
experience factor.
And let's go ahead and check out
what that looks like when
you hover over this element.
Alright, so let's go back to our
Border and Radius site and
do a quick review of all of the
elements that we styled
and marked up in this level.
Alright, so let's do a
quick review here.
We have our promo section with
our large promo image and its
nifty little hover state
that we created.
We have our beer selections
elements rendered in rich web
fonts, we have our menu buttons
with rounded corners,
text shadow, and a nice smooth
transition on hover.
And as we move into our block
elements, we've already hit on
our news section and how much
the CSS3 properties add to the
overall experience, including
that hover state.
And then finally, we've got our
specials section and our
nifty little hover state
for our image.
We've managed to create a rich
user experience with just a
few subtle effects in CSS3 and
effectively organized our
markup using HTML5.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Alright, so now it's time for
you to apply what you've
learned in this level.
So let's go ahead and
jump into the code.