You're watching Rails Best
Practices, Super Deluxe
Championship Edition.
I'm Gregg Pollack, and
this is lab three.
When we talk about model best
practices, the most common
thing you hear over and over
is that us Rails developers
need to get better at indexing
our foreign keys in our
database, right?
So obviously, if we're going
to do current_user.tweets,
we're going to want to
have a migration
that adds that index.
Hopefully we added it when we
created the table in the first
place, but you can add it after
the fact if you have to.
But let's take a look at
a more complex example.
Let's say we have a series
of queries here in our
application that
get run a lot.
So we need to make sure that we
have the proper indexes in
our database.
What might those indexes
look like?
Well, for the first query, you
might want to add an index
that looks like this.
It's a compound index of the
user_id and created_at field.
So you even need to index stuff
that you're ordering by.
That's important.
So the second query, where we're
doing a topic, you might
want to add the compound
index with started_training
and mentions.
So again, something from
the where clause
and the order clause.
There's two things you really
want to keep in mind when it
comes to indexes.
First of all, the more indexes
you have, the longer it takes
to re-index the table.
So every time you create a
record or update a record, the
more indexes you have, the
slower it's going to happen.
The second thing you need to
keep in mind is that if you
have a query, a long running
query, that only runs a few
times a week, who really
cares, right?
When it comes to your database,
you should only be
really caring about the queries
that take a long time,
and are getting run
very often.
How do you figure out what
those queries are?
Well, you might want to use
a tool like New Relic.
Here's some screens
from New Relic.
So New Relic RPM gives you, over
here, the queries that
are the most time-consuming.
This is one table they have.
They also have a database
report.
If you look closely here, you
can see-- now this is the most
popular query, total time it
takes, and the average time.
So in this case, even though
it's a popular query, it only
takes 6.4 milliseconds
to run, so we don't
really need to refactor.
If, on the other hand, it was
taking, say, 300, 400
milliseconds, you might want to
look and see if maybe we're
missing an index.
A few years ago, the
guys from Less
Everything wrote this article.
The title is "Use Attribute
Protected or We Will Hack
You." And they basically showed
some of the code they
used to hack a friend
of theirs' website.
The most important bit here is
right here, where you can see
that they're writing an is_admin
column to true on the
new users that they're
creating.
So obviously, to protect
yourself, you need to make
sure that you're doing
one of two things.
In their article, they used
attribute protected is admin
to protect that column
from batch updates.
However, there's another way you
can write that, and it's
more of a best practice.
Really, you should be using
attribute accessible rather
than protected, because when
it comes to security, white
lists are better, right?
This is so you don't shoot
yourself in the foot later.
You might add columns later, and
you want to force yourself
to have to add that column to
attribute accessible if you
want it to be able
to batch update.
Otherwise, it'll stay safe.
I'm going to show you some model
code, and I want you to
try to figure out what's
wrong with it.
So before we create, we're
setting a time zone.
What's wrong with this?
Well, if we're always setting a
column to a static default,
we shouldn't be doing
that in the model.
We should be doing that
in our database.
Our database has that ability.
So here, you can see a migration
where we're changing
the column to give it
the default of EST.
Now let's take a look at an
example where we couldn't set
the default in the database.
So here you can see,
we have before
create, set trend, ending.
So whenever we create this
topic, we're going to set the
time when it should
finish trending.
And if you do the math here,
you'll see that basically
we're saying, finish trending
one week from now.
Rails comes with a set of date
helpers, which can help us
simplify code that
looks like this.
So instead of having that math
there, we can say time now
plus 1.week.
We can even take it a step
further, and make it so that
finish trending is
1.week.from_now
Pretty nice.
If our application had a lot
of topics, and we want to
optimize this code, there's
something we can do to make it
even better.
You see that 1.week?
Every time this method gets
called, every time a topic is
created, we're calling 1.week?
So to make it even better, what
we can do is take the 1.week,
move it up into a global
variable we're going to call
TRENDING_PERIOD, and then we
write TRENDING_PERIOD.from_now
in our method, and that
means 1.week is only going to
be run once.
I thought it'd be useful at this
point to take a look at
all the different call
backs we can use on
Active Record models.
So you can see here, these are
all the call backs when we
create an object, updating
an object,
and deleting an object.
Also, I want to make sure you
know about all the different
Rails date helpers.
So you've got the ability to
do 1.minute, 2.hours,
3.days.
You can use the singular
or the plural form.
You can also do things like
beginning_of_day, beginning_of_week,
or end_of_month, end_of_quarter
next_week, previous_week,
and then you can
add modifiers onto
the end, like 2.weeks.ago
or 3.weeks.from_now.
So you know how when somebody
follows you on Twitter, you
get an email that looks
something like this.
So let's think about a moment.
What happens there?
So somebody follows you, it
probably puts something onto a
background queue, and
then sends an email.
What might that code
look like?
So here's our Following model.
And after_create, we want to
send_follower_notification.
We want to check to see the user
wants to receive emails,
and if they do, queue up
a new_follower_email.
The first way we could refactor
this code is by moving the
method to queue up the email
into the after create, and then
specify a method that's
going to call to check
to see if it's true.
So it's only going to queue up
an email if that if method
returns true.
The next way we can simplify
this even further is by
wrapping the whole thing
inside of a proc.
So it's going to run this proc
to see if it's true.
If it is true, then it will
queue up a new follower email.
Next up, let's take a look at
a custom validation, and
figure out how we can
improve on it.
So here, you can see that we're
validating to see if the
name is suitable, basically
checking for swear words, and
if it's not suitable, if it's
inappropriate, then we're
going to go ahead and add an
error to this model for the
name, which is now
inappropriate.
So how can we improve
this code?
The first thing we can do is
wrap validation itself in a
method we're going to call
appropriate content.
We're then going to say validate
appropriate content,
and it will get run when we
attempt to save the model.
However, there may be multiple
fields in our application--
not just in this model, but in
other models that we want to
check to see if it has
any bad words in it.
How might we do that and
reuse this code?
Well, it might look something
like this.
So first of all, in our topic,
we're going to do validates
name appropriate true.
So just basically going to
follow the same convention for
doing validations.
Then we're going to create
a new file called
appropriate_validator.rb.
We're going to put it in
our lib directory.
This class is, of course,
going to be called
AppropriateValidator, and it's
going to extend from
ActiveRecord::EachValidator.
It has to define a method called
validate_each, which
sends in record, attribute,
and value-- all the values
that we're pretty much
interested in.
So ContentModerator
is suitable.
We want to check, just make sure
the value is suitable,
and if it's not, we're going to
add an error to the record,
and say that attribute
is inappropriate.
One thing that's worth
mentioning before we move on
is that you shouldn't forget
to require this.
Depending on where you put this
EachValidator file, you
may need to require it at
the top of your model.
In this case, I put it in the
lib directory, and lib isn't
autoloaded by default anymore
with Rails 3.
What that means is that to make
this work, I would have
to add that require line
at the top of my model.
If I made it so that everything
in the lib
directory was autoloaded,
then I wouldn't have
to worry about it.
If you've been creating Rails
applications for a long time,
you definitely did something
ugly, which look like this at
some point, where inside of your
migration, you created
models in the database, what
you might call seeds.
Well, back in Rails 2, we
were given a better way
to deal with this.
We have a seeds.rb file in our
DB directory, and we can put
all of these model create
methods in there.
To run these models, you
just run rake db:seed.
However, in this case, I ran
this, and it wasn't working.
Do you know why that was?
Well, I looked inside the topic
model, and it turns out
I had attribute protected in
there, so mentions wasn't
getting set when I tried
to set it this way.
To fix that, I refactored it.
I put all the topics I wanted
to store inside of a hash,
iterated through each of the
topics, and then created each
of them by setting the
variables explicitly.
You'll notice here, I'm
using the block syntax
of the create method.
It kind of makes it a little
bit more readable.
But what if we wanted to be
able to update the seed?
So maybe I've got another couple
topics I want to add,
but I've already populated
my database.
I want to be able
to update it.
What code would I add to this?
Well, one way I could solve
this problem is by adding
topic . destroy all, so that
every time I ran this file, it
would destroy all the topics
and recreate them.
However, this is a little bit
dangerous, for a few reasons--
one of which is that if a lot of
relationships, you've got a
lot of models, lot of seeds that
relate to each other, it
might be dangerous to just go
around deleting stuff, because
you might be left with stray
models in your database.
So how do we fix that?
Well, one way we could do
that is by using
find_or_initialize_by_name.
So what this is going to do is
it's going to go into the
database, search for a topic
by the attribute name.
If it doesn't find it,
then it's going to
create a new one.
But if it does find it, it's
just going to return that.
So either we're going to find
it or create a new one.
Then I'm calling
the tap method.
The tap method just sends in the
object that got returned
by the finder initialize by, and
then I'm going to set the
mentions, and then I'm
going to save it.
Sorry if you've never seen
those two methods before.
It may seem a little
overwhelming.
So find_or_initialize_by tries
to find the object.
If it does find it,
it returns it.
Otherwise, it initializes
it and returns it.
And tap is just going
to send whatever it
returns into the block.
So it's basically going to set
t equal to whatever it
returns, and then we can
basically set mentions, and
then call t.save.
Congratulations.
You're over halfway done now,
and it's time to get your
hands dirty with the level
three challenges.
Good luck.