You're watching Rails Best
Practices: Super Deluxe
Championship Edition.
I'm Greg Pollack.
And this is level five.
[HUMMING]
You've made it all the way to
the final level, level five,
where we're going to be taking
a look at how to improve some
of your view code.
So remember, the example we're
working through is Twitter.
And on the sidebar of this main
Twitter page, we've got a
bunch of information.
And we're going to take a closer
look, in particular, at
the Following and
Followers list.
It may seem intuitive, but one
of the most important best
practices for view is to keep
the queries out of your
view.
So for this example, we might
have something that reads like
this, where we're listing out
who we should follow.
And it really should have
an instance variable.
So let's go ahead
and add that.
So we're going to move the query
down into our tweets
controller, store it in
an instance variable
called who_to_follow.
And then just access that who
to follow instance variable
back up in our view.
Let's take a look at some
more view code.
So here we have a div, where
we're listing out our
followers, the current count
of our followers, going
through and listing out each
of them with an image.
And then down below, we have
the people we're following,
the following count.
And then we're looping through
each of the people that we
recently followed.
This piece of code is a good
candidate for a helper for two
different reasons.
First of all, we've got a lot
of complex Ruby code in our
HTML, which makes it look
a little bit cryptic.
And second of all, you can see
here, both of these snippets
of HTML are very similar.
So similar that we could create
a single helper that
creates both sets of divs.
Once we create our helper,
our view is going to look
something like this,
where we have two
different Follow boxes.
And we pass in all of the
attributes needed
to render the HTML.
So now if we open up the tweets
helper, we can write
the follow_box method.
The first thing we're going to
do is just simply store the
HTML in an str variable.
We're then going to go through
each of the recent followers,
store that in the string, and
then call raw on the HTML
before it gets returned so that
it's not escaped when we
print it out on the page.
I know, I know, this helper
looks really ugly.
So let's go ahead and start
cleaning it up.
The first thing we can
do is use a proper
link_to and image_tag.
So let's go ahead and
rearrange it.
So we can say, link_to user do
So we're using the block form
of the link_to method.
image_tag, just like that.
The next way we can clean
this up is by
using some HTML helpers.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So here you can see
we're going to use
content_tag, div class.
And then content_tag.
And then we're going to
enclose it in a block.
The last way we can improve this
code is by trying to get
rid of that str variable.
It's just sort of annoying
that we have
to carry that around.
To get rid of that variable,
we can rewrite it like so.
So here you can see we're just
adding a bunch of these
strings together.
We're doing a collect instead
of an each, an then joining
the collect together.
So now we're going to take a
look at another example from
this Twitter page.
We're going to look at
the Trends section.
If you've played around with
this before, you'll know that
it's Ajax friendly.
So when you change the country,
it'll actually change
the trends.
So we're basically going to
create a partial for that
particular section.
You know, you create a partial
for two reasons.
One, if we're going to reuse
that content elsewhere.
And the second reason you might
want to do it is if
you're doing some form of Ajax
and you want to re-render that
part of the page.
So here in our indexed view, we
might have a Trends title.
And then we're rendering out
the trending partial.
Our trending partial might
look something like this.
We have a trending area, which
might be the country.
We then loop through all the
different topics which are
trending, link to them, and add
an image_tag if they're
marked as promoted.
The first thing we can do to
improve this code is up at the
top of the page, instead of
doing render partial trending,
we can just do render
trending.
The other thing that's kind of
gross about this partial is
that we have some instance
variables in there.
It's sort of a bad practice to
have instance variables in
your partials.
So let's go ahead and
move those up into
our original view.
We'll then specify local
variables, which we'll then
use inside of the partial.
In this case, called
area and topics.
You see in that loop we're
pretty each of the topics
using an li, or list item?
Well, if there's a standardized
way of printing
out topics that we're using
throughout the website, we
might consider pulling that
out into its own partial,
which might look something
like this.
So maybe inside of the topics
view directory, we have a
topic partial, like so.
And then inside of our trending
partial, we would
just do render topic,
topic, topic, topic.
There's a lot of topics
there, isn't there?
Yeah, not so nice.
There's a better way
to write this.
We can simply do render topic.
And by default, it's going to
use the class name to find the
partial in the topics directory
called topic.
There's one more way we can
simplify this further by
bringing the collection into
the partial syntax.
So we simply say, render
partial => topics/topic,
collection => topics.
And it's going to use that
partial and iterate through it
for every item in
that collection.
Again, there's a better
way to write this.
We can simply write,
render topics.
And if everything is named
right, it's going to
print out our list.
Next up, we're going to look at
a few small view snippets
that might look familiar.
If you've got some code that
looks like this, where you're
checking to see if something is
blank, you can also write
that as, unless user.email?
So you can rid of using
the blank keyword.
Also we have something
that looks like,
if user.email.present?
So present is the opposite
of blank.
We can write, if user.email?
Let's say we want to print out
the location of the user based
on what location information
we have.
We can do something like this.
So we want to print out the city
if we have the city, the
state if we have the state.
Otherwise just "unknown."
There's a problem
here, though.
If city or state is actually a
blank string, it's going to
return just that blank string.
So how might we get
around that?
One way you may have dealt with
this problem is simply by
checking to see if
it's present.
And if it's present,
set a variable.
And then you can really do
city or state or "unknown."
But there's a better way
to do this, using
the presence method.
So here, it's checking to
see if city is blank.
If it's blank, then it's
returning false and moving on
to the next item.
Is state blank?
Maybe it's not like blank.
Maybe there's something there.
And it's going to return
it at that point.
Here's some of view code where
we're either printing out the
city or "unknown."
Well, what might happen
if city is nil?
Well, in this case, it's going
to return undefined method
titleize Nil:NilClass.
Not so good.
How might you deal with this?
Well, the simple answer might be
to just add a conditional.
If the user city exists,
then titleize it.
Otherwise, return unknown.
You might write this all in
one line using the ternary
operator, something like this.
But there's a better way
to do this using try.
So here we can do,
user.city.try(:titleize)
In this case, titleize will only
be called if city exists.
Otherwise, it's just going
to return "unknown."
Next up, we're going to take
a look at some HTML that we
might use if we had
favorite tweets.
So we're back in our index view
where we're iterating
through each of the tweets.
Our div has a unique ID of tweet
underscore tweet ID.
And we have a special class
only if that tweet is a
favorite of ours.
We're then going to print
out the tweet itself
and close the div.
Since we have so much Ruby in
our HTML, this might be a good
candidate to refactor
into a helper.
In this case, our helper's
going to be
called tweet_div_for.
And it's going to be
a block helper.
We're going to define this
block helper inside the
tweets_helper file.
We're sending in the tweet,
the user, and the block.
First, we're going to
check to see if
this tweet is a favorite.
We're going to create
the class variable.
We're then going to
do div for, tweet.
When you send a record into div
for like this, it's going
to create an ID consisting of
the class name followed by the
ID, just as we want.
We're then going to
set the class.
And then we're going to yield.
What yield prints in this
example is the tweet.status.
Now let's take a deeper look
at yield and some best
practices we can use it with.
So you're probably most familiar
with yield because
you've seen it inside your
layouts, which looks
something like this.
But what happens when we want to
insert some content into a
certain part of our layout that
our normal view doesn't
have access to?
Well, this is where we might
want to create another yield,
give it a name, like sidebar.
Then in our view, we can create
content for block and
specify the HTML we
want printed in
that specific location.
But what if all of the actions
in our tweets controller need
that sidebar?
Well, we could take all of
the content for blocks.
And we could copy and paste them
into each of the views,
which wouldn't be
very efficient.
Or we can do something else.
Maybe what we do here is create
a new layout for
our tweets controller
called with_sidebar.
The with sidebar layout has our
content_for(:sidebar) block.
And then we tell our application
to render the
normal application layout.
Did I blow your mind?
I know it's a little complex.
Let's go over it
one more time.
So first, we have our
layout with sidebar.
The layout with sidebar defines
our content_for.
And then we tell our application
to render the
normal layout.
Some people call this technique
nested layouts.
And it's really beneficial when
you have a controller and
you want every action in that
controller to render
a content_for block.
I've got one more example I show
you guys of using yield
for a best practice.
And it has to do with meta
content and the title at the
top of your page.
You see, you take a look
at this page here.
This is the show tweet page, if
you're actually viewing an
individual tweet.
And I'm calling attention
here to the title.
So here's our application
layout.
You can see here we
have a title.
We're optionally setting
a description.
And we also have a default
if that hasn't been set.
And same thing with key words.
This is a common pattern you may
have used in one of your
Rails apps.
And then, of course, in your
controller, you set the title
of the description
and the keywords
when it really matters.
In this case, we're setting
it on the show action.
And we're setting the title
equal to the user name, the
description equal to the status,
and key words equal to
the hashtags.
I consider this a bad practice
for two reasons.
First of all, you're cluttering
up your controller
with instance variables.
And so every time you need to
set these, you've got three
more instance variables in every
one of your actions.
The second reason why this kind
of sucks is that you're
dealing with stuff that doesn't
really belong in the
controller.
These are sort of
view concerns.
So we should probably
figure out how to
move them to the view.
So how might we do
that using yield?
In this case, we're going to
replace each of our instance
variables with yield.
What does this get us?
Well, now we can go into
each of our views.
And we can use content_for to
set title, description, and
keywords and keep
it in the view,
where I think it belongs.
If we wanted to make this
look even nicer, we
could create a helper.
So in our application
helper, I'm going to
create a title method.
I'll create a description
method.
And I'll create a
keywords method.
Then in our view, all we simply
have to do is title,
description, and keywords.
And it's become a lot cleaner
and easier to read.
Well, you've watched
all the videos now,
level one through five.
All that's left is to do the
level five challenges to
complete the course.
Good luck.