Hello,
I'm Gregg Pollack, and you're
watching Rails Best Practices
Super Deluxe Championship
Edition, Level One.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Level one is entitled
Controllers in Space.
So we're going to be going
through and doing some
controller best practices.
As we go through, you're going
to notice sometimes we use sad
smiley faces to signify that
we have some bad code that
needs to be refactored.
And then sometimes we'll be
having happy smiley faces,
which will show you that this
code has been refactored and
it is a best practice.
They should be useful when you
go back and reference the
slides later to figure out
which is the sad code and
which is the happy code.
The example we're going to be
using throughout this whole
tutorial is going
to be Twitter.
So you're going to see code that
we might have written if
we were writing Twitter
from scratch.
And we'll, of course, show you
some sad code and how to make
happy Twitter code.
The first best practice we're
going to take a look at is a
pretty common one, called fat
model, skinny controller,
which, of course, talks about
taking code out of your
controller into your model, so
your model should be fatter,
not too fat, and your
controller's skinny.
So let's take a look
at some code.
The tweets controller
has a retweet action
which fetches a tweet.
If the person who created that
tweet is us, well then we're
going to simply return
"Sorry, you can't retweet
your own tweets."
If we've already retweeted that
tweet, well, we're simply
going to say, "you've already
retweeted this."
Otherwise, we're going to go
ahead and create the retweet
like this.
You can see that string we're
putting together with the RT
keyword that you see across
Twitter a lot.
We'll then give notice that we
successfully retweeted and
redirect back to showing
that particular tweet.
The first thing we're going to
do to refactor this is we're
going to take those Flash
notices and we're going to
move them up to the
top of the action.
We'll then move the redirect
up to simplify this
controller.
The rest of this code we're
going to refactor, and we're
going to refactor it into a
method called retweet_by on
the Tweet model.
So we're going to send in who
is retweeting this tweet.
Then in the tweet.rb model,
we'll go ahead and define the
retweet_by method.
It's going to send in the
retweeter, so retweeter is the
user who's trying to
retweet obviously.
And then, we just need to
specify self where we need to.
And as you can see here, this
method is going to return a
string, which then gets
set into the notice.
Next we're going to take a look
at two different types of
scope to improve our code.
So let's take a look inside the
index action of our tweets
controller.
Here we might want to pull a
list of tweets, and we might
also want to pull a
list of trends.
There's a couple ways we
can improve this code.
The first thing you might notice
is that we're not using
the new active relation method
chaining syntax.
So let's go ahead and
refactor that.
So up at the top, we're going
to change that to use the
method chaining.
And let's go ahead and do that
with the second query.
The next thing we can do to
refactor is you'll notice that
we're querying for the tweets
for a particular user.
Well, a user has_many
tweets, so why not
scope it by that user?
So we'll change this so it reads
current_user.tweets, and
we've properly scoped it
to the particular user.
We can also now take this code
and put it on a single line,
since we've simplified it.
The next type of scope we're
going to be talking about is a
named scope.
So inside of our model, we're
going to define a scope
keyword that's going to be scope
:recent because there may
be different parts of an
application where we want to
query for recent tweets.
In this case, a recent tweet
is going to be defined by a
specific order.
So we're going to take order
from out of the prior query
and move it down
into the model.
So now we can use the recent
named scope in our original
query inside of our action.
On most of the screens that
we're going to see tweets,
most the time we want them
listed from newest to oldest.
So you might argue that this
should be the default scope.
So we can do something
like this.
If this particular order is the
default scope, then we can
refactor our original code
and simply get rid
of that recent keyword.
Now let's flip back over to the
second query that we had
in our action.
So this is where we've got
all of the trends.
How might we use named scope
in this instance?
Well, maybe in the topic
model we'll have a
scope called trending.
So let's go ahead and move
down the query methods.
So now we can specify topic
trending limit five.
However, this query is only
going to work once, the first
time we run it.
Why is that?
Well, if we run it the first
time, it's going to print out
a date and time that
looks like this.
The second time we run it, it'll
print out a date and
time that looks like that.
This is the same time,
you'll notice.
This is because of the way Rails
deals with named scopes.
The first time it runs
the scope, it
actually creates a method.
And the second time you run it,
it just runs that method.
So how might we fix this?
Well, what we might do here to
make it work is add a lambda.
So we wrap in a lambda,
it works properly.
And every time someone calls
that scope, it regenerates
that date and time.
There's another way we can
improve the scope and that's
by maybe adding a parameter.
So we're going to send in the
number of trending topics we
want it to return.
In this example, we have five.
How might we do that?
Well, since we're using a
lambda, we can just specify a
block parameter called num.
And we can specify limit num.
And it works, just like that.
However, this allows us to do
topic trending five, but what
if we wanted to be able to do
something like topic trending
to get back all of the
trending topics?
If we ran this code, it would
give us back wrong number of
args, zero for one.
So how might we fix this?
Well, in Ruby 1.9, we were given
the ability to specify a
default for a block parameter.
We can simply specify
num equals nil.
We could also make
this a number.
So if we wanted to default the
limit to five, we could say
num equals 5.
But the interesting part about
putting equals nil is that
means it's simply going
to ignore the limit.
Since nil gets passed into
limit, it's simply going to
return all of the
trending topics.
Now you saw earlier that we're
specifying a default scope for
our tweet model.
But what we want to override
the default scope?
Can we simply do a query
like this where we
specify order status?
That's actually not
going to work.
It's actually going to keep
the order of created at
descending.
And it's not going to
order by status.
Sometimes you might want to
override the default status.
How do you do that?
Well, you can do that
using the unscoped
keyword as you see here.
And now it's going to properly
order by the status column.
Earlier in this video,
you saw some code
that looked like this.
We're creating a retweet.
Now we can improve this
code a little bit by
properly using the scope.
So if we're creating a retweet
for a particular user, why not
scope it to that user?
So we might have some code that
instead looks something
like this, where we do
current_user.tweets.create
and then we
send in the parameters.
Next up we're going
to be talking
about controller filters.
Now in Rails for Zombies, if
you watch that, we had this
example here where we had a
Tweet.find(params[:id]), and that
was happening in a bunch
of different actions.
And we moved that up into its
own method called get_tweet.
And then we specified a before
filter for that method and
then specified that should
only happen on the edit,
update, and destroy actions.
Well, there's a couple things
wrong about doing this that
aren't so much of
a best practice.
The first thing that's a little
fishy is that get tweet
method should probably be in
a private section of our
controller, maybe down
at the bottom.
Another reason why people don't
think this is a best
practice is because it's kind of
hiding instance variables.
What does that mean?
Well, some people have the idea
that instance variables
should only be declared inside
of your actions.
They should never be hidden in
some private methods at the
bottom of your file that
you might forget about.
So how might we fix this?
First we might declare the tweet
variable inside each of
our actions and have
each of them call
the get_tweet method.
Another best practice along
the same lines is that you
might want to have parameters
only being accessed from
inside the action.
So let me show you what
that might look like.
So here we're referencing the
parameters and sending that
into our get_tweet method,
which now has another
parameter itself called
tweet_id.
And you might be asking
yourself, at this point, well,
what's the point of a helper
if it's that simple?
And you might have a point.
In this case, you might just
want to do Tweet.find(params[:id])
in each of those.
But for more complex examples,
where you want to be able to
test each part of your
controller, you definitely
might want to encapsulate
that inside of a method.
So what are some good examples
of where you do want filters?
Well, if you have any sort of
authorization, that's a good
use of filters, any
sort of logging.
Or maybe you have a wizard,
maybe a multi-step form where
somebody goes through different
steps, and you might
want to control some of
that through a filter.
So let's take a quick look at
a couple different ways you
can use filters.
So here you can see we're using
it for authorization.
We can use the only keyword.
We can also use the except
keyword to specify which
actions shouldn't
run this filter.
If we want a filter to be run
across all of our actions and
all of our controllers, we can
put it in our application
controller.
In this case, if we're requiring
login, we don't want
it across all of our pages.
For example, we wouldn't want
it on our sign in form.
So in that case, we might want
to use the skip_before_filter
syntax like you see here.
So that pretty much
wraps up Level One:
Controllers in Space.
And now it's your turn to take
some of the code you learned
and apply them to the challenges
in this level.
[MUSIC PLAYING]