Hello.
I'm Gregg Pollack, and you're
watching Rails Best Practices
Super Deluxe Championship
Edition, Level Two.
[VIDEO GAME SOUNDS]
Welcome to Level Two, Controller
Command, where
we're going to be taking a look
at a few more controller
best practices.
The first thing we're going to
take a look at is a poor
implementation of Twitter's
Settings pages here.
So you can see here, we've got
the username and a couple
check boxes.
So what might look like if it
was a poor implementation?
Well inside of our user model,
you can see we have a has_one
account setting.
And our edit view might look
something like this, where
we're entering in our
name, our email.
And we're going to have some
nested fields for
account_setting here.
Those nested fields are
just going to be a
bunch of check boxes.
Here comes the sloppy code
inside of our controller.
So our create action might
look something like this.
We're getting the User values.
We're getting the AccountSetting
values from the form.
We're trying to save the User,
and only if the User is
successful, do we then save
the AccountSettings.
Then, we're going to redirect
or simply render
out the form again.
To improve this code, we're
going to implement some nested
attributes.
Once we do so, this controller
code is going
to become much simpler.
It's going to look a lot more
like the default Rails
scaffolding where we're
only worrying about
creating a user object.
To implement nested attributes,
first of all,
we're going to flip back over
to our model which has our
has_one relationship, and
we're going to add
accepts_nested_attributes_for
:account_setting.
The cool part about doing this
is that when we try to save a
user, it's going to validate,
not only against the user, but
against account_setting.
So if account_setting has any
validations that fail, it
won't save.
The next thing we have
to do is modify
our edit view slightly.
We have to make sure we
have f.fields_for.
And lastly, in our
users_controller, new action,
we're going to want to create
an account_setting for a new
user object.
We have to do this, because if
we view the new user form
without it, it's not going to
show the account setting
fields otherwise.
The next best practice we're
going to talk about is using
models that aren't Active
Record models.
And the example we're going
to use is a contact form.
So on our site, we want people
to be able to fill out a
contact form that doesn't get
stored in the database, but
basically, sends an email.
So what might this
code look like?
First, let's take a look
at our Contact Us form.
You can see here, we have a
couple text fields and a
Submit button.
Pretty simple.
Next, if we flip over to the
ContactUsController, we have a
new action and a send_email
action.
This is going to take in the
parameters from the form.
It's going to check to see if
any of the parameters are
blank, and if it is, it's going
to set a notice and
render the action.
Otherwise, let's go ahead and
send that email, tell the user
the email has been sent, and
redirect back to the root_path.
So obviously, this is the sad
code, and now we're going to
figure out how to implement a
non-Active Record model to
make it much cleaner.
So the first thing we'll do is
declare a ContactForm object,
create a new object there,
send in the parameters.
We're then going to treat it
just like an Active Record
model with its validations,
so we can say
contact_form.valid?
And we'll then send in the form
to deliver the email.
Also, in our new action, we're
going to want to create a
contact_form.
Now, there's three things that
we can clean up with this
before we take a look at
how to declare the
contact form class.
First of all, we can switch the
code to use the positive
inflection.
So here, we're saying if not.
So let's switch that around.
Instead of saying if not, we can
say if contact_form.valid?,
then do this.
Otherwise, do that.
The second thing we can improve
with this code is we
can use the new redirect
notice syntax.
So instead of having flashing
redirect on two lines, we can
have it on a single line.
Lastly with Rails 3, we were
given a way to shorten
our render syntax.
So instead of render :action
'new', we can simply say
render :new.
Now, let's slip over to the
contact form and see what we
needed to change there to
properly use our new model.
So before, we were just
specifying symbol contact.
Now, we just put in the contact
form instance variable.
Finally, let's go over and
figure out how to implement
the contact form class.
So here's our ContactForm.
It's just a plain
old Ruby model.
It has a couple attribute
accessors.
There's some getters
and setters.
And we're going to specify it
validates_presence_of :name,
:email, :body, just like we
would in a normal active
record model.
To get the validations, we need
to include
ActiveModel::Validations.
Now remember, in our view, we
changed it to use form_for
@contact_form.
Because we're using the syntax,
we also need to
include ActiveModel::Conversion
and include this persisted?
method at the bottom.
This is because the form_for
helper needs to know if we're
doing a post method and creating
something, versus
doing a put method and
updating something.
You may remember from our
controller, we're doing a
batch update to instantiate
the contact form.
In order to make that work, we
need to declare an initialize
method where we can send in a
hash of attributes which will
then set each of
our variables.
Once we have all this
code in place, we
can now use our form.
And when we miss out on fields,
it's going to give us
validations just like it would
any other active record model.
The next best practice we're
going to be talking about is
properly using REST.
So here, you see we have a
UsersController, and we've got
two actions--
one which subscribes to a
mailing list, and one which
unsubscribes to a
mailing list.
These two methods are in
our UsersController.
And when you think about what
they're doing, they're
actually creating a subscription
and destroying a
subscription.
So they kind of belong in
their own controller.
So let's go ahead and
refactor this.
So these should both go into the
Subscriptions controller.
And the first method would
probably be called create, and
the second method, we're going
to be calling destroy.
Ah, much better.
Much more RESTful.
When it comes to using REST
effectively, you really need
to use your best judgment.
You don't want to go too
far off the deep end.
There's such a thing as too
much REST, most certainly.
One example of that would
be using more than
two levels of nesting.
So in this case, users
post comments.
You don't need that
much nesting.
Also, not using REST is OK.
You should keep that
in mind as well.
In our previous example, where
we had a contact form, our
routes file looks something
like this.
We just create a get action
and post action.
Since in this case, the URL is
Contact Us, in my opinion, it
didn't make sense to create or
update a Contact Us or destroy
a Contact Us.
I didn't make too much sense.
It made more sense to me to
simply have a Contact Us
controller and ignore REST
for the time being.
The next best practice we're
going to take a look at is
properly using a Presenter.
And the example we're going to
be using is this front page of
Twitter on the right side bar.
On the right sidebar, you see
there's a lot of information
pulled from a lot different
data sources.
So if we were to implement this
and implement this badly,
it might look something
like this.
We have an index controller
with a
ton of instance variables.
There's a couple reasons
why this is bad.
Not only is it hard to maintain
and sort of sloppy,
but it's also really hard
to test properly.
So we're going to use a
presenter in this case.
And once we implement a
presenter, our controller is
going to become a
much simpler.
It's simply going to look
just like that.
To set up presenters in our
application, in my case, I
want to use a presenters
directory.
So I'm going to make sure, in my
application.rb, I've got an
autoload_path set for
that directory.
And my first presenter is going
to be created in the
Tweets folder, and I'm going
to call it index_presenter.
The first thing it will do is
initialize the presenter, and
I'll send in the current user.
Let's go ahead and move this to
the top of the page, so we
have more room to build
out our presenter.
So here, you can see there's
our old controller.
And step by step, we're going to
take one piece of that at a
time and move that into our
presenter, starting with the
followers_tweets.
So we create a followers_tweets
method.
Then we'll take two more parts
of that and create the
recent_tweet method and
the trends method.
As you saw a moment ago, to
instantiate the presenter
inside of our controller, we
do something like this.
And then in our view, to access
the data, we simply do
presenter. recent_tweet.body.
It's going to call the method,
return the recent tweet, and
we can call .body on that.
But what if we call
this presenter
method more than once?
You might look at that and go,
uh oh, it's actually going to
do two different queries.
Well, because Rails has a query
cache, it's actually
just still doing one query.
But it is creating two
different objects,
which is also bad.
How do we get around that?
Well, we use something
called memoization.
To memoize the value, we declare
an instance variable,
and we use the or
equals syntax.
Now when the recent_tweet method
is called, the first
time, it's going to
run the query.
The second time it's called,
it's actually going to return
to the cached value.
There's a second way to do
memoization in Rails, and
that's by including the
ActiveSupport::Memoizable
module and then specifying, at
the bottom of our file, which
methods we want to save.
So in this case, we're doing
memoize recent_tweet.
We can also specify additional
methods that we want to
memoize down here
at the bottom.
One of these memoization
methods is
better than the other.
You see, when you use or equals,
the value is not going
to be stored is false
or nil is returned.
So if you happen to have a
method that returns false or
equals in this case, it's
not going to get stored.
So every time you call that
method you thought you
memoized, it's going to call the
query over and over again.
So that's not so good.
That's one reason to use
this method instead.
There's another reason to use
the Active Support module, and
that is, let's say we have a
method that looks like this
that actually has a
parameter sent in.
If we have code that looks like
this and we're calling
these two different methods with
two different variables,
well, these second two methods
are going to be loaded from
the caches.
Memoize is actually going to
be saving it based on the
parameters you send into
that particular method.
It's pretty powerful.
This next best practice may be
really obvious to you, but
it's worth mentioning, and that
is to be careful about
SQL injection.
So a piece of code like this,
where you're basically taking
somebody's parameters and
putting them right into the
database, is not good, right?
You should be doing something
like this, where you're using
the question mark syntax.
You can also send in a hash,
which is going to be safe.
It's also worth mentioning that
you can have this string
with symbols inside of it and
specify the names of the
symbols as a hash.
And in this particular example
where we have two different
dates, we can actually simplify
it further and send
in a range.
Kind of neat.
Lastly, I want to go over the
Rails 3 responder syntax.
So here, we have a default
scaffold that you might get
out of the box with Rails.
And we can simplify this.
First we're going to move the
respond_tos up into the header.
We're going to specify what this
controller can respond
to, in this case HTML,
XML, and JSON.
And then in each of our actions,
we're going to
specify the instance method
that we want it
to respond to with.
So in this case with index, we
want to respond with @users.
In the case of show, we want
to respond to @user.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Congratulations, you've made
it to the end of Lab Two,
Controller Command.
Now, it's time to see if you can
get past those challenges
and make it to Level Three.