You're watching Rails Best
Practices, Super Deluxe
Championship Edition.
I'm Greg Pollack, and
this is Level Four.
Level Four is entitled Model
Bert, and as you might guess,
we're going to be going over
more model best practices,
starting with N plus
1 is Not For Fun.
So here's some code.
We're trying to find all the
recent followers, and we're
going to list them out by name,
and call .to_sentence.
So I get back something
that looks like this.
Now if we take a moment to think
about what queries are
going on in the back
end, it might look
something like this.
So first, we're getting all the
followers for our user.
Then we want to get the name, so
we select user ID 2, ID 3,
basically for all of them.
We need to get the
user account to
get the name, right?
And this is not good.
So how do we get around that?
Well, we get around that by
using the includes method.
So we're going to includes(:user),
and then it basically
does two queries, one to get the
follower, and one to get
all the users.
It's also worth mentioning
the bullet gem.
The bullet gem, you install in
your application, and it lets
you know if you're running
N plus 1 queries.
So if you have a big, bloated
app that is running tons of
queries that maybe it shouldn't
be, check out the
bullet gem.
Next up, we're going to
talk a little bit
about counter caching.
So here's some code where we're
going through a list of
tweets, we're printing out the
tweet, and then printing out
the number of times it's
been retweeted.
The output might look
something like this.
The first thing we might notice
about the output is
that it's kind of got some bad
English going on here.
It's saying one retweets,
when really, it
should be one retweet.
And so we can improve this
code by simply using the
pluralize method,
just like so.
And then when we run that, it's
going to properly do two
retweets, one retweet,
and zero retweets.
Much better.
Now let's take a look at what
this function is doing.
So basically, for each tweet,
it's going to select all
retweets where the
user ID equals
that user.
It's going to populate an array
of tweet objects, and
then it's going to
call length.
That's what happens when you
call .length on an array.
So that's obviously
not efficient.
What if we used count instead?
What would it be doing,
then, on the back end?
Well, for each tweet, select all
retweets where the user ID
is our current user, and then
it's going to properly do a
count query.
That's still obviously not any
good, because we're doing one
count query for every single
tweet every time we go
through this loop.
So how do we improve that?
Well, we want to use
a counter cache.
Once we put a counter
cache in place--
I'll show you how to do
that in a minute--
we'll be able to call .size,
and then for each tweet, it's
going to select all the
retweets, and then
there's no step two.
It's going to know how many
retweets that it has on each
item there in the database.
So how does it do that?
Let's take a look.
Before we dive into code, we
need to make sure everyone
understands what a retweet
really is.
So here we have an original
tweet, and we have a retweet.
It's the same model.
So a tweet belongs to what I'm
going to call an original_tweet
and an original_tweet
has_many retweets.
But it's a self-referential
relationship.
So what does that look like on
the model side of things?
In the class model, we have
Tweet belongs_to original_tweet,
class_name Tweet,
foreign_key tweet_id, and then
the other relationship direction
we have has_many
retweets, class_name tweet,
foreign_key tweet_id.
So that's how we do the
self-referential relationship.
To add a counter cache, the
first thing we need to do is
add account column
in a migration.
So here, we're going to add a
column to the tweets table
called retweets_count.
And it's important to notice
that an original_tweet is
going to be the one that
has a retweets_count.
To create the counter cache,
the first thing you might
think we need to do is add
counter_cache true.
However, if we actually had this
code-- and this is what I
started with in my code--
it errored out-- basically said,
"Unable to find tweets_count."
This is because by
default, when you have a
counter_cache column, it's going
to look for the class
name, it's going to
pluralize that,
and append _count
so in other words,
tweets_count.
So what we need to do to make
this work is take
retweets_count, move that up,
and now we're going to specify the
name of the count column that
we're going to use.
With this in place, when we
create a new tweet, not only
will it go and create that new
record in the database, but
it's also run a query which
looks something like this.
So we're basically incrementing
that counter column.
It's important that you know
the different ways you can
count the items in a has many
relationship, and which ones
not to use.
So here's a table that
makes it simple.
Without a cache counter, if we
call .length, it's going to
pull all the records, and then
call length on the array.
With .count
it's actually going to
run a count query, and with
.size, it's also going to
run a count query.
If we're properly using a cache
counter, when we use
.length, it's also going to pull
all records and called
.length on the array.
With .count, it's going to do a
count query, and with
.size, it's not going to
do any query all.
It's simply going to
look at the cache.
So I guess you could say in this
case, size does matter.
Let's take a look
at a rate task.
What's bad about that?
Well, if we have millions and
millions, maybe even billions,
of tweets, the first thing this
is going to try to do is
get all of them, and load
them into memory.
That's not good at all.
How do we get around that?
Well, this is where we might
want to use find_each.
By default, find each is going
to pull batches 1,000 at a
time, and run that block, and
then pull another 1,000, and
then run that block, and
repeat until it's done.
If we want, we can specify
the batch size to use.
In this case, we have 200,
so it's going to be
pulling 200 at a time.
Our best practices tutorial
wouldn't be complete without
going over the Law of Demeter.
If you're familiar with this
already, bear with me.
I'm going to be using it in a
slightly different way that
you may not have seen before.
So Law of Demeter says, "Each
unit should have limited
knowledge about other units.
Basically, don't talk to
strangers." So if we have
three objects, A, B, and C, what
we're saying is, A can
talk to B, B can talk to C, but
A shouldn't really know
about C at all, or be able to
communicate with C. In the
example I'm about to show you,
we're going to look at the
tweet, user, and account
settings object.
So in this case, tweet really
has no right to know about
account settings.
So here's a little
code snippet.
Inside of our tweet model,
we have a method
called location data.
We want to check to see if the
user has location on tweets
turned on, and if they do,
return the location.
Otherwise, return
unavailable.
Now a Law of Demeter violation
here happens when we realize
that the tweet shouldn't know
about account setting.
So how might we fix this?
Well, one way to fix this would
be to simply create a
method on user called
location_on_tweets.
There's a cool way
we can do this.
Inside of our user model, what
we're going to do is we're
going to use delegate.
We're going to say delegate
location_on_tweets
to account_setting.
We can add additional
methods as well.
We could say delegate
both of these two
methods to account_setting.
In this case, we're delegating
to two methods in the account
setting model that happened
to be linked directly to
attributes in our database.
However, it should be said, when
using delegate, you can
link it to any method
on any other class.
It doesn't have to be linked
to an attribute.
So now we're properly using
Law of Demeter.
But what happens with the
delegate method if we have a
user that doesn't have an
account setting object
associated with it?
Well, if we did
self.user.location_on_tweets,
and that user didn't have an account
setting, it would basically
error out, which
is not so good.
So this is why I want to
let you know about
an option on delegate.
You can specify allow_nil
true.
This will make it so that if you
call self.user.location_on_tweets,
and a user doesn't
have account settings, it's
just going to return nil.
It's not going to error out,
and you don't have to deal
with conditionals to see if
it's been set or not.
Next up, if you've been in Rails
for a while, odds are at
some point, you've had a model
that had something like this,
a display name.
And in the view, you just call
user.display_name.
Well, there's another convention
you probably should
know about.
Basically, if you define in your
user model a to_s method,
you then don't have to call any
methods to print out the
so-called display name.
You can just do @user, and it
will properly call the to_s
method and get you back what
you previously called your
display name.
Next up, we're going to talk
a little bit about
SEO-friendly URLs--
or basically, human readable
URLs, which are which are a
great practice.
So by default, Rails of the box,
you're going to get URLs
that also look something like
this, which aren't very
pretty, and aren't
very friendly.
What would a friendly
URL look like?
Maybe something more
like this.
Rails out of the box gives you
a very easy way to start
generating friendly URLs that
look a little bit like this.
How do we make this happen?
Inside of our topic model, we
have to declare a method
called to_param.
Inside there, it's just going to
create a string, which has
the ID, along with
name.parameterize.
Now that we have that code in
place, when we create a link,
like so, it's going to generate
a URL, which looks
like what I showed
you a minute ago.
When somebody goes to that URL,
the ID is going to get
equal to that string, it's
going to call Topic.find(params[:id]),
basically sending
that string, and the find
method actually is going to call
to_i, which is going to run
basically find, and
then that ID.
So really, that's all the code
that you need to set, and you
get these beautiful
URLs which are
SEO-friendly and human readable.
Now it's time for you to take
these techniques I taught you,
and use them in the challenges
to get to Level Five.