Git--
a distributed source
control repository.
I try to picture clusters of
information as they move
through the file system.
Were the commit messages
like history books?
I kept dreaming of
a repository I
thought I'd never see.
And then, one day, Git Real.
You're watching Git Real 2.
I'm Gregg Pollack.
And in this level, we're
going to be taking a
closer look at rebase.
First of all, before I get
into it, let's make sure
everyone's on the same page with
what exactly rebase does.
So here, you can see we have a
master branch, and here are
the last three commits.
And here we have a unicorns
branch, and here are the last
three comments.
As you can see, they have
some common commits.
So if we were to illustrate this
out in a tree, we can see
the master branch has two
unique commits, and the
unicorn branch also has
two unique commits.
Our objective here is that we
want to get our unicorns
branch up to date.
We basically want to replay
commits from the master branch
onto the unicorn branch.
So to do this, we first check
out the unicorn branch, then
we run git rebase master.
The first thing this is going
to do is move the unique
commits on the unicorn branch
into a temporary area.
Now the unicorns branch
is moved to the
final commit of master.
Then the commits we put in the
temporary area our replayed on
top of the unicorn branch.
So here's what our branch
looked like
before we ran rebase.
And here's what it looked like
after we ran rebase.
Now it may be tempting to say
that the commits for master
we're moved onto the
unicorn branch.
But that's not really
what happened here.
Basically, once we moved the
new commits on the unicorn
branch to the temporary area,
the next thing that we did is
change the unicorn branch
to point to the
last commit on master--
to the final comment on
the master branch.
And then, we re-ran the commits
from the temporary
area on top of that branch.
At some point while you're
working with git, you're going
to run into a situation where
you want to redo the commits
on the same branch you're
working on--
change them in some way.
This is where git rebase
-i comes in,
or interactive rebase.
In our case, we want to redo the
last three commits, so we
do HEAD~3, meaning
three commits
before the current HEAD.
When we execute this
command, it's going
to pop up an editor.
Inside this editor, we find
the rebase script.
You can think of these as
commands that are going to get
run once we save and
exit this editor.
Here you can see we're using the
pick command for each of
our commits.
And in the next couple slides,
we'll go over what the other
commands do, and why
you might use them.
Now if we save and exit
the editor, what is
it going to do exactly?
Well, first it's going to move
those three commits into a
temporary area.
Then it's going to go through
and run each of the commands
in our script.
In this case, since we're using
the pick keyword, it's
going to re-run each commit one
at a time, just like so.
And nothing is going
to change.
Interactive rebase alters
every commit
after the one you specify.
So if we specified HEAD here--
well, there's no commits
after HEAD, right?
So in this case, it would pop
an editor with basically
nothing to do.
No op.
If we did git rebase HEAD, with
a carrot, that means go
to the parent of HEAD.
So that means go to
the last commit.
Inside the editor, we would
simply have one
commit, as you see here.
So now let's use git rebase to
manipulate some of our commits.
If we run git log, we might
notice that, well, two of our
commits are in the
wrong order.
How might we switch the order?
All right, so here's what
our branches look like.
And we just want to switch the
order of two of our commits.
Well, the first thing we might
do is run git rebase -i--
same command we saw in the
previous slide-- and that's
going to pop up this editor.
One thing that's interesting to
notice is when we run git
log, it's showing us a list of
commits from newest to oldest.
But when we run the git rebase
command and we jump into our
rebase script, it's showing
our commits
from oldest to newest.
Notice how the order's
slightly different.
So in our case, we want
to change the
order of these commits.
And all we have to do to make
that happen is switch the
order inside this editor,
as you see here.
Now if we save and exit the
editor, it's going to rerun
the commits in the order we
specified inside this script.
And if we run git log,
we'll see that it's
actually been switched.
So what's happening here when we
exit that rebase script is
its rewinding our code, taking
the commits into a temporary
area, and then replaying them in
the order that we specified
inside the script.
Now what if we look back at
our commits, and we notice
that we used a bad
commit message?
Well, rebase interactive can
also help us fix that.
To do that, we simply run our
same rebase command, and
inside the editor, we simply
need to change the pick
command to the reword command
for the commit we want to
change the message on.
Then, when we save and exit this
file, another editor is
going to pop up.
This is where we can edit
our commit message.
So go ahead and edit
the commit message.
And then when we save and exit,
it's going to rerun
those commits, change the
message so that when we log
out the commits again, we can
see that the message has
properly been changed.
Another way we can manipulate
commits inside interactive
rebase is when we
need to split a
single commit into two.
Maybe there was too much code in
that single commit, and it
really should have been split
up into two, or even three.
So here's what our branch
current looks like, and we
want to split that last
commit into two.
To do this inside of our rebase
script, for the commit
that we want to split, we change
the keyword pick to
edit, because we want
to edit this commit.
When we save and exit this
file, it's going
to re-run the commits.
And when it gets to the commit
that we specified the edit
command for, it's going to run
that commit, and spit us out
onto the command line with the
message that you see here.
If we wanted to add things to
this commit, we could stage
some code, and then use commit
amend to attach it to this
commit, and then use git
rebase continue.
But what we want to do
is split this commit.
Well, it's already been
committed, so the first thing
we're going to have to do on
the command line is to type
git reset HEAD, which is going
to roll back our last commit,
leaving the changes in our
working directory.
If we would have done a hard
reset here with that dash dash
hard option, it would have
actually erased our changes.
But we want to split
our current
changes, not erase them.
So what we might do now is
simply stage the files we want
in our first commit,
and commit them.
And then stage the files we want
in our second commit, and
commit them.
At this point, now we want to
run rebase --continue.
This will continue running
any other commands
in our rebase script.
But in our case, this was the
last one, so now when we do a
log command, we can see that
the commits have been split
like we wanted them to.
Sometimes we might have
the opposite problem.
We might have two or
three commits that
should've been just one.
So we need a way of squashing
them together.
In our case, we have those two
commits we just split.
Well, what if we wanted to
squash those back into one?
So we want to squash
the commits.
Well, in this case, we're going
to run the git rebase
command, this time on the
last four commits.
Here's our editor.
Inside our editor, we are simply
going to specify which
commit we want to squash into
the previous commit.
Once we save and edit the rebase
script, another editor
is going to pop up.
This is going to show us the
commit message from the first
commit, and the second commit
that we're going to squash
into the first.
And as you can see here,
it says, enter
a new commit message.
So in this case, we're simply
going to write a new commit
message that combines
them both.
In this case, just change
plurals to capybara.
Now when we save and exit this
file, well, the two commits
are going to be squashed
into one.
And if we take a look
in our log, we can
see that's what happened.
Visually, here's what's
happening.
So when we run git rebase,
it's taking those four
commits, moving them to a
temporary area, and then
picking out each commit, and
re-running it onto our timeline.
Then when it gets to the squash
command, it's taking
that commit, and merging it
with the previous commit,
giving it our updated
commit message.
Well, you've received the
end of level one.
It's time for you to have some
fun with rebasing on your own.