Git Real.
You're watching Git Real 2,
and this is Level 6, where
we're going to be talking
about reflog.
So there Gregg is, going
through his code.
And he's got the third
section, second
section, first section.
Hmmm.
And he decides to
drop a commit.
Easy way to do that is to do
the git reset hard and then
specify which commit to go back
to, effectively blowing
away the third section.
But wait.
That was a mistake.
Maybe he actually does
want a third section.
But now how do we get back
that commit that
we just blew away?
Well, luckily, Git never
actually deletes a commit,
partially because of situations
like this.
So right now, we have our branch
and our HEAD pointing
to the second commit here.
But we want to restore
that last commit.
How do we do that?
Well, the commit's not
listed in the log, so
that's not any help.
But Git keeps a second log,
which is only in your local
repo, called the reflog.
So if we do git reflog,
we'll see something
that looks like that.
And if we read through the
reflog, we can see, oh, look.
It knows when we called reset.
It also knows about the
last three commits.
And we can see the commit
that we want back.
So good.
It still exists.
That's what we want.
And let's keep note of
that hash there.
Every time our HEAD moves,
either because we have a new
commit, or we change branches,
or we do a reset, another
entry gets put in our reflog.
So that's why we have an entry
for when we did reset, as well
as an entry for each commits.
In the left column, the reflog
shows us the SHA of the commit
that the HEAD was pointing
at in its current state.
It also shows us a shortname
that we can use to refer to
that particular commit.
And, lastly, it gives us a
description of what caused the
HEAD to move.
So the second entry here, that's
the commit that we want
back that's currently not
attached to any branch.
To get it back, we can use git
reset hard and then specify
that commit.
Or, if we want, we can use that
shortname to check out
that commit.
And if run a git log at this
point, we can see that our
commit is now back
at our HEAD.
You should note that the reflog
only keeps track of
what your HEAD is doing
locally, right?
So if Jane clones Gregg's repo,
she's not going to be
able to see his reflog.
Her reflog is starting
from scratch.
All right.
It's time for another story.
Jane's working on a
new aviary branch.
But she's decided that
it's not needed.
So she goes to destroy it.
And it tells her, uh-oh,
are you sure you
want to delete it?
You've got code on that branch
that hasn't been merged.
But she says, yeah, yeah, I
don't need that branch.
And she uses a capital D, which
of course is going to
delete the branch anyways.
And then, lo and behold,
she goes, oh, no.
I actually did need
that branch.
I need to get it back.
Well, how does she
get that back?
As we saw before, Git never
really deletes any commits.
It just deleted the branch.
So if we can find the latest
commit from that branch, we
can create a new branch which
points back to that commit.
That's all we have to do, and
it'll be like the branch was
never deleted at all.
So to find the last commit for
that branch, we need to go
back into the reflog.
Now, we could use the same
command as before.
But that only gives us
one line for each
time the HEAD changed.
If we want more detail,
we can run git log
dash dash walk reflogs.
And that will give us more
information about each of
these commits.
So here we can take note of
the shortname of the SHA.
Then, instead of doing a reset,
like we did before, to
recover the commit, we're going
to create a new branch.
So we'll do git branch
aviary--
that's the name of
our new branch--
and then reference the hash
of the last commit.
We can, obviously, also
use the reflog
shortname of HEAD 1.
Now, we can check out
that new branch.
And if we run a log on that
branch, it's as if we never
deleted it.
The birds have been
resurrected.
You've reached the end
of the videos.
It's time to restore some
deleted commits.
And I'll see you in
the outro video.