[MUSIC PLAYING]
Git Real.
You're watching Git Real 2.
And this is level three, where
we're going to be talking
about purging history.
So our coworker Bob did
something he shouldn't have.
He committed the passwords.txt
file to his repository.
And how should he fix this?
Well, he could create another
commit, which
removes that file.
But then the next time he pushes
up his commits, well,
it's going to push up that file
as well because even if
it was deleted, well, Git keeps
a history of everything
that was created and deleted.
So what do we do in
this circumstance?
There are commands in Git
to rewrite history.
But with great power comes
great responsibility.
So you need to know some
things about this.
First of all, there's
some reasons
not to rewrite history.
First of all, why bother?
Your data is already
compromised.
Maybe you should just change
your password in this instance
and not worry about messing
with rewriting history.
Also, everyone's got to update
their work to get
your revised commits.
And the ones that you deleted
the file, so maybe they
shouldn't even see that
that commit existed.
When should you revise
history?
Well, when, perhaps, what you
committed violates somebody's
copyright, like you're using
someone's library that
shouldn't be in there.
Obviously, you might want to
rewrite history, get rid of
that commit so those files
have no trace in your
repository.
Also you might have accidentally
committed large
files to your repository,
for example,
maybe large video files.
We've done that a
bit around here.
And so we might want to delete
those commits that have
records of those files so that
our repository stays small.
And, lastly, it's OK to rewrite
commits if you're
doing it on your local
repository.
As soon as you push up changes,
you should probably
consider those commits
set in stone.
The first thing that we're going
to do before we rewrite
history is to make a backup,
pretty straightforward.
So we can run git clone petshop
petshop-filter.
And this is going to clone our
repo, so we have a backup,
just in case we accidentally
delete some commits that we
didn't mean to.
To rewrite history, we're
going to use the git
filter-branch command with
the tree-filter option.
We can then specify after
that any shell command
that we want to run.
What it's then going to do is
check out each commit into a
working directory, run that
command against it, and then
recommit the code.
Bob might want to do this and
run rm -f passwords.txt, which
is going to go through each
commit and remove any file
that's called passwords.txt
on it.
If we had some large video files
we wanted to remove, we
could run this shell command,
which finds any files with the
extension mp4 and
removes them.
Let's go ahead and run the
passwords command.
And we're going to need to
specify at the end --
and then --all.
What this is going to do is
run this command on all
commits in all of
our branches.
We could also specify head
instead of all here if we only
wanted this filter to run
in our current branch.
Now if we take a look inside
of our log, we can see that
our passwords.txt file
has been removed.
What would happened, though,
if we ran rm passwords.txt
without that -f?
Well, not every commit
is going to have that
password.txt file.
So the ones that it doesn't
are going to fail.
And then the entire filter
is going to fail.
So that's why we add the -f
option to our remove command
to make sure that, even if the
file doesn't exist, it doesn't
return a failure, and our
filter doesn't stop.
As you might imagine, checking
out every commit and running a
command against and recommitting
it can take a
while, especially if you
have a large code base.
That's why there's a different
option you can use here called
index filter.
The commands we specify to set
an index filter must operate
on a staging area.
Git's going to run this command
on every commit, but
it's not going to check
all the files out.
So whatever command you specify
it needs to operate on
the staging area.
What this means is that our rm
-f passwords.txt command isn't
going to work.
What we need to do,
in this case, is
specify a git command.
In this case, we might use git
rm, with the --cached option,
which will operate in
our staging area.
Do you see that unmatched
option?
Well, if we didn't have that and
we just did the command as
you see here, it would fail
the first time that
passwords.txt isn't present.
Just like with tree-filter, if
the command we specify fails,
it's going to stop
doing the filter.
So we want to make sure that
when we run this git rm
command, we specify
--ignore-unmatch, which make
sure that the command runs
successfully even if the file
doesn't exist.
If you try to run filter-branch
a second time,
you might get this error
message you see here.
What happens is the first time
you run filter-branch, git
leaves a backup of your tree
in the .git directory.
So what you'll need to do, when
you run this a second
time, is make sure you specify
the -f option.
-f stands for force,
which forces it to
override the backup.
If you're deleting files from
history, some of your
commits might end up empty,
which isn't good.
Why would you want to leave a
commit around if it doesn't
actually do anything
to your code?
Here you can see our
commit history.
And there's one commit in
there that's empty.
How do we get rid of it?
Well, we can run the
filter-branch command with the
--prune-empty option.
This is going to delete any
commits which are empty.
Now if we run git log again,
we can see that the empty
commit is gone.
We could've included this
prune-empty option when we ran
filter-branch initially
and removed the
passwords.txt file.
And if it found any empty
commits, it would simply get
rid of them.
All right, it's time
for the challenges.
But be careful when you're
rewriting history.
You wouldn't want to erase
yourself from the time stream
or make any breaks in the
time space continuum.