Git Real.
You're watching Git Real 2.
And this is Level Four where
we're going to be talking
about working together.
As you may know, different
operating systems sometimes
use different lines
separators.
So with OSX or Linux,
we use a Line Feed.
And if you're familiar with
string encoding, this also
sometimes is represented as /n.
And if you're on Windows,
the line separator by default
is going to be a carriage
return followed by a Line Feed
or a /r and then a /n.
Problems with this arise when
you have some team members
that are working on OSX or
Linux, and maybe they have
some line separators in their
file like this, and then
another team member on Windows
opens up that same file and
since there's no carriage
returns, they don't see
separate lines at all.
Luckily, Git comes with
some configuration
to deal with this.
If you want a Unix-like system
like Linux or OSX, then you
run this configuration command,
as you see here.
This is going to make sure
that any files that you
commit, or there's any carriage
returns followed by
Line Feeds, then it's going
to change them all
to just Line Feeds.
Then on Windows systems,
you can run this
configuration command.
What this is going to do is
change all line feeds to
carriage return line feeds when
you check out the file.
That way somebody on Windows is
going to properly see all
the line endings.
And it will convert them
back to Line Feeds when
you commit the files.
If you're working in a team
that only uses Windows and
doesn't need to worry about
getting rid of the carraige
returns or adding them, then you
can use this configuration
command, which is just going to
leave the characters there.
You don't have to rely on
everybody setting that
configuration item though.
Instead you can create a
Git attributes file.
This sits in your file root.
And on the left side,
it has file types.
And on the right side, it
has conversion settings.
And over the next couple slides,
we'll describe what
each of these mean.
First, let's talk about file
type, which is on the left
side of the file.
If you have a star, it's
obviously going
to match any file.
You can do star dot HTML, which
obviously will only
match .HTML files.
And of course, .jpeg will
match any jpeg file.
Then on the right side of the
file, we have conversion
settings, which allows you to
specify how a particular file
type should be handled.
In this case with text=auto,
it's going to detect
whether a file is a text file.
And if it is, it's going
to convert it properly.
Then if it says text, it's going
to treat the file as a
text file, properly converting
the line endings.
If you want to specify exactly
how our text files are
converted, we can use these
configuration settings here.
EOL stands for End Of Line.
So if you a top command here--
CRLF--
when you check out code,
it's going to add the carriage
returns, so you can see
the line breaks
if you're on Windows.
And then when you check in the
code, it's going to remove the
carriage returns.
Whereas the second command here,
it's simply going to
make sure that there's
never any carriage
returns in your code.
Lastly, the binary configuration
option is going
to treat the files as binary.
So it's not going to try
to do any conversion.
Here are some typical rules
that you'll find in a Git
Attributes file.
First of all, up at the top,
you have a star text equals
auto, so by default convert
line endings for all text
files that you find.
Then secondly, let's go through
and make sure all HTML
and CSS files are treated
as text files.
And obviously these aren't
needed, if you're using the
text = auto above, because
it's going to detect
the HTML and CSS files as text
files and convert them
appropriately.
If we needed to make sure that
our images were interpreted as
binary files, then we can
specify *.jpeg binary
and PNG binary.
And lastly, we want to make sure
that all shell scripts or
or .sh files never have carriage
returns in them and
are treated appropriately.
But .bat files, which might
be batch files in Windows
format, do have the
carriage return.
So when we execute them,
they work properly.
Next up, we're going to be
talking about cherry picking.
When do you need
cherry picking?
Well, let's say we're
working in our
current production branch.
And we realize that we need a
piece of functionality that we
coded in another branch.
However, that piece of code that
we need is a commit in
the middle of a bunch
of other commits.
Well, what we need to do here is
cherry pick that commit and
put it into our production
branch.
Visually, here's what our
branches look like.
And what we want to do is take
a commit that's currently in
our development branch and
cherry pick it into our
production branch.
To do this, the first thing
we're going to do is check out
our production branch, make
sure we're on the right
branch, and then we're going to
write git cherry-pick and
specify the hash for that
particular commit--
in this case, the one that
starts with 53212--
and that's all you have to do.
Now, if we run git log on our
production branch, we'll see
that particular commit has been
cherry picked and put
onto our branch.
Notice here that the SHA on
our cherry-picked commit
changed when we copied it from
the development branch to the
production branch.
That's because it has a
different parent on the
production branch.
Sometimes we might want to
have a different commit
message when we cherry-pick
pick a commit, in which
case we can use the
Edit option.
When we execute this command,
it's going to pop up an editor
where we can edit the commit
message and change it to
whatever we want to be.
Once we save and quit, the
cherry pick proceeds as usual,
but with a different commit
message, as we can see down
here in the log.
Sometimes we might want to take
multiple commits from a
branch, cherry pick them, and
combine them into a single
commit in our current branch.
How can we do that?
To do this, we're going to use
the no-commit option and then
specify the two different
commits we want to combine.
The no-commit option takes the
changes from these two
commits, applies them to our
current head, but does not
make any commits.
So while we're going on git
status, we can see the changes
that applying these commits
made, but they haven't made
any commits to the local
branch, which
we need to do now.
So now all we need to do is
commit these changes into our
own commit in the production
branch.
This no-commit option is really
useful when you want to
cherry-pick a commit, but make
small changes before you
commit them to your
local branch.
When you cherry-pick, it's
really useful to keep track of
where that commit came from.
One way to do this is
to use -x option.
What this is going to do is
insert into the commit message
what you see here.
So you can see it was
cherry-picked from commit, and
it shows you the hash
right there.
Now when we run the log command,
we can see which
commit this came from.
This is only useful when you're
cherry-picking from
public branches.
Because if someone checks
out your code, and you
cherry-picked from a local
branch, they don't have your
local branch, and so that
hash isn't going
to lead them anywhere.
When you cherry-pick a commit,
the author of that commit also
gets moved over to
the new commit.
But you might need to keep
track of who did the
cherry-picking, because that's
where the --signoff up option
comes in handy.
This is going to add to the
commit message, showing who
cherry-picked this commit,
or really who
signed off on this commit--
same thing.
We've reached the
end of Level 4.
It's time for you to get into
the challenges, and maybe do
some cherry-picking.