You're watching Get Real 2.
And this is level 2, where
we're going to be talking
about stashing.
So there you are working on a
feature branch, and you're
about part way through a commit,
when your boss calls
and says, hey, there's
something
wrong with the server.
I need you to make a
commit right now
to the master branch.
And you go, well, huh.
I need to go back over to the
master branch, but I'm right
in the middle of this HTML file,
about halfway done with
this gerbil right here.
And you can't go ahead and
commit it halfway through.
That would be kind of bad.
So what do you do?
Well this is where stashing
comes in.
Stashing allows you to take some
files that may not make
up a full commit and store them
away in a temporary area.
So you can restore them
at a later time.
So in our case, if we run git
stash save, it's going to take
those files haven't been
completed yet, and it's going
to save them away in
a temporary area.
It's also going to restore the
state from the last commit.
So in this case, if I git diff,
there's no changes.
And if I run git status, I can
see that there's nothing to
commit on our gerbil branch.
So now we can safely go back
over to our master branch from
here, and make all the
changes that we need.
We can pull down updates.
We can make commits.
And we can push up
the changes.
Now when we're ready to resume
working on our feature branch,
we can go ahead and check out
that particular branch, and
then run the command
git stash apply.
This will re-run the changes
that we stashed away before so
that we continue working
on that code, and
eventually make a commit.
Every time you run git stash
save, it pushes that stash
onto the stash stack.
It's a stack of stashes.
So if you run git stash list,
you'll see a list of all of
the stashes that you've
used there.
You'll see it says WIP, as in
work in progress, on master.
That's the branch where
we stashed.
And it gives you the last commit
before we stashed.
Because a stash is
not a commit.
It's giving you the commit that
was right before the time
that we stashed.
The stashes are each given a
name that you can reference if
you want to apply
a certain stash.
So we wanted to apply just the
middle stash, stash number 1,
we could call git stash apply
stash 1 like you see here.
And it would be applied
to our code.
Stash 0--
obviously that's the one at
the top of the stack--
is going to be applied by
default if we don't specify a
stash by name.
When we run the stash apply
command, it's going
to apply our stash.
But it's not going to pop our
stash from the stash stack.
In order to drop that stash off
the stack, we can run git
stash drop, like so.
And that's going to remove
it from the list.
And we can see if we run
git stash list again.
We can see that it's gone.
There's some intelligent
defaults for
running stash commands.
For example, we can just run git
stash, and it's the same
thing as running
git stash save.
If we run git stash apply, it's
going to run the stash at
the top of the stack, which
is going to be stash 0.
Git stash drop is going to
automatically drop the stash
at the top of the stash stack.
And lastly there's the git stash
pop command, which runs
git stash apply and
git stash drop.
So it actually applies a stash,
and then pops it off of
the top of the stack.
Just like when you merge
branches, there is the
possibility of running into
conflicts or other problems
when you try to take two files
and put them together, and
merge them together.
So when you run git stash apply,
well sometimes you
might get an error message
that looks like this.
In this case, it wasn't able
to modify the local file.
So what it says here is commit
your changes or stash them
before you go ahead and try to
run your stash apply command.
So it actually didn't
run the stash apply.
It's saying, this isn't going to
work until you either roll
back your changes or commit
your changes.
Then do the apply again.
Sometimes when you run git
stash apply, it will just
merge and it won't abort, in
which case you're either going
to want to merge the changes and
make a commit, or maybe
even roll back.
If you're using the stash pop
command and you find some
merge conflicts, you'll want
to resolve them as usual.
However, you should note that
it doesn't automatically pop
the stash off of the stack.
That's because you might want
to just do a hard reset and
then do the pop command again.
So it doesn't assume that you
want to delete that stash.
So in this case, if it does run
into conflicts when you're
using pop, you're going to want
to go back into the stash
list and manually
drop that stash.
So Jane is currently working on
some code, and she has some
changes she wants to commit
and some that she wants to
stash for a later commit.
Well she might try running
git stash save
on her working directory.
But, if she runs git status,
she'll find that it stashed
everything, including
the staging area.
So that wasn't right.
Let's get our changes
back into our
current working directory.
So if Jane runs git stash
pop, it's going
to restore the state.
And you'll notice there that git
stash will save both the
changes in the staging
and unstaged area.
So let's try this again and this
time we'll use the
--keep-index option.
What that's going to do is keep
around the files that we
already have staged and
ready to commit.
So now if we run git status,
we'll see that only our
unstaged files have
been stashed.
Now Jane can go ahead and
make that commit.
And then to restore the files,
she can run git stash pop.
And then she can get
back to work.
But what if some of the files
that Jane needed to stash
weren't tracked files?
So they were brand new files
that were just created.
Well, when she ran git stash
save, and then run git status,
she would see that those
untracked files aren't getting
saved into the stash.
It's only going to stash files
that git knows about.
To fix this, we can run git
stash save with the
--include-untracked option.
This is going to include all
of the untracked files.
So after we run that, and we
run git status, we can see
that it has properly
stashed it.
And then to unstash it, we can
run git stash pop, and it will
properly pop, tracked
and untracked
files off of the stack.
When you have a bunch of stashes
is in your stash list,
sometimes it may be hard to tell
them apart and figure out
which one you want.
Well luckily, we can run this
with several options.
We could run this with the
--stack command, as
you see here.
And it would list out all the
different stats for all the
different stashes.
But really we can use any option
that we would typically
use with the git log command.
We can use the options here to
get more details about each of
the stashes.
If we want more information
about one particular stash, we
can run git stash show, and then
specify the name of that
stash, like you see here.
If we run git stash show, and
don't specify any stash, well
it's going to show us details
about the most recent stash.
Just like git stash list, git
stash show can take any option
that the git log
command takes.
So in this case, we
could do git stash
show dash dash patch.
It shows the file changes
within the stash.
When you run git stash save, you
can optionally provide a
stash message, just like
a commit message.
And then when you run git stash
list, you're going to
see that message on the list.
So Gregg is back working on the
gerbils again, and well he
started working on the
gerbil toy section.
But then again management called
and said, hey, you need
to go ahead and deploy those
gerbil things that you're
working on.
So let's go ahead and stash
save the toy section that
we've been working on.
And then we will maybe merge
our existing code over into
master, to deploy to master.
But what if hypothetically,
Gregg destroyed that gerbil's
branch, the one where we stashed
the current work we
did on toys.
Well now we need a new branch
to restore that
stashed toys page.
Well we can use this command,
git stash branch gerbil toys
stash zero.
What this is going to do is
it's going to create a new
branch name, called gerbil toys,
and it's automatically
going to pop off of the stash
the work that we did on gerbil
toys onto that branch.
Then, we can go ahead and
make our first commit
onto this new branch.
One last thing before you
get to the challenges.
What if you have a bunch of
stashes in your stash list,
and you no longer need them?
Well, that's where they git
stash clear command comes in.
If you run that command, that
blows away all your stashes,
as you can see here.
Now it's time for you to start
stashing things away in the
challenges.
See you in the next level.