You're watching Git Real 2,
and this is level 5, where
we're going to be talking
about submodules.
If you're working on multiple
projects that solve similar
problems, odds are you're going
to have some similar
code, or may be some code
libraries that you want to be
able to share between them.
There's a couple different ways,
good and bad ways you
can share code.
First, you can copy the
libraries into each project as
you need them.
Only problem with this is that
you're going to make updates
to them, maybe locally, and
there's no easy way to then
push up your changes so
the other projects can
get access to them.
Also if you do things
this way libraries
can quickly get outdated.
Because you copied them in and
you might lose track of when
it's time to maybe copy in
additional changes when new
releases come about.
Also another alternative, you
could post libraries on a
central server.
So they're up on a central
server, maybe they live in a
separate directory separate
from your project.
Unfortunately, this may make it
harder to test the library
in the context of
each project.
This is where Git sub
modules come in.
Giving you a way too
easily share
libraries across projects.
submodules allow you to pull
down updates easily, so as
that shared library gets
updated, you can pull down
updates into your project.
You can test your changes within
the context of the
existing project.
You can also share
changes easily.
So if you're inside a project
and you make an update to that
shared library, you can easily
push it up to the repo, and
then pull it down to through
the other projects.
And since a submodule is just
a Git repo that lives inside
of your Git repo, you have a
history of changes that is
independent of your project.
Gregg and Jane are two coders
who are working on two
separate projects, the aquarium
project and the pet
shop project.
And they want to be able to
share the CSS and JavaScript
directories between the two.
So for these, we're going
to create two
different submodules.
As I mentioned, submodules
are just independent Git
repositories.
So we create them just like we
would create any other Git
repo and then we add them to the
aquarium, and the pet shop
project as submodules.
They're Git repositories inside
our Git repository.
This way if Gregg is working
inside the aquarium project
and he makes changes to the
CSS, and JavaScript sub
modules, those changes can be
pushed up to the central
repository.
And then later on Jane, if she's
working in the pet shop
project, can pull down those
changes into her project.
This way updates can happen on
each of the projects and they
can both contribute
to each other.
Let's pretend we haven't linked
these projects to the sub
modules yet.
How do we first add a sub
module to a project?
Well first, we have to
create that Git repo.
Or if you're using a online
service like github, you would
go and you would create
the repository there.
Then you would go into your
project that's going to use
that as a submodule and write
git submodule add, and
specify the Git repository
address, like you see here.
This command is going to first
clone the project into a CSS
directory, inside your
current repository.
And now if we run Git Status,
we'll see that it also created
a git submodules file, that
we'll look inside in a minute.
It also created a new
file called CSS.
But it's not actually
a new file, that's
actually a new directory.
Then we need to commit both of
these and push it back up to
our server.
That's all we have
to do to add sub
modules to our project.
Here's what we see inside the
.gitmodules file that was
created for us.
You can see here it has
submodule CSS, then it specifies
the path to this sub
module directory.
And then we have the origin
or the URL of the origin
repository.
If we add additional sub
modules later, the
configuration will be appended
to this file.
Now let's walk through the
process of making an update to
the files inside
of our submodule.
Because there's two
things about it
that aren't that intuitive.
So first what we're
going to do is go
into our CSS directory.
Then we're going to check out
a branch, in this case the
master branch.
See, submodules by default
don't start at
any branch at all.
So we need to remember
to go to a branch.
Then we can make changes
to our files.
Then if we run get status,
you can see that
we've made some changes.
Then we'll make a commit
and then finally
push that submodule.
Now there's one more
thing we have to do
before we're done here.
Which is, also push
our parent repo.
Let's take a look at that.
So if we jump back into our
parent directory and we do a
get status, we're going to see
that it knows there's some new
commits inside of the
CSS directory.
So from here, we need to
add that CSS directory.
And commit it, basically saying
that we updated, then
make a commit.
And lastly, push that
parent repository.
The reason why we have to update
the parent, is that the
parent has reference to a commit
on our submodule.
And if we update that sub
module, we need to change the
pointer on the parent to point
to the new commit that's on
the head of that submodule.
Now let's take a look at the
perspective of somebody
installing a new git repo that
has some submodules in it.
So here comes Gregg, he's going
to clone the aquarium project.
Here's the directories he has.
He gets the git modules
file, which has
reference to the submodules.
He gets all the project files.
He also gets the CSS and
JavaScript directories, but if
we look inside there, we'd
find them empty.
That's because we need to
initialize the submodules.
To do that he would run,
git submodule init.
This is going to read the
.gitmodules file and add an
entry to the local
git configuration
for each submodule.
It looks something like this.
Then Gregg needs to run to
git submodule update.
This is what's going to go out
onto the internet most likely
and pull down those
submodules.
It's going to clone
those submodules
into our parent project.
Now our submodules
have files.
So Gregg pulled down our new
repository and let's say Gregg
made some changes to our
submodules, to our CSS, or
JavaScript directory,
and pushes those
back up to the server.
The next time Jane comes back
to the project and does a
pull, she might notice
that the CSS sub
modules been updated.
As you see here.
If she runs get status, again,
she's going to see that the
CSS submodule has some
new commits on to it.
And if she runs git diff, she
can see the parent project has
been updated to reference a new
commit for our submodule.
This is a cue that she needs
to run, git submodule update.
Git submodule update is going
to go out to the git
submodule repositories.
And see if there's any commits
that need to be pulled down
onto this local repository.
Then if Jane runs, git status
again, she can see that her
project is completely up to
date, and she's ready to start
working on it.
Now Jane needs to make some
changes to the submodule
inside the CSS directory.
So she goes and makes those
changes to those files.
Then goes inside the CSS
directory, checks the git
status, there's the file that
she changed, let's go ahead
and add that to the staging.
And then make a commit.
Oh wait, there's one thing
though, there's one thing that
she forgot.
Do you see it?
You see up there at the
top, it says, not
currently on any branch.
If you work with git sub
modules, likely you'll do this
at some point as well.
So how do we deal with it?
Because we have this commit
that's not on a branch.
If we try to push, well,
nothing's going to be pushed
because the commit is
not on a branch.
See every time we run git
submodule update, the code gets
checked out in a
headless state.
Which means, it's not pointing
at any particular branch.
So if we make commits,
where do they go?
They don't go on any branch,
which means we
can't push them anywhere.
Don't worry, if you make
this mistake there's
a way to fix it.
What Jane needs to do here is
associate the commit that we
made onto a branch.
So from here, we can
check out a branch.
In this case, we're going
to check out master.
And it even notices that we
have one commit that's not
connected to any branches.
And it gives us a suggestion on
how to create a new branch
which include that commit.
However, what we want
to do is simply run
this commit on master.
To do this, we simply can run
git merge, and then specify
the hash for that commit.
When we do that, that gets
run on our master branch.
And if we run git log, we can
see that it's become a part of
master history.
Now Jane can safely push
that submodule.
But remember that's not the only
thing she needs to do.
After you push a submodule, you
need to then go up to the
parent directory, and if we
run git status, we can see
that there's been some
new commits there.
So we need to simply add that
directory and then commit it,
and push it.
So when you make change the
submodules, you have to
remember to push two different
repositories.
First, you push the sub
module repository.
And then you push the
parent repository.
Step one and step two.
However, if Jane in this case
had forgotten to push the sub
module, and she just pushed
the parent repository.
The next time Gregg runs git sub
module update, it's going
to try to update
the submodule.
And update it to the commit that
it has a reference to,
that it just pulled down.
But Jane forgot to commit
that particular update.
So it fails, as you
can see here.
So basically collaborators get
stuck until Jane goes back and
she pushes up the submodule.
So it's really important that
you remember to push twice
when you're editing
submodules.
If you're worried about
forgetting though, there's
some options to help you.
First, there's the recurse sub
modules option on git push.
This will abort a push
if you haven't pushed
the submodules yet.
And this is something
you want to run
from the parent directory.
If you don't want to have to
worry about pushing twice, you
can simply run your push command
with the recurse sub
modules on demand option.
What this is going to do is push
your parent repo and it's
going to go to see if any of the
submodules need pushing.
And if they do, it'll
push them as well.
It's a good practice if you're
dealing with submodules to
alias
this command.
So here we're aliasing
it as pushall.
So when we ever push this
project, we would
run git pushall.
And if any of our submodules
need pushing, it's going to
push those as well.
If you don't get it,
don't worry.
I didn't get submodules the
first time I tried to
understand it either.
So feel free to go back
and watch the video.
Or maybe you'll get some
understanding when you start
learning by doing in
the challenges.
Good luck.